<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042029" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2003-01-15" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Royce Ong | Interview 1 | January 15, 2003</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Royce Ong</interviewee><interviewer>David Washburn</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|23(7)|43(3)|55(5)|69(12)|83(12)|95(2)|109(15)|126(2)|129(3)|143(5)|164(12)|180(13)|196(3)|209(10)|219(11)|232(3)|254(14)|272(5)|284(14)|301(7)|317(2)|329(10)|344(9)|358(4)|374(4)|396(8)|405(6)|418(16)|432(11)|451(12)|470(11)|486(14)|508(2)|520(1)|534(6)|551(5)|566(13)|583(8)|600(9)|615(2)|634(2)|653(6)|668(16)|683(1)|700(3)|713(12)|732(10)|748(13)|767(9)|782(2)|800(3)|821(8)|842(2)|855(4)|875(14)|889(1)|909(3)|934(2)|955(12)|967(10)|979(1)|985(5)|1001(4)|1021(12)|1037(14)|1050(5)|1067(18)|1087(2)|1110(3)|1126(3)|1139(3)|1157(1)|1172(10)|1187(3)|1206(10)|1226(13)|1245(2)|1261(14)|1279(4)|1294(4)|1314(5)|1331(3)|1349(2)|1374(5)|1385(10)|1411(6)|1425(1)|1440(11)|1461(1)|1481(6)|1498(1)|1514(9)|1540(8)|1557(13)|1579(3)|1598(2)|1622(13)|1637(9)|1662(2)|1684(9)|1701(12)|1718(4)|1731(5)|1747(2)|1767(3)|1781(13)|1795(6)|1811(9)|1827(7)|1841(11)|1857(13)|1872(12)|1890(15)|1908(13)|1930(15)|1951(2)|1974(13)|1990(2)|2002(1)|2025(4)|2042(10)|2067(5)|2089(7)|2103(3)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>RlEtK7CkTh8</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Raised in Point Richmond, Ong attended high school in Richmond during World War II. He lived with his mother in their family home--established by Ong's grandfather near the turn of the 20th century. Discusses: school environment during 1940s, life in Point Richmond, mother's job at Standard Oil during the war, Chinese-American community in Richmond.</description><rel /><transcript>WASHBURN: Today is January 15, right?

ONG: I think it is, isn&#039;t it?

WASHBURN: We&#039;re recording with Royce Y. Ong. My name is David Washburn, the
interviewer. We are at the University of California at Berkeley. Royce, I&#039;d like
to start with some rather simple questions just to establish a few things.

ONG: All right.

WASHBURN: When and where were you born?

ONG: San Francisco. You want the year I was born? 1930.

WASHBURN: You had told me that you were baptized Baptist.

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: What can you tell me about where you were baptized?

ONG: It was First Baptist Church in Point Richmond.

WASHBURN: So you were baptized in Point Richmond.

ONG: No, I was baptized over in town, but that&#039;s the church I attended, First
Baptist Church in Point Richmond. I was baptized, I think, over in Richmond, in
Barrett Avenue Baptist Church. That was the main church in the Baptist area, in
downtown Richmond.

WASHBURN: In San Francisco, do you remember what your parents did for work?

ONG: My mother was a homemaker, my father was a chauffeur.

WASHBURN: Chauffeur for whom?

ONG: I don&#039;t know who he chauffeured for, but somebody with money. He worked
only half a day, because all he does is just drive the man around.

WASHBURN: I understand that you moved to Point Richmond when you were younger.
Although you were still a young boy, what do you remember about growing up in
San Francisco?

ONG: Not much. Only thing I remember, we had cousins who would take me up to
where Hunters Point was. Used to be up there, nothing but wild animals and
things. That was before it built up. Then one time we brought home a dog and my
mother made him take it back. He followed us home. And then I remember, the
stockyard was there. You see the animals going to the stockyard slaughterhouses.
That&#039;s the only thing I kind of remember. And I remember going downtown to see
my grandfather, who lived in Chinatown. We lived out in Butchertown in them
days, what is known as Bayview District.

WASHBURN: So you lived out towards what is now Bayview-Hunters Point.

ONG: Yes. In the early years, everybody bragged about it if you were born in
Butchertown. That&#039;s where Lefty O&#039;Doul was born, the famous ballplayer and
manager. That&#039;s why they have a bridge named after him on Fourth Street, the
Lefty O&#039;Doul Bridge. He always used to brag that he was a Butchertown boy.

WASHBURN: Why was it called Butchertown?

ONG: They had slaughterhouses there, for the cows and the sheep. But they were
gone when I left. They probably left in the fifties.

WASHBURN: Has anybody told you why your family settled in Butchertown and not in Chinatown?

ONG: The reason was my paternal grandmother bought a house down there. All my
mother&#039;s brothers lived across the street. So she lived down there across from
them. My grandmother wanted to live there too, but she only lived two years
after I was born. She died in the hospital with a tumor and so they picked that
area to live in. It was very unusual, because there was hardly any Chinese in there.

WASHBURN: I think you described to me once that there was a shrimp camp out that way.

ONG: The shrimp camp is where the Hunters Point Shipyard is. They used to pay
ten cents a pound for them to peel the skins off of the shrimp. My mother used
to do that for extra money. That&#039;s the only thing I can remember. But all my
uncles worked uptown, except for one uncle who would work at the slaughterhouse.
In later years, before he retired in the seventies, he became superintendent.
But they weren&#039;t doing that much slaughtering of animals.

WASHBURN: When and why did your family move to Point Richmond?

ONG: The reason was my mother owned a property since 1903. When they had the
1934 strike, that Harry Bridges and the maritime had, just like the one they had
a couple months ago, the town became unionized. My father, since he was a
Chinese man, never was in the unions. They didn&#039;t allow them, so the man that
hired him didn&#039;t dare keep him, because the whole San Francisco Bay Area became
union. So they had to let him go. My mother was lucky, owned a home, so she had
to tell the people she rented out to they had to leave, and she moved back in.

WASHBURN: Right before your family moved to Point Richmond, your father&#039;s job
became unionized. He was a chauffeur, you said?

ONG: Yes, but he didn&#039;t marry my mother until 1922. His job was a chauffeur and
odd jobs, and then when the strike came, he was non-union so he lost his job,
and during the Depression you couldn&#039;t find work. We had to rent, but she owned
a home already so we moved back over there, so not to pay rent anymore.

WASHBURN: What year was that, about?

ONG: 1934, in July.

WASHBURN: You had described to me when we first met about how your mom owned the
home. Can you describe who built the home?

ONG: My grandfather built the home and he put the property under my mother&#039;s
name. So the day the property was bought, my mother was the owner of the
property. I don&#039;t know much about the house, but the lot was owned by her. She
had to pay a twenty-dollar gold piece. That was a requirement in them days. I
found out later from people, other kind of monetary fund wasn&#039;t acceptable for
property. Only gold was, so paper and silver didn&#039;t mean anything. That&#039;s why
the deeds all say that.

WASHBURN: When did your mother&#039;s father establish the home there?

ONG: Far as I could tell, the year the house was built. He might&#039;ve been there
earlier, but 1903 was the year the house was built. Some famous carpenter built
all the homes there. He had it built.

WASHBURN: Do you know why he built it there in Point Richmond?

ONG: Got me. Very unusual, because, like I was telling you, the Asians didn&#039;t
get allowed to own property, so I was surprised that he bought a lot and they
sold to him.

WASHBURN: But at that point in 1903, your mother was born here in this country.

ONG: Yes. She was a citizen, so he automatically just put the property under her
name. [phone interruption]

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s go back once again. By 1903, your mother had already been born here.

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: You describe that your grandfather put his property in her name.

ONG: The property is all under my mother&#039;s name, so she&#039;s the owner of the property.

WASHBURN: It&#039;s kind of a naive question to ask, but just for other people--why
did he have to do that?

ONG: Because--I think it was the Exclusion Act that didn&#039;t allow the Asians to
own property. It started 1898, but in 1915 they kind of put it back on. I don&#039;t
know if it was still in effect through those years. I always want to go to the
library and read up more about it, but the law was that no Asian person was
allowed to own any property, or buy it, even.

WASHBURN: Asian immigrant.

ONG: Yeah. &quot;Asian&quot; especially meant &quot;Chinese.&quot;

WASHBURN: However, Asians who were born here could own property.

ONG: No, they really couldn&#039;t. The Exclusion Act had stopped them from
immigrating and stopped them from owning property in the United States,
especially California. I think they had their own law that was a little [more]
stringent than the United States law. They were even segregated in the schools,
when you read history. But you read the Japanese didn&#039;t, because they protested
it. Their government was strong.

WASHBURN: I remember reading that.

ONG: Yeah, you seen that on Channel 9, how the Japanese went back to school and
the Chinese didn&#039;t have a strong government. They didn&#039;t dare say anything.

WASHBURN: That was between Teddy Roosevelt and the Japanese government.

ONG: Yeah, because he was trying to be friendly with them. So the Japanese had
more privilege. They yelled and he right off stopped it.

WASHBURN: Can you describe the house that your grandfather built to live in?

ONG: He just built a small bungalow, like. It wasn&#039;t real big, because he was
ready to go back to China soon as they made their money here. The Chinese always
had that theory, to make enough and go buy a big farm in China, and then they&#039;d
have all the relatives work off the farm. But there&#039;s not too many of them did that.

WASHBURN: How did you learn that that was your grandfather&#039;s idea?

ONG: My mother told me, and my great-aunt, who lived in the city--didn&#039;t live
with us, but she remembered all that.

WASHBURN: Can you describe the neighborhood that the house was built in?

ONG: Point Richmond&#039;s a kind of influential area. It still sits there in the
same area.

WASHBURN: For those that don&#039;t know about Point Richmond, can you describe it?

ONG: Point Richmond was a town that was built up when Santa Fe [Railroad] came
in the early 1900s. Standard Oil, which is now known as Chevron, built there
too. Most of the people that lived there in the early part of the century were
either Santa Fe or Standard Oil workers. So the little town grew up. Santa Fe
had their yard there, and Ferry Point was where the ferryboats--wasn&#039;t
ferryboats; was kind of like tugboats--carried the passengers or trains over to
San Francisco. Most of the people who lived there either worked in the yard as
engineers, firemen or track people. The town was bought up by [John]
Nicholl--that&#039;s where the town still has Nicholl Knob--and Ellis Landing, they
bought the property. They were hunting birds and things, they thought it was a
good place to start building up. So Point Richmond now is a place to live. All
the wealthy people are moving back in there. It&#039;s a little historic part of
Richmond. Historic district.

WASHBURN: So when your parents moved over to Point Richmond, what did they do
for work when they arrived?

ONG: They were unfortunately unemployed during the Depression. My father and
mother survived on social security. A form of social security; I don&#039;t know what
they really call it. They used to give you food stamps every two weeks or
something. You go over to town, they give you anything that was available from
the farms, like rice, dry fruit. They&#039;d give you cornmeal. That&#039;s your diet of
food all the time. Then, in the late thirties, my father didn&#039;t want to go to
work, but the WPA [Works Progress Administration] came in. So they told him he
had to go to work because he had a family. So he worked on the dam road, where
it is now, El Sobrante, and widened the road up, took the blackberries out. He
worked making the causeway to Mare Island. Then in 1940 my mother got
encouragement from a Scottish lady up the hill. Mrs. Brown, who was a pioneer
lady, told her my father was too lazy, it&#039;s best to divorce him. I think she was
one of the early Asian women to get a divorce. So after that, my mother became
what is known now as a single parent.

WASHBURN: What were some of your earliest memories, moving to Point Richmond?

ONG: Only thing I remember was the Point was a small town, and there was mostly
now you call them Caucasian people living there. Only me and a girl and a boy
that was Mexican were the only other minority people there. Half of the
population in them days was all Italian people. My neighbors next door were
Italians. They had thriving businesses in Point Richmond, because that used to
be the main part of town until--about 1912 or 1913, they moved over to proper
Richmond, and that started building up. City Hall and everything left downtown,
but the police station, for some reason, stayed downtown until 1950 when the new
modern City Hall was built.

WASHBURN: You moved to Point Richmond when you were only four years old.

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: Back in San Francisco, you said they spoke Cantonese to each other.

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: So you grew up speaking Cantonese in the household.

ONG: My mother spoke it. My father spoke a little bit, but he never was around
much. I imagine he did. I don&#039;t remember him much, because he left so early. My
mother knew English, but she always wanted to speak Cantonese, but I didn&#039;t. I
always answered in English, made her mad.

WASHBURN: So moving over to Point Richmond, you didn&#039;t have any problems with
language or anything.

ONG: No, but the only thing is, I was telling my father this, I&#039;m telling
everybody now, I don&#039;t believe in bilingual education, because for some reason I
was lucky to have a first-grade teacher--I did not know English until I was six
years old. My mother, for some reason, neglected to teach me English. I went to
the teacher--she passed away, I knew her for years and years--Miss Ruby
{Simmons?}, she taught me English, she taught me to write, and I&#039;m amazed what
she did for me. After my first grade I started picking all that up. So I always
say, if you&#039;re a foreign person and you don&#039;t learn English, it&#039;s just too bad.
Because I had that trouble. Like everybody said, I could have been sent
backwards because of my language trouble.

WASHBURN: How was it for you moving to Point Richmond and not knowing so much
English? Do you remember having difficulty?

ONG: Never had people around me that spoke English. [laughs] Always seeing my
mother and my aunts and uncles.

WASHBURN: And in Point Richmond, nobody spoke Cantonese, so do you remember any
language difficulties when you were younger?

ONG: Looks like I didn&#039;t. I got along with them real good, so I must have picked
it up real easy. I never had trouble with talking to people, and I learned it
just as fast, so I was one of the lucky persons. A lot of people want the
bilingual education, I tell what could happen. I had it happen, and I&#039;m lucky I
got out and ended up with good jobs. See, I was born without English language
knowledge, which was bad. So I know how it is, with people that didn&#039;t, but it
was my case that since I was so young, I picked it up real good. Then I think
what helped me was that Scottish lady that was like a grandmother to me. She
always made me pronounce words and things.

WASHBURN: This was at Washington Elementary School.

ONG: Yes. So I had to stay back one semester, because I was too late going to kindergarten.

WASHBURN: For those who don&#039;t know where Washington Elementary School is, can
you describe it?

ONG: That&#039;s in a suburb of Richmond, Point Richmond historic district.

WASHBURN: But where it&#039;s located is--

ONG: It&#039;s in the city proper. Since we have a post office in Point Richmond
itself, there&#039;s no way to stop us from using the Point Richmond address, but the
city frowns on it. But nobody who lives there ever says you live in Richmond.

WASHBURN: You entered elementary school in about what year?

ONG: 1937 to spring of &#039;42. First grade all the way up to sixth grade.

WASHBURN: What&#039;s probably your most vivid memory about the classrooms at Washington?

ONG: The first school building was a three-story building. It was big rooms with
high ceilings, and it didn&#039;t have heat. They only had central heat in the
hallways. The stairs were made out of mahogany or something, because it was an
old 1913 building. During that time in the forties, the WPA built a school that
was a low-floor, and looked like kind of Washington building, George Washington.
Had a little thing for weather vane on top and the building kind of resembled
George Washington&#039;s building. It&#039;s still there to this day, but they added more
classrooms. It was a very modern building for its year.

WASHBURN: Did you attend the older building?

ONG: Yes, I attended about a year and a half or two years. The building stayed
until after the war, because the army came and took it over.

WASHBURN: At that age, can you remember what were some of your favorite subjects?

ONG: I liked to draw a lot. We used to listen to the Standard Oil music. All the
kids went down the stairs to the auditorium. They turn on the radio, listen to
Standard Oil opera music. They sponsored it, like Texaco did. Texaco used to
have operas, from back East. They used to go down there. That&#039;s where you go on
rainy days, and they had their PTA meetings with your parents.

WASHBURN: Most of the kids who went to school at Washington Elementary, where
did their parents work?

ONG: Most of them either were Standard Oil or Santa Fe, and then a lot of them
did other work. Some of the mothers work at downtown Richmond, [which was] very
vibrant then, had all the major stores, like Kress, Woolworth, shoe stores,
Montgomery Ward&#039;s, so a lot of them worked there as sales clerks.

WASHBURN: Would you say that during the Depression, like yourself, many of those
kids were working, where their families were living on social security, also?

ONG: Not very many. It was a very influential area, even then. Most of them had
a job.

WASHBURN: How would you say the Depression affected the other students?

ONG: Most of them, I think, had good incomes. They all had nice houses on the
bay side, where the people are still building the $500,000 homes or more.

WASHBURN: What was it like for you, then, with your family living off social
security, and these other kids--

ONG: I never had trouble. I sailed right in with the kids, go to their houses,
and they&#039;d come to my house. We were around them, everywhere we went. The
movies, and everything. So, even as poor as we were, nobody looked down on me.

WASHBURN: Who were some of your best childhood friends? Do you remember their names?

ONG: I can&#039;t hardly remember. One was Robert Chamberlain. And Arthur Hudson.
Those were the two guys I used to hang around with. They had brothers. Then I
had--one was Dick O&#039;Connor. His cousin was the famous Donald O&#039;Connor in the
movies, the dance star. His father was a big shot at Standard Oil. Those were
the kids right in my neighborhood. The only funny thing, my neighborhood never
had any girls. They always had boys. Then another guy was a guy we called
{Schnookie?} next door. The {Amantini?} family were close, and they still live there.

WASHBURN: What would you guys do as children in town?

ONG: Always play soldiers. We thought soldier was a great thing. Now, everybody
knows better. Go over and get killed or something, but during World War II we
thought soldier was the best thing in the world. In them days, everybody had
little toy guns.

WASHBURN: So would you go over to their house and they&#039;d come over to your house also?

ONG: Yes. They lived right next door to me, some of them, some farther down the
street. But most of them moved away, and some I don&#039;t know what happened. A very
few of my schoolmates left in the town. There&#039;s only about three or four left;
all the rest are newcomers, because they all went over to Richmond where the
newer homes were built in the forties.

WASHBURN: What kind of foods did your mom cook when you were growing up?

ONG: My mother cooked Chinese food and American food, but I don&#039;t. I just eat
regular American food.

WASHBURN: When these friends would come over, would they come over for lunch sometimes?

ONG: No, they just come to visit and play.

WASHBURN: So they never came over and your mom cooked them Chinese food or something.

ONG: No. We had one family that came and ate apple pies and stuff, because my
mother used to get it from a relative in Salinas. They used to send them up by
railway express every year in apple season, three or four crates of it. So my
mother made apples. One family did eat the apples. We had a lot of relatives
that lived in Salinas.

WASHBURN: One thing I want to focus on with you--I&#039;d love to talk more about
your childhood, but--

ONG: The war years, that&#039;s the main thing.

WASHBURN: I want to talk a little bit about the war years, right. [interruption
to check recorder]

ONG: You know what mystified me? In the war years, I got a book from my
friend--had to give it back to him--the National Park there published a book on
the coast artillery of the Bay Area. They mentioned 1941, when they had a
training, never mentioned why the soldiers went from Fort Lewis, Colorado, down
to Fort Roberts to train. They never mentioned it. We were little kids, though.
The war had started--no, the war didn&#039;t start.

It was November, the month before the war start. We seen about a hundred army
trucks pulling 40 mm cannons, going from the ferryboat, going down Cutting
Boulevard, which was Highway 17, heading south. Two weeks later they came back.
Some stayed. Two weeks later, the war come. So I cannot understand; I think
somebody knew something was going to happen. So when the war come, the army was
already there. They put up the guns for the Japanese to bomb us. They were right
behind my house; they put up 50 mm machine guns and the 40 mm cannons,
anti-aircraft. So that was a funny thing, how they knew and stayed, because it&#039;s
never mentioned in any books why they were doing that. Just like I heard some
guys on the bus one day as a kid, just right after the war, say they went two
weeks before the war, they went out and met a Japanese tanker out two hundred or
three hundred miles out in the ocean, and gave them gasoline.

WASHBURN: I&#039;m sure there are lots of stories like that. But when we first met,
Royce, you had mentioned that you were going to school down at Washington
Elementary School when activity at the Kaiser shipyards started. What do you
remember about the construction activity in that area of town?

ONG: I was a traffic boy. There was a company called {Marco?} that built the
shipyards. They come through with a rock quarry, with the trucks, and we had to
make sure the kids didn&#039;t get run over, because they came through the tunnel
carrying rocks. That&#039;s when they start building the shipyards up. Shipyard Three
was already built in early 1941, because, as a boy, I went down there to watch
them launch Liberty ships for the British. Then when the war come, I later
read--because them days I didn&#039;t read much, being young--Kaiser was authorized
to take over all the shipyards. Henry Kaiser ran them all, even {Todd?} was
under his command, because the Maritime [Commission] took them over. But that
was already building ships for the British.

WASHBURN: Maybe you were too young, but what do you remember about them pumping
out from the canal and establishing that area down there by the canal as
building it up for the shipyards?

ONG: Yeah, they start bringing the rocks on the quarry around the canal. You
still see the scar in the hill. That&#039;s where all the rocks came from. You know
where the sewage plant is? On the side, you still see a big scar. A lot of the
rocks were taken off the hill to make the shipyards.

WASHBURN: So what did they do with those rocks?

ONG: Fill in the shoreline on the canal there. But, like I said, Shipyard One
was already built. That&#039;s the one that&#039;s still there, that they&#039;re collecting
the coke, where Rosie the Riveter is near, that&#039;s the one that already was built
before the war. Shipyard Two and Three was built after the war started, but they
did it real fast.

WASHBURN: You went to school about eight o&#039;clock in the morning or so. Do you
remember going to school and also seeing workers arriving at the shipyards?

ONG: When the shipyards got finished, yes, because you hear all the commotion
going all night. Hammering and everything, all through the night. It was lit up
like a big city. With the three yards going, they had lights on because the
Japanese weren&#039;t going to bomb us any more. They had a hundred thousand people
working three shifts. It was just like a town on its own, noise and everything.

WASHBURN: Do you remember hearing those noises?

ONG: Yeah, you&#039;d hear the hammering on the metal of the ships.

WASHBURN: Did you hear that at school and at your home?

ONG: At school, and you hear it sometime at night, if they&#039;re really hammering.
Daytime, like I said, they had entertainment for the employees here, dance bands
and music and people singing, because that was the Big Band era.

WASHBURN: Why did you hear that music?

ONG: Because the school ground was only about a block away from it. We see all
the cars going in and out, and see the electric trains run. Right back of the
school they had a big platform. Then when I went to junior high, the war was
still on, you see all the buses downtown taking the workers to work.

WASHBURN: At what age did it strike you that all this activity was for something
really big?

ONG: When I first was eleven, twelve, it didn&#039;t dawn on me. When I was thirteen,
fourteen, I knew it was a big war on. Then I remember the big explosion in Port
Chicago--I was already going to junior high--on a Friday night. Next day, I
didn&#039;t know it, but I went over and one of my friends at school was selling
newspapers that had a big explosion at Port Chicago. That was July 1944 where it
blew up two ships and a railroad disappeared, never seen again, and blew up all
the barracks. Later--funny--in 1963, myself worked there as a grownup man.

WASHBURN: Port Chicago.

ONG: Yeah.

WASHBURN: At that age, what do you remember thinking about that explosion?

ONG: I thought it was something bad. Horrible. You could see the explosion and
hear it in the air, but you couldn&#039;t see it good.

WASHBURN: Did you see the smoke in the air?

ONG: I think it was a flash. You hear it, a little bit, up in the sky like an
atomic bomb would be, and that was then. We heard it about four or five or six
o&#039;clock at night. Then we turn the radio on and they mention a big explosion,
but them days, I didn&#039;t know where it was. We never had a car, so I never
traveled out of town. [laughs] Funny. Never knew where all those cities were. My
mother never had a car, she never liked to drive, so we always stuck just in the
Bay Area. And all the later years, I worked at all those places they mention.

WASHBURN: I&#039;d like to ask you about the construction activity. You weren&#039;t a
worker at the shipyards, but you were very close to the activity going on there
so you could kind of observe it from an outside point of view. For somebody who
doesn&#039;t know what was going on there, what would you tell them was one of the
most vivid memories that people living nearby the shipyards had?

ONG: Right across from the schoolhouse, they start building {Ellis Morelda?}
Village for the workers, and they built {Floyd Terrace?} on the side with the
sewage disposal. They had houses on tiers going up kind of like Vallejo did,
because they didn&#039;t have much room to build in the hills. Then, on the left
side, I used to deliver papers there when I was about thirteen, fourteen, but
Canal [Boulevard] housing came up, hundreds and hundreds of big buildings, kind
of like Hunters Point. Five or six families lived on decks, tiers, upstairs,
downstairs. They must have had about a hundred buildings. Then they had a row of
buildings just for the bachelor men. From then on, every empty lot in Richmond
had war housing on it. Later, I read in the paper they had 28,000 war housing.
So everywhere you went, you seen war housing that wasn&#039;t downtown. That area,
where the shipyard was, was hardly any people living there. It was all open land.

WASHBURN: What was there before they built the housing?

ONG: Nothing. People that owned the property never built. They only had two or
three houses on that side of the area. Most people lived in Point Richmond or
downtown Richmond itself, and that was all just open lots. But people owned
them; my aunt herself owned one, but she didn&#039;t want it back after the war. They
gave it back to her. They confiscated everybody&#039;s lot, and put housing on it.

WASHBURN: What do you remember about what natives were saying about all these
people coming into Richmond and all this activity? How can you describe it from
somebody who was raised there before the war?

ONG: It was okay with me, but the saying in them days and a lot of the native
Californians say it, it&#039;s not nice: &quot;Go back where you come from.&quot;

WASHBURN: So people did say that.

ONG: Oh, they did say it. Californians are kind of nasty people, when you look
at it. Even up north in those small counties, they don&#039;t care if you&#039;re from
down here. Like Amador; lot of people laugh when you hear them. You didn&#039;t have
to be some other color person, you were from some other state, they just always
say, &quot;Go back where you come from.&quot; That was a good slogan. [laughs] You tell
people, they&#039;re mystified. They faint.

WASHBURN: You said you went to Roosevelt Junior High in 1943.

ONG: I went from 1943 to 1945.

WASHBURN: When do you first remember as a student experiencing this influx of
people into the schools who weren&#039;t from Richmond? All these migrants?

ONG: A lot of the people that migrated, from memory, a lot of them didn&#039;t have
children. Later, they grew up after the war, but from what I observed and later
looking at newsreels and things, I think most of the people were single people.
They might have girlfriends or wives, but there weren&#039;t that much kids. Well,
they were little. My mother worked for a family, took care of kids, they were
only about two, three years old, so they weren&#039;t in the school when the war was.
They were later in grammar school, but by that time I already was grown up,
going to high school. There weren&#039;t that many really grownup kids. They didn&#039;t
bring very many older people, but I had some people when I went to grammar
school that came from Oklahoma. They were ten or eleven. [laughs] Here&#039;s a thing
that is going to shock you. The white kids used to chase them home every night,
throw rocks at them, because they were from Oklahoma. The only kid that defended
them was two boys. They were Catholic, and their mother didn&#039;t like that, so we
threw rocks at them too, even though we knew them. How do you like that for prejudice?

WASHBURN: Why was that?

ONG: Because they were poor. In those days, they had an awful expression, they
always call people that weren&#039;t born in California &quot;Okies&quot; or &quot;Arkies.&quot;

WASHBURN: Because they were from Oklahoma and Arkansas.

ONG: That&#039;s what people did. A lot of people think that they&#039;re prejudiced
against other races; they were prejudiced against white people themselves that
weren&#039;t born here. We used to chase them home. When you look back, that was kind
of bad. My mother never knew about it, but she would have been mad. We even had
two girls that joined in with us. How do you like that, David? That shocks
people when I tell them.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve heard that, a little bit. Do you think that was because--

ONG: All those people, they were brought up middle-class thinking. It&#039;s just
that the parents didn&#039;t know it, and they got the idea that the people that were
from another state were kind of dumb or they didn&#039;t fit in a pattern. You heard
that before, when you talk, huh? That&#039;s funny. I tell people I kind of think
it&#039;s funny, but I tell how people are.

WASHBURN: So the few kids that did come with their parents during the war, that
you knew in Roosevelt Junior High, did they stick to themselves?

ONG: I used to stick mostly with the kids I knew and a lot of the Mexicans. I
somehow blend in, because of the darker skin than the others, so I had a lot of
friends that were Mexicans and grew up in high school. And later years, I knew
them, too. I had friends from both sides, but I knew a lot of Mexicans, because
they tend to hang around themselves in them days. So I always got in with them.
They grew up and had good jobs. Because Mexicans, in them days, were frowned on.
They were like the Afro-Americans of nowadays, because Richmond didn&#039;t have a
big Afro-American population until after the war. The Mexicans were kind of like
a scapegoat because they all were laborers at Santa Fe and their parents didn&#039;t
speak English, even then. But the kids did pretty good.

WASHBURN: The Mexicans were the largest minority in Richmond before the war.

ONG: Yes, what you call minority. There probably weren&#039;t over two or three
hundred. But out of twenty thousand people, they were the minority of Richmond.
Because Richmond was a very conservative city, and as I grew up later I seen on
newsreels and Channel 2, they were the only city that allowed the Ku Klux Klan
to parade.

WASHBURN: Why do you think it was such a conservative city?

ONG: I don&#039;t know. I couldn&#039;t understand that, but on the papers, you read back
in history, they were very conservative, and they were very prejudiced. The
councilmen, everything. They were kind of like the racist people, the
supremacists back in the early century in the South. I was surprised when I read
that in the papers.

WASHBURN: How did that affect you when you were--

ONG: Because I lived in the Point, I never was over downtown, but I remember
there was a Chinese market in &#039;37, the people were trying to put it out of
business. I seen it in the paper in later years. They were picketing, said they
were nasty and they weren&#039;t clean, they wanted a Seventh Street market.

WASHBURN: About what year what was that?

ONG: In the late thirties, &#039;36 or &#039;37. The white people picketing in the market,
wanted to put it out of business. But it stayed and lasted until up to the
fifties. So it looked like they were very prejudiced in them days against
Asians, too.

WASHBURN: Did any folks ever tease you when you were younger?

ONG: No, because in the Point, my mother knew everybody. They were kind of more
friendlier, but downtown Richmond, I imagine, was kind of bad. But then, since I
don&#039;t live there, I never have seen those people.

WASHBURN: Can you describe a little bit the difference in the two societies
there? The folks that hung out in the Point and the folks that hung out in
Richmond? Was it divided?

ONG: Richmond was more business people, but they had a lot of Standard Oil
people. Most of them weren&#039;t old-timers. They were probably later people, came
in the twenties or something. Point people, most of them were descendants of the
people that was there when the city first started. But after the war, like now
all the people I know all came after the war, from Texas and Oklahoma. I mean,
they were friendly, but they were not native. Most of the natives have passed
away. Most of the people that were born there died in the seventies and
eighties, more and more.

WASHBURN: What was that like for you? It seems like you spent most of your time
as a child hanging out in the Point.

ONG: One thing is, when we was poor, there was a white lady called Mrs. {Lee?}.
She put us on kind of like a welfare thing, and we got free milk all the time,
because she knew my mother was unemployed. She had a lot of authority. One time
at school I remember, I was about seven years old, she called up the principal
of the school and said she had a fresh fish, and &quot;I want one of you boys to take
him home.&quot; So during the mid-day, even when the school was on, I had to go home
with one of the boys and bring the fish home. The school principal did it, so
she must have had a lot of influence in the Point.

In them days, my mother knew the police chief and my grandfather knew a
lieutenant down there, and when my grandfather died in &#039;44, my mother was
already divorced and my father always threatened to kidnap me, so she was afraid
he&#039;d kidnap me. So she went down and asked them, &quot;Is there a private detective I
can hire?&quot; The lieutenant said, &quot;Don&#039;t worry, we&#039;ll take care of it.&quot; Next day,
when my mother went back down to make sure, he said--I think the funeral was
somewhere middle of the week--next day, they had a police inspector to take me
over in a police car. Nowadays, they would have fired the whole department.
Turned out, the police inspector was the son of the police chief, Chief [L.E.] Jones.

WASHBURN: I was going to ask, Royce, what was that like for you? It seems like
you spent a lot of your time growing up as a boy in the Point. What was that
like for you then to go to Roosevelt Junior High, which was in Richmond proper?

ONG: I met more different races of people than I did in the Point.

WASHBURN: For someone who doesn&#039;t know where Roosevelt is, can you describe how
you went from your house at the Point?

ONG: You caught the 72 bus and went about a mile, and downtown Richmond, on A
Street on the right-hand side of Macdonald. It was a middle school, you call it
now, but in them days it was junior high. Up on Twenty-third Street they had
Longfellow, which was the middle school for the wealthy people of Mira Vista.
That half of town was 100 percent Caucasian people, and this was for the people
that were poor and the Point Richmond people.

WASHBURN: So Roosevelt was more the working-class school.

ONG: Yes. Longfellow was for the higher-class people. Mira Vista in them days
was like North Berkeley: real high-class, high-price, real deluxe homes, and it
still is to this day.

WASHBURN: When you were going to school there at Roosevelt, what can you
describe about the activity that you saw on the streets during the war?

ONG: It was very busy. You had about seven movie houses, and the movie houses
operate twenty-four hours. On Cutting, which is near where I lived, they had
about fifteen grocery stores. They stayed open all night and day. I heard in the
later years, I didn&#039;t know, but people slept in the all-night theaters, that
didn&#039;t have a place to sleep, when they were working at the shipyards. Then some
people, I heard, one trade the bed at daytime; at night somebody else took over
the bed. People with helmets were everywhere, the shipyard helmets. We seen
people and people.

But then the shipyard train brought in a lot of people from San Francisco and
Oakland. We used to go home with my mother after we shopped--we had to ride the
streetcar until Ashby Avenue, for the buses were saving gasoline and rubber
tires, so the 72 bus didn&#039;t go all the way to Oakland. At night, around nine or
ten o&#039;clock, you&#039;d hear the shipyard train go by with the little horn. They were
the elevator trains, about seven, eight cars. People smoke in the back, because
you&#039;re not allowed to smoke inside. Full of men and women going to the shipyard,
because the shipyard train went as far as Ninth Street in Berkeley, then it
turned toward the bay and went on the old Southern Pacific tracks and then over
to the shipyard railroad tracks.

WASHBURN: When did you ride the train with folks who were working at the shipyards?

ONG: Never did. All those years, I never did ride it. That was a shame. Always
rode the local, but never rode those. Just to ride it in daytime, to ride out
there. I always liked electric trains; I have never rode it. But I see the
people go by when I was on the other transportation.

WASHBURN: The shipyard workers didn&#039;t ride the local buses?

ONG: Local ran from downtown Richmond, but in Oakland all they used is the
trains. They ran the shipyard trains and they ran the regular modern articulated
trains, too, because they had steps. The shipyard trains had to stop at
platforms. You couldn&#039;t get out anywhere, if you lived in one of the war housing.

WASHBURN: You said your parents were divorced in the early 1940s. What did your
mom do? What was the first job that she got?

ONG: She always was a housekeeper all the time for people, clean houses and
cook, and took care of children. During the war, she managed to get a job for
three years at Standard Oil.

WASHBURN: I&#039;d like to spend five minutes talking about that, because I think
that&#039;s really important.

ONG: She worked in the marketing department.

WASHBURN: How did she get a job at Standard Oil?

ONG: She knew a councilman, Mr. {Tiller?} and another councilman, Mr. {Scott?}.
One worked at Standard Oil, and one was the owner of a trucking company, so they
had influence with Standard Oil. She asked them if they&#039;d hire her, so they got
permission to hire her. Because they&#039;d never hired anybody but Caucasian people.
So she was one of the only Chinese there. They put her in the marketing
department. She set up food and stuff for the Standard Oil ships. They had a
little streetcar going there. It went out during the fifties, but they load them
up and brought the food to the Standard Oil tankers.

WASHBURN: So why do you think your mom got a job there if the people who were
working there discriminated against her?

ONG: Well, it was a shortage of people and they needed help, so that was a good
reason they would hire her. They needed a woman there to do that kind of work.
With the war on, they needed all the help, so they can&#039;t discriminate and not
hire somebody. So she got a job there, but she lost it when the war was over,
because every place laid off, and the veterans got their jobs back. She worked
at only menial work, but she quit working in 1950 and I worked, too. She got
sick, so I went and got a job working for the government.

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s talk about how her job working there at Standard Oil during the
war, how that affected your life.

ONG: We had a lot of money, and we put electricity and gas in the house, and did
a lot of building on the house. Later, when I worked, we had enough money to put
a full foundation of concrete around the house, and steps. Modernize the house some.

WASHBURN: Prior to the war--

ONG: She was only making about sixty dollars a month doing her little jobs.

WASHBURN: So you guys were rather poor.

ONG: Yeah, really. We were really poor. Now, you&#039;re poor, you go and ask for
welfare and they pay your house rent and food, but them days it was never heard
of. My mother never bothered to ask my uncles. She didn&#039;t want to ask them for
help, so she just had a little job all the time. So my poor mother really worked
hard to bring me up. My father never gave us any--what do you call it--he didn&#039;t
send any money. He didn&#039;t do it, and you couldn&#039;t get him to do it.

WASHBURN: Do you remember how much she was getting paid there at Standard Oil?

ONG: Standard Oil, I don&#039;t know what. I think they paid about seventy-five cents
an hour, or something less than that. I don&#039;t know what the wage was. I think
the shipyards paid a dollar an hour. Eight dollars a day, but a lot of them
worked overtime and, let&#039;s say, they got rich off it.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve read that that wasn&#039;t just the case for your family, that many
families were poorer during the Depression, and once jobs came around in the war
their livelihood really improved.

ONG: Yeah, they went to the shipyard and really made money, and a lot of them
bought--some of them--down below. Miss {Moxley?} my mother knew real well,
worked at the shipyard, her and her husband worked a lot of overtime. They
bought some apartment houses. From the forties, fifties, sixties until they
moved back to Kansas, they had rental property. A lot of them did that. They
bought up old property and rented them. The ones that did save their money, that
didn&#039;t go back to Oklahoma or something.

WASHBURN: How did you feel once your mom started working at Standard Oil?

ONG: Didn&#039;t mean much. We just had a decent job, and finally had electricity in
the house.

WASHBURN: What did you do before you had electricity?

ONG: We used kerosene and coal. [laughs] So I was like people living on the
farm, so I had both ends of it. To this day, everybody laughs: &quot;You know how it
was to be poor; you know how to be middle class.&quot;

WASHBURN: Did your neighbors have electricity?

ONG: Yes. I think we were one of a few houses. One more family there, but they
had a good job. I don&#039;t know why they had it, but we were about the only ones
that still lived like on the farm. My father had a chance to put electricity in
for eighteen dollars but he told the local electrician that he was robbing him.

WASHBURN: If your mother didn&#039;t speak English so well--

ONG: She spoke English good.

WASHBURN: Oh, by the time she got a job there she spoke English?

ONG: She always had a good English vocabulary. She was good in spelling and
everything else. The only thing, her downfall was she never finished school. She
only went to third grade and she was not good in mathematics. But spelling, she
was great, and she really wrote good. To this day, people are amazed at her
handwriting. And she really knew how to spell. I had to ask her. My spelling was
never that great, but I got better by using a dictionary.

WASHBURN: Do you remember her telling you any stories about discrimination she
felt working at Standard Oil, that people treated her differently?

ONG: No. She used to walk down with some of the ladies that worked there. They
came during the war, and got along real good. She knew everybody in town. They
grew up with her. She didn&#039;t go to school with them; they grew up later and they
knew each other, all through my grandfather. My grandfather was very smart. He
knew algebra and things. One family behind us that lived there, his son used to
take care of my mother. When she was divorced, we moved into that house and
lived there six months until we finally got my father out of her house. He
wouldn&#039;t move. In them days it was hard to get anybody evicted, so when the
papers came the marshal come and told him he had to leave. So we lived in a big
fancy house up on the hill, owned by Mrs. Brown, whose husband was a civil
engineer for Standard Oil. So I have to say I&#039;ve lived in a real fancy house in
my lifetime, for six months. It was a real good house.

WASHBURN: Your family was really connected within Point Richmond.

ONG: My grandfather was there. He didn&#039;t stay long, but his name was known and
everybody knew him.

WASHBURN: He was there since the beginning.

ONG: Yeah. All the firemen knew my late aunt, too. She one time had a little
restaurant there. Most of the people knew my grandfather. All the shopkeepers,
when my mother used to visit them, came back to who her father was. They all
knew her, so she always stopped by to talk to them.

WASHBURN: So he was a real pioneer.

ONG: Yeah, she knew the German guy that owned the liquor store, selling beer and
things. She knew the Jewish guy that was a clothier. She knew a lot of people in
town. My great-aunt knew the firemen in the firehouse, so they used to ask how
my great-aunt was doing. I said, &quot;She&#039;s living in the city now.&quot; They asked me
if my great-aunt was my aunt, and I said &quot;Yes.&quot; The judge remembered my
grandmother owning the Republic Café, over where BART is now. There used to be
a street on the right-hand side and there was a little district until the
fifties, and they tore it down. She owned a Chinese restaurant open twenty-four
hours a day.

WASHBURN: Growing up, what was your contact with other Chinese?

ONG: None, except for my relatives coming to see me. There was not another
Chinese family in Point Richmond, even a café or anything. Outside of my own
relatives, I never had seen another Chinese.

WASHBURN: How often would you guys go back to San Francisco to visit?

ONG: Well, my aunts and uncles come over to see me, see my mother all the time.
But my mother, after the divorce in 1940, we never seen my father&#039;s side of the
family at all.

WASHBURN: Did you go over to San Francisco often?

ONG: Used to, once a year when my grandmother and grandfather had a birthday. It
was protocol, everybody come over to the birthday party. That was the only time
I ever went to the city. So my recollection of San Francisco is: I remember
riding the ferryboats, and I remember the Sacramento Street cable car, because
my grandfather had a house right on Wentworth Street, right across the street
from Portsmouth Square, and the Sacramento cable car ran down Sacramento Street
and Clay Street, so we&#039;d just walk a block and rode the ferry home.

WASHBURN: Where did the ferry go in Richmond?

ONG: They first had one come down to Ferry Point, the Yosemite, but that went
out in &#039;36. Not enough riders. So we had to either ride the five-minute ferry on
the end of Broadway, which was five cents. Even with the fare of ten cents, it
was still cheap enough for my father to get us over there.

WASHBURN: Broadway in Oakland.

ONG: Yeah, that was the five-minute ferry. Southern Pacific ran it, but lot of
times, we came back on the Key System, which ran the electric train. They had a
pier that went two miles out in the open bay, right underneath the Bay Bridge.

WASHBURN: What did your relatives who were coming over to Point Richmond think
about you guys living there?

ONG: My mother&#039;s side didn&#039;t know we were poor, but my father&#039;s side, he used to
make fun of us. He said, &quot;Boy, this is a mansion on Golden Gate Avenue. You have
a castle here.&quot;

WASHBURN: Even though the house was small?

ONG: He used to say that. That was to make fun that we were the poorest house on
the corner.

WASHBURN: Oh, he was making fun of you.

ONG: Yeah, but that was my uncle on my father&#039;s side.

WASHBURN: What did they say about you guys being Chinese and not living in a
Chinese neighborhood? Did they think this was strange?

ONG: They never liked it much, because my mother never liked Chinatown. They
always said, &quot;Your mother&#039;s funny. She never liked Chinese.&quot;

WASHBURN: Why do you think that was it?

ONG: I think because the Chinese, she&#039;d never associate with them. Funny, huh?
My uncles always knew that, but she never cared for them and was glad to move
right out of there fast. Her friends always were Caucasian people.

WASHBURN: So she felt very comfortable living outside the Chinese community.

ONG: No. I&#039;m so Western that even to this day, people say that you act like a
Western person.

WASHBURN: Well, you&#039;re third generation here, yeah?

ONG: Yeah. I mean, I&#039;m not a prejudiced person, but I know there&#039;s other races
of people. Well, let&#039;s say I look at you just the same as anybody else. But I
don&#039;t look at you that I like you because you&#039;re a Caucasian. In my case, I was
brought up that I never looked down on other people either. So I can associate
with anybody and act like them, and they like me because I act like them. But
then, I was born where it was nobody but Caucasian people, and I&#039;m kind of like
a person that was adopted and he has a white family that adopts him, like Asian
girls or boys. They grew up. The family kind of grows on them. Like, you know,
they take orphan kids from Asia, or some people raise up Afro-American kids and
you say that you&#039;re a family, they&#039;re like you. So I grew up with Caucasian
people, so I like Western culture, I like their museums, I like football, I do
everything that most people do. Some don&#039;t like it, think it&#039;s a shame. Some
people always like to go back to the homeland, and that&#039;s why I think people get
prejudiced, because they don&#039;t act like them, they don&#039;t want to do things like them.

Like some of these people now, the poor Muslim people. They have their own
culture and they always get down and pray, but most people in America are
Christians. Don&#039;t you think so, David? And they act kind of strange, and they
wonder why people don&#039;t like them, because they don&#039;t want to act like the other
people. I always got my idea of &quot;you&#039;re in America, act like an American.&quot;
You&#039;ve been to Europe; somebody told me that if you don&#039;t speak their language
they tell you to get out of town. What did you find out in other countries? If
you don&#039;t speak their language, they kind of bounce you out?

[begin file Ong2 01-15-03.wav]

WASHBURN: I wanted to talk to you also about growing up in Richmond and what you
remember about the Japanese internment. Let me describe first: when did you
first remember knowing that the Japanese were being interned?

ONG: I really didn&#039;t know. We didn&#039;t have a radio. We didn&#039;t get radio until my
mother put electricity in, about &#039;42 or &#039;43. When I was younger, I heard about
the Japanese were--I really didn&#039;t know about it, because I was that young, I
didn&#039;t read the newspaper. My mother or father probably read it. We had to wear
a badge for a while, but that didn&#039;t last long. It said, &quot;I&#039;m Chinese.&quot; But
being without a radio, we didn&#039;t know much about what was going on.

WASHBURN: You don&#039;t remember seeing stuff in the newspaper about it?

ONG: No. Never much was a newspaper reader when I was young. That was too bad. I
knew in later years that they were in there, but when they went in there, didn&#039;t
know a darn thing about it.

WASHBURN: You had mentioned the first time we met, about Chinese people making
clear to people that they were not Japanese.

ONG: Yeah, they had little pins that say, &quot;I&#039;m Chinese.&quot;

WASHBURN: Why did they wear those?

ONG: People in Chinatown would make them and sell them, to make sure they didn&#039;t
pick on them because they thought they were Japanese, because most Caucasian
people didn&#039;t know the difference.

WASHBURN: Did your mom ever have to wear one of those?

ONG: She wore it a little while, but I don&#039;t think too long. She never went over
to the main part of town or anything. But after March of &#039;42, all of the
Japanese were in internment camps, so there was nobody but Chinese. Wasn&#039;t that
the date? I think for sure it was March.

WASHBURN: March of &#039;42.

ONG: That was the end of it. Why wear pins when they were already gone? They
couldn&#039;t distinguish the two different people.

WASHBURN: Did folks ever say anything to you about being Chinese? Did they ever
confuse you with being someone of Japanese descent?

ONG: No. My mother definitely looks it. Most people always thought my mother
looked like Indo-Chinese, because she had different eyes and features, but she wasn&#039;t.

WASHBURN: The Japanese invaded mainland China in the early thirties. What do you
remember your mom saying when you were growing up about Japan?

ONG: She never spoke much politics, but on my family&#039;s side, they were always
mad about the Japanese. But my mother never made issues of anything.

WASHBURN: How were they mad?

ONG: They just didn&#039;t think much of them. They wouldn&#039;t buy their goods, and to
this day--when my great-aunt passed away in 1983, she wouldn&#039;t buy anything made
in Japan. Which was untrue; she probably bought a TV and didn&#039;t know it, or
didn&#039;t care, but she wouldn&#039;t buy anything that had &quot;Japan-made&quot; on it. She was
the only person I knew that was still alive that was up in age that was from
that era, because the rest of the people were like my cousins. They were just
young like me.

My cousins, we have a big age range in my family. Some of my cousins are twenty
years older than me, so when World War II come, one of my cousins--the only one
still alive--I don&#039;t know how he did it, he was Chinese, but he was a bombardier
on the planes flying out of England. He was an officer. Them days, they were
called &quot;master sergeant&quot; because--I read a lot on airplanes--they had a shortage
of officers so a lot of enlisted men only had enlisted men titles. He was a
master sergeant. I know a man down the street who was a navigator-radioman. He
was a master sergeant. Most of them were supposed to be second lieutenants, but
they didn&#039;t give them that title. They were like the navy, had chief petty
officer fliers. They flew airplanes like a regular officer, but they weren&#039;t
that rank. So he flew over Germany.

WASHBURN: This is in your family.

ONG: Yeah, he was with, I don&#039;t know which bomber squad, the Eighth or the
Ninth. They were all coming out of Germany in those days, B-17s. He served, and
then I had another cousin that died in the Battle of the Bulge.

WASHBURN: Growing up, a lot of people called World War II the Japanese War. Some
people do. They don&#039;t even call it World War II. Some people just refer to it as
the war with Japan.

ONG: Yeah, Pearl Harbor. &quot;World War II&quot; didn&#039;t come out until after the war, to
differentiate it from World War I. That was the war with Japan. &quot;World War II&quot;
was after the war was over and history come up, they had to put the &quot;II&quot; on it.

WASHBURN: So when you were growing up, did you refer to it as the war with Japan?

ONG: Yeah. We remembered Pearl Harbor. Songs, everybody would talk about it, and
everything that flashed through the war said &quot;Remember Pearl Harbor!&quot; or
pictured a Japanese or something. We knew we were fighting in Germany too, but
this end of the country was definitely Japan, because all the soldiers going out
of Fort Mason and everything was going to fight in the Pacific. We always know
this as the Pacific War. All my relatives got called up and they went to the
European War.

WASHBURN: They did? They didn&#039;t fight in the Pacific?

ONG: All we knew were fighting the Germans.

WASHBURN: What do you remember about the patriotic sentiment in the Chinese
community? Do you remember?

ONG: Before Japan attacked us, they used to collect what they called the &quot;rice
bowl.&quot; &#039;37, &#039;38, &#039;39, they collect money for China, in Chinatown itself. We
never participated in it, but I knew they did it, because you go to Chinatown
and you see those jars and they had big things they collect money in for China.

WASHBURN: To fight against Japan.

ONG: Yeah, to fight against Japan. Then my father, when you think of it, he did
have a little job working for some airplane company in San Francisco, building
components for airplanes for China, but I never know, because I never asked him.
I don&#039;t know which company it was or what type of plane, but we did sell some of
the minor planes that wasn&#039;t used in the air force to China itself.

WASHBURN: This is before World War II.

ONG: Yeah.

WASHBURN: So the sentiment in the Chinese community--

ONG: Were against Japan way before everybody else was.

WASHBURN: Exactly.

ONG: Because I remember reading history: Lindbergh thought the yellow race was
the worst people in the world until the war come and he had to fight Germany.
Hitler gave him medals. Lindbergh was a patriotic American, but he didn&#039;t think
much of the yellow race.

WASHBURN: Growing up, were you--

ONG: I never seen him.

WASHBURN: Sure, but growing up, when do you think you became aware that in some
ways the Chinese community was allied with the once-discriminatory white
community in fighting against the Japanese?

ONG: Because I remember we had relatives, a friend in Oakland, that had
newspapers mentioning it, how they were collecting money and everything. Then
you hear it from the American newspapers too, that they were collecting money.
Not too much. Most of it, I learned later years in history. Well, I knew they
were collecting money for China, because that was the popular sentiment in
Chinatown, against the Japanese. Then the Japanese attacked China twice, &#039;33 and
then in &#039;37, the main war. So I&#039;m a war historian, because I read all about wars
all through the centuries. I know a lot about airplanes, too. When people ask
me, &quot;How do you know all that?&quot; I say, &quot;I read up on it,&quot; even though I wasn&#039;t
there. I mean, I was there but I wasn&#039;t that old. I kind of amaze people when I
tell them what they want to know. All through World War II. They&#039;ll ask me about
airplanes. I know all about it.

WASHBURN: Do you remember what it was like when the war ended?

ONG: Kids downtown were selling, &quot;Extra! Extra! The war&#039;s over in Germany!&quot; Then
when Japan was on the radio, everybody celebrated, but I wasn&#039;t in San Francisco
where all the sailors from Camp Shoemaker--they used to all make fun of them.
They were guys that never went overseas, but they did most of the damage ripping
everything up. There was a camp near Livermore called Camp Shoemaker and they
were processing all these sailors, and they went down toward the town. But just
like the paper says, they never went overseas any time. They had all the
streetcars, they yanked the trolley poles down and stopped all the streetcars.
To this day I wish I had a lot of pictures of them, because the newspapers
showed a lot of pictures of it in them days. And the shipyard laid everybody
off. Unemployment started real bad in &#039;48. Couldn&#039;t hardly find work.

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s talk about that. The shipyards started laying people off in &#039;45.

ONG: Yeah. There was unemployment all the way up to &#039;48.

WASHBURN: There was unemployment how?

ONG: Around the government installations, because I had a man that worked for me
in Camp Stoneman and he had to go over to Guam to work. Those years, the sheet
metal men. He was laid off, and he couldn&#039;t find any local work. He was still in
the service but couldn&#039;t find local work.

WASHBURN: How did you notice the changes that were taking place in Richmond
after the war? I mean, immediately. You entered Richmond High in about what year?

ONG: &#039;46, the year after the war. School didn&#039;t change much.

WASHBURN: When did you, as a young man, start noticing the changes that were
taking place in Richmond?

ONG: After they closed the housing down, more and more people were moving into
town. There was minorities, and the white population were moving out. Because
when I went to school, graduated in &#039;49, downtown Richmond still had a white
population. A lot of the schoolgirls and boys were still living downtown. I
didn&#039;t think about it until later years, what happened, because I never think
about those things. But later years, I thought about a lot of the school kids
that used to live on Chancellor over there, and their addresses--they weren&#039;t
there. They moved out to the suburbs, El Sobrante. A lot of the kids that grew
up with me in the fifties moved to El Sobrante. That&#039;s still there; it was more
of a farmland. They got out of proper Richmond. A lot of my Mexican friends
moved out there. They got married and they moved out there. Some moved to
Hayward. So Richmond lost a lot of the original population.

WASHBURN: Why do you think that was?

ONG: They&#039;re prejudiced. [laughs] I don&#039;t know what you want me to say. They
were prejudiced people. It wasn&#039;t because they had more money; they were
prejudiced and didn&#039;t want to be living there. They were, kind of. Because
Mexicans, growing up as a kid, Mexican people and blacks never got along too
good. I know a lady that had a woman that cleaned her house, but during the war
she got a job as supervisor at Santa Fe, on the trains. She was a black lady,
and she didn&#039;t think much of the Mexican workers.

WASHBURN: We can speculate what other people think, but what was it like for you
when you started interacting with more black people in Richmond?

ONG: My mother was always liberal. Never had that trouble. She liked everybody.
So in my case, I never was taught to dislike other people. Never did to this
day; never will. My mother was friendly, liked everybody, so I was taught up. My
grandfather believed in the Golden Rule.

WASHBURN: What was that?

ONG: That was a Ten Commandments-like, everybody used to use. He was very
religious and the Ten Commandments--I imagine it&#039;s like the Bible thing. You
treat everybody as he is due, and all those things. I don&#039;t remember every verse
of it, but--

WASHBURN: What was the first time you remember hanging out with black people in town?

ONG: Over at junior high, but I didn&#039;t hang around them. They were there. I
never hang around them even in high school. But I hang around when I started
working with them; I rode with them, I went to their houses. I got along with
them real good. They&#039;re my best friends, were black people, and some of them I
visited their widows, until they passed away too.

WASHBURN: In the schools, though, did you notice that people mixed, or was it separate?

ONG: No. Just like even to this day, they all sat in their own place.

WASHBURN: How so?

ONG: When I work at the navy, and that was the eighties, the black people sat in
one corner, the white people sat in the other, even in modern times.

WASHBURN: What was it like in the Richmond schools in the forties, though?

ONG: There weren&#039;t that many black children, but like I said, they were all
little kids. There was only a few--well, maybe less than a hundred grownup kids
that were black, I mean school-age.

WASHBURN: In the high schools.

ONG: Very little. Now, there&#039;s 60, 70 percent. But then, the regular kids that
grew up, they were just little three- or four- or five-year-old kids,
six-year-olds, so they weren&#039;t in my classes. I knew there was a lot more after
the war, but they were not old enough to be in high school. So Richmond High in
the late forties had a very small black population. Most of them came from North
Richmond, which is a predominately black area, which is still now. Because what
happened was, when they closed the war housing down, a lot of them moved to
other cities.

WASHBURN: What do you remember about the changes in the war housing? You
described the construction of the war housing; what do you remember about the
destruction of the war housing?

ONG: When they tore it down? What happened was, an awful thing happened. The
city manager of Richmond, can&#039;t remember his name, he went back to Washington
and asked permission to rip the war housing down. When he went back there--this
was years later when I read up on it, because I was young--Washington told him,
&quot;When we want those war housing ripped down, we&#039;ll tell you.&quot; The theory was, if
you rip the war housing down, the blacks had to move out of Richmond, which was
a boomerang because they ended up buying all the housing downtown, and didn&#039;t
move out. But the Richmond council&#039;s theory was, if the housing are gone, the
blacks have no place to live, because that&#039;s when the restriction law was still
around, so the blacks weren&#039;t allowed to buy into certain areas.

WASHBURN: So they wouldn&#039;t have been able to buy anywhere.

ONG: Yeah. So they thought that was it. It didn&#039;t work.

WASHBURN: They thought that that would get rid of them?

ONG: Yeah. It was in all the newspapers when he went back there. Blacks were
always segregated in the war housing, too. They lived in one end of Canal;
whites lived in another end. The black area was kept longer because they didn&#039;t
have no place to go, but the whites&#039; were already torn down. So they had
segregated housing, even like back East, in some of the federal housing.

WASHBURN: So you don&#039;t think that the migration and all the people that moved in
really affected the school system until when?

ONG: Until after the kids started getting school-age.

WASHBURN: When was that?

ONG: I would say most of them started getting older around the fifties. That&#039;s
when Richmond High started losing a lot of its population, moving out. Late
fifties, &#039;52, &#039;53, &#039;54. That&#039;s when a lot of them moved out. Thirteen, fourteen.
The Korean War, that&#039;s when the school started getting more minorities in. They
were grown up by then. Because California had very little minorities up this
area except for Oakland. Oakland was known as the little Detroit.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s what they called it. You graduated Richmond High in what year?

ONG: Spring of &#039;49. They were slowly coming into the lower grades, but not
enough to really say. It was still an all-white school.

WASHBURN: For the most part, still all white.

ONG: El Cerrito was an all-white school until about the sixties. That grew out
of the Richmond School District. Then they opened another high school. [Harry]
Ells became a high school during the war, but that was pretty near the war was
over. That&#039;s still there. It&#039;s now a middle school. Then Longfellow always was
white. Ninety-nine percent; there was hardly any Mexicans even there. That was
ripped down, they put up Harry Ells. So Roosevelt was the longest one with
minorities in it. They shut it down to become Gompers Continuation School in the
seventies. It&#039;s for people that drop out, and they try to get a high school education.

WASHBURN: You said that you noticed people in Richmond moving out to El Sobrante--

ONG: Concord--

WASHBURN: In about what time, would you say?

ONG: Oh, in the fifties. Big mess. That&#039;s why Concord grew up so big. They all
went to central Contra Costa.

WASHBURN: Where did these people who moved out--as best you can remember, where
did they keep their jobs?

ONG: A lot of them already had jobs somewhere else. Some of the kids I knew
owned service stations up on Solano Avenue. There weren&#039;t too many worked in
Richmond subsequently, worked for Standard. There weren&#039;t too many
manufacturing, even, so a lot of them work other places. They just happen to
have been born here, they stayed here; but when they got old enough, they moved
out on their own. Some of them still had their parents living here, like my good
friend who owned a barbershop. He moved to Napa. He used to have a good house on
McBryde, but his wife was a Caucasian woman, she didn&#039;t want to stay in Richmond
anymore, so she left. Funny thing: a lot of people that moved away from Point
Richmond in the fifties--they were older people--they came back in the
seventies, because that was the in place to live.

WASHBURN: But this move to the suburbs did not affect Point Richmond very much?

ONG: No. A lot of the younger people moved out, but a lot of the older people
from other places stayed, from the shipyard days.

WASHBURN: For people who don&#039;t know Point Richmond so well, why did that move to
the suburbs affect Richmond more than it affected Point Richmond?

ONG: Point Richmond, a lot of them were Californians that never go anywhere.
Californians used to have a habit of never moving out of their own property. I
read an article once--up to the late sixties, 70 percent of Californians never
went out of the state. They stuck to their home, until later when the airplane
come around. It was amazing to hear that.

WASHBURN: So the community was more established in Point Richmond?

ONG: Yeah, established to this day. The only community I ever hear of you can
still walk the streets without getting scared at night. That&#039;s why everybody
loved it. One time, Washington School was going to close, not enough students.
Then they brought in a lot of minority students so they make up 30, 40 percent
of it now. They bus them in.

WASHBURN: When did they start tearing down war housing along Cutting?

ONG: All along the fifties. They really went fast. The government owned them;
they got out of it. They kept a few war housing on Fourteenth Street and one
over on Lincoln Avenue is the only reminder of the war years.

WASHBURN: Atchison Village, also.

ONG: The Richmond Housing Authority took them over in Easter Hill. But Easter
Hill was not a government project; it was later built. So those were the only
three projects that you can say were from the war years. All the rest were
demolished and gone.

WASHBURN: What do you remember about the activity to take apart those houses?

ONG: Just that to me, the war was over, so it didn&#039;t really dawn on me. The
shipyard people weren&#039;t there, so they had to tear them down. Later, industry
shot up there; now there&#039;s all this high-tech industry.

WASHBURN: Right after they tore them down in the fifties, what did they--

ONG: Nothing, just empty lots.

WASHBURN: They were empty lots.

ONG: Richmond was really hurting. They didn&#039;t have anything to take those
properties, and high-tech didn&#039;t come in until the late sixties and seventies.
So they had a lot of--no work; there was nothing there, just open land.

WASHBURN: So if you would have driven around Richmond in the fifties--

ONG: Oh, it was nothing. After the shipyard left, it was kind of a town that
fell apart. It was just residential. It&#039;s still running, a part. A lot of
businesses come in, but they don&#039;t live there. But the town itself was just
nothing. That&#039;s why it was always called a shipyard town.

WASHBURN: Can you remember how all of the postwar change affected the commercial
areas in town?

ONG: Downtown was still vibrant, because the malls were never built yet. So
people from all the surrounding areas used to come down to Richmond. We had five
or six blocks of stores. We had Ward&#039;s, we had Gallenkamps, Woolworth, Kress. It
had Breuners, Kahn&#039;s Shoes, which is nationwide. We had Anita&#039;s, a nationwide
store. They had all the nation&#039;s big stores or franchises all around the country there.

WASHBURN: Travellini&#039;s also?

ONG: Yeah, Travellini&#039;s, but they went out when they had that riot in 1969.

WASHBURN: I&#039;d like to talk about that later on, but for people who don&#039;t know,
where were all those businesses located?

ONG: They disappeared when Richmond thought they could redevelop downtown.

WASHBURN: But where were they located originally?

ONG: They went up to El Cerrito Plaza. El Cerrito Plaza was supposed to come to
Richmond. Richmond didn&#039;t want it, they said it was going to hurt downtown.

WASHBURN: I mean, where was that business district in Richmond?

ONG: Right down Macdonald Avenue, the full length of it. That&#039;s one of the
longer streets in the Bay Area for downtown. Went from Fifty-fifth Street to
First Street.

WASHBURN: There was businesses all along there?

ONG: Only from Fourth Street all the way up to Sixteenth was the main part of
town. Twenty-third had another district. That&#039;s what still survives. On San
Pablo Avenue is the only residual of a district in Richmond. The rest is just a
little shopping center came in ten years ago.

WASHBURN: How can you describe to somebody the process of those businesses
moving out of Richmond?

ONG: It was bad. The city tried to rebuild, but they tore every building down
and left it looking like a war zone. People laughed. It looked like a war had
been there. Empty lots everywhere. Every major street had empty lots. All the
major stores were gone. The last ones to leave were Macy&#039;s and [JC] Penney. They
went up to Hilltop [Mall]. Penney&#039;s hang on the longest. I think Woolworth did
too, but Woolworth started closing the basement up, and you knew suddenly what
was going on. Then after that, was not a major store in town until 1989 or &#039;90,
FoodCo came in. That&#039;s about the only one. Walgreens, FoodCo, and little stores
that minorities operate was the only thing still left. They&#039;re surviving,
because a lot of Latinos moved in from Mexico, and Afro-Americans go there, so
they&#039;re doing pretty fair.

WASHBURN: When did all this change take place? When did the change of the
businesses like Breuners--

ONG: &#039;69, &#039;70, when the city redeveloped and bought everybody out. In other
words, they bought them out and forced them out.

WASHBURN: Why did they do that?

ONG: They thought a developer was going to come in. Some man from southern
California was going to build a big mall, but a city mall with pedestrian
bridges between the major streets. Later he found out that the people that were
middle class do not come down to Richmond. Even Ward&#039;s, which has a nice store
on Forty-second Street, lost 80 percent of its middle-class people. Even today,
it&#039;s closed. Nobody come in there but local people.

WASHBURN: When was Hilltop Mall established?

ONG: 1975.

WASHBURN: So all these businesses moved out of downtown--

ONG: No, they went to El Portal first. It was a little shopping center in San
Pablo. A lot of the men&#039;s stores moved up there, and women&#039;s stores. Then they
were doing pretty good, and then they themselves went out of business.

WASHBURN: So the central shopping area moved down to San Pablo for a while.

ONG: Yeah. The Safeway used to be on Twenty-third. Had a nice Safeway; it&#039;s a
Grand Auto now. It moved up to the end of town near El Cerrito, on San Pablo and
Macdonald. So that&#039;s where Lucky&#039;s is. Outside of FoodCo coming in, there was no
major store downtown at all. Then when Penney&#039;s left, that was the end of it.
Downtown, once in a while I go there, because my barber&#039;s there and I go to
Walgreens, but 90 percent of the people from the Point goes over to Marin County
to shop, or go up to El Cerrito.

WASHBURN: Even when you were going to high school, up until &#039;49, do you remember
having friends in school who, one day they were there, then the next day they
had moved away?

ONG: A lot of them. Their families moved up. Some moved up to Marysville area,
or moved completely out of the Bay Area.

WASHBURN: This was even in the late forties.

ONG: Yeah. The family moved, moved up more to the country estate. Lot of them
already had country homes to begin with.

WASHBURN: Can you think of someone you knew who did that? The story of a friend
of yours?

ONG: I don&#039;t know, I don&#039;t keep up with them. [laughs] The Hudson family moved
out. They moved up to Colusa or something, but I never kept up too much with the
people who left. If they left, they left.

WASHBURN: As best you can remember, what was the Hudsons&#039; story?

ONG: The mother and father had a fair job. They were kind of poor, but they
weren&#039;t that poor. They rented. They didn&#039;t have a fabulous job; they didn&#039;t own
a home. They were the only ones I knew who rented. They had two brothers and a
sister. But they left early; after the war they all moved out of Point Richmond.
One time there was a big exodus from Point Richmond because the homes were old
and they all want the newer, 1940s-style home. Stucco, big windows. Then, the
funniest thing--I always laugh nowadays--everybody coming back that could come back.

WASHBURN: What can you describe about that feeling, that people wanted to have
these newer homes.

ONG: Oh, I felt they were lucky to get out. We never worried about it, but they
left, everybody I knew. Hardly anybody I knew anymore. To this day, I don&#039;t
hardly know just a few families from my era. Ninety-nine percent are new people.
Or some that didn&#039;t have kids my age--they were little kids--now I know them,
but some were my age, they came from the South or something to work in the war
years. Some didn&#039;t come until after the war.

WASHBURN: You had mentioned in Richmond that there weren&#039;t many Chinese folks there.

ONG: No, as far as I know.

WASHBURN: When did they start coming?

ONG: Around &#039;49, &#039;50, a lot of them when they started letting them immigrate
again. A lot of the families started coming in, opening grocery stores. They
weren&#039;t the owners themselves, but they were the workers they hire to work for
them, probably at a low wage or something. There was a couple Chinese markets
called Food Bowl, where they had a two-store chain. They were the big stores in
downtown Richmond and out there near San Pablo.

WASHBURN: Food Bowl was a Chinese-owned store?

ONG: Yes. It was a very big store, too. They brought in one Chinese boy, he was
younger than me. I had to take him around school all the time because he didn&#039;t
speak English.

WASHBURN: Tell me about that. Who was he?

ONG: I can&#039;t remember the boy&#039;s name, but I had to show him around and
everything. Since he didn&#039;t know anybody else, he always hang around with me. I
already was a senior; he was just a freshman.

WASHBURN: In high school?

ONG: Yeah. So when I left, that was it. He was on his own.

WASHBURN: Did you guys speak Cantonese together?

ONG: I tried to understand him, and I managed to figure out what he talked
about, but I wasn&#039;t that much on Chinese. Very bad. This day, I&#039;ve kind of
forgot all of it, because I never spoke to anybody after that in Chinese after
my mother died.

WASHBURN: How did your family meet his family?

ONG: Didn&#039;t know them. Only knew this guy through school and I knew where he
worked at. We didn&#039;t know them at all, except for the boy himself. His father
and him worked the store. They came from China. After school he would work there
too. He was not the major family. One of the girls in my school, same grade as
me, was the owner&#039;s daughter, but they spoke good English so they must have been
here years ago.

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s talk about what happened after you graduated high school.
Graduated in &#039;49--

ONG: I went to City College one year. My mother couldn&#039;t work, so I worked at a
department store at Christmastime, the Dollar Store. It was downtown. Just
worked a few months. Never liked the job, because the owner happened to be a
relative of my mother&#039;s through marriage and he didn&#039;t care for me. There was a
man there that was learning to be a manager, he said, &quot;This isn&#039;t a job for you.
You ought to go and work for the government.&quot; So I started taking government tests.

WASHBURN: Did you move over to the city?

ONG: No, I still lived there. Took government tests and became a government
employee for thirty-six and a half years.

WASHBURN: Took the civil service exam.

ONG: And passed. Them days was before affirmative action. In them days, you had
to go out and compete. They didn&#039;t say, &quot;We want ten of this and ten of that.&quot; I
always passed the test real high.

WASHBURN: Before I ask you about that, you mentioned that you worked for the
Dollar Store because your mom couldn&#039;t work.

ONG: My mother worked a while. Then she got sick, couldn&#039;t work. The guy that
ran the store, the manager, was a relative of my mother&#039;s. He was her in-law, my
mother&#039;s brother&#039;s wife was his wife. So he hired me for a few months. I worked
there, and then went to the government.

WASHBURN: You had mentioned that a lot of things changed when your mom got a job
at Standard Oil. How did your life change once the war ended?

ONG: We had electricity and gas come in. We already had running water, but never
had electricity and gas. That was a big difference than having coal oil and coal
to cook.

WASHBURN: Sure, but once the war ended she lost her job.

ONG: Yes, but we already had the modern conveniences, considered modern. Before,
we were living like on a farm back in the 1900s. That makes a big difference.
People that don&#039;t have electricity, like the poor homeless guy living in the
street, you know how it is. You don&#039;t have no modern convenience. Then we had a
radio, but didn&#039;t have TV until later. My mother never liked TV, so we never
bought a TV. So I didn&#039;t get one until &#039;58.

WASHBURN: How did you guys make do after the war, after she stopped working at
Standard Oil?

ONG: My mother did menial work and cashed in a lot of her bonds. We survived,
though. Then when I got a job, she didn&#039;t have to work any more.

WASHBURN: You supported her.

ONG: Yeah, she was very sick. She died at fifty-four years old.

WASHBURN: What year was that?

ONG: In 1958. Like people say, she died at a very early age.

WASHBURN: You were young; you weren&#039;t but twenty-something.

ONG: Twenty-eight.

WASHBURN: So you passed the civil service exam, and where&#039;d you get a job?

ONG: June of 1951. I worked at Camp Stoneman in Pittsburg, California.

WASHBURN: Doing what?

ONG: I was a stock clerk. I worked for the quartermaster. Funniest thing--I seen
guys go overseas to fight in the Korean War, here I would issue them clothes.
Lot of them thought I was in the government as a soldier, but I wasn&#039;t. So I was
issuing clothes. I stayed there until &#039;54, and they closed up because the war
was over. I went straight over to Benicia Arsenal, which is in Benicia. They
were an armament place. I worked there until &#039;63. When they closed, I went over
to the Naval Weapons Station off Port Chicago until I retired in 1986 as a
missile mechanic, which was a fabulous job. I made missiles.

WASHBURN: So you worked in defense industries your whole life.

ONG: Yeah. Defense department. Always in military, various stations.

WASHBURN: Was it a state job, or a federal job?

ONG: Federal. Always worked in military installations. Some people just work in
an office; I didn&#039;t. The first one were embarkations, send the troops to Korea.
Later one, they were rebuilding tanks and guns for the allies, and then the last
one was building missiles and stuff for all the navy. Vietnam War, we sent out 7
percent of the ammunition, and then later when I retired, they were already
sending the missiles for the Persian Gulf War. They were still making them.

WASHBURN: That seems like a pretty stable job to have, working with the federal
government. Did sometimes your views on the wars that were being fought differ from--

ONG: We were kind of prejudiced. We were for the war. We were like a hawk.
People laugh, I was a war hawk.

WASHBURN: Why was that?

ONG: Because everything I did was for the war. Even when the place closed, my
mother and everybody write letters to keep it open.

WASHBURN: Did you always support what was going on in the military?

ONG: Yes, because you were brainwashed that the Communists were bad.

WASHBURN: Why is that?

ONG: You had to sign a statement that you weren&#039;t a Communist, and everything in
the war remind you of the enemy. Like World War II, but there it was more
patriotic. Here was a war we didn&#039;t fight, so everything I did was to fight the
Russians. They were a menace from &#039;49 on.

WASHBURN: So you always remember them being the number-one enemy.

ONG: Yeah. I was a war hawk. I hate to say it. Now I&#039;ve kind of changed, because
I don&#039;t think we&#039;re living on wars anymore, but everybody that worked there had
that same--well, some people didn&#039;t. They used to have some woman complain about
the Vietnam War. People tell them, &quot;Get out of here. You don&#039;t have to work it.&quot;
She thought it was awful they were going to draft her boy, or something. Which
they did, draft a lot of people; called me up for the draft, and I didn&#039;t make
it. I didn&#039;t have the weight.

WASHBURN: Do you remember--you&#039;re working in the defense industry and the
Communists are your enemy, and yet in 1949 or early fifties, the Communists take
over in China.

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: Did you follow what was going on?

 ONG:

Yeah, I always thought Chiang Kai-shek was the good guy. I mean, he was kind of
a dictator, but he was fighting the Communists that even then was bad,
especially how they treat people. I read all through history, myself. Even
Russia didn&#039;t have a good time in the thirties. They killed a lot of people and
everything. He was like Hitler, Stalin was.

WASHBURN: What was it like in the Chinese community when the Communists took
over there?

ONG: I had a man that was a herb doctor, like an uncle to me. He was upset no
end, because the Communists killed a lot of his family in the villages. A lot of
people didn&#039;t know it until I talked to him and his wife, they execute a lot of
people just on the spot, like the Germans did. But it&#039;s never come out in
history. But now I know the Red Guard even had a war with some of the
ex-veterans in 1952. It was on TV one night. The documentary was {Civic Ocean?}

WASHBURN: Did you ever feel like people ever thought of you as maybe more of a
Communist, because you were Chinese?

ONG: No. Only thing bad was when the Korean War come, the Chinese entered the
war. My mother couldn&#039;t--the herb doctor couldn&#039;t get more herbs from China.
They passed a thing, I don&#039;t know when. They had an embargo until real late in
the sixties. They tried to send things from Canada to her as a civilian. Because
he wasn&#039;t a herb store person, he wouldn&#039;t let her get it. A lot of people don&#039;t
realize we were really mad at the Chinese.

WASHBURN: Chinese Americans were mad at the Chinese.

ONG: No, not about us, but the Chinese in China, because they entered the war on
the North Korean side.

WASHBURN: And yet you were working for U.S. defense industries, supporting the south.

ONG: I worked when the war started. So I was drafted, even before the war
started, and went to an induction camp. I just didn&#039;t make the weight, otherwise
I would have been in the army for two years, if I was called up. They didn&#039;t
want me; they rejected me, but otherwise I would have been sent to Korea. See,
when I work at Stoneman, I found out that all the guys drafted was going to
Korea, fast. Six weeks of training and you were gone, and a lot of them didn&#039;t
come back. I&#039;ve even talked to men now that were older men, but worked in my
yard. They were officers and they said a lot of guys they knew joined up the
Marine Reserve, because they were making money at sixteen. They were taking
sixteen-, seventeen-year-old kids, and they all came back in a pine box. When I
was called in February of &#039;51, the Chinese had entered the war and they were
sending us reeling backwards. All these poor guys that were drafted never fired
a gun. They didn&#039;t have a chance to get those veterans of the Chinese-Japanese
war. Some of those guys had ten years of fighting under their belt. This guy
tells me, all his friends that joined the marines all came back in a box.

WASHBURN: How would you describe, as best you can, what you were thinking,
working for the U.S. defense industries?

ONG: I was glad I had a decent job. My mother always preached to me to get a
good job, and I did.

WASHBURN: But I mean, what was your mentality working for defense industries
while the Communists were in China and then ultimately they started fighting
against U.S. forces in the Korean War?

ONG: Well, I entered when the war already had started. I was for it, fighting
against them. Everybody knew them days that Communists were a menace. Didn&#039;t
think that much about them, but when they called me up I knew I had to go and
fight them. I wasn&#039;t ever that crazy to be in the army, except for maybe when I
was a ten-year-old boy or something. I never was never really crazy over the
military. I worked with them so much, I know how they act and everything, but I
never cared to be one. You always made more money as a civilian. They had to
work alongside me, the navy guys, and they made half what I made and they do the
same work I did.

WASHBURN: Camp Stoneman was in Pittsburg?

ONG: Yes.

WASHBURN: The defense industries in the Richmond area started to close down and
move away, or just closed down completely. Did other people in the Richmond area
go to work at defense industries?

ONG: When the Korean War came up, they built back up. Because Port Chicago--I
was never there, but a guy whose brother worked there--they dropped from two,
three, four thousand down to less than five hundred people. But when I went
there, the Vietnam War was on, they built back up to over twelve thousand people.

WASHBURN: During the Vietnam or the Korean War?

ONG: Vietnam War. I worked through all the wars, except for World War II. I
worked the Korean War, I worked in the Vietnam War. If I had have stayed I would
have been in the Persian Gulf War, but I retired by then. I took early
retirement. I had a lot of years then, so I was exactly one month and fifty-six
years old, I went home. I didn&#039;t have to work that long, because I got a good
pension at that age. So I was lucky; I got out real early from a lot of other
people, because I started working at twenty-one.

WASHBURN: If you didn&#039;t work for defense industries at twenty-one, where do you
think you would have worked, in retrospect?

ONG: It was hard to get work then. Very hard in the fifties for a young person
to get a job. I could have got a lot of work delivering stuff, but I never had a
driver&#039;s license. I had many offers, but, &quot;You have to drive,&quot; they say. I had a
license in &#039;54, but I really didn&#039;t get a car until &#039;60. I drove ever since.
People think I drove when I was a young man; I never did. I&#039;m a fairly good
driver, a more than average in driving, so a lot of people think I drove all my life.

WASHBURN: You had mentioned something about being brainwashed to really--

ONG: When you work for the government, you always knew the enemy was the
Russians. That&#039;s the first thing they taught you. In my case, I was passed for
confidential and secret, because I became a printer. For those, you have to sign
an affiliation that you know what you&#039;re there for. Everybody that worked with
the government always knew the Russians were our enemy, because of the Cold War.
That&#039;s the reason they kept going. In a way, I have to say thanks to the
Russians for keeping my job going. They kept the Cold War going all those years;
they would have closed down after World War II. Hard times. A lot of people
didn&#039;t realize that all these cities in Contra Costa County, like Concord and
everything, grew up during the Korean War. When I first worked there, Concord
only had five thousand people. Then the Korean War come, they went up to a
hundred and fifty thousand now. So a lot of the cities up here grew up from the
war years.

WASHBURN: How did the Cold War affect the Richmond area?

ONG: Didn&#039;t do much, because there was nothing here for them to do. Ships were
not needed. Standard [Oil] might&#039;ve done good, but then they always sold
gasoline. Santa Fe [Railroad] didn&#039;t have more business than any other years,
but the only thing--they kept the passenger trains going because they carried a
lot of soldiers and stuff. But the war years didn&#039;t do Richmond a bit of good.

WASHBURN: You mean the Korean War years?

ONG: Yes. It didn&#039;t do Richmond good. It didn&#039;t have anything related to the war
then. But Benicia had just the arsenal, and when they closed it was hard times
for them. Pittsburg was real hurting till about the sixties when the camp closed
down. That was one of their major source of work.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve talked to some people I&#039;ve interviewed, and I&#039;d like to hear your
opinion. Some people say the reasons why white middle-class people started
leaving Richmond was one, because there were more black people moved into town,
and they didn&#039;t want to live near them. Also, according to what you&#039;re saying,
there were no jobs, so they needed to move to Concord.

ONG: There were no jobs for white people except they work out of town. And
remember, a lot of those Southern--

WASHBURN: But Royce, what is the story? Did they move out of Richmond because
they were prejudiced, or because there were no jobs?

ONG: A lot of them were prejudiced. They wouldn&#039;t show it outright, but they
were. Remember, a lot of the Southern white people were from the South. Most of
the shipyard people were from the South, white and black. Naturally, they never
lived with them, and why should they live with them when they get a more modern
house somewhere else? The black people lost their jobs, so they bought the older
houses. They still worked, but they couldn&#039;t afford the houses that they were
building up in the suburbs, and they didn&#039;t want them, anyway, because the races
tend to stay together.

WASHBURN: What was the mentality that Southern whites brought to Richmond?

ONG: They just showed that the Southerners were prejudiced, a little bit, that
you never knew before. Well, Californians always had prejudice. The Native Sons
[of the Golden West] people were what you call now very conservative. I read
articles in later years that Richmond was a very conservative town. Very
conservative. They frowned on a lot of things that other cities didn&#039;t frown on.
Richmond, in the early years, everybody was kind of middle class. They all had
good jobs, because they all work at the industries. So Richmond, with twenty
thousand people, all of them either Standard or Santa Fe, except for a few
people that did menial work.

WASHBURN: Or Ford or Pullman.

ONG: Yeah. Except for the war come in, they add another eighty thousand people,
you had people that were very conservative, had nice houses, had good income.
Even in the Depression they were driving--like, the kids I knew all had &#039;38, &#039;39
Oldsmobiles. They had cars, in those days, up-to-date cars. Their mothers, some
of them worked in jewelry stores in Oakland and stuff, besides their father
worked for Standard. They had a good two-income, before two-income really was
known. The guy I know, Bobby Chamberlain, his mother owned a jewelry store near
University Avenue and did real good, until she moved out of this area. Father,
naturally, was a Standard man, had--well, not a big paycheck, but a steady
income, had a nice little house on Washington Avenue. They weren&#039;t hurting at
all. Depression didn&#039;t mean a thing to them. They just seen it in the newspaper.

WASHBURN: Some people could say that after the war, let&#039;s say I was a
middle-class white person who lived in Richmond, they could say, &quot;Well, I didn&#039;t
move out of Richmond because I was prejudiced. I moved out of Richmond because
there were no jobs.&quot; Would you believe them?

ONG: Well, a lot of them moved out and probably went back home. A lot of them
went back to Oklahoma. I knew a lot of people, they said they went back, because
a lot of those people who worked at the shipyard weren&#039;t that educated, either.
They taught them how to weld, but the education wasn&#039;t good in the white or
black area, but the blacks had no future. Like now, everybody love California,
even if you&#039;re from a foreign country. [laughs] The blacks said this was better
than the South, so they stayed. The South had nothing for them. They were
treated--segregated schools, segregated drinking fountains, everything. And
jobs; they did the worst job, so naturally they were the ones that would stay. A
lot of whites went back to their farm or family, but the blacks had nothing to
look forward to. So naturally they stayed in California. But a lot of them
didn&#039;t live in Richmond, either. A lot of the young people that worked with me,
their family moved to Berkeley, but the young people came back where the housing
were cheaper in Richmond, because they build a lot of the houses on
twenty-five-foot lots in the late fifties.

WASHBURN: What would you say to somebody who says that, &quot;I moved out of Richmond
not because I&#039;m prejudiced, but because there were no jobs.&quot;

ONG: They weren&#039;t a prejudiced person, then. They tolerate people.

WASHBURN: Would you say that maybe that&#039;s just an excuse?

ONG: A lot of old people now I know, that lived locally themselves, older men,
they&#039;re prejudiced as a son-of-a-gun. They always lived there and they still
don&#039;t like them. They mention them when they have like a chief that&#039;s a
minority. They say, &quot;Here we got a bum running as the police chief.&quot;

WASHBURN: Still to this day.

ONG: To this day, they still say that, the older men. I never was that way, but
a lot of older white men still say that.

WASHBURN: Why do you think they haven&#039;t changed?

ONG: Because it&#039;s hard to change a person. Their mind is already set up. They
know they&#039;re inferior or something, so they feel to this day they&#039;re a bunch of
dumb guys. And the jobs they work on never had black people. One guy I know
worked for the Key System, never hire a black person until the late fifties. One
guy. You want to know something funny? Reading on the history of the war, the
Capitol [Transit] Company in Washington, D.C., had a shortage of men. They never
had women operators. They had a big streetcar system, and the law was supposed
to hire anybody to fill in, so they hire one black man for a token. They gave
him so much trouble that he finally quit.

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s talk about the civil rights era in Richmond.

ONG: Richmond only had two black policemen.

WASHBURN: Who were they?

ONG: One&#039;s name was [Douglas] Ellis and one&#039;s name was [Lonnie] Washington.

WASHBURN: Where was their beat?

ONG: Downtown and the shipyards. They weren&#039;t allowed to stop--I heard from
black people now; I never knew then--but black people said they weren&#039;t allowed
to draw the gun out to arrest a white man if he speeded or anything.

WASHBURN: When did the city start changing its hiring practices?

ONG: I would say late sixties or more. You used to never see black firemen, or
anything. The city was very prejudiced. This city never hired much people. I
would say it was &#039;60 when they started a lot of black people for working. Most
of these guys were younger men, that were working. There was hardly anybody
that&#039;s my age that was working for the city. They didn&#039;t hire them. Probably had
a few in the City Hall, but not much. Because I used to never see black
policemen at all, except for these two guys. One of them, Washington, I think,
quit early. The other guy quit because he shot a black boy. They called him
prejudiced. The black people always hated him. Black kid ran away from him, he
shot him.

WASHBURN: When was that?

ONG: Oh, in the late fifties. They shot him in the back, somewhere. They shot
him in the back, or something. I never heard that, because I never kept up with
them. Bus drivers didn&#039;t have blacks, not in this Richmond division. They hired
women because they had to.

WASHBURN: Even though people in the fifties moved out of Richmond, were the
people who were in the city council--

ONG: It was all white people.

WASHBURN: Who had moved out of Richmond?

ONG: They had to live in Richmond, so they still lived in Mira Vista, the fancy
area. We never had people from the Point, even, until the late eighties.

WASHBURN: If someone doesn&#039;t know what Mira Vista is like--

ONG: It&#039;s a real fancy area like North Berkeley, Kensington. It still looks that
way. They have nice, fancy homes.

WASHBURN: Where is it located?

ONG: All custom-built, with big yards. Fancy rock walls. Big living rooms. I
used to have a teacher there; she always asked me to go up. I finally went,
after I was older and safer, and they were old-aged. Her house was built by
themselves, because her husband--she was my schoolteacher, he was a worker with
Standard, and they have a fabulous house. Even to this day, you&#039;d like to live there.

WASHBURN: Where is it located?

ONG: Up on Barrett Avenue. Up near the Richmond Golf Club. Or else the Mira
Vista Golf Club.

WASHBURN: When did the city start changing, start becoming more of a diverse body?

ONG: In the sixties and seventies, when a lot of people moved out of Oakland
because the houses were cheap. The housing in Richmond were getting run down and
the absentee landlords started owning old houses. They were mostly people from--

WASHBURN: I mean, the city government.

ONG: Oh, the government in the early seventies when they start diversifying. The
white people were dying and retiring, and they were voting in more black
councilmen and mayors. Then later, in the nineties, the white lady that lived
where I did became mayor. We end up with a white mayor for eight years, and we
have more white councilmen back on again, like one guy, {Jim Rogers?} the lawyer
that&#039;s on TV. He&#039;s back on, and we got a white guy from my area. One time we had
four white people, all living in the Point.

WASHBURN: For somebody who doesn&#039;t know what happened at Travellini&#039;s, will you
describe it?

ONG: What happened was the Roosevelt Junior High, this was &#039;69, there was mostly
black girls there and they went into some department store, I forgot what the
name was. Department store on Seventh Street, couldn&#039;t remember the name. They
ran in and took clothes, ran out the other end. The police tried to stop them,
and they didn&#039;t, and--what the hell did they do? Then the police went after
them, arrested some of the girls. The owners shut the store down for a day, and
that night, they called police brutality, they burned down all the stores on
Eleventh Street and burned down Travellini&#039;s Department Store, which hired a lot
of minorities. He always complained that, &quot;I hire them, and they work for me.&quot;
They burned a little section of town down.

WASHBURN: Where was the police brutality?

ONG: They claim it because they were arresting the young girls that ran through
the store, running out the other side. Then that night, they burned down that
part of town.

WASHBURN: How many stores burned down?

ONG: Only Travellini&#039;s and a few small stores.

WASHBURN: Was there a crowd of people that gathered to do this, or was it just a
small incident?

ONG: It was a bunch of young black kids that did the stealing and burning. The
police chief called for mutual aid. I didn&#039;t know the barber then; I wish I was
there, I could go to the barber and take pictures through the window. But what
they did, he gave the order which you would never use nowadays--Chief Brown:
shoot to kill.

WASHBURN: The police force was still mainly white at this time?

ONG: White police chief. He used that statement. You would never use it in
modern times, but that was the statement. Shoot to kill.

WASHBURN: Shoot to kill the rioters.

ONG: Yes. And they called for mutual aid. Of course, Richmond being a
conservative town, every little white town in Contra Costa sent police. They had
police from Clayton, they had police from Concord, they had police from Walnut
Creek, they had police from San Ramon, and San Francisco sent its famous
tactical squad, carrying shotguns and helmets. They went up the buildings,
carrying shotguns and watching the town for about a week.

WASHBURN: When was this, do you remember?

ONG: &#039;69. Late part of &#039;69 somewhere. Richmond really had what you call martial
law. All these cities: &quot;Hurry up, send police in.&quot; I had a camera, but I never
knew the guy in the barbershop. I would have took pictures. It&#039;d be
worthwhile--all these foreign police cars traveling up and down town through
Richmond with their police insignias on them. But like I said, I rode a bus. And
San Francisco sent in their tactical squad.

WASHBURN: Had the black community complained about police brutality?

ONG: They couldn&#039;t complain much.

WASHBURN: No, in other instances.

ONG: I don&#039;t think they liked them. The newspaper was pro-city, so I never heard
anything complaining. The way they had it was like martial law. They had more
police than ever.

WASHBURN: Did this incident start a process that started some change in Richmond?

ONG: Yeah, a lot of people thought it was getting out of hand. A lot of people
that seen it still mention to this day, laugh about it. I had a girlfriend that
was a young girl going to college, she went through there in her Corvette and
she remembered the police wouldn&#039;t let her go through. She was just driving
through; she wasn&#039;t going to see anybody. So that was kind of a black eye in
Richmond that year. Showed how mean they could get.

WASHBURN: Lot of people I&#039;ve talked to mention that.

ONG: When the police chief [ordered] shoot to kill, that was a no-no. But he
said it, and everybody didn&#039;t condemn him.

WASHBURN: Brutal.

ONG: That was the thing; they were glad to hear it. That&#039;s how funny it was.

WASHBURN: Well, we have to kind of end things up here. Is there anything you
want to add?

ONG: It&#039;s just too bad that Richmond deteriorated. It was a good town once and
it still could be nice, but they got more people on welfare. I read in the paper
one time, Richmond had 11 percent welfare and eleven thousand women on welfare.
That don&#039;t help the city much. With all the dope selling on the street--you go
down Pennsylvania Avenue you see it. It was real bad, up to a few years ago. You
see these guys with {painter hats?}, and guys from Marin County, everything,
would come over to buy dope. That don&#039;t help. Richmond has as much shooting now
as Oakland, for its small size.

WASHBURN: What do you think needs to change in Richmond?

ONG: Well, you got to get more jobs, but that&#039;s never going to happen. Everybody
says that; more jobs and more kids willing to go to school. But they&#039;ve been
brought up third-, fourth-generation welfare, they think it&#039;s cheaper to do
nothing, to have babies, than work. A lot of them are. They&#039;ve been on welfare
since the forties; that&#039;s four generations. A lot of unwed mothers. The
Hispanics seem to do fair, but their trouble is they don&#039;t speak English. They
have a big Laotian population there, the boat people, they brought them over and
just today I read in the paper they have a lot of problems because they don&#039;t
know how to speak English. The other day, had an article where a family came
five years ago. Mother and father don&#039;t understand the kids, they all speak English.

WASHBURN: I have to turn this one off.

ONG: What do you think? I think that&#039;s a downfall.

[End of Interview]</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>