<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00100835" dt="2022-07-01"><version>5.4</version><date value="2010-06-25" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Betty Reid Soskin | Interview 4 | June 25, 2010</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><subject>Community and Identity</subject><subject>Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</subject><interviewee>Betty Reid Soskin</interviewee><interviewer>Julie Stein</interviewer><interviewer>Javier Arbona</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|2(9)|17(1)|25(9)|34(1)|43(11)|57(11)|70(10)|79(17)|90(15)|109(2)|120(11)|140(13)|155(5)|168(5)|178(6)|189(5)|201(3)|215(16)|226(8)|235(3)|243(7)|254(12)|267(10)|276(11)|284(13)|296(2)|304(7)|319(14)|334(12)|344(3)|365(5)|374(12)|383(11)|393(3)|403(8)|411(1)|427(6)|440(1)|450(12)|458(10)|465(2)|474(3)|499(4)|510(5)|519(7)|530(17)|541(11)|551(8)|569(1)|579(6)|590(4)|605(10)|616(4)|633(3)|645(2)|656(1)|663(13)|678(8)|688(7)|700(8)|711(16)|722(11)|731(5)|738(12)|748(11)|760(3)|771(1)|783(8)|795(10)|805(4)|819(4)|831(6)|844(2)|865(2)|884(6)|909(3)|923(5)|933(1)|939(8)|950(2)|957(8)|966(2)|979(3)|987(7)|1003(1)|1020(11)|1030(5)|1043(3)|1051(6)|1065(6)|1073(9)|1081(5)|1091(7)|1107(2)|1116(12)|1125(7)|1135(10)|1145(11)|1156(1)|1164(9)|1174(10)|1188(1)|1198(14)|1211(1)|1219(8)|1230(3)|1239(13)|1252(6)|1262(8)|1274(6)|1289(5)|1300(13)|1310(12)|1320(8)|1327(13)|1336(1)|1348(9)|1356(10)|1365(5)|1380(9)|1386(9)|1395(3)|1403(11)|1414(2)|1423(3)|1432(3)|1441(12)|1452(2)|1466(2)|1479(14)|1496(8)|1503(3)|1525(9)|1539(6)|1553(6)|1572(1)|1584(5)|1594(7)|1602(3)|1611(12)|1622(11)|1631(8)|1641(1)|1663(12)|1673(14)|1682(3)|1690(11)|1699(11)|1708(11)|1718(1)|1727(8)|1736(13)|1746(1)|1754(9)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>UFOPMWUroSU</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>STEIN: It&#039;s June 25, 2010, and we are here in Richmond, California with Betty
Reid Soskin. This is Julie Stein and Javier Arbona. And this is tape one. Thank
you so much for sitting down with us again. We have some semi-general questions
when we were reading through your first transcript and wanted both to get your
take on what you think, of the historic record, needs to be fixed and then some
other questions that we were curious about. So I know that you have done some
more research into your early life, about the timing of your family&#039;s move.

SOSKIN: Yes.

STEIN: I&#039;m curious about the revisions or what your research has done that you&#039;d
like to fix the record on.

SOSKIN: I noticed, first off, that I gave my age in coming to California as age
four. And I had never had occasion to try to refine that before in my life. No
one has taken an oral history. And that time was always kind of foggy for me. I
didn&#039;t know why that was. But since then, I&#039;ve discovered very, very factually,
that the age I came in was six. I remember, for instance, entering first grade
in California. I remembered the actual storm, the hurricane in 1927. I
remembered that that was a reason that we came to California. And at some point,
I read that that 1927, which put the age up two years. And then when I
remembered, really, the trauma. I&#039;m, for instance, phobic about lightning and
thunder. I&#039;ve never understood why. I&#039;ve never had any reason to understand. But
I remember my grandmother telling me to jump into bed at the first sound of
thunder because had I ever heard of anyone being struck by lightning in bed? And
all the way into my adulthood, I would jump into bed the minute thunder rolled.
So I began to connect that storm, that hurricane, with my entry into California.
And gradually, after that first interview and that four-year-old--I began to
realize why I would have buried that time, because it was so traumatic. It
completely uprooted and changed my life. I was a child in New Orleans; then
suddenly I was in my grandfather&#039;s home in California. And it also seemed to
have been connected to the fact that I was born into a strongly Catholic family.
Completely rooted to the church. My grandfather lay in state for three days
after his death, because the church we grew up in was Corpus Christi, which is
the church he had built. He was an architect and engineer. That storm happened
on Good Friday. So the symbolism, the religious symbolism, also would&#039;ve been traumatic.

So I began to understand after that first oral history, why that period was
cloudy for me. And I began to make connections. I completely was out of the
Catholic faith by the time I was a teenager. I&#039;ve never really tried to figure
out how that period figures into my becoming an atheist. But the fact that Good
Friday figured into it seems to be symbolic. So there&#039;ve been all these openings
that have occurred since that time. And I think that&#039;s probably why
memory--memory is so layered that I think that we often begin to find out much,
much, much later incidents, how they figure in the overall.

STEIN: Did you have a sense of whether the hurricane happening on Good Friday
affected the faith of other members of your family?

SOSKIN: No. There was never any indication that I--and I never discussed it. So
the truth is that I&#039;m not really sure what the answer to that is. My father
remained a Catholic, and he was an official in the St. Vincent de Paul at St.
Benedict&#039;s Church. My dad died a Catholic. My mother died a Catholic, but a
cafeteria Catholic. My mother was practicing birth control--she only had three
children--so that she could not accept the sacraments.

STEIN: Do you know what that meant at that time? Were diaphragms available?

SOSKIN: No.

STEIN: So what did--?

SOSKIN: No. My mother had to choose between abstinence, I think, and her
religion. And I think my mother chose her sexuality. And then it was
interesting. When I was beginning to outgrow my faith, I didn&#039;t discuss that
with my parents because they would never have understood. Catholicism was a
Charbonnet--it was in the DNA. So that that didn&#039;t become an issue for me until
I adopted my first child from Catholic Charities. And when that happened, I had
to promise his birth mother that he would be raised a Catholic. And I then began
to explore my Catholicism and why I had dropped away, because I needed to follow
the dictates of that agreement with the Catholic Social Service.

I went back to church and got a conversation with a priest, asked for an
appointment. Because I told him I had this child, adopted at nine days old; he
was my first child; that I really wanted to honor his mother&#039;s wishes; but that
I had some questions, and could he answer them, maybe, and help me to understand
so that I could do that; that my word was important to me. And he listened to me
and he said, &quot;Mrs. Reid, you are attempting to be intelligent about what is a
faith. And it&#039;s a gift of God and must not be questioned.&quot; And I thought as I
walked out, &quot;He doesn&#039;t know any more than I do.&quot; [they laugh] And I never went back.

I went to my mother--that&#039;s what it was--and I said that I really was trying to
raise Rick the way his mother wished, and that I&#039;d never discussed the fact that
I just wasn&#039;t going to church; but that I also noticed that she wasn&#039;t going to
church, so what was it that--I don&#039;t think that I thought she intellectually
thought her way out of it. But I needed some support. And she said, &quot;You know,
Betty, some things are just not the priests&#039; business.&quot; [they laugh]

STEIN: Sounds like good advice. I&#039;m actually really curious about--some of my
own research has to do with adoption and motherhood and stuff around that. And I
know that one of the aspects of adoption at the time was that they were very
religiously based, or was often religious charities.

SOSKIN: Right. Right.

STEIN: I&#039;m curious. I don&#039;t know if you would mind talking about--

SOSKIN: No.

STEIN: --the process of both finding a Catholic adoption agency, or whether they
were also racially grouped. Because I think today, we do adoption, I think, much
more about skin color and much less about religion; whereas it seems like it
wasn&#039;t always that way.

SOSKIN: My motivation for adopting was so simplistic. My sisters--one was four
years older, one was four years younger--we were spaced so that there wasn&#039;t
much companionship between us. We were never in the same growth periods at the
same time. We were not in the same schools at the same time. My older sister
married at nineteen. My younger sister married at sixteen, I think it was. But
they were both pregnant at the same time, and I was not. And I had fulfilled the
expectations of my parents, and my community, by becoming married. But I was
really supposed to be pregnant by now. And so at a very, very early age, I was
not going to be left behind; I was going to have a baby. What agency would&#039;ve
allowed me, at that age, to become a mother, [laughs] I don&#039;t know. The Catholic
Social Services must&#039;ve been desperate.

STEIN: How old were you? Was it 1945?

SOSKIN: Yeah. Rick was born in 1945. And I was married in 1942. So that I
must&#039;ve been twenty-three or twenty-two. But I should&#039;ve been really questioned
at that point. Now I wonder how anybody would&#039;ve ever done that. Because I just
didn&#039;t want-- I was just fulfilling my destiny as a Catholic woman. [laughs] Or
even as a woman.

STEIN: Were there overt ways that you felt that pressure? People talk about in
that time period, the baby boom and everyone was having children. How did--

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t remember the baby boom. And certainly, that would&#039;ve been--no,
it would&#039;ve probably followed that. That was pretty early for the baby boom
because 1945 is when the war ended.

STEIN: Right.

SOSKIN: And the baby boom would&#039;ve been nine or ten months later.

STEIN: Right. [they laugh]

SOSKIN: So that at the point of pregnancy, that probably wouldn&#039;t have been a
factor. I think the factor really was that particularly as an African-American
woman, there were no models in my family for any alternatives to being--a
successful woman was married by the time she was twenty. If you were twenty-six
and unmarried, you were considered a spinster. A successful woman began her
family in her early twenties. I would have fulfilled the expectations of my
community by being such. So that the pressures would&#039;ve come from the community,
not from the larger world, I don&#039;t think. I think I felt it within my family. My
sisters were both expecting children, and I was not.

STEIN: Was it their first child, both of them?

SOSKIN: Yes. Yes.

STEIN: Was there any stigma to adoption? Or were people just so thrilled that
there was another child in the family?

SOSKIN: It was simply an alternative. I don&#039;t remember it being blessed in any
way by my family or--I would think that my parents probably felt I wasn&#039;t going
to bear children because I had started trying to have a child when I was
married. First night. [they laugh] This is what we do. So that I think that by
the end of three years, if I hadn&#039;t produced a baby, my family would&#039;ve
assumed--as I did--that I was probably barren. And continued to try. It was
another three or four years before I had my first child naturally.

STEIN: It&#039;s really fascinating to talk to someone of this generation, where
having a large family probably wasn&#039;t even really questioned. It was almost
assumed. And then to see how you not only balanced family, but then went on to a
career and to various careers.

SOSKIN: But that was not anticipated. I had my first significant job after the
age of fifty.

STEIN: Which doesn&#039;t follow the traditional, let&#039;s say, feminist narrative of--

SOSKIN: Not only that, there weren&#039;t any models for me. I could not have
envisioned what my life became after my children grew up, how many of the
societal issues I would have lived out. My first child, for instance, was gay.
My last child is developmentally disabled. I had to care for my aging parents
until they died, at ninety-five and 101, respectively. So all the issues of gay
rights, of developmentally disabled, of elder care--all of those things had to
be lived out over these eighty-eight years. And had to be lived out personally.
I had to know what those things were. I think it sparked a life of activism, and
very early. But not as a working woman. I guess I worked in a dress shop in
Walnut Creek at the time when I was anticipating, maybe, a divorce, and needed
to begin to explore how I would take care of myself.

STEIN: And at this point, you had four children, correct?

SOSKIN: Yeah. So career was never anything. In fact, I never even attended
college. I never had a break between belonging to my father, whom I respected,
and belonging to my husband, who was my best friend, who I married, who I met at
the age of thirteen or fourteen. It was a predictable marriage. And I can&#039;t say
that I questioned any of that. It&#039;d be great to say I was a feminist; I didn&#039;t
know what that was. [laughs]

STEIN: Right. Nobody did. [laughs] You can&#039;t blame yourself for that one.

SOSKIN: No. I really, really was living a prescribed kind of life. Until I moved
into Walnut Creek and found that I had to either choose sides racially and
politically or not survive emotionally.

STEIN: Can you talk a little bit more about that transition to Walnut Creek and
some of the--?

SOSKIN: I understand that a lot better since I&#039;m a park ranger.

STEIN: Wonderful. [they laugh] Fantastic.

SOSKIN: Because I&#039;ve had to look at the whole context. Up until I began to work
as a National Park Ranger, I could only look out of Betty&#039;s eyes, this woman who
grew up behind these eyes and how she had personal experiences. When I became a
park ranger and began to look at that entire home front experience, for
instance, I had to make room for the context. That had never been true for me
before. When I moved into Walnut Creek--and even, I guess, in the first oral
history--what I understood was my experience, objectively; the fact that Mel and
I had grown up in California. He was a fourth generation Californian. He had
grown up in a family that had come out here during the Civil War. So had never
grown up--well, certainly, racial bigotry existed; we were aware of it. It was
simply not a problem in our lives. And I&#039;ve learned since that had the civil
rights response and revolution depended on the community that I grew up
in--which was largely Creole, Catholic, out of New Orleans, somewhat
privileged--had it depended on us, the civil rights revolution would&#039;ve been
another thirty years, probably. [they laugh]

Because life was tolerable for us. We knew that that bigotry existed, but we
could find our ways around that. And it was mostly the people who came in from
the South, both black and white, and who had to play that out in the context of
the home front mobilization, that accelerated that social change. They had to
come up with those 747 ships in three years and eight months, with the social
system that was in place then. Henry Kaiser was not a social reformer. He was a
savvy industrialist. And he delivered ships faster than the enemy could sink
them; that was his charge. And he did it with all these thousands of
sharecroppers he brought in, white and black, from the South.

When the war ended--and this is where it gets to the move to Walnut Creek--Mel
and I had been forced, over those four years, to become a part of the migration
population. In part, because we lived and were working in that framework. But
our wishes for our lives were based upon House Beautiful and Sunset Magazine
[they laugh] and Formica countertops and all this stuff, and a house. We had
saved our money. We had gone into business for ourselves, for instance, because
who wanted to work for white folks anymore? We had become, to some extent,
radicalized; but not really. So that we wanted to build a house, and could
afford to when the war ended. And his family, his parents had moved to Danville
and had a little truck farm. They wanted to raise horses and have a garden. And
there weren&#039;t enough people in Danville then to resist anything. So that in
visiting, we would pass through Walnut Creek on the way to have the kids ride on
the horses at Grandpa&#039;s house. And my husband picked out this lot in an
unincorporated area of Walnut Creek, between Lafayette and Walnut Creek. And we
wanted to build a house; we could afford it. We chose an architect to design it
who was a Quaker, so had no problems with designing our house.

STEIN: Was that a conscious decision, do you think, to hire--?

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t know because I wasn&#039;t a part of those discussions. I was
pregnant with David. And my father, who was a contractor, or had done
contracting with his father, was working with Mel. This was man&#039;s work. They
were going to provide for me and the children. And I had Rick and Bob and was
pregnant with David, so there were two children at that time. And so I was not
really involved in those--except that when this lumber began to be stacked and
word began to get out that an African American family was moving into this area,
we began to get threatening letters from the neighborhood.

STEIN: And these were sent to your home in Berkeley?

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t know. Either I don&#039;t remember or I&#039;ve blocked it out. I don&#039;t
know how Mel got those letters. I remember reading them. I remember one being
from the county. And the county had apparently been told that Father Divine, who
was the great black leader at that time, religious leader, had purchased the
property to create a &quot;heaven.&quot; [laughs] And that they wanted us to understand
that this property could not be used for anything other than a private home. We
didn&#039;t know where those rumors were coming from.

What I didn&#039;t know, and what I began to learn as a ranger, was that the thing
that came about with the end of the war was that returning servicemen were using
their GI Bills to begin the suburbs, the suburbanization of the country. Because
the GI Bill was administered locally rather than federally, the local banker
could determine where they would float a mortgage. So that white people would be
coming to the suburbs, but black people could not follow. And the white people
were trying to escape me! [they laugh] And here we are, this young couple with
two children, moving into the midst of the lion&#039;s den. I could not have
understood that context at that time. And I spent the next five, ten years in
kind of awfulness of rejection, of having to sort out where I was in that whole
thing, becoming the object of ridicule and hostility. As I was telling someone,
the very first year, summer vacation--no, it was just before summer vacation,
that my oldest child, who was I think maybe in third or fourth grade, entered
the school, which was Parkmead. One of my neighbors, who was actually the wife
of a psychiatrist who had moved from Berkeley because we were there--they were a
Jewish couple. Marian Powelson came to me and said, &quot;You need to know that
Parkmead PTA and faculty are holding a minstrel show as a fundraiser.&quot;

STEIN: In the 1950s?

SOSKIN: In the 1950s. And I went to the school and the principal&#039;s office. And
there on his door was his end man costume. And that evening, they were going to
be, all of them, in blackface, the teachers and faculty. And I walked in and
said, &quot;You know this is wrong.&quot; And he said, &quot;I didn&#039;t know until I saw your
face. But you need to know, Mrs. Reid, that we&#039;re not really making fun of black
people; we want to show you as happy-go-lucky.&quot; And I said, &quot;Do I look
happy-go-lucky?&quot; [they laugh] And he said, &quot;No.&quot; And I said, &quot;Well, you do know
that minstrel shows grew out of ridicule of African Americans.&quot; Blacks; it
wasn&#039;t African Americans then. &quot;And that this is wrong. And how do I explain
this to my son?&quot; And I said, &quot;I know that it&#039;s too late for me to do anything
about this or for you to call off your show, but you&#039;re going to perform it in
front of me.&quot; And I sat in the audience that night, in the front row, and made
them put on the show in front of me. It was that kind of thing that began my
activism. But I always felt that it was wrong and that people were going to
discover it was wrong because basically, people were good. [laughs] How I
maintained that, I do not know. But do you know that the same community that
fought my being there so hard sent me, in 1972, to Miami to represent them as a
McGovern delegate to the Miami convention?

STEIN: So it sounds like you were right. [laughs]

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t know what you do with that. I don&#039;t know what you do with that.

STEIN: Right. You mentioned not having models for an idea of feminism at the
time. Were there models in terms of activism, in terms of anti-racist activism?
It sounds like you fell into it quite naturally.

SOSKIN: I fell into it as a matter of survival. And I almost didn&#039;t survive. I
sort of suffered a mental break when Dorrie was about two and a half, and was in
therapy for about three years. Out of which I sort of redefined myself and
learned to live with my insanity. [they laugh] It&#039;s true. I figured out that all
the things that were bizarre about me were the things that were wonderful. [they laugh]

STEIN: That sounds like an excellent lesson.

SOSKIN: Yeah, I didn&#039;t need to be sane. All the sane people I knew were crazy. [laughs]

STEIN: Well, it sounds like in a lot of ways, you were put in a very crazy
situation, with--

SOSKIN: I was! That&#039;s why I say--I know now that I have never lacked intellect.
I know that all the important things I ever learned, I probably knew when I was
six. I think I out-thought my mother when I was about eight years old. So that I
do have a sense now--I didn&#039;t have the ego to support that until I began to
enter later life, and I began to realize that the only difference between me and
my first husband was that I had a sense of how much there was to know and he
didn&#039;t. And so he thought he knew. [they laugh] And that that was true of most
of the adults in my life, when I was a little kid; that I really was never sure
of anything when I was a child. I was always open to question. And as I aged
into my, oh, maybe seventies, I began to realize that that was probably the root
of much of my confusion; but that ultimately, I was right. That the world
contains so much more than any individual could possibly know. And that it was a
mark of intelligence. That I had a sense, always a sense of the beyond. And that
religion stopped that process. As a kid, I didn&#039;t think my way out of
Catholicism; but somehow, the answer that God made the grass green-- [they laugh]

STEIN: Didn&#039;t fly.

SOSKIN: --failed when I was about five.

STEIN: Well, I want to ask you one other question, but then it sounds like this
will be a good time to talk about the Unitarian Church a little bit.

SOSKIN: Oh, sure!

STEIN: But before we get there--so many questions--did you and your husband
consider not moving? Do you ever recall a moment when it got to be too much?
When the threatening letters or the obvious racism of the school system--?

SOSKIN: No.

STEIN: No.

SOSKIN: And see, I can&#039;t speak for Mel. He died. After we divorced, so that I
don&#039;t know whether he entered that kind of period of summation that I did at
maybe seventy and beyond. He didn&#039;t live long enough to be that; he died in his
sixties. So it&#039;s hard for me not to apply the wisdom acquired in the last ten or
fifteen years to an earlier period in life. I don&#039;t know whether Mel discovered
that. I do know that the pride of being a Charbonnet probably stood me in good
stead, because I had this--someone once told me it was very hard to feel
superior to somebody who refused to be inferior. [they laugh] And I think that
was true. I never believed that I was inferior. Even through all of those times.

There was an attorney who lived just around the bend in Walnut Creek. His name
was Robert Condon; Eleanor Condon was his wife. And that&#039;s C-O-N-D-O-N. She was
a well know ceramicist, and he was a well known liberal radical attorney. He was
a partner of Robert Treuhaft, who was Jessica Mitford&#039;s husband. And they were
both involved with Democratic politics. And when he discovered I was there, they
offered to give a dinner party to introduce us to the neighbors. Because they
were absolutely enchanted with our presence. We were going to become their--no,
that was going to be their champion for the year, because we were their cause.
And I remember saying, &quot;Absolutely not. You will not give a dinner party, which
would suggest that you were giving me permission to move into a house which we
have built and have a perfect right to.&quot; And I missed his anger, because we
never got to be friends with him.

But I got pushed against the wall, or we got pushed against the wall. But what
came out was this feisty, proud Betty that apparently was the birth of this
woman who later became a political activist. At that time, I was fighting for my
right to be there, and feeling perfectly deserving, and wanted to set an example
for my children. It was really, really personal; it was not a part of any
movement. I was not a member of the NAACP or anything. And that was, I think,
the beginning of wanting to stand on my own. I remember saying, &quot;I don&#039;t want
you,&quot; the Condons, &quot;to feel responsible if I don&#039;t mow my lawn. You cannot give
me permission, because you would then define my life as I live it.&quot; And I
remember those conversations, so they must have been pivotal. I can remember the
words and the expressions. And I think that maybe those are the road signs that
trace me back to a deliberate progression toward my political awareness now.

STEIN: Did you maintain social relationships with your friends who were still
living in Berkeley?

SOSKIN: No. We lost not only those connections--our home, because we had a
swimming pool, which was not usual in our family, family members would come out
for picnics. And occasionally, as my kids grew up, cousins would come out. We
had belonged to social clubs, which we&#039;d given up. But it felt natural to me
because all of my friends and family were then creating their nuclear families
and turned into those finding their way. So it didn&#039;t seem to me unusual that we
dropped away. But the other thing that was happening was that my marriage was
falling apart, in that my husband, once the house was built--because he had
physically joined the building of the house, the hammering; my husband and my
father literally, with a couple of laborers, built the house.

STEIN: Wow.

SOSKIN: But once that was done, he turned his attention back to the business.
And I was left pretty much alone in the suburbs. Not unlike my counterparts who
were white suburbanites. This was all pre-Betty Friedan. [they laugh] So we
really were all kind of women together raising children. So it didn&#039;t seem, even
then, unusual for me. I was becoming a typical suburban housewife, with the
addition of being an African American. And when I say it was extreme, Mel would
leave at seven in the morning and come home after midnight sometimes. Most of
the time.

STEIN: Wow.

SOSKIN: And worked throughout the week. And built a very, very successful
business at one point. Successful in a limited kind of way. And was becoming
more and more involved in a world that I wasn&#039;t a part of. And I was becoming a
part of a suburban lifestyle that he wasn&#039;t a part of.

STEIN: When you say becoming a part of it, sometimes historians talk about women
in the suburbs in the fifties as very isolated. And there are other people who
talk about women joining social groups or throwing parties together or
playgroups or--

SOSKIN: I think both those things are true. I think it&#039;s both. I remember
working with women on fashion shows at the country club. I also remember being
socially active. As members of the Unitarian Church, political activism was a
norm. Giving luncheon speeches. I remember being advertised at the local
Presbyterian church, with a sandwich board out in front saying, &quot;Betty Reid,
colored housewife,&quot; [they laugh] to a group of enlightened Presbyterians.

STEIN: Oh, my!

SOSKIN: And I remember my speech with that sign. I said, &quot;You know, it seems to
me that I could be described as an artist,&quot; because at that time, I was doing a
lot of painting and a lot of writing and music, &quot;or I could be described as a
mother, or I could be described as a political activist. But that sign limits
who I am.&quot; And I said, &quot;I find it offensive.&quot; [laughs] And they were not
stirred, but I think I gave voice to a lot of things then. Well, I had nothing
to lose. I didn&#039;t have a feeling of being a part of anything. Except the
Unitarian Church, which really, really was a changing agent in my life.

STEIN: How did you find the Unitarian Church?

SOSKIN: Because long after--maybe several years after--the initial shock of our
being there, and when people who wanted to use me to authenticate their liberal
views found me, I began to build this circle of liberals around me. There was
Helen Scharmer, all these people from the greater valley. I learned of a couple,
a black couple who bought a house in Gregory Gardens, which was a rather
low-cost housing development out in Pleasant Hill, which was just developing.
Median income was--the guy was a truck driver, I think, and his wife was either
a nurse or a nurse&#039;s aide. I didn&#039;t really know them. But there were a series of
stories that began to occur in the local press about these people coming
into--and the problems that the community was having. The fact that the
improvement association was meeting on thus-and-so night to decide on how they
were going to get rid of these people. And blithely I figured that I had
experienced this here; that I was probably the only person in the valley that
knew that you could grow beyond that; and that my community had gone through the
same kind of thing, and that we had come out the other side. And that maybe if I
told that, went to that meeting and explained that you could get beyond this,
that maybe they would. And so I don&#039;t remember how it came to his
attention--maybe through a mutual friend--but David Bortin--that&#039;s
B-O-R-T-I-N--who was an attorney in Walnut Creek, heard that I was planning to
attend the meeting.

STEIN: Was it the improvement association?

SOSKIN: This was the improvement association.

STEIN: Okay, so you were going to go right up against--

SOSKIN: Yeah!

STEIN: --your adversaries.

SOSKIN: They were just people. And I knew that you could get beyond that. And so
why not?

STEIN: Absolutely.

SOSKIN: And so David called me and said, &quot;Do you realize that this is really
emotionally dangerous?&quot; He introduced himself and said, &quot;I understand that you
plan to go out and--people can really be cruel.&quot; I said, yes, I knew. I had
suffered through that, and I knew that people could get beyond that; and that
that couple had bought their house and they deserved to live in it; and that I
knew that that could happen. And I said I was going to go. And he said, &quot;Well,
okay, if you insist. I will be in the room. So just be--.&quot; And I did. I dressed
my very, very nicest, very conservatively, all beiges and browns [they laugh]
from I. Magnin&#039;s, and drove in my wood-paneled station wagon. All the
stereotypes of suburban living, right?

STEIN: Right.

SOSKIN: I drive out into the grammar school building in Pleasant Hill and jumped
out of my car and walked into the room. And it was filled. And I sit on the end,
about in the middle. And unfortunately, no one recognized me as being African
American. I had told David that my color was going to protect me, because the
people don&#039;t say those things when there&#039;s a person of color present, and that I
knew that was going to protect me. And when I walked in the room, they didn&#039;t
recognize that I was a person of color. And the meeting went on as if I weren&#039;t
there. And I heard things I had never heard before. At the point where someone
said, &quot;If we fail to get them out under any other basis, we can use the Health
Department, on the basis of the filthy diseases they bring in.&quot; At which point,
I got up and went to the front of the room and said, &quot;I really am feeling like
I&#039;m eavesdropping. I need you to know that I&#039;m one of the undesirables,&quot; because
they kept saying undesirables. They didn&#039;t say niggers, they said undesirables.
I said, &quot;I&#039;m one of the undesirable people that you&#039;re referring to. And I want
you to know that.&quot;

And then I went into my little speech. Maybe took the floor to a stunned
audience of about ten or fifteen minutes, and then panicked and ran out of the
room into the dark, because it had become dark. When I walked into the building,
it was daylight. Ran out of the building, hearing footsteps behind me as I ran
out. And I didn&#039;t know whether I was being chased--. Now, all the warnings of
David Bortin began to surface, that I was in a dangerous situation. But by the
time I reached my car, a man came up and tapped me on the shoulder, identified
himself in the dark as a reporter, and wanted to know my name. Said that he had
to get back in there to see what happened as a result of my talk, but that he
wanted my number because he would call me as soon as the meeting was over, when
he got back to his office. And then the next person who came up--and by now, I&#039;m
getting into my car, panicked--is David Bortin. And he said, &quot;Betty, I&#039;m here.&quot;
He said, &quot;Go home and I&#039;ll call you.&quot;

I went into my house and I&#039;m trembling. It was the scariest thing I think I have
ever done. I didn&#039;t know what had happened. But the reporter did call. And he
said, &quot;Those sounds you heard as you were coming out of foot--.&quot; He said, &quot;What
they did was that they decided--.&quot; Someone got up and said that he had gone to
high school with me and that he didn&#039;t know what had happened to me, but that
the Communists use people like this to spread their message. And completely just
tore me up. He said, &quot;But the people who came out behind you left the meeting
when you did.&quot; He said, &quot;I don&#039;t think that the improvement association will
ever meet again.&quot; And they didn&#039;t. But I didn&#039;t know that most of those
people--and this reinforced my sense that people are good--most of the people
apparently were in there out of curiosity. They were not there because they
wanted those people out. What I reinforced was their conviction that this was
something that needed to be done. So ultimately, that reinforced my sense that
we can get beyond this stuff. That there have always been people trying to get
it right. The history&#039;s been written by people who got it wrong. And I don&#039;t
think anything in my life has denied that, ever since. Time seems to be on the
side of justice. The people really do. Except today. [they laugh]

STEIN: One exception. So when you made this connection with David Borsten--

SOSKIN: Bortin. He was a Unitarian.

STEIN: Okay, so then did he--?

SOSKIN: That&#039;s when I became a Unitarian.

STEIN: And was it that he followed up the next day, or after that he--?

SOSKIN: We remain friends. We remain friends. He introduced me to a whole group
of people who were meeting then, about twenty-five or thirty families, in Nona
Bickerton&#039;s living room in Walnut Creek, who were an offshoot of the Berkeley
Unitarian church [First Unitarian Church of Berkeley], led by Dr. Raymond Cope,
C-O-P-E. [laughs] And I discovered that there was a religion, or at least a
philosophy--I didn&#039;t know what it was at that time; I couldn&#039;t tell what it
was--that was not based on answers; that all it was a collection of individuals
who were convinced of one thing, and that&#039;s that questions were where the action
is. And that if I develop my questions, that those answers are ever changing.
But that there were Christian Unitarians, that there were Buddhist Unitarians,
that there were Jewish Unitarians, that there were atheist Unitarians; that that
was not where the emphasis was. It was not in what we agreed upon. Those were
not things. It was possible.

At that point, I had a child who tested in the 99th percentile in science and
math. Rick--this was my gay son--Rick was so bright, the adopted child, that I
had tried--and I&#039;m still trying to make him a Catholic, right? [they laugh] Even
though I couldn&#039;t be a Catholic. Because I had promised his mother, right? Who
was nonexistent. And when he was about seven or eight years old, he was building
crystal sets. He was receiving radio signals. And I put him in catechism class
to study for his first communion, because my parents were saying, &quot;Doesn&#039;t
matter what you believe; you&#039;ve got to raise these children in a belief system
to save them, make them go to heaven,&quot; which I didn&#039;t believe in. And he was
coming home saying, &quot;Mom, if it takes thus and so many light years for a star&#039;s
light to reach from this star to the next one, how long does it take an angel?&quot;
I think, &quot;This kid&#039;s not going to make it.&quot; [they laugh] This kid is not going
to be a Catholic. So in order to satisfy my need for an intellectual community
in which I could expand my religious beliefs, or at least my spirituality, and
that I wouldn&#039;t have to answer my children&#039;s questions with God made the sky
blue, that this was the place for me to be. And it still is. I finally outgrew
that, but it did suffice for most of my lifetime. And it provided a community
that I considered to call home.

STEIN: Were your children ever involved in the Unitarian Church?

SOSKIN: My children were raised in the Unitarian Church. One is now a devout
Catholic. [laughs]

STEIN: Oh, wow.

SOSKIN: And I go with him to church occasionally. But that&#039;s his right. And I
think it&#039;s largely because of the family history and his need to tie to that.
Bob is probably an atheist, or at least an agnostic. Because the nature of our
conversations--and thank God my husband was away because I got to control all
the religious life of my children. His confusion--. [laughs] But Bob, his coming
in one day and saying--he was late for dinner. And I said, &quot;Where were you?&quot; And
he said, &quot;I was just sitting on the front porch with Randy and his mother.&quot; And
he said, &quot;We were having a conversation.&quot; And he said, &quot;You know, she kept
spouting the Bible to me, and she would do chapter and verse. And she asked me
something that I couldn&#039;t answer.&quot; And I said, &quot;What was that?&quot; And he said,
&quot;She asked me if I was an atheist.&quot; And he&#039;s now about thirteen. And I said, not
knowing what the answer was going to be, &quot;Are you?&quot; And he said, &quot;Well,&quot; he
says, &quot;I didn&#039;t know, but,&quot; he said, &quot;on the way home, I realized I&#039;m not.&quot; And
I said, &quot;Okay, so what do you say you are?&quot; And he says, &quot;Well,&quot; he said, &quot;I
don&#039;t know what I am, but,&quot; he said, &quot;there&#039;s no one up there not to believe
in.&quot; I thought, &quot;This is profound.&quot; [they laugh]

STEIN: Coming from a teenager.

SOSKIN: This is a thirteen-year-old. And we still have the most spirited
conversations about spirituality.

STEIN: Fascinating.

SOSKIN: And then I felt successful. And I do still. That David can be a
practicing Catholic and that Bob can be whatever he is, which I don&#039;t know, is a
sign of success. Because there&#039;s room for all of us, because we&#039;re not dependent
upon answers. So, yeah.

STEIN: You said--[comments with crew]--that there were some liberal members of
the community who wanted to befriend you to sort of authenticate their expansiveness.

SOSKIN: I think that&#039;s always true, yeah.

STEIN: Did you feel that same sentiment within the Unitarian community?

SOSKIN: No. No. That proved out to be authentic, as an experience and as a
connection. If there were those people initially, they evolved beyond that. An
indication is that when the sixties occurred--and I&#039;m living out there in the
suburbs, not being quite black enough for the city and not quite white enough
for the suburbs--[laughs] and this was my community, initially, it was upsetting
because I didn&#039;t know where I was. I was enjoying, by now, all of the advantages
of being a suburban housewife, and all of the disadvantages; but having lots and
lots to share with the people I was living among. When that, which could&#039;ve been
as disruptive, happened those people financed individually my experiencing the
black revolution nationally. They sent me to conventions that were black
caucuses. Not as a corporate decision, but people would send me checks with
notes saying, &quot;This, you ought to understand.&quot; And I was bringing back reports from--

STEIN: And you weren&#039;t--

SOSKIN: And I was on the national board of the Unitarian Black Caucus when the
Unitarian intellectuals had pulled out of the body. And I had pulled out with
them, with the consent of my church, who supported me in that. My minister and I
were collecting money for the Panthers and delivering it to Kathleen and
Eldridge Cleaver in San Francisco. In the suburbs. We brought a black dance
company in to perform at the local auditoriums&#039; civic center, so that that could
be experienced in the white suburbs. They supported me in my growth toward
blackness. And there&#039;s nothing fake about that. They supported my involvement in
the Black Caucus on a secret ballot, and there were only two votes against. And
both those people who voted against my being supported sent me notes. And their
fear was that I was going to be distanced from them. So even in that, there was
a positive thing.

STEIN: That&#039;s amazing.

SOSKIN: That experience was amazing. I don&#039;t know who can make that kind of
claim. And I think all that went into where my life went.

STEIN: Do you think that there is a larger role of the Unitarian Church in
advancing race relations or discussions of the sixties that has been left out of history?

SOSKIN: I think that the effect of the sixties in the Unitarian Church was
heading toward that kind of global change in attitudes racially. I think that it
got sidetracked, because we went into the eighties, which was the &quot;me&quot;
generation--the Werner Erhards and the human potential movement--and people
turned in, even in the Unitarian Church.

And that broader thing shrunk. Its African American membership, I think, may be
greater now than it&#039;s ever been, but I don&#039;t think it&#039;s ever been the way it
should be. Mostly because the African Americans are still-- I think that
fundamentalism is still the strength of the black church, and that there&#039;s not
that much of a pool of black intellectuals that will be attracted by
Unitarianism. I think it&#039;s the only way to go. [they laugh] But I outgrew it
because I didn&#039;t really need it anymore.

STEIN: Right. It&#039;s a really fascinating story.

STEIN: Once again, we&#039;re here with Betty Reid Soskin. This is Julie Stein, June
25, 2010, tape two. So we&#039;ve been talking about the Unitarian Church, about your
experience in Walnut Creek. I would love to jump backwards in time just a little
bit, if you don&#039;t mind, and talk a little bit more about high school and your
earlier life. I don&#039;t know if this is things that you remember quite as well,
but it sounds like your memory&#039;s really remarkable. But in your last oral
history, there was some stuff that you mentioned about academics and teachers.
I&#039;m curious if you could talk a little bit more about the social side. You
mentioned some really remarkable young men who you dated briefly. [they laugh]

STEIN: What was social life like as a young high school student in--East
Oakland? You were in high school there?

SOSKIN: Yeah. I attended Castlemont High School, when it was actually a castle.
[they laugh] Really, it was a beautiful, beautiful castle. But didn&#039;t survive, I
guess, earthquake damage. Or it was retrofitted and all those bricks had to come
down and the parapets. But at the time that I was in high school, there were
very few African Americans in that high school, or even in East Oakland. We
probably knew all the families that were in East Oakland, and were related to
many of them. But my high school, I don&#039;t remember very much on campus. It was
mostly spent in my social life, outside of campus because where my schoolmates
were dating the guy who pumped gas at the local gas station, I was attending
activities at fraternities and sororities on the UC campus. The men in my life
were two or three years older, as was the men that I married. So that I was
probably more mature in my social development than the white kids that I was
involved with.

STEIN: Do you know why? Or what led to you hanging out with the college students?

SOSKIN: Because my social world was controlled by my parents. And that world was
largely French Creole out of New Orleans who had migrated to California during
the teens and the twenties. You have to understand that long before the Second
World War, Pullman porters were discovering the West Coast. This was a place
where, for instance, schools were not segregated. This is where one lived was
not dictated by real estate developers or social mores; that this was, in the
African-American community, at least in my part of the African-American
community, really, the land of opportunity. And when you were leaving the
hostile South in those years--for instance, my family came in 1927--they set up
social systems here on the West Coast that weren&#039;t dependent upon institutions
that were general. The fact that Mary Castro, who would&#039;ve been my friend, who
was Portuguese, that I went through school with, her life centered around the
Holy Ghost Hall. Portuguese. That vying for being the queen of Columbus Day was
big in her life; Mardi Gras was big in my life. So that there were things like
the YWCA that were segregated. We knew that Lulu Chapman was our mentor; that
there were kids in our community who went to the Jewish school on Saturdays;
that there were these ethnically diverse institutions, which my high school kids
went to. So that my going to the YWCA or going to black fraternity and sorority
events was not a place of being separated out. These were affinity groups. So
that I didn&#039;t feel that my not participating in the prom was any particular
incident. I went to--was it my junior prom? Which was very disillusioning.

STEIN: In what ways?

SOSKIN: It was at--I don&#039;t remember the hall. But it was the first time I had
ever attended a social event where everybody was white but me. But before the
evening was over, everybody was drunk. That had never been true in my world. In
my world, people held debut parties when they turned eighteen. We were highly
socialized. If anything, I thought we were snobs. So I didn&#039;t feel separated out
from my high school experience; but nor do I remember this being memorable.
Because weekends were the times when I came alive. And because my parents were
not involved. I didn&#039;t even bring report cards home. In fact, I don&#039;t remember
ever discussing anything in high school with my mother and father, except maybe
the language choices. My mother thought I should take Spanish because I look
more Spanish than--and assuming then, of course, that I would pass when I got a
job. I wanted to take French because that was the language of gossip in my family.

STEIN: Right. [laughs]

SOSKIN: And maybe because they wanted to protect it, essentially. [they laugh]
No one ever taught it to us.

STEIN: When you would go out on dates with boys who you were seeing, would you
bring them home? Were your parents involved in that aspect of your life?

SOSKIN: Oh, yes! Oh, my, yes. My social life was very, very controlled. We
belonged to a young women&#039;s club. There were weddings and christenings and debut
parties. We had a very, very rich social life. And didn&#039;t really--high school
was a non-event. I don&#039;t remember very much about it, except the rough places.
The place I guess I mentioned, about trying out for Miriamne in Winterset, and
being turned down because they couldn&#039;t pair me with the white guy I was reading
with. I remember that. I remember public speaking class. I remember not very
much because it wasn&#039;t important. I also don&#039;t remember striving very hard. I
don&#039;t remember being tested. I think I wasted an awful lot of--I always got
passing grades; I never failed anything. I always got A&#039;s and B&#039;s. But I never
was tested. I never had to strive. I didn&#039;t know that that was probably because
I was very bright.

STEIN: Right. Right. So it sounds like the really important times were not in
school, but the social aspect of life, at that point.

SOSKIN: Yeah. And to the extent that I was successful eventually in the suburbs
probably is based on the fact that I was very successful socially as a Creole.
So that I was taking my rightful place, right? [they laugh]

STEIN: Right. I&#039;m curious, what was a sort of an off topic that you mentioned:
Mardi Gras. What was Mardi Gras like as a New Orleans migrant community out in
the East Bay?

SOSKIN: It was not picked up. It was not celebrated. I remember the religious
aspect. I remember the novenas during Lent. From a very, very early age, I
remember my entire family being involved in the Catholic rituals of Lent and
Easter and Good Friday. I remember my mother&#039;s set getting together the night
before--I guess it was Shrove Tuesday, which would put it in Mardi Gras. And the
women would get together to make head cheese, which was one of the meals, one of
the--whatever it was. I don&#039;t remember them making it any other time during the
year. I remember my dad, who was an amateur musician, getting his little trio
together and their banging the pots and pans and playing combs and tissue paper.
I remember the internal home Mardi Gras kinds of things, events. I don&#039;t
remember there being any collective kinds of things when I was a kid growing up.
And during the Great Migration of the home front, that would&#039;ve been buried
under by the kinds of African-American culture that came out of the South with
the people who came here. Which means that I heard the Negro national anthem
[Lift Every Voice and Sing] for the first time when I was twenty-one. And I
thought it was very subversive. [they laugh] How can you have a Negro national
anthem, when we already have one? Because those people had learned of it in high
schools and colleges, in black institutions. So that that Mardi Gras thing, that
Creole thing, was completely shot down, and has only, I think circuitously, come
back with celebrations rooted in the Caribbean, in recent years.

STEIN: That&#039;s so interesting.

SOSKIN: But are not something that I feel necessarily a part of.

STEIN: Then to jump back to what we were talking about before, historians are
starting to look at things like dating, social life more seriously. So if this
sounds like a silly question, forgive me. [they laugh] But were there rules that
you remember in dating culture? Were there people who went steady? Were there
people who were dating people, one date with every boy that they knew? Was there
a division of good girls versus fast girls? Do you remember some of the rules
around that?

SOSKIN: No, it&#039;s very funny. I suppose two weeks from now, I&#039;ll think back.

STEIN: Well, you give me a call; I&#039;ll be here. [laughs]

SOSKIN: But it was such an individual thing. There were unwritten rules that we
all knew from our parents. Good girls didn&#039;t stay out all night. There was no
question of cohabitation. We wouldn&#039;t--I don&#039;t remember whether or not one
kissed on the first date, but I don&#039;t think we did. I think that that would&#039;ve
sent a signal that wasn&#039;t necessarily--I don&#039;t remember much effort being put
into attracting boys. The girls in my group pretty much attracted boys. [they laugh]

STEIN: Didn&#039;t have to try to hard.

SOSKIN: We were kind of pretty. At that point, color and texture of hair were
really, really important in my community. That&#039;s since gotten much, much less
important. I remember it becoming important again during the sixties, when I
tried to get a natural and couldn&#039;t. [they laugh] It wouldn&#039;t stand up.

STEIN: Did you recall anybody getting pregnant in high school, before there was--?

SOSKIN: Yeah. I certainly do remember that. But those girls disappeared. I don&#039;t
remember what even happened to them. But you just dropped out. I don&#039;t remember
anyone being pregnant in high school. You were hidden away by your family.

STEIN: But you knew about it to a certain extent?

SOSKIN: Only as rumor. After the fact.

STEIN: And they just went away?

SOSKIN: Yeah. No one ever really admitted that that was what happened. Or you
came up with a little brother at some point, a little sister.

STEIN: Right. Right.

SOSKIN: But that was really shame.

STEIN: Were there, I guess on the flip side, people who got married quite early?

SOSKIN: No, I think that that must&#039;ve been driven by the fact that there were so
few options for my generation. That women&#039;s choices were to be an agricultural
or domestic servant. Marriage, when you&#039;re given those choices, is really,
really premium. If you could marry a successful man, a student in college who
was heading for a career, you were considered the most promising of women.
That&#039;s when you were successful. As I think I said, or I heard myself say in the
oral history, that my mother once said of a very unattractive girl that they
better educate that girl because she&#039;s not going to get a husband. [they laugh]
So that there was a premium on physical attractiveness. And those of us who were
married at twenty were really considered successful women.

STEIN: You said that one of your sisters was married at sixteen.

SOSKIN: She was married during the war, to a serviceman. So that would have
jarred up all those customs.

STEIN: So those rules were different.

SOSKIN: She would never have--she must&#039;ve married about 1944. She married a serviceman.

STEIN: Was he leaving--?

SOSKIN: Someone that she had known. But they married because naturally,
that--and she went with him to a Texas base or something. So that broke through
those customs.

STEIN: I assume she couldn&#039;t have gone if she was just a girlfriend.

SOSKIN: Oh, no, no. No, no, no, no.

STEIN: That would&#039;ve been--

SOSKIN: No, she wouldn&#039;t. You&#039;ve got to be married.

STEIN: Yeah. Okay. I can pass it off to you for a minute. I have about a million
more questions, but I want to make sure that--

ARBONA: Yeah, okay.

STEIN: Do you want to switch places?

ARBONA: Sure.

STEIN: Okay. Well, I know that he&#039;s going to ask some questions about Port
Chicago. But since we&#039;ve gotten to World War II, in the first oral history, you
certainly speak about the war years. But I think because the project was so
focused on Richmond, Richmond, there&#039;s a sense to which I think there&#039;s more to
learn about how the war affected your life. Not being someone who was working in
the shipyards, but I&#039;m sure that there were--or I imagine that there were still
some really profound shifts in your life because of that. Is that something that--?

SOSKIN: You&#039;d have to be more specific.

STEIN: Well, I suppose first of all, do you remember Pearl Harbor? Do you
remember the--?

SOSKIN: Oh, yes. I remember great fear about that. I also remember being very,
very confused. And I think that that colors my whole response to all these
questions about the war. Because I wasn&#039;t always sure who the enemy was. There
was the Double-V campaign. There was the fact that I was being re-identified
externally. There were all kinds of prohibitions now that hadn&#039;t been before. I
was being blocked in with people that I had little in common with, I felt.

STEIN: Were these the black newcomers?

SOSKIN: Just newcomers, period. I remember being terrified of the air raid
sirens, of living in a dim-out, living where everything had been turned down,
where the sides of street lights that face the ocean were painted deep gray in
order to not silhouette the Bay Area for submarines. I remember being very,
very, very aware of all of those things, of being in a constant threat of
bombing. And as I say, not having the security of that built-in patriotism that
came with being a part of the war effort, I didn&#039;t share with the people around
me. I don&#039;t remember feeling--well, wait, that doesn&#039;t even doesn&#039;t get at it.
There was a schizophrenic kind of thing, where I had grown up as a proud
American, devoid of color; and therefore, had this sense of shame about what
America was doing. And to the extent that I was a part of that colorless system,
I couldn&#039;t understand what we--in which I am now incorporated--were doing to all
these people like me, the schizophrenic African American. That schizophrenic
stance, I think, is almost at the root of the mental break that I suffered many,
many years later. Also that marks my movement to the suburbs and becoming in a
white world, as opposed to becoming a political activist in the black world. All
of that was set in motion by the war years, where I had this awful thing going
of feeling, on the one hand, a part of and benefiting by a system that negated
my worth as a person, as a black person. And it was very confusing.

STEIN: You mentioned that your husband had enlisted and was given the option to
be, what, a cook?

SOSKIN: Yeah. He&#039;s in his third year, his senior year at the University of San
Francisco. Is also a renowned athlete; he was a halfback with the San Francisco
Dons. He went on to be a professional football player, quarterback, and of some
note, had made All Coast, the Pacific coast; and volunteered, as his American
self without color, to fight for his country. Because he had grown up in the
West, without any of those old bans that we would live with. He volunteered and
found himself at Great Lakes. And had been, he felt, tricked into the Messman&#039;s
Corps, because that was the only thing an African American male could do in the
Second World War in the navy. So that he had chosen to fight for his country,
and objected. And lasted three days, under intense questioning by a board of
examiners. And because he was fair skinned with Caucasian features, though
African American and always been proudly so, was sent home with mustering out
pay, with an honorable discharge. And with the advice from the psychiatrist who
had examined him that he didn&#039;t know why he had entered the service as a black
man; that he should&#039;ve come in as a white man; but that the Navy could not
afford to put him onboard a ship with men who might be easily led, because he
was a natural leader of men. And he found himself on a train for home three days
later. Now, that colored his withdrawal, and he went to work then as a trainee
for the shipyards.

STEIN: Was that a similar awakening experience for you? What experiences--?

SOSKIN: Well, I was having my own experience, because I went to work for the Air
Force. While he was gone, or two weeks before he was gone, I was transferred
from the Civil Service Commission in San Francisco to a job with the Air Force,
which had taken over the Leamington Hotel on Franklin Street in Oakland. I was a
transfer, and therefore had not filled out application papers and didn&#039;t know
that the Air Force didn&#039;t hire African Americans, except in the canteen, to be
service workers. And found myself in a position that I would not have had, had
they not misread my race. And the lieutenant in charge of our section took it on
himself to notify the woman whose desk abutted mine, to say that he thought that
she ought to know that I was black. Or colored. And when she came back to her
desk, very red-faced, I asked what he&#039;d said. I had discovered, meanwhile, by
meeting another African American, who was actually passing, in the restroom,
that she was claiming to be German. And she asked me what I was passing for, and
I very innocently said, &quot;Nothing.&quot; And she said, &quot;You must be, because they
don&#039;t hire black people.&quot; So this happened just a couple of days ahead, or maybe
the day before. So I was sensitive to what that might have been, that I was
being discovered.

So I walked up to the lieutenant and asked him why he had seen me fit; that I
was not passing, and who had told him that I was colored? I understood from him,
or at least from someone, that someone in the canteen who was also African
American had turned me in. Because I was working as a clerical worker and I was
not supposed to be doing that. But he did say that I shouldn&#039;t worry because he
had talked with my supervisor and that my work was very good; and that the women
in my section were, quote and unquote, &quot;willing to work with me.&quot; At which
point, I said, &quot;But will they be willing to work under me when I&#039;m upgraded?&quot;
And I walked out on the Air Force, just before I heard that Mel was coming home.

STEIN: That&#039;s fascinating how parallel--

SOSKIN: So that this happened to both of us. Which is why we went into business.
We would not work for anybody else. He was working at the shipyards in order to
facilitate his growing business so that we could become independent, eventually.
And we did. So that World War II experience was really a coming-of-age thing for
us, racially. And we had to choose. We had to choose an identity.

STEIN: And that was basically forced upon you because of--

SOSKIN: Oh, sure.

STEIN: --the organization of the war industries.

SOSKIN: Yeah. I&#039;m not sure what our lives would&#039;ve been like. But then they all
give you experience. I don&#039;t know what that would be.

STEIN: That&#039;s so fascinating that they really are one and the same; the racism
of the war, it sounds like, you were confronted with almost immediately.

SOSKIN: That&#039;s right. But people who came out of the South to work as
sharecroppers--and this is something that comes with my ranger self. When I read
now treatises, doctoral papers, studies that are only now beginning to come
out--people are only beginning now to study that era. But you read a
sharecropper&#039;s experience, who, in Mississippi, would have had to step off the
sidewalk when a white person was approaching; could be lynched by making eye
contact with a white woman in a town--. When you realize that those two
people--that that white person who had right of way on the sidewalk and that
black person who had to step into the gutter to let that person pass--was then
brought here to the greater Bay Area in huge numbers to build those ships; the
black person, with this huge expectation for a fuller life because those Pullman
porters hadn&#039;t been lying, things are better in the West; and that white person,
who was expecting a continuation of white privilege, came together in this
cauldron and changed social reformation--I mean, forever; and that Mel and I,
who had grown up without the complication of having to choose sides, who were
first and foremost Americans, had to suffer the disappointment in that
definition, as well as being lumped in with people whose experiences we had not
shared, had to be a period of huge, huge dislocation for us.

STEIN: Absolutely.

SOSKIN: I can&#039;t imagine why it wouldn&#039;t have had its effect upon who we became.
Mel&#039;s life, in his business, became more centered in the African-American
community. My life became more centered in a changing suburban community. I was
lucky enough to feel myself a part of that change. That because I didn&#039;t
compromise in my suburban existence, I brought my whole self with me into the
suburbs and lived that out. And I think that that--we could not have stayed
married. I think that we were destined to live separate lives because our lives
took us in those directions. And I think it&#039;s telling that we remained friends
after our divorce; that we reclaimed that fourteen- to seventeen-year-old kids&#039;
friendship, because we had parented four children. And that identity as parents
withstood the divorce, even though I remarried--he never did. But even though I
remarried, we remained friends.

STEIN: Let&#039;s take a transition here. Yeah, pause for a second. [audiofile stops, re-starts]

ARBONA: So now this is Javier Arbona on the recording now. And we&#039;re still on
tape two, right? Actually, now that you&#039;re mentioning that article, perhaps we
can just warm up a little bit. If you can just summarize what you wrote in this
article for The California Historian. And that could be a way to transition
between what you were talking about, the Bay Area in the forties and the Port
Chicago explosion.

SOSKIN: Yeah. The article came about at the invitation of the editor of The
California Historian, which is the journal of the California Historical
Societies of the State of California. These are not academic papers. These are
largely oral histories from members of the historical society. When I was
invited to write the article, I had never written such an article. I&#039;m not an
academic, and my career is based totally on memory. I don&#039;t pretend to be a
historian. But this was asking me to sort of codify that into a statement about
that period. Because I&#039;m not a professional writer, I kept getting lost. Every
time I would try to rewrite a sentence, it would turn into something else.
[laughs] Because I was not coming out of it as an academic, as a trained writer.
I finally wound up with so much paper, with so many paragraphs, with so many
pages, that I turned it over to our chief interpreter and said, &quot;Somebody has to
know what I&#039;m saying, because people are going to read this as if it is formal
history from a historian. And you at the park, you need to know what I&#039;m saying,
because my claims are not based in any kind of proven fact.&quot; And nobody really
had the time for it. Naomi Torres, who was at that point chief of
interpretation, said, &quot;It&#039;s too long, Betty, but I don&#039;t know how to cut it
down. You&#039;ll have to edit.&quot; And I said, &quot;I don&#039;t know how to edit, because
everything that&#039;s here is important.&quot; So on a chance, I sent it in, submitted it
to the paper and said, &quot;You are free to edit this in whatever way you can, for
continuity and for content; but I don&#039;t know how to edit this. I&#039;m being
perfectly honest.&quot;

It takes a global view of the greater Bay Area, which my belief is that this has
to all become, at some point, a heritage district, that Richmond does not stand
alone, that there were thirteen shipbuilding operations here, that there were
innumerable sites that all--. Some of them have been destroyed, but all of them
need to be remembered. And at some point, I think this story is going to have to
be--that Rosie is simply one piece; that Port Chicago is one piece; that all of
these Lettermen in the Presidio--all this stuff--Hunters Point, there&#039;s
Marinship--all of these things have to become a part of it. So I made the case
for that in this article. About a month later, I get a letter from the editor
saying, &quot;We would like to use this as the cover article, and we&#039;re not going to
edit it. [laughs]

ARBONA: Well, we&#039;ve got to look that up.

SOSKIN: Obviously, it came out. It&#039;s about five or six pages long. [laughs]

ARBONA: Well, in reference to Port Chicago, I guess what I want to start with
was to ask you about the party that you have referred to in so many places.
You&#039;ve talked about the party in your last oral history and in the news. Can you
walk us through that day? Maybe how you were getting ready and whatnot.

SOSKIN: I&#039;m not sure I can recapture that. It&#039;s mostly in my memory in sort of
broad strokes. I lived in a small duplex at 3107 Sacramento Street in Berkeley.
The reason that&#039;s important is that down Sacramento Street was the Santa Fe rail
line, in the middle of our street. So that the home front was playing itself out
right in front of my door. Day and night, there were huge, long trains of people
being brought in from the five Southern states--or at least from everywhere, but
mostly from the five Southern states--to work in the shipyards; hanging out of
windows--because at that time, the windows weren&#039;t sealed in trains--hanging out
of windows, leaning out of the vestibules, waving. And we were sort of the
welcome committee, all along our street. We would wave people into California.
And down Ashby, which had Ashby Camp, which was a camp of all African-American
soldiers who were MPs. I think they could only arrest black AWOLs. [laughs] But
they were MPs, nonetheless. So they were a presence in the community. They were
at the foot of Ashby Avenue, at Camp Ashby. So the presence of the war was
there. I only discovered that there were black USOs, I guess since I&#039;ve been
working for the National Park Service, because I simply knew that the USO was
segregated, that it did not entertain African American service people. Because
as I say, we were in the black community--well, it was not the black community
until that time, but there were lots and lots of African Americans living--

We entertained the servicemen--either from Port Chicago, from Camp Stoneman,
from Camp Ashby--in our homes. This was largely innocent lemonade parties,
Saturday afternoons. These were not places where--we were sort of the homes away
from home. And we were young, as I was saying, twenty--. This was maybe 1942.
Because I was married, so it would&#039;ve been after May 1942, which is when I was
married. Through 1944. Would&#039;ve have been that two year period, that would have
been common. But it was common to all the families, the African American
families, who felt this camaraderie with the African American people. And
because we knew that they were not permitted in the [USOs].

So that that afternoon, there must&#039;ve been maybe a dozen or so young people from
Port Chicago who--and I don&#039;t remember how we would&#039;ve gathered them up. That&#039;s
a piece that&#039;s missing. I don&#039;t know that because of my upbringing, we would&#039;ve
been gathering people in off the streets. I don&#039;t know whether it would have
been at San Pablo Park, which we would--Mel was working at San Pablo Park during
the day, as a playground director, which was in the community. And he was
working a swing shift at night. So he might well have met these people in the
park, because we wouldn&#039;t have felt safe to bring people in off the streets. So
my guess is that they would&#039;ve been hanging around maybe baseball games or
tennis matches, and he would have brought them home. So that would account for
their being at the house.

We were dancing to records. It would have meant that my neighbor around the
corner, Lela, whose husband worked with Mel in the shipyards, would&#039;ve been one
of those girls. They were probably unmarried young women, though maybe not,
because Johnnie, Lela&#039;s husband--but they were men that he worked with on the
ships, that would--. And there were also athletes that would&#039;ve been a part of
his life. My guess is that these were probably young, unmarried people. I don&#039;t
remember any of them outside of the men. And this young sailor named Richert,
R-I-C-H-E-R-T. And the reason I remember him was because he looked white. He
would&#039;ve been like Mel, only more Caucasian in appearance. And that people
questioned his being there. For the first hour or so, they didn&#039;t know what he
was doing there because he was obviously an outsider. And he had to defend his
status as a person of color. And I don&#039;t know what the conversation was, except
that we learned in that conversation that he was only sixteen. He had lied about
his age to get into the service. And he was the one, probably because of his
age, that I have continued to worry about all these years, as to what was his
fate. And I remember because my name was French, Charbonnet, and his name was
Richert, was R-I-C-H-E-R-T, that there must have been an affinity between us.
And his name does not appear on the memorial. So he has continued to be an
enigma to me. I don&#039;t remember any of the other names.

I remember when they left it was because there was some sort of curfew, either
in their company or at their jobs; or that it was related to that they would be
traveling in the dim outback to Port Chicago, because they left before dark. And
that that explosion happened at ten-thirty and we were not yet asleep. And that
we didn&#039;t recognize it as an explosion, but thought it was finally that Japanese
had made it, that somewhere there was a bombing; or that there was an
earthquake, because we lived in earthquake country; and that that wouldn&#039;t
become clear until morning news, when the announcement came that Port
Chicago--there&#039;d been an explosion in which two ships were lost. And my
immediate connection and my immediate sense--that scar has continued to live
with me, because I never knew what happened to Richert.

ARBONA: Would that come from the radio or the newspapers, how you found out
about it the next day?

SOSKIN: It would probably have come from the radio. Either that or whenever
there was a development of import, there would be the shouters, the news hawks,
who would go down the street yelling, &quot;Extra, extra, read all about it.&quot; Those
people were a part. And I remember them as being related to the sounds of my
childhood; of the hawkers of fruits and vegetables or of cream cheese, which
came in little cups; and that there would be, then, street vendors saying,
&quot;Watermelon, red to the rind;&quot; and that this would have morphed into those
&quot;Extras&quot; that were part of my childhood; and that those became a part of the
World War II extra news of disasters; that there was a timeline in which all
those things were related. So I would guess that that would--. And I don&#039;t know
whether that would&#039;ve come during the night, either the Call-Bulletin or the
Chronicle or the Examiner, which were the papers of the day, which is probably
likely. They would have preceded even the radio.

ARBONA: Can I go back for a moment to also thinking about this party? Because
this young man that you mention is actually pretty typical of some of the--at
least there were other Port Chicago men who also enlisted before the age of eighteen.

SOSKIN: Oh, yes.

ARBONA: I think Joseph Simon and--so it&#039;s interesting to think of a party where
maybe these teenagers are dancing with maybe women that are, what, in their
twenties. So it&#039;s quite different from maybe what you think of a party today.

SOSKIN: I think that there&#039;s implied in your question, or even the way it&#039;s
phrased, that these would have been, quote, &quot;older women&quot; with younger men, with
teenagers. I think that I would&#039;ve framed this that these would&#039;ve been
hostessing young service people. But not with any kind of sensual, sexual
implications. They would&#039;ve seen themselves as the Hollywood stars saw
themselves, as being USO hostesses. There&#039;s an innocence about that. I don&#039;t
remember it being as anything other than that. There probably were some younger
girls mixed in there. And the women would have been in the minority. And the
more we talked about it, the more I would think that these men would&#039;ve come in
as a result of Mel&#039;s inviting them; that sports would&#039;ve been probably the topic
of conversation; that the status of the latest black barnstorming baseball team
would have been what they were talking about. These were definitely not what
your question hints at. It would have been simply very innocent.

ARBONA: Well, I&#039;m curious. What would be the polite thing to do? How would
people go about dancing? Would somebody ask somebody out for a dance, or how
would that work?

SOSKIN: I think the dancing would have been incidental and that there never
would&#039;ve been more than two or three people on the dance floor. I think the
conversation would--in fact I know that the conversation was probably key. Those
kids would&#039;ve been talking about their families or what they left behind.
Because the young people who would&#039;ve gathered at my house would&#039;ve been
Californians. The people who were the guests would have been from different
cultures, from different communities, from places beyond what we would have
known; that there would&#039;ve been a lot to talk about besides--I think what we
shared was probably a common songbook; that the music would have been the
uniter. We would all have been listening to the same records; that our songbook
was not the songbook of the white people, who would&#039;ve been singing The White
Cliffs of Dover, and we&#039;d have been listening to Slim Gaillard. [laughs] There
were cultural differences, and that that might have been what the hunger in
those kids would have been, was for zapping into that culture. And we would have
been curious about what they were bringing with them. I&#039;d never heard basic
blues before, except maybe my grandfather, when I was gardening with him when I
was a kid. But I didn&#039;t recognize those as blues, or even folk songs; I thought
they were Papa George songs. But that became what I heard from the migrants who
were coming in, was a Papa George connection.

ARBONA: Would people pop in with their own records?

SOSKIN: No. African Americans were very-- That&#039;s why we went into business.
Black music was very, very hard to come by. And Aldo Musso, who was an Italian
man who owned the property that we purchased, the duplex in which we lived, had
built that house for his wife when he married, and loved Mel and I because Mel,
at the age of twenty-three, had saved up enough money to pay a down payment on a
property. We moved into a duplex that Mel bought when we were married. I&#039;m
twenty and he&#039;s twenty-three, and with paper routes and all that sort of thing,
had saved up enough money to buy the house. Which says something about the
stability of this kid and this marriage. And Musso so admired this in him. And
he had a juke box route, and he would take Mel out during the day to service
those boxes. Some of them were in the emerging black communities. And it was
Aldo Musso who had the sources for finding those race records, which they were
called, in among the jobbers, the one-stops, that were bringing them in from the South.

And it was this that launched Mel, who decided that there was a business to be
created here by opening up a retail store where those could be purchased by this
new population that was coming in that had the demand for this. And so our
introduction to those young people from Port Chicago would have fed that; that
they were bringing tastes and music discoveries from the South that--we knew who
Duke Ellington was and Erskine Hawkins and Jimmie Lunceford and all of these
greats; but there was a whole genre of African American music that we didn&#039;t
know. And they were bringing this with them. So that there were things that made
those parties--and I don&#039;t remember there being that many--comfortable for us.
There were things that we were learning from one another. So that dancing
wouldn&#039;t have been--it was socializing, the conversations. It was that stuff.

ARBONA: I&#039;m curious about the conversations because of so much that we read
today about Port Chicago and the conditions and the lack of safety. Was that
discussed? Was that in the conversation? No?

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t remember them. That&#039;s only something I&#039;ve discovered after the
fact. No, I wish I could shed light on that. I know when I read Dr. [Robert L.]
Allen&#039;s book, I kept wanting to fill in blanks with the current Betty. But at
that time, I was not politically aware enough to even be listening for that. I
would not have been--the things that struck me about Dr. Allen&#039;s book was that
Joe was only twenty-three and he was a leader of those men. Which reinforced the
notion that those kids were just kids.

ARBONA: Joe Small.

SOSKIN: Yeah. And he was only twenty-three and he was one of the elders in
there, among those groups. There was another story, and I don&#039;t know whether
it&#039;s turned up in any interviews or my blog; maybe you&#039;ve read it. But I
remember as a ranger, of sitting in at the first day of remembrance at Port
Chicago as a ranger. Or maybe I was not yet.

STEIN: The memorial was inaugurated in &#039;94?

SOSKIN: No, I would not have been aware of the memorial in &#039;94. I had blocked,
pretty much, that era out. I was reintroduced to that whole period as a field
representative for a member of the California State Assembly, because the State
of California owned the property under the Ford plant and the Ford plant was
built on air rights. So that I was sitting in and became aware of the park, even
of Port Chicago, at the time, because I had lived whole decades and decade of
life beyond that World War II period, which was now painless to remember. So I&#039;d
pretty much wiped that out.

But that first day of remembrance, I remember seeing the first two rows that had
signs on them that they were reserved for the survivors of Port Chicago. And
there were only two, I think, African Americans in those seats as they began to
file in. And I didn&#039;t understand why, because by now I had at least become
familiar with the Port Chicago story because I was now involved with the park.
And why were there not more survivors? And I had read Robert Allen&#039;s book, and
he was the speaker for that year, the keynoter. And there was a member of the
National Park Foundation out of Washington, DC, which is involved with
African-American aspects of the story. She was sitting next to me. And at one
point, I remember turning to her and asking her if she could see why there were
not--why were they all white? And as people began to testify, when the keynote
speaker was gone and people began to jump up to talk about their experiences,
they were all survivors of the town of Port Chicago.

So their memories were of being in the theater, of being in bed, having their
walls collapse and windows shot out. And then I remembered that Robert Allen&#039;s
book spoke of the men at Port Chicago, and that I didn&#039;t remember men; I only
remembered boys. And that I suddenly realized that what was being remembered was
dependent upon who was in the room; and that history doesn&#039;t necessarily do a
disservice to African-American memory, as much as it is dependent upon who&#039;s in
the room. And that in time, who was in the room was going to be dominated by the
town of Port Chicago; and that the African American story, even though there
were 202 men lost, was going to simply be covered over--not by design, but by
circumstance; and that those men were too young to have left survivors. And that
the fact that they were boys was key; that those kids who had been in my house
were not married, they would not have fathered children; and that now in
whatever this year, 2006 or 2007 or whatever this was, the remnants of those
lives were suddenly going to be lost. And that it was terribly important that as
a participant in the creation of this park, if it was going to be a
park--because at that time, it was only a monument--I needed to be a surrogate
survivor; that that history was dependent upon people like me remembering. And
that that&#039;s often how history happens; that it&#039;s not that people don&#039;t want to
remember, it&#039;s that circumstances crowd out truth.

STEIN: We have five minutes left on this.

ARBONA: One question I&#039;ll ask, maybe that we can do in these five minutes. Did
you follow the mutiny trial in the papers?

SOSKIN: No. As I say, it&#039;s awfully tempting to speak from the politically savvy
Betty Soskin of today. That woman that I was, was not politically active at that
point. Now, I did become, over the next twenty years, along with everybody
else--as I said in my article, that this became the cauldron for social change,
and I was it. I really do feel that I was contemporary to all those changes as
they developed. And yes, I did become that. But in that period, I would not have
been--I would&#039;ve been aware of the unrest, I would&#039;ve been involved--. I
would&#039;ve been probably aware of the protests. I since have seen pictures of
people protesting outside of the Fairmont Hotel in San Francisco, African
Americans with signs with NAACP. I would have been aware of those. There is a
photograph, an E.F. Joseph photograph that exists in part of the things in the
present collection. I don&#039;t know when I became aware of those. I don&#039;t know,
again, since I moved into the suburbs--in 1950, I would&#039;ve probably moved into
the suburbs. I don&#039;t know whether some of that turmoil happened after I was out
of the city. But I don&#039;t know how, given my later activism, that would escape
me, but I can&#039;t recall that.

ARBONA: Maybe now&#039;s a good point to switch tapes.

ARBONA: So this is now tape number three, on June 25, 2010. And I&#039;m here with
Betty Reid Soskin. This is Javier Arbona. You&#039;ve told us that you blocked out
Port Chicago for a while. But you went back to it. And in your previous oral
history, you talk about going back during--I suppose it&#039;s the sixties?

SOSKIN: Yeah.

ARBONA: Can you talk about what brought you back there?

SOSKIN: I don&#039;t remember how I came about it. Probably it was related to
bringing up children. My mentor during those early activist years was a
Unitarian minister named Aron Gilmartin, who was--

STEIN: How do you spell that?

SOSKIN: G-I-L-M-A-R-T-I-N, A-R-O-N was Aron. I can figure out that he was an
active Socialist. He must&#039;ve been. People have told me that I&#039;m a Marxist. I
have never understood even what a Marxist is, except that whatever it is, Gil
has [laughs] claims on my conversion. But he was also a close friend of Norman
Cousins. His credentials, in terms of activism--he was a member of Ethical
Culture before coming here. He was an uncompromising liberal progressive. And I
don&#039;t know whether I learned from him in words or by inference, that a belief
was not valid unless acted upon; that that&#039;s how one activates a belief. And in
trying to pass that on to my children, whenever a social problem out there
occurred--and this was probably during the sixties and maybe before that,
even--and I think now that maybe it was already embedded in my psyche, because
of the fact that I was able to deal with those people in Pleasant Hill head on;
that it must&#039;ve been there anyway.

But it led me into a series of political acts that involved standing with others
on the roadway to Port Chicago, in a protest, twice. The first time, I flunked
activism. [laughs] The first time, I went out there on my own. And this was
because I wanted--by now, I knew that my son Bob had become politically active
because we&#039;d run into each other at the Oakland Induction Center. [they laugh]
He had cut school. And I was being driven, in part, by Bobby&#039;s political
activism as much as my own, because I needed to prove myself. So that I was sort
of out of my generation, acting out in Bob&#039;s generation. Because this was
Vietnam protests, right? So that Bob was turning up in lots and lots of places.
And he didn&#039;t turn up at Port Chicago. But I knew that there was an action going
by Quakers. So I drove out there. Maybe so I could tell Bob. [laughs] But there
were maybe a dozen people that I didn&#039;t know standing along the roadside. Not
interfering, but challenging the trucks as they went by, by their presence.

And while I was there, a young African-American teenager turned up. None of
these people were speaking, so they may have all been strangers to one another.
Maybe all motivated by the same thing I was. I didn&#039;t know anybody there, and I
didn&#039;t hear any conversations. But it was a vigil. We were clearly individuals
who were acting on principle. And this kid, who was obviously very much younger
than the rest of us, took his place separate and apart from the others. Maybe
because he was from Pittsburgh; I don&#039;t know where he was. But maybe because we
were all grownups. Maybe it was just that. But he, I recall distinctly, standing
back about maybe six feet over and three feet back from the rest of the line.
And I was at the other end of the line. And trucks began to come by. No, cars
began to come by. This was a Sunday afternoon. And cars began to come by. And
there would be families of them, whole families, holding up their middle fingers
at those of us standing on the--. And I remember wondering how people could do
that, with children. And they would scream out obscenities. And here were all
these people going by. And I was struggling. I remember that being my first
action, I think against Vietnam or supporting the peace action or whatever it
was, and wondering how people could do that with their families. This was a
family outing, obviously. And they were going by screaming insults at us. And I
couldn&#039;t escape the notion that something I was doing was causing that.

It was really, really a struggle for me to stay there, because I felt like I was
making those people do that. And it may have been, also the fact that I was
coming out of--either going into or coming out of--a real mental break. But I
can remember those feelings. And finally a truck coming by--the trucks would
travel as close as they could to us without striking us. And those people that I
was standing with would not give an inch. And I was falling back each time. And
I can remember the trauma even now, of not knowing what a war was like;
realizing I&#039;d never been in a war and I didn&#039;t know what war was, but I knew
what a truck was and I was afraid of those trucks. And at one point, when I
stood back and I saw this kid, who had never been in the frontline, but standing
back, he was fingering a knife. And I knew these were Quakers that I was with
that were defying this thing, this drama that was happening in front, and that
they didn&#039;t know that he was armed. And I knew that that kid could have--that we
were all on the same side.

But how these fit together, how those families driving by with their obscenities
and those servicemen who were going by in their trucks and these Quakers who
were standing there on the road, how it all fit together became overwhelming,
and I ran. I was in tears. I got into my car, and I drove to my church, and I
told Aron Gilmartin that I flunked, [they laugh] that I had absolutely failed.
And he said, &quot;Only for the moment, Betty. You will go back.&quot; And he was that
kind of person. And I did go back. But I went back and it was years later. I
don&#039;t even remember.

But it was also at Port Chicago that I returned to, the day after a Unitarian
man had had his legs severed by a train. And I went back there as more of a
mature adult, having lived a lot of episodes in my life; having more of a
conviction about the war, about all wars; of being more sure of myself; of being
older; of being confronted and going through realities that I did not think I
could have survived. And that day, I was able to stand with--there weren&#039;t that
many of us; there may have been three or four. But all standing. Now I knew that
I was standing there, right?, but I don&#039;t know whether his name was Brian. Is it?

ARBONA: I assume you&#039;re referring to Brian Willson.

SOSKIN: Yes. Never knew him before or since. I since did see him at the Berkeley
Unitarian Fellowship some years later. But I didn&#039;t know him at the time. But
isn&#039;t it funny? His name came to me just before you said it. And he&#039;s not
someone I knew.

ARBONA: It&#039;s yeah, Brian.

SOSKIN: That is wild.

ARBONA: Yeah. Willson, with two L&#039;s, W-I-L-L-S-O-N.

SOSKIN: That is wild. How&#039;d that come up for me? But that&#039;s when I really had it
worked out, and I was able to stand my ground. For him. And because of rightness
and the position of anti-war. And that shuts the book on Port Chicago for me.
Until I became a park ranger. And that all began to open up. And by now, the war
has ended, the Vietnam war&#039;s over and we&#039;d confronted a lot of stuff. And now
that&#039;s been made a national park.

ARBONA: Going back a little bit to this Willson episode, did you find out--this
is in 1987.

SOSKIN: That when it was?

ARBONA: Yeah.

SOSKIN: Yeah, well, I told you it was years later.

ARBONA: And this is during the Central American--well, this Iran-Contra, around
that time. Reagan&#039;s in the White House.

SOSKIN: Isn&#039;t that bizarre? So, yeah. So a lot had gone down since that initial
Port Chicago experience. It wasn&#039;t just Vietnam, it was Nixon, it was the
whole--. Oh, and meanwhile--I don&#039;t know whether before or since--I was invited
to be an artist in residence at a meeting of the SDS students at Colorado
Springs. This was after Kent State. And they had gone there to protest Nixon&#039;s
speech at the US Air Force Academy. I don&#039;t remember the year. I was invited as
one--. [laughs] That&#039;s another time. Bob, who was living in Big Sur, turned up
at the conference and his mother was there. [laughs] Oh, my God. But I was one
of only six adults that they had chosen to join them for a week at Colorado
Springs. One was Ric Masten, poet from Big Sur. I think Rennie Gaines, who was a
part of Elisabeth Kübler-Ross&#039;s operation. He since has acquired an African
name, which I don&#039;t remember anymore. I think it was David Rendl-hast, of
Ontario. I don&#039;t remember any of the others. But anyway, there was that week
period at Colorado Springs. And I don&#039;t know whether that was before--I imagine
that that was since, that Nixon would not have--

ARBONA: No, it would&#039;ve been before.

SOSKIN: It would&#039;ve been Reagan that would&#039;ve been--when Brian Willson&#039;s thing, right?

ARBONA: &#039;87, yes.

SOSKIN: Okay, then this was under Nixon, because Nixon--they were protesting the
speech at the Air Force Academy. So that that had to be even later.

ARBONA: And they went to Port Chicago to protest.

SOSKIN: Who?

ARBONA: The six you mentioned during that Nixon speech, [inaudible].

SOSKIN: [over Arbona] No, no, no, this was in Colorado Springs. They had invited
me to their--it was a national conference, a continental conference. There were
kids from all over the country. And some of them had been at Kent State. So that
was after Kent State. It was the same year. But I seem to have been in all of
these iconic situations all along the line. By no design. And almost, except for
Bobby, alone. [they laugh] Don&#039;t know how Bob feels about that.

ARBONA: Now, why did you go back in &#039;87?

SOSKIN: Go back?

ARBONA: To Port Chicago.

SOSKIN: Because of Brian. I read about it in the paper. And it may have been
that I knew that he was a Unitarian, so I might have heard it from inside the
Unitarian community. Maybe he was a speaker at some Unitarian event later on. I
don&#039;t know whether he--my guess is that he was either a Unitarian or a fellow
traveler with us. [laughs] A lot of my activism was coming out of the fact that
I was in a community of activists in the Unitarian denomination.

ARBONA: And then the memorial happens.

SOSKIN: Yeah. Then the memorial happens.

ARBONA: Later on.

SOSKIN: And that day of remembrance brought--and all of those seemed to be
singularly iconic. All of those things, even though years apart, lead to the
same thing, same reality. The rightness of my being involved there as a park
ranger. There&#039;s some kind of authenticity about that. I tend to think of it only
as minimally involved in Port Chicago, and based in that party. But I hadn&#039;t
remembered these other events until now. So that there&#039;s not been that one
connection to Port Chicago, there&#039;s been several.

ARBONA: Several.

SOSKIN: And mostly pretty traumatic.

ARBONA: Yeah, I can&#039;t really figure out a way of asking this question, but it&#039;s
just fascinating how the site brings together so many different threads.

SOSKIN: Oh, yeah. Sure.

ARBONA: And that you&#039;ve participated in those. Those threads have also been a
part of your life.

SOSKIN: Yeah. And I don&#039;t know what the answer to that is. Some of those threads
I hadn&#039;t connected until now, in the telling. Because they&#039;ve not been evoked by
anything. There&#039;s been no way to connect them. I have done the day of
remembrance on my blog. And even now, they&#039;re unfolding. As I was saying, I
guess on the day of the tour, that it wasn&#039;t until I was speaking at the US
Customs House in San Francisco that I looked at that DVD that I put together
that incorporates that Joseph photo of the caskets, and suddenly saw the missing
flags. So that&#039;s still unfolding. That story is still unfolding for me. And my
suspicion is that some researcher is going to feed into that narrative at some
point, using that photograph as proof that those people could not have gotten a
fair trial.

ARBONA: Why don&#039;t you tell us a little bit about that photo?

SOSKIN: That photo, there&#039;s an E.F. Joseph photo. And we maybe need to get some
background. E.F. Joseph was an African American, was actually from the island of
Santa Lucia. He was from a Caribbean island. And he settled in the Bay Area in
the twenties, and took everything related to African Americans, all social
activities and political activities, until the mid-seventies, when he died.
Among those photographs is one taken at Port Chicago--no, taken at Port Chicago,
but taken after the explosion--of a portion of the twenty-two caskets in which
the remains of African-American--. Now, how they told African Americans from any
others, I don&#039;t know, because they were all fragments of bodies. But they were
buried in twenty-two caskets, in the colored section of Golden Gate National
Cemetery in San Francisco.

There is an African American [inaudible]. Now, that comes out of the fact that
blacks and whites were traditionally separated, even after death, and that the
national cemeteries also were--gathered in the photograph are people who I
recognize as being African American union officials from Boilermakers Auxiliary
36, that I worked for. So that those men--Mahlon Roles, who was the
secretary-treasurer of that auxiliary, Boilermakers A-36; Spencer Jordan, who
was his assistant; Reverend Smith, who was the uncle of Mahlon Roles--are the
three African Americans. They are standing with other Boilermaker Union
Auxiliary members or officials and some Kaiser Permanente people. Now, because
I&#039;m of that era, I recognize those people. So I knew what that is. And there are
a portion of the twenty-two caskets.

I went online after this revelation of these caskets being missing their flags,
and looked at the inscription that&#039;s at Golden Gate cemetery site, and saw that
in the graphic on the website, it talks about the general who&#039;s buried there,
the other people who were buried there at Golden Gate Fields; now, it&#039;s not the
colored section. And it mentions, give a couple sentences to the Italian
American, German prisoners of war who died in captivity, who were also buried
there. And then, as an afterthought, also buried in this cemetery, in the
colored section, are the twenty-two caskets of--and it says twenty-two, I
think--buried as unknowns in the cemetery, without mentioning that there were
320 or whatever it was who died, without mentioning an explosion, without
mentioning that they&#039;re even sailors. The only reason we know that is because
they were court-martialed, which meant that they were servicemen. But in this,
it says African Americans. They could&#039;ve been stevedores. Right? It doesn&#039;t
mention that there was an explosion.

And I suddenly began to see what was missing in the inscription on the website.
And when I&#039;m watching from the dark, the presentation of this thing which I&#039;ve
created and which I&#039;ve been through so many times, and suddenly thought, there
are not flags over those caskets, and began to wonder why. And where are the
remains of the white servicemen who died, also? Civilians or maritime or
whoever, sailors. There were 196 of those or whatever it was. Are they also
here? And are there photographs? And were those caskets flag draped? So those
questions, even after all these years, began to haunt me, much as Richert haunts
me at this site. That there are undisclosed facts about Port Chicago that I
connect to, and I don&#039;t know why. And that story is incomplete, and probably
will be even when I die. But maybe some of them are embedded in my memory; I
don&#039;t know. I don&#039;t know how it would figure.

But since those attitudes that prevailed at the time would not have allowed them
to be identified as sailors, who would not have been honored with flag-draped
caskets, that may suggest the fact that those remaining survivors should be
exonerated, because they could not have received a fair trial. And maybe that
photograph is proof of that, that it indicates the attitude that prevailed in
those years. And I think it&#039;s an important question for somebody to research,
because we need photographs of the white people who survived--I mean who were
lost, and to see how they compare.

ARBONA: Wow, there&#039;s so much to unpack.

SOSKIN: Yeah, but those are stories that are untold, and they really are
fascinating. And we really need some graduate students to start delving into
some of that stuff.

ARBONA: I think I have one other question that&#039;s somewhat--I don&#039;t mean to
deviate from that last thought--

SOSKIN: No, fine.

ARBONA: --but I guess that I was interested in hearing about how you&#039;ve gone
back to the site now these last few years. And I was wondering if you&#039;ve met
George Miller, for example.

SOSKIN: Oh, yes.

ARBONA: And maybe to ask you to reflect on his work, and perhaps there&#039;s other
people that you&#039;d like to mention that also come to mind, with him.

SOSKIN: Yeah. As I said, and it really wasn&#039;t just in passing, I&#039;ve become more
aware. Or at least it&#039;s been confirmed for me in these later years, maybe in the
past decade, mainly, that there have always been people trying to get it right.
George Miller&#039;s one of those. Dion Aroner is another of those. They&#039;ve been in
and out of government and they&#039;ve been in and out of power positions. But they
date back as far as the fact that there was a ship built in the Richmond
shipyards by Henry Kaiser that was named for Toussaint L&#039;Ouverture. Would you
not like to see a copy of the transcripts of the discussions that went into how
that was arrived at? We&#039;re still fighting the Haitian revolution. I mean, literally.

And that is an example of people trying to get it right. I think that there have
always been those. I think that our current President is trying to get it right.
Whether or not he dominates is whether or not the supports that he needs to be
there; whether or not people like me--. And I really think it&#039;s my job. [laughs]
I really think it&#039;s my job. And I don&#039;t know when I came to that. But it&#039;s my
job to create pressure on the people with the power; that I may not prevail, but
that I am leaning in the direction of positive social change, with unseen
others. And it&#039;s my faith in those unseen others that are out there trying to
get it right that keeps me strong. It really, really does. If there&#039;s any faith
in this, it&#039;s in that, that there are those people. And I may not be aware of
who they are, but they&#039;ve always existed. And someday there&#039;s going to be a
critical mass of us. [laughs] And it waxes and wanes; sometimes we&#039;re in and out
of power. But the &quot;we&quot; of me is always out there. And that if I don&#039;t do it,
it&#039;s not going to be done, because my voice is needed. And I may not ever be
able to see where those supports are, who they are. I may not recognize them,
but they&#039;re there. And I do really, really, really feel empowered.

ARBONA: In what way would you like to see that Port Chicago chapter developed?

SOSKIN: I think it&#039;s still going to be true that what gets remembered is
dependent upon those doing the remembering. I think that we&#039;re in danger, or
have been in danger, of having that commemoration based upon the loss--the
generations who have succeeded those of the experience being those who are
remembering. So the explosion at Port Chicago and the destruction of the town of
Port Chicago will move to the forefront--. Unless we can revive the history of
those men and what they went through, using the trials of exoneration, which
should sometime come up because there are people interested in seeing that those
come, because those will expose the stories of those boys who were lost. And
because of their unintended gift to us, which was that was the trigger that
caused President Truman to desegregate the armed forces; that the role that they
played, even by being destroyed, fed into the desegregation of the armed forces,
which subsequently led into the entire dismantling of the system of--. And we
wax and wane; we go back and forth. Right now we&#039;ve got some regression.

But Port Chicago plays a pivotal role in that. I think it triggered the modern
Civil Rights Movement, that I think began with the response to Port Chicago,
because that&#039;s where African Americans said, we will not be backed up any
further than this. That&#039;s where people began to not accept the status quo. Also
that by happenstance, the city of Berkeley began to change visibly. And this is
something I experienced. I remember when Mr. DeBonis, Charles DeBonis, the
ultraconservative of Berkeley, who was on the city council--. And that Berkeley
could have been described as being like any other Midwestern town, as
conservative; but that because this was the place that was on the edge of
everything--that we were on the edge of the Pacific, we were on the edge of
scientific change; we were the birth of the atom bomb, we&#039;re the birthplace of
the United Nations--. This is where everything happened, from the World War--the
beginning of that war until its end and until the twenty years that followed
that; that we became that cauldron. But people began to converge on Berkeley
because it was believed to be the change agent, the liberal capital of the
world. And they made it so, by a self-fulfilling prophecy. They came in such
large numbers that they made it what they believed it already was. And I watched
that transformation. It was one of the most exciting things I think I&#039;ve ever
seen. And even in the happening of it, I seemed to be aware that it was
happening. I was recording it. I have papers in my files, where I was
standing--I was standing in the crowd when S.I. Hayakawa was, with his bullhorn,
on top of San Francisco State, with people who were protesting.

All of those things I was watching happen close up. And I watched--and that&#039;s
what this article was about--I watched the greater Bay Area become the catalyst
for a change which is still occurring. We began to lead the nation and the world
in social change. It radiated out from this nexus. And still does. UC Berkeley
is, of course, not nearly as progressive as it was during those years, and
there&#039;s been that kind of regression, but we&#039;ve never dropped back as far. And
we&#039;ll always have those pulsations. But it&#039;s amazing. And my life has paralleled that.

ARBONA: And so your hunch is that also Port Chicago had a big part of that.

SOSKIN: It was the catalyst. It&#039;s my belief that Port Chicago really did
trigger, by making visible those things which, up until then, had been accepted.
Eleanor Roosevelt was doing her thing, in terms of social change, even before
her husband was; but he was sort of going along as far as he could, without
changing anything, really. The GI Bill, as I say, was not effective. The changes
put into employment practices were never enforced. A. Philip Randolph&#039;s
confrontation with Roosevelt did not yield very much. They were in name only.
But Port Chicago, it really did become the catalyst. This was the game changer.
I think that we&#039;re going to find, when the academics take it on, when you take
it on, that a lot of what happens consequently came out of Port Chicago. It
really did. And I&#039;m just convinced that those men&#039;s lives were not wasted; that
they were sacrificed, but that they were not wasted; that they did really,
really trumpet--they dictated the next twenty years of social change. We were
being asked before then, as African Americans, to fight, to work, and even die
for social changes which we would not enjoy for another twenty years. And many
were doing that. Many were doing that. That&#039;s amazing, when you really think
about what African Americans withstood over the following twenty years. And I am
convinced. That is what Port Chicago means to me.

ARBONA: So I could keep asking questions all day, but I worry that it&#039;s been
already a long morning.

SOSKIN: I really don&#039;t even have any idea what time it is. [they laugh]

STEIN: Pause for a minute?

ARBONA: Yeah, we could pause.

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>