<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042069" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2003-03-10" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Don Hardison | Interview 1 | March 10, 2003</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><subject>Community Driven by WWII</subject><subject>Growing up During the Great Depression</subject><subject>Ranching/Agriculture</subject><subject>Education</subject><keyword>Ranch</keyword><keyword>Mare Island</keyword><keyword>Housing Projects</keyword><interviewee>Don Hardison</interviewee><interviewer>Jess Rigelhaupt</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|13(8)|26(6)|35(11)|44(5)|51(13)|59(11)|66(7)|72(12)|85(8)|97(14)|105(3)|114(6)|123(2)|134(9)|142(4)|149(3)|155(13)|168(13)|179(10)|187(10)|197(7)|204(4)|211(1)|219(12)|230(10)|239(13)|251(7)|260(5)|267(4)|280(3)|290(1)|296(1)|307(13)|316(11)|325(2)|336(8)|347(5)|354(1)|361(8)|368(7)|377(9)|384(14)|393(15)|401(8)|407(9)|416(14)|423(7)|430(1)|438(6)|447(12)|457(8)|463(14)|472(6)|480(7)|492(1)|496(12)|503(10)|509(2)|516(4)|522(4)|529(2)|538(1)|547(13)|556(13)|564(11)|573(3)|581(1)|588(11)|595(1)|601(11)|609(5)|618(1)|626(4)|634(3)|641(9)|648(16)|658(6)|666(1)|673(8)|681(8)|690(4)|697(13)|704(13)|712(1)|718(6)|723(11)|733(5)|742(6)|752(2)|760(11)|767(1)|776(7)|783(6)|791(6)|796(5)|807(5)|816(4)|823(9)|829(3)|835(14)|846(3)|854(14)|864(4)|873(6)|880(9)|890(6)|899(10)|907(6)|915(1)|926(3)|936(4)|943(7)|953(14)|961(12)|972(7)|978(6)|987(4)|1000(4)|1008(4)|1017(7)|1024(7)|1032(12)|1040(3)|1048(4)|1056(4)|1061(7)|1069(9)|1076(3)|1085(11)|1094(5)|1102(8)|1114(8)|1120(6)|1127(8)|1133(1)|1141(10)|1152(8)|1162(4)|1173(3)|1178(5)|1185(7)|1193(12)|1204(5)|1211(7)|1218(9)|1228(1)|1235(3)|1240(14)|1246(4)|1257(14)|1266(9)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>xKbFCdNZLlI</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index><point><time>0</time><title>Early Life on Southern California Family Ranch</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>We lived up on the slope of the valley. We could oversee the valley, which is really a very beautiful part of Southern California. Interestingly enough, it is very much today as it was when I was a kid.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis>Early life was spent on a ranch in Fillmore, a rural town in Southern California. Parents moved there from Caribou, Maine. Agricultural practices at the time were different than they are today. Hardison recalls a Mexican man who used to work on the farm. The family ranch grew citrus and was part of the Sunkist Cooperative.</synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>agriculture;Early life;family ranch;Maine;Sespe Preserve;Southern California;Sunkist Cooperative;Ventura County</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>family;family history;Southern California</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>843</time><title>Experiences in Grade School</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Today we would consider it unfortunate, because my initial elementary schooling was segregated.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis>Elementary school was segregated; attended an entirely Caucasian school and there were separate schools for the Latino children. Describes the different interests and lifestyles of his three brothers. Recalls teachers that stood out to him. Particularly enjoyed math and civics.</synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Chaffey Junior College;civics;interests;math;school;segregation;siblings;UC Santa Barbara</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>family;school;segregation</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1491</time><title>Teenage Years During the Great Depression</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Everybody had little home gardens where they could survive. But it was a very difficult time.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis>Difficulties of teenage years during the Great Depression. Local citrus packing house board decided to dump oranges in the Sespe River because shipping and selling them was so unprofitable and costly. Grandfather was the mayor of Fillmore in 1922. Spent high school years working on uncle's dairy. Bought a $35 automobile.</synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>1923 Chevrolet;citrus packing house;family;Great Depression;Sanitary Dairy;Sespe River</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>automobile;family;Great Depression;school</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>2104</time><title>Pursual of Architecture at UC Berkeley</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>As a matter of fact, from that very moment that I turned in that little house plan in mechanical drawing as a junior high kid, I decided I wanted to pursue architecture. </partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis>Recalls the bemusement of his parents at his interest in architecture.Studying in the Department of Architecture at UC Berkeley required many hours of hard work. Tendency of his peers to stray from traditional and classic design, and veer towards more modern styles.</synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>architecture;Department of Architecure;Frank Lloyd Wright;High Y;Jack Kent;Le Corbusier;Marvin Sturgeon;modern design;Ridge Route;Roy Wilson;Sydney Williams;Theta Kappa Nu;UC Berkeley;Walter Gropius;William Wurster</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>architecture;UC Berkeley</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>2749</time><title>Early Work After College</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>It was an extremely difficult time. I also visited every prominent architect—. Well, I should say I visited a lot of architects who were not so prominent. [laughs]</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis>Graduation from UC Berkeley in 1938. Difficulty with finding a job afterwards. Work as an apprentice carpenter, and then in David J. Witmer's firm. Work at the hull department of the Mare Island Naval Shipyard. Fear of a Japanese attack at the Pacific Coast. Meeting his wife and marrying her in 1942.</synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Betty Decker;David J. Witmer;Hawaiian Raymond Turner Company;Mare Island Naval Shipyard;WWII;Wyvernwood</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>ship design;WWII</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>3772</time><title>Move to Richmond</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Atchison Village;C.P. Bedford;John B. Moore;Kaiser Shipyards</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>housing demand;Richmond;WWII</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>5227</time><title>Richmond During WWII</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Easter Hill Village;Housing Authority;housing demand;lack of resources;Maritime Commission;West County Court Building</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>post-WWII;Richmond;WWII</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>6036</time><title>Richmond Architecture Firm</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Chamber of Commerce;County of Contra Costa;Easter Hill Village;First Presbyterian Church;George Rhoda;Richmond Arts Center;Richmond High School;Richmond Housing Authority;Ted Moist;YMCA</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>post-war;post-WWII;redesign</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>7036</time><title>Easter Hill Village</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>American Institute of Architects;Easter Hill Village;Lawrence Halprin;Public Housing Administration;Vernon DeMars</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>crime;cultural shift;drugs;housing;low income housing</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>8561</time><title>Japanese Community in Richmond</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Charles Strothoff;Shigego Richard Komatsu</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Japanese internment;Pearl Harbor;WWII</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>8927</time><title>Current Projects</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Ford Plant;Judy Hart;National Park Service;Red Oak Victory;Richmond Museum of History</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>parks;restoration</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point></index><type></type><description>Don Hardison grew up in a small ranching town in Southern California. His parents were from Maine, he talks about early friendship with someone who worked on his family's ranch and was an immigrant from Mexico, family ranch was part of Sunkist, was more grown up during the Great Depression so clearly remembers all of the difficulties of that time, attended Cal after high school, worked in architecture in Alameda and then Mare Island after graduating, work at Mare Island even before Pearl Harbor, move to housing project Atchinson Village, says Kaiser was significant to WWII Richmond because it developed a connection between all of the people who lived and worked there, post-WWII fewer ships being built so Hardison knew he had to think about what else he would do for work, helped with designing Richmond High and housing projects-- talks about issues associated with housing authority, recalls a personal friend impacted by Japanese internment</description><rel /><transcript>RIGELHAUPT: It&#039;s Monday morning, March 10, 2003. We&#039;re here in El Cerrito. I&#039;m about to do
an oral history interview with Don Hardison. So if I could just start by getting
you to say your full name and date of birth.

HARDISON: Donald Leigh Hardison; March 23, 1916.

RIGELHAUPT: Since this interview&#039;s focused on Richmond at some level, are you from the
Richmond area?

HARDISON: No. I was raised in Southern California, little town of Fillmore, which is
largely a citrus and avocado ranching area. My dad, my folks had a ranch.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little bit about what your childhood was like on the ranch?

HARDISON: It was really a wonderful experience. We had to go to school about three or four
miles away. Picked up a bus every morning. Walked about half a mile to the bus
stop down on the highway. We lived up on the slope of the valley. We could
oversee the valley, which is really a very beautiful part of Southern
California. Interestingly enough, it is very much today as it was when I was a
kid. In other words, this particular town had not developed subdivisions like
has been so common in Southern California.

RIGELHAUPT: Where is the town of Fillmore located?

HARDISON: It&#039;s about in the middle of Ventura County between Santa Paula and Piru. Ojai is
around the corner through Santa Paula. It&#039;s in what is called the Santa Clara
Valley because the Santa Clara River runs right through it. You were asking me
about my childhood. I was not too much involved in social activities as a child
because we had so many personal opportunities on the ranch. We would hike a
great deal. We had horses. By horses, I just mean my brother--my immediate
brother--and I each had horses, which we rode a lot, so we didn&#039;t feel it was
necessary to join the scouts, and it was easier for my folks not to have to
transport us over to the scout meetings. But later on in high school I became
active in sports. I wasn&#039;t very good at it, but I got active in it because it
was a small school and they desperately needed guys my size. So I played a bit
of basketball as the heavier team, the main team. Then also I was very active in
a band, and music, I loved music and early on learned to play the saxophone.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little more about your family? Who was living on the ranch?

HARDISON: I had three younger brothers. All of us were born in Fillmore. I was born in my
grandfather&#039;s house, which had been converted from the first schoolhouse in
Fillmore, so I can say I got my first education upon birth. Later, we lived
three miles out of town. It was sort of a rural area called Sespe, which is now
prominent for the presence of the last wild condors in California--the so-called
Sespe Preserve. It is there that we used to hike as kids. But now it is
prohibited, because of the preserve.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you tell me a little bit about your parents. Where were they born?

HARDISON: My parents were from Maine. My mother was born in Nova Scotia but met my dad in
the little town of Caribou, Maine, which is one of the most northerly towns in
the States. It&#039;s great potato country--Aroostook County, and before Idaho and
California potatoes took over the market, Caribou potatoes, I mean Aroostook
County potatoes--on the East Coast at least--were known as the best potatoes in
the country. And the current California Hardison clan, started from Caribou, way
back to the 1600s. We have not been able to go back further into Europe. They
all were interested in agriculture. However, some got sidetracked into oil in
Pennsylvania, and left Caribou to go into the oilfields, and some gained enough
wealth that they decided to come to California, which was at that time another
opportunity for oil. And the town adjacent to Fillmore, in Ventura County, Santa
Paula was the place where the Union Oil Company was co-founded by a Hardison.
Stewart and Hardison started Union Oil right there, close to where I was raised.
Subsequently a lot of things have happened in the oil business and most of my
family got involved in citrus in Ventura County and were part of many initial
citrus and avocado organizations. For example, Sunkist, which was a co-op for
marketing oranges and lemons. They were also involved in the early avocado
business. Colavo Association. Although background in my family was agriculture,
early on, when I was fourteen, in a drafting class, actually a mechanical
drawing class. We were supposed to be drawing gears and all kinds of mechanical
things, but I was much more interested in architecture. I asked the teacher if I
could draw a house. So that&#039;s where my architectural career started. And, I
subsequently went on to Cal, [University of California at Berkeley] and except
for visits--never returned to Southern California for any length of time.

RIGELHAUPT: The family that you had in Fillmore, did they move to California via
Pennsylvania, or did they come straight from Maine?

HARDISON: From Caribou, Maine. My folks were married there in 1912 and came to California
shortly thereafter. My dad worked on a ranch that was called the Hardison Ranch
Company. It was owned by a combination of Hardisons who had come from Caribou.
Subsequently, my folks bought their own property of ten acres, that eventually
grew to160 acres.

RIGELHAUPT: So you had a lot of extended family in the area?

HARDISON: Yes, there were a number of Hardisons including an uncle--my dad&#039;s brother--who
had a dairy, which today is designated as a historic place, and has a silo with
a large &quot;SD&quot;--Sanitary Dairy--between Fillmore and Santa Paula. And there were
other Hardisons at this Hardison Ranch that I mentioned, including my dad&#039;s
cousin who managed it.

RIGELHAUPT: So what was a typical day like for your mother and your father when you were
growing up?

HARDISON: Well, I&#039;m sure they worked hard. My mother was a mother to us and a housewife so
she, to my knowledge, did not do any work outside the home. My mother maintained
the house, and Dad was very active out in the orchards. Early on, we had a young
man--in fact, I think he started with us when he was only fourteen years old and
living with an older brother. A Mexican, probably an immigrant, I wish I knew
just exactly where he was born. So dad did have some help on the ranch, and
eventually this young man became a very valuable part of our family, married and
lived in a house on our ranch. His name was Camilo Pulido and it after he had
learned all the trades on the ranch he left us and went to Los Angeles as a
mechanic for Greyhound. But we&#039;ll always remember that early relationship with
an immigrant from Mexico.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little bit about what was the work on the ranch?

HARDISON: In those years, the technique of maintaining irrigation and cultivation of the
orchards were quite different from today. In those years, they would cultivate
between the rows of the trees and irrigate with ditches that were formed once a
year by plows that ran through the rows. Then, large amounts of water were run
through a concrete irrigation pipe system, serving those ditches. But it took a
tremendous amount of water, and then at the end of the rows, a lot of so-called
wastewater would go down the roads and--. Actually, Southern California didn&#039;t
have that much water, but a pumping system was available to the ranchers--a
cooperative system--provided the water. Nowadays, irrigation is all done by a
drip system, which takes just a fraction of the amount of water, and they
seldom, if ever, cultivate between the rows. I remember Dad plowed some rows
near the house, and would planted corn. He&#039;d plant corn and string beans, and we
even raised some pigs. It was sort of a well-rounded ranching operation with
always a tractor that did the heavy pulling work. An old truck--it wasn&#039;t too
old then, but seems old now--on which I learned to drive when I was just a kid
of probably twelve or thirteen. It was a Ford truck with a bed and Dad would
haul the fruit over to a Sunkist packinghouse, where the fruit would be stored,
packed and shipped out.

RIGELHAUPT: Your family was part of the Sunkist cooperative?

HARDISON: Yes. In those years all of them were. There was one other competing
organization, but Sunkist was the overwhelming choice for distributing fruit. Of
course, today it still exists, and you&#039;ll find Sunkist labels on boxes in
grocery stores, but now there&#039;s a vast number of other distribution means for ranchers.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little bit about your experiences in school. Elementary school.

HARDISON: Today we would consider it unfortunate, because my initial elementary schooling
was segregated. I should have described Fillmore as a very interesting small
community. In those years it probably had a population of maybe three thousand.
Mexican immigrant labor was very common on all the ranches. I knew of no black
families in the town. There were two or three Japanese families who had their
nurseries out in the valley, but it was largely Caucasian and Mexican. My
experience as a child did not include kindergarten, and I went to first grade in
a school that was entirely Caucasian. The Mexican children had separate schools,
many of which were out in the countryside. There&#039;d be small schools--maybe two
or three classrooms. My life in elementary school was very pleasant. We&#039;d get on
the bus to ride to and from home, and I got very well acquainted with the bus
drivers and made friendships, of course, with classmates that exist to this day.
Some went on to Cal with me, and live in the Bay Area--in Northern California.
We still see them regularly. Seventy years, eighty years ago. Let&#039;s see, I
remember I learned to play tennis as even the elementary school had tennis
courts. I wasn&#039;t very good at it, but I enjoyed it. I did not belong to any
youth organizations. Until later in junior high and senior high. So it was just
an idyllic life, that&#039;s the way I would describe it compared to some of the
experiences that young people have today.

RIGELHAUPT: Just for clarification, where were you in relation to the order with your brothers?

HARDISON: You mean in age?

RIGELHAUPT:  Yeah.

HARDISON: My immediate brother was Richard, who was a year-and-a-half younger. He was
particularly enamored with ranch life and much more help to his dad than I was.
Also loved horses and cattle and he was also a hunter. Of the four boys he was
the only one that really liked to hunt. I enjoyed target practice as a high
schooler, and owned a pistol. That&#039;s the limit of my relationship to arms.
Richard died prematurely a number of years ago, but until his death he was very
interested in the open country, the animals and everything that&#039;s involved in
farming. He did not complete college but attended Chaffey Junior College in
Southern California, which is known for its agricultural, and particularly
citrus, training programming.

RIGELHAUPT: And your other brothers?

HARDISON: I had two other brothers, one of whom never got into any illegal trouble, I
should say, but Jim was really a rascal. I was in college when he was just
making a lot of fun out of life. He went off to the oilfields when he should
have been in college. I think it was the oilfields in Wyoming, where he had
heard one of our distant relatives had an oil lease. He just tried so many
different activities. You could write a whole book on what he was up to. Never
went to college. My younger brother, Bill, graduated from UC Santa Barbara in
engineering did have a very successful career in engineering with a company in
Riverside, California. I guess he was probably more inclined towards
technology--like I was--than were the other two brothers. We were all quite
different even though we were raised under the same roof and given the same
attention by our parents.

RIGELHAUPT: Jumping back to your experiences in school, do you have some favorite memories
of elementary school--classes you really liked, teachers you really liked?

HARDISON: Yes, I remember certain teachers more than others. I can remember the ones that
gave me opportunities that encouraged me to do certain things. I enjoyed
sketching and doing artwork, and not all kids are interested in that. I do
remember one teacher, Mrs. Richie third grade, who was very helpful to me when I
did a sort of a stupid thing: I was playing on overhead handlebars, that you
hang on, I fell and broke my arm. She was very sympathetic and helpful to me
during that recovery period. There were other teachers who got me interested,
for example, in literature and writing. It&#039;s a little bit hard for me to pick
out influential elementary school teachers, whereas when I got into what they
then called junior high and high school, there were specific teachers who
impressed me in ways that I&#039;ll always remember, because they were sort of
specialists in certain fields. For example, I&#039;ll always remember my chemistry
and physics teacher, Mrs. Hill. While most of the kids in my class were not
interested in that subject; however, there were three or four of us in my
class--all of whom went on to be either engineers, physicists; architects--who
were really interested in what that teacher was talking about and I really
enjoyed that very much. And then, of course, there was a math teacher whom I
will never forget: Mr. Thornton, who just kept banging away at us to get us to
learn algebra and trigonometry. In those years, we didn&#039;t go as far as they go
today, but geometry and algebra were sort of tough. He just kept pressing us,
and I&#039;m always appreciative of his efforts.

RIGELHAUPT: What would you say your favorite subject was in high school?

HARDISON: That&#039;s a tough one. I guess it was probably math, probably math. I remember
another teacher, who taught civics, it&#039;s sort of political science, but that&#039;s
not what they call it in high school. It&#039;s really about attitudes of the public
and voting and political issues that are on ballots. I found that very
interesting, because even in those years, when I was probably seventeen years
old, we were already beginning to form attitudes towards public policies and
things. Of course, we never heard anything about the environment--that&#039;s
something that came up in later years--but we did hear a lot about good
government and how cities, counties and states should be run, and I&#039;m always
appreciative of that course as well. Even though I was not interested
particularly in pursuing a public career, I found it fascinating and I do, to
this day. I am very interested in knowing what&#039;s going on with our various politicians.

RIGELHAUPT: So you were a teenager during the Great Depression.

HARDISON: That is true. I graduated in &#039;34, which was either the bottom of it, or one year
from the bottom of the Depression, and I can well remember the difficulties that
we were all having in those years. I remember, I told you we were in the orange
production business, and the local orange packinghouse board of directors
elected to dump oranges rather than market them because the price was so low
that they could not get enough out of the marketing process to pay for the
shipping. Our big market was always in the East--The East Coast loved California
oranges. In fact, it was a well-known fact that Florida oranges made the juice,
but California oranges were the ones that everybody loved to eat. So shipping
them was very costly, and from our ranch up on the slopes of the valley we could
look down on the--. There was a creek, really a small river--called the Sespe
River, and we could see the slopes where the packinghouse had dumped virtually
tons of oranges that the poor and the hungry could have used in Los Angeles or
somewhere. But there was no government agency that would even pick up the fruit
that was dumped. That was my most spectacular memory of the Depression. We were
not in the city or community where there were long breadlines or anything like
that. Everybody had little home gardens where they could survive. But it was a
very difficult time.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember much about how that decision was made to dump the oranges?

HARDISON: No, no. I would&#039;ve been too young. Well, maybe not too young, but I wasn&#039;t in
the loop of any information. My dad was on a lemon board. I don&#039;t recall them
every dumping lemons. I remember Dad was just as distressed as I was that they
had to dump the fruit. But also my dad was on the school board that built a new
elementary school. I should mention that, which I&#039;m very proud of, because it
still exists today, whereas 90 percent of the schools that were built in those
years have failed seismic tests and have been rebuilt. But this, which my dad&#039;s
name is still on the &quot;corner stone&quot;. The building bears his name along with
other board members. That was the first integrated elementary school in
Fillmore, I went there in the third grade. I mentioned the segregated school
that we went to in the first, and second grades. So my first experience of
having Mexican classmates was in the third grade. I should also report, since
I&#039;m talking about the little town of Fillmore--my grandfather, in whose house I
was born, that I mentioned earlier--as a former schoolhouse--was the mayor of
the town in 1922. So there is a family history in the little town where I was raised.

RIGELHAUPT: How long did he serve as mayor?

HARDISON: I believe it was four years. Under his tutelage, the town initiated its first
water system with a tank on a hill. I really don&#039;t know how they did it before,
but I presume everybody had wells because hey built a tank up on the hill, and
this was the first water system for the town.

RIGELHAUPT: You mentioned that growing oranges on the ranch took a lot of water. Do you
know, were there fights over the water, where it came from. Do you remember {inaudible}?

HARDISON: Yes. Oh, yes. We were up on the slopes of the valley, and the water source that
was most dependable was down virtually on the shores of the river that ran
through the valley. So there was a big pumping facility that the ranchers on our
side of the valley operated as a cooperative, and the water was pumped from that
source. Some ranchers had reservoirs that they filled with water, just so there
would be adequate storage volume during their actual irrigations, which usually
took place every thirty days during the summer season.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you have any jobs while you were in high school?

HARDISON: That&#039;s an interesting question, because I mentioned earlier that my uncle had a
dairy, the Sanitary Dairy, on the highway and in order to make ends meet, he
sold gasoline and he also my aunt had a little drink stand right at the dairy,
right on the highway. This stand sold milk and orange juice, which I used to
squeeze with an electric squeezer. Then we also sold candy that was made by one
of the family members, and I hand pumped gas. I did that probably when I was a
sophomore through my senior year. So I was probably fourteen when I started
working. Otherwise, I used to help my dad, on the ranch, but of course I didn&#039;t
get any pay for that.

RIGELHAUPT: You just said that you worked to make ends meet. Was this money that you were
able to use as spending money as a teenager, or did it go back into the family?

HARDISON: I don&#039;t recall what I did with it, but I probably spent it to maintain an
automoble. Let&#039;s see. I remember when I was probably a junior or a senior--.
First I should say that the laws have changed, at least in California,
concerning the age when you can get a drivers license. Back when I was a kid,
you could get one when you were fourteen. I think I mentioned earlier, I had
driven the family truck on the ranch--not on the road--when I was probably
twelve or thirteen, and then the very day that I got to be fourteen, my dad
drove me to Ventura County Courthouse, and I took my exam and got a driver&#039;s
license. Of course, I always wanted a car, but this was the Depression. Finally,
in a blacksmith&#039;s shop with my dad in Fillmore. (Incidentally, the blacksmith&#039;s
shop not only did horseshoeing, but they did a lot of structural work for trucks
and wagons and things that the ranchers needed--) I spotted a 1923 Chevrolet. I
asked how much the blacksmith wanted for it, and he didn&#039;t know whether they
wanted to sell it. Well, I went back another time and he said, &quot;Okay, $35.&quot; So,
I&#039;m sure that some of my earnings from making orange juice went to buying a $35
automobile. I really enjoyed it. It was a touring car; in other words there was
no top, a seat in back, and it just took an awful lot of maintenance. And of
course it had no starter--had to crank it. I got in trouble-- I don&#039;t know what
we were celebrating in high school--but I remember going down Main Street where
the school was located with guys hanging all over this car. There must have been
eight or ten hanging on my car. They were standing on the running boards when
and I got stopped by the local police chief--who was our one and only cop and
who gave me a ticket. I managed to avoid going to court, but that experience
discouraged me from breaking the law from that point on.

RIGELHAUPT: When you were in high school, or sort of a teenager, did you have any idea--for
lack of a better way to put this--what you wanted to be when you grew up?

HARDISON: As a matter of fact, from that very moment that I turned in that little house
plan in mechanical drawing as a junior high kid, I decided I wanted to pursue
architecture. Which I think my folks had quite a bit of trouble understanding
because I did love the ranch and they, of course, were taken by ranch life and
living out in the country. They couldn&#039;t quite understand why I wanted to go
into architecture, because, frankly I didn&#039;t know anything about it. It&#039;s a
small town. I didn&#039;t see any good examples of it. I finally met an architect,
Roy Wilson in the neighboring town of Santa Paula, who during two summers, while
I was in college, allowed me to work--and I mean &quot;allow&quot;--allowed me to work as
an apprentice without pay. So, it all started right there in Fillmore, and,
other than just remembering my excitement with being able to draw and produce
something that could be built, I just don&#039;t have any other recollection of why I
got into that particular field.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little bit about your experiences at Cal--the years you were
there and what you remember about it.

HARDISON: They were great years. I remember, the first trip to Cal my folks drove me up to
Berkeley, and what a tedious route we used to have to go. The Ridge Route was a
real obstruction between Bakersfield and Los Angeles. It was a long drag to get
up there in a day. But my folks and I managed it. They let me off at a
fraternity. I had no idea that I would be interested in a fraternity, but--a
classmate of mine, Jean Sturgeon, who also came up to Cal the same year; had a
brother, three years older, who was the president of the Theta Kappa Nu
fraternity on Haste Street in Berkeley. He invited me to join the fraternity
and, even be his roommate, which was a great opportunity for a kid from a small
town who was very concerned about going to the big city of Berkeley. So my first
experiences were handled by Marvin Sturgeon, who became sort of my mentor, and
I&#039;ve always appreciated that. He&#039;s still around, and I&#039;m still in touch with
him, even though he&#039;s more than ninety years old. There are so many memories
connected with Berkeley that it&#039;s just hard to put them in a short form. I
should say that the Department of Architecture in those years--and, of course,
even today--is relatively small. In those years, it was a department under
Letters and Science, so only--students in Architecture--were in that particular
department. Whereas, since the early fifties, when Dean William Wurster headed
up a new college to be known as the College of Environmental Design--which
included three other fields: Landscape Architecture, Planning and Urban Design
and Design. As architectural students, I met members of my class and formed
lifelong relationships. The faculty--Mr. Torossian, our freshman professor, I
will never forget. There were many others: Michael Goodman, and Warren Perry,
who was the head of the department. Architecture was a very close-knit type of
school, which became famous for all-night sessions before students turned in
their plates. It was considered one of the hardest-working fields at the
university, and friends and others would say that they went by the school at two
o&#039;clock--. The school was right there at the North Gate, and used to be called
the Ark. It&#039;s now a different department. It&#039;s been restored to its original
shingle appearance, but it&#039;s no longer architecture. And people would go by
there at two or three o&#039;clock in the morning and they&#039;d say, &quot;See all these
lights in the classrooms.&quot; We were all working on the boards trying to get out
the projects. So, my early memories of Cal was a lot of hard work. I was one of
only two of us in my class who got into any activities early on. One of them was
Jack Kent, who went on to be the first planning director of the City of San
Francisco. Jack was interested in--what&#039;s the swimming, where you play ball in a
pool? It&#039;s an Olympic event. Water polo. He was very interested in water polo,
so he would break away sometimes from this long tedious work session we had to
play water polo. And I would also break away to go to the band rehearsals. On
Saturday morning we would practice for the field events, whereas now, being in
the band is almost like being in a profession. In those years it was rather a
short-term commitment during football season. I played in the band for four
years--. Maybe that&#039;s the reason my grades weren&#039;t as good as they should have been.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember any sort of famous architects that you admire while you were in college?

HARDISON: Very good question, because we were in class in which virtually all of our
professors were Beaux-Arts trained traditionalists. They either had been to
Paris and trained there, or they had used that concept in their college
background studies in the States. So we were the first--one of the
first--classes to really be inspired Frank Lloyd Wright, Le Corbusier and
Gropius, who came from Germany to the States about that time. These Modernists
were influencing our lives but not our professors. I will never forget one plate
that on which we were supposed to be doing the four classic orders and we had to
show illustrations. Classmates Jack Kent and Sydney Williams--were the rebels in
our class. They were so impressed by the Modernist movement that they refused to
do the classic Greek and Roman orders and instead did modern concepts that were
a reflection, probably, of Corbusier. They each got an &quot;F&quot; grade on their
plates. That episode became sort of the symbol of what we were to experience
during our professional careers. Our work has been a clean, straightforward type
of expression that was such a contrast traditional classic orders and features
that were being used in prominent buildings, including city halls and bank
buildings, all of which seemed to have these columns and caps. I was determined
to change that throughout my career. Nowadays the pendulum has swung back and a
lot of designers are returning to that characteristics of the tradition. Happily
now others are going even farther out then we did with very wonderful,
conceptual shape of structures that computers draw and would be all but
impossible to do manually.

RIGELHAUPT: I wonder if you could talk a little bit about what you did right out of college.
Right after you graduated.

HARDISON: I graduated at the end of &#039;38 because I had to go back for one additional course
but I still graduated in &#039;38 because the semesters end in December. It was an
extremely difficult time. I also visited every prominent architect--. Well, I
should say I visited a lot of architects who were not so prominent. [laughs] I
remember going to William Wurster&#039;s office, and many others in San Francisco.
None of them had any opportunities because the Depression had really pretty much
closed their practices, except for government work that some of them were doing.
Of course, we didn&#039;t know it, but we were approaching war. So, after trying for
six months to get work up here in the Bay Area, I went home to Fillmore, pretty
depressed, and through a friend--. During high school, I was active in a YMCA
group called High Y--I don&#039;t even know if it exists today--but it was a group of
my fellow students, and their director was very helpful to all of us in a number
of ways. I called him he lived in Santa Barbara, and asked, &quot;Do you have any
idea of whether there&#039;d be any opportunities for an architect graduate in Santa
Barbara.&quot; He said, &quot;I just happen to know an architect.&quot; It turned out to be a
very prominent firm largely responsible for the work at the university of Santa
Barbara--UC Santa Barbara. The architect told this fellow that he didn&#039;t have
any work but, he said, &quot;I happen to know an architect in Los Angeles and who
might be interested in giving you a job.&quot; So, I was excited about that, went to
Los Angeles and, met the architect David Witmer, and it was a great experience.
He said, &quot;I do not have a job in the drafting room right now, but we&#039;ve got this
big housing project called Wyvernwood out in east Los Angeles. And I think I can
get you a job there as an apprentice carpenter.&quot; But, you&#039;ll have to join a
union.&quot;--and that was an interesting experience. I worked as an apprentice
carpenter for a number of months. Got acquainted with some carpenters who were
very helpful, showing me how to detail framework by hand saws, before the area
of the Skill saws. Then I was called back to the office and worked there for a
number of months. This was the firm of Witmer and Watson, David J. Witmer went
on to become very prominent, because the Pentagon design had been started but
was apparently in chaos--they couldn&#039;t seem to get the drawings out, or
something. So, Mr. Witmer, a World War I vet reservists, was called back in
service to be the architect on the Pentagon, and is credited with completing
that building. I was very pleased to have that professional experience before I
returning north. I wanted to come back to Northern California if I could
possibly find another opportunity, and it finally came.

RIGELHAUPT: Where did you find this opportunity in Northern California?

HARDISON: A fellow--Cal graduate--called me and said, &quot;Don, there&#039;s an opportunity for an
architect to work in Alameda at a contracting firm called the Hawaiian Raymond
Turner Company, contractors on the Pacific air bases, and it was really a
marvelous opportunity because the bases wee all designed by the famous architect
Albert Kahn, who had been doing work in Detroit for all the major automobile
manufacturers. He had designed these bases, which ultimately were all subject to
Japanese attacks but of course we had no idea of that. This was 1940 and my job
was not designing--which I would like to have done--but rather, it was checking
shop drawings for the steel that was shipped to these islands out of the Alameda
air base. This conglomerate the Hawaiian Raymond Turner Company--was made up of
huge firms: Turner Construction of New York, Hawaiian Bredging Company of
Hawaii, and the Raymond Pile Company--had the job of doing the building on the
bases, and they wanted to be sure that the steel that was being shipped out
of--. It was pre-fabricated steel, incidentally with all of the bolt and rivet
holes pre-punched-- and they wanted to be sure that that work had all been done
accurately checked before it left Alameda. It would be very difficult to make
changes out there in the Pacific. So my job for a number of months was to check
shop drawings, the originals of which were prepared by this prominent architect.
As the work in Alameda, was tapering off--it looked like I&#039;d only have a few
more months of work--I was urged to go to the Mare Island Naval Shipyard. They
were looking for architects and engineers who could sort of adapt to naval
architecture and to work on the hulls that were being either designed or
repaired. Ultimately, when the war came, we repaired a great many--we did the
designs for the repair of many destroyers.

RIGELHAUPT: I&#039;m going to ask you more about Mare Island, but I&#039;m going to have to change the tapes.

RIGELHAUPT: We had just gotten to your experiences on Mare Island. Shall we talk a little
bit about your work at Mare Island?

HARDISON: Yes. I was assigned to the hull department, headed by a fellow by the name of
Gibbons. Of course, I was on the drawing boards and got my first instruction,
you might say, in how to modify hulls, which of course is a little bit unusual
for an architect they are all steel. I got acquainted with welding and welding
techniques. Adjacent to us in the hull department were the mechanical and
electrical departments that took care of those aspects of ships. Mare Island has
a long history, going way back to the mid-nineteenth century, both in building
ships and repairing ships. It was really a very proud operation for all those
who worked there for so many years. See, I started working there in the spring
of &#039;41, and of course, December 7th, &#039;41 was yet to come. The drafting room was
in a three-story building right across from the very large power plant, which
had huge arch windows which at night the glow of the fire in those boilers was
just terrific, just lights up the building and almost seemed to light up the
sky. There was almost terror when this occurred because everyone was so sure
that the Japanese were going to bomb the coast of the States, because we had
virtually lost our navy, so we imagined that these big glowing windows of that
building would be the first target of the Japanese bombers. Well, fortunately,
that never happened, but that was our fear at the time. Also, within what seemed
like a matter of days, &quot;barrage balloons&quot; were put up in the sky, held by
cables, to discourage dive bombing the naval base, because it was assumed naval
bases or ports of that nature--would be the Japanese targets. So it was a
spectacular time and we occasionally worked overtime in order to accomplish our
work. Once the December 7th bombing had occurred. I was rooming there, having
moved from Berkeley, and I can well recall the relief of being able to live
there rather than commuting, because in those years,--what is now highway
I-80--was then U.S. 40--a three-lane highway all the way to Vallejo. So, of
course, in the morning, we were all trying to dominate two lanes going towards
Vallejo and you had to really be alert because there were so many crashes,
resulting from competition for that middle lane. Then, upon returning, it would
just be the reverse. Those of us driving home to the Bay Area from Vallejo would
try to dominate the two lanes that were going that way. Shortly after I moved up
there, I became socially very courageous We used to park on the Mare Island, and
as we were heading out a very attractive lady--I thought--was often seen in a
crosswalk, from our building, had these drafting rooms above, and it was in the
shop superintendent&#039;s office below that this lady worked. One of the fellas in
my car--a friendly engineer commuting from Berkeley--said, &quot;Oh, I know that gal.
That&#039;s Betty Decker.&quot; I said, &quot;Gee, I&#039;d like to meet her.&quot; Anyway, to make a
long story short although, I was a rather modest sort of guy, I did get up the
courage to call the Decker residence in Vallejo and ask for Elizabeth Decker. A
man answered, who turned out to be her dad, said, &quot;We have no Elizabeth here. We
have a Betty.&quot; I said, &quot;Well, maybe it&#039;s Betty.&quot; So anyway, I met my future
bride in that way. On June 14th, 1942 we were married at the Presbyterian Church
in Vallejo, and subsequently took up residence in Richmond because during the
time that we were engaged I was pressured-- really pressured by Kaiser which was
desperately looking for someone with my type of engineer-architect background to
help them with their ship engineering, drafting, and naval architecture in
Richmond. I debated long and hard whether to make the move, because there was a
real possibility, regardless of whatever I did, I was about to be drafted. But
both Mare Island and Kaiser assured me that they were so desperate for this kind
of help that arrangements would be made for deferrals. So I decided to take
Kaiser up on its offer. It was a private company, and I felt that maybe my
opportunities in the future would be better with that company. So I moved to
Shipyard One and had worked there for several months before Betty and I were
married. Then she came to Richmond and we moved into one of the--now
historic--housing projects, Atchison Village, which is on the list of sites of
this new national park in Richmond. We moved it&#039;s a brand new apartment. So,
we&#039;re quite experienced with what one goes through as a new resident of that
housing project, and became very familiar with its design. That was our stepping
stone to Richmond.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk a little bit about what Atchison Village was like, maybe even
more from the perspective of its architecture, and then, too, sort of its
broader social life.

HARDISON: Atchison Village is a very well-planned--I say &quot;is&quot; because it still exists--a
very well-planned community. There were two parts to it. One was the basic plan,
in which the architecture not only included a layout of streets with very
interesting curves and patterns, but also the variety of building types and the
manner in which the general layout was made. We were very fortunate to be able
to find a place there, and now there is a lot of talk about how the community of
Richmond accepted the new employees from across the country--many of whom were
minorities--because, as we discovered after we moved in--. Well, first I should
say that, while most people seeking housing at Kaiser went through the Kaiser
housing operation, which was actually constructed and originally maintained by
the Maritime Commission later, it was assigned to the Richmond Housing Authority
to administer. This was an early part of the Kaiser operation as I arrived. Even
though it was after Pearl Harbor, the only work being done at Kaiser at that
time were on thirty cargo ships that Kaiser had contracted with the British
Government to build. They were Liberty ships and it was anticipated that there
would be future contracts for the U.S. government. But this was for Britain,
which was really under a terribly serious German attack at that time. While
other shipyards were under construction, they were not yet operational, I was
one of the early employees. Shipyard Number One had been in operation for a year
or so when I got there, but the major part of the Kaiser operation in Richmond
was yet to come. So it was the early part of the influx of people. As a couple
that came to Richmond, just like a lot of other people, we were so fortunate to
be able to find housing--through a college, friend who had been our best man,
whose father Fred Newsom was manager of the Richmond Independent and a member of
the Richmond Housing Authority said, &quot;Why don&#039;t you call Dad? Maybe he can help
you find a place.&quot; I had already befriended some people at First Presbyterian
Church in Richmond and before my marriage rented a room from a member. Then, of
course, we moved to Atchison when we got married. This was our great fortune
because Mr. Newsom had said: &quot;You know, we&#039;re just getting ready to take renters
at Atchison Village, but,&quot; he said, &quot;the pressure is just so tremendous, I don&#039;t
know whether I can help you. But I&#039;ll give it a try.&quot; So, lo and behold, a
couple of weeks later he called me back and said, &quot;Don, I think we&#039;ve found a
place for you.&quot; We were delighted with our apartment in a one story, fourplex.
We were at one end and, as coincidence would have it, friends of ours from Cal
were in the unit at the other end, and they had also just gotten married. He
worked at Standard Oil, which is now Chevron-Texaco. Our immediate neighbor was
a Richmond fireman, and across the rear court from us was one of the Kaiser
superintendents. All of us were Caucasian. It was at a time the heavy influx of
people was just adding pressure for housing and Atchison Village was quickly
filled. So that&#039;s how we got into Atchison, which we found very but tiny. I
think it had something like 530 square feet, including a small bedroom, but it
was a space that was ours. It had a rear yard with a clothesline and later,
under that clothesline, we raised some vegetables in what was called a victory
gardens. Another thing about Atchison: it had a central community center, which
was an opportunity for social contacts, and there was also the administrative
office. I mentioned earlier that Atchison was built in two parts. I don&#039;t
remember exactly when the second section started, with--as I recall--something
like two hundred units to Atchison, which were done in sort of typical wartime
designs, unlike the original Atchison design, which was done by local
architects, administered locally, also constructed by a contractor locally. This
addition, the Annex, as they call it, consisted of stock duplexes. Quite
different from the design original of Atchison, which, for those years, was
really well done. For example, we were in a one-story fourplex, but there were
also one-story duplexes, and two bedroom, two-story duplexes. In other words,
the whole idea was to create an atmosphere that was not overly congested. There
was a lot of lawn space in between the buildings, and there were play yards for
the kids. For a congregate living situation, it was very pleasant.

RIGELHAUPT: Jumping back to your role at Kaiser, could you talk about your job at Kaiser
shipyards, and any sort of new techniques or things you developed, or was
developed in the larger workplace at that time?

HARDISON: Okay. That&#039;s a very good question too, because Henry J. Kaiser&#039;s greatest
achievement, of course, was the technique that he developed and expanded to
prefabricate the ships, and thus speed up to a great degree the time it took
from keel-laying to launch. My future part in that became evident the day I
started working, because of the introduction by John B. Moore--my first
supervisor and of course his staff there, in a small drafting room. I remember
they laid out for me the large drawings of the ships that were designed by
George G. Sharp in New York City. He was the major naval architect for the
Maritime Commission. These huge drawings were very cumbersome. And, of course,
there&#039;s a lot of wind in Richmond. If you take one of those plans out on the
ship that&#039;s under construction, it tends blow all over the place. So they showed
me how, instead of those large drawings, we were to make what they call
subsection hull drawings, which were probably on sheets that were--maybe 18 by
24 inches. I&#039;ve really forgotten. But they were relatively small sheets, and on
each one, we would put an element or a subsection, and working out systems for
identifying them as part of the whole. You start with the bow and go back to the
stern--a whole series of these subsections, and also starting with the
double-bottom sections, and then adding deck sections. Well, first, the drawings
were taken to the mold loft, where as a part of the shipbuilding operation,
wooden molds or patterns were created for the steel that is going to be used on
the ship. So, our drawings would show each element each piece of steel that
would make up each small subsection. The mold loft would take those drawings and
lay out, each piece of steel and shape them in wood. Then the wood section--this
wood &quot;mold&quot;--would be taken down into the plate shop, which normally was below
the mold loft. There, plates would be first cut to match the molds, usually with
burning torches, and finished off. Then they would be run through rollers to
provide the shaping that was necessary for, particularly, the sides of the hull.
They would be using our drawings also to show how they&#039;d be assembled after they
would be run through this process. And they had these assembly decks out by the
ways, where the ships were being assembled, and on these decks, or &quot;skids&quot; they
were called, --the shipfitters, welders and burners--would lay out exactly what
our drawing showed. Our drawings were, you might say, a mechanic&#039;s
interpretation of the original design. And from that they would then put
everything together in a single piece--a single section--aligned in such a way
that four giant whirly cranes could pick up the four corners and, on tracks,
wheel them over to the ships on the ways. That was my experience at Yard One,
which was not too long, because shortly after I got there Mr. Moore said, &quot;You
know, they&#039;re getting ready to finish yard number three, and that&#039;s going to be
for building an entirely different kind of ship. It&#039;s going to be a troop ship,
that&#039;s called a C-4. It&#039;s more than twice the size of a Liberty Ship.&quot; Mr. Moore
and a number of us from Yard One went over to Yard Three to do that operation,
which was different, because, while the fabrication process was identical--the
way the ship was assembled was quite different. At Yard One, and later at Yards
Two and Four, there were sloping ways upon which the ship was assembled and then
launched into the Bay, whereas Yard Three had dry docks, the only yard in the
country so built during the war. So there were five dry docks into which these
ships were built. The Prefabricated sections would be lifted by four whirly
cranes off these &quot;skids&quot; and brought over to the dry dock where the ship was
being erected. In other words, after erecting all of the sub-units, the ship was
launched from the dry dock, by just filling it with water. The ship would rise
up and they&#039;d open the gate and the ship would float out with the help of tugs.
Whereas, at the other yards, with conventional ways, the ships--when launching
time came--they would pull out the wedges and the ships would slide into the
water. Ships from all yards would then be moved to the outfitting dock. In other
words, after the launching, they would outfit the ship with all the machinery,
electronic and mechanical equipment that would make the ship operational. And
you asked what newly created ideas we helped produce, and I think we were all in
this together. I learned about prefabrication at Yard One, because they&#039;d
already started doing that, but as the months went on, during the war, we
refined this technique to a major extent and more and more stuff could go into
the sub-assembly unit, so that it would take the time off of the ways or the dry
docks, and make the production of ships so much faster. While I was not involved
in the record-breaking ships that were built at Yard Number Two, this was all a
part of the technique that we at Kaiser developed. A group of engineers and
architects, and hull people, made it possible for the sub-assembled cabins to be
painted and have all the switching and wiring in place and so when they were set
on the ship, they were already connected up. There had to be connecting links.
The fastest ship, of course, was built in just slightly over four days, which is
a record to this date. And it was only possible because these sections were
practically complete when they were assembled on the ways. Those were big ships,
perhaps 460 feet long, and almost 10,000 tons. That&#039;s a big chunk of metal.

RIGELHAUPT: One other person that I believe you worked with, was C.P. Bedford. I was
wondering if you could tell me a little bit about your interaction, the
strengths you saw working there, the kind of person he was. How would you
describe him?

HARDISON: Kaiser ultimately was given the opportunity to build ships in two locations; one
was in Richmond and the other was in Vancouver, Washington. The Richmond
operation was headed entirely by Clay P. Bedford, he was also involved in the
construction aspect of the yards. He had an assistant whose name was Einer
Larson, who was in charge of the actual construction of the shipyards, and he
headed a large engineering department, located in Richmond, that produced the
documents used by the contractors to build everything in the shipyards,
including the ways and the huge warehouse that exists today at Yard Three. I
think Mr. Bedford was over all of this early on, but then when the shipbuilding
started, it&#039;s my understanding that he was transferred to the administration of
the shipbuilding. Mr. Larson continued in the construction area for a number of
months before he, too, came to administer the shipbuilding. So, Mr. Bedford--in
my opinion, was sort of a technical genius that produced the results that were
achieved in Richmond. Mr. Kaiser, obviously, is credited--very properly--with
the vision of doing all of this work at two different geographic locations. He
also had a reputation for amazing work in building dams and heavy construction
early on. But the actual on-site work, and particularly the prefabrication that
we achieved in Richmond, was a pioneering effort that should be credited to Mr.
Bedford. And it&#039;s through his leadership that the Richmond Kaiser
Shipyards--competitively exceeded the records of the Vancouver yard that was
managed by Mr. Kaiser&#039;s son, Edgar. The fun aspect of doing such tough work was
that we were competing with another shipyard within the same top management. Mr.
Bedford chose very skilled administrators or leaders, foremen who did the actual
work. Shipyard Number Three I became well acquainted with yard. Superintendent
O.H. McCoon, Shop Superintendent Victor Cole; Outfitting Dock Superintendent,
Kenneth Flood and his assistant, Jim McCloud. The superintendents were
experienced construction people with Kaiser, and both were ingenious in the way
they adapted their style--their construction technique--to shipbuilding, which
was so vastly different from pouring concrete and building dams and structures.
So, I think Clay P. Bedford should be largely credited with that accomplishment,
because it was he who was in charge. On rare occasions Kaiser would appear if
some outstanding honoree was launching the ship or a specific ship justified Mr.
Kaiser being present. My relationship to Mr. Bedford was of course, as a lower
level department head. During the most active period, my department had
seventy-two draftsmen, and only on rare occasions when there was some policy
involved on how we were to do our work or maybe an issue with the Maritime
Commission was a meeting with Mr. Bedford justified. The Maritime Commission
kept changing their plans shown on large drawings from Mr. Sharp&#039;s office in New
York, and we would be the ones who would have to quickly modify our shop
drawings to record the changes. And sometimes there was the issue as to whether
we would make the change on one hull or wait for the next. On rare occasions I
would have the opportunity, with other supervisors, to be in meetings with Mr.
Bedford in which these things were discussed. But most of my work was through
Mr. Einor Larson who was Bedford&#039;s assistant in the same office. I just didn&#039;t
have occasion to have much contact with Mr. Bedford.

RIGELHAUPT: Switching gears a little bit to the larger social setting in Richmond during
World War II, what do you remember most about how Richmond changed during the war?

HARDISON: This is the story that I think is most significant in connection with this
relatively small town of 23,000 people, which was selected by Kaiser and the
Maritime Commission to start these shipyards. It&#039;s my impression, because I did
have some contact through Richmond friends that I knew before my time in
Richmond, so I associated myself largely with the old town. We were the early
ones to arrive, and we were accepted very readily as part of the old town--with
a few exceptions.

But our observation was that Richmond was extremely ill-prepared to function as
the support community for shipyards that at one time total amount 100,000
employees. Because transportation was difficult, it was hard for people to
drive--not only because the roads were limited in their access, but fuel was
hard to come by. You could get an allotment of fuel for commuting, but it was
very difficult. They finally built a streetcar rail--between Oakland and
Richmond but, for various reasons, that was not very successful. So really, what
Richmond was supposed to do was provide housing for virtually thousands of
families that came into the community. The community didn&#039;t have the resources
and the federal government was slow to act. Atchison Village was the only
project--which was very small in terms of the need--and so everyone had to wait
until the Maritime Commission had gotten their projects under way. Thousands of
apartments were eventually made available in Richmond. Very emergency-like
techniques were utilized in the acquisition of property. If the owners of open
land could not be found the property would be condemned and assembled for six
unit stock apartment houses on these properties. So Richmond, as a community,
whether you&#039;re talking about the grocery store, the banks, or the theatres, or
medical community, was just very--very inadequate. Richmond&#039;s response has been
criticized by a number of authors who have written either articles or books, and
there was even an exhibit in Washington DC that we visited several years ago
that suggested that Richmond was just not equal to this task. And I must agree.
Now, as time went on, everything was expanded, and the fire department was a
local organization--in other words, the Maritime Commission would build the
buildings but the fire department would be expanded.

So even the firemen, who are traditionally a rather close-knit lot, would
include people from out of the community. The schools were terribly
overburdened, and there are many teachers still around who remember their
difficulties with overwhelming sizes of classes, and the double sessions that
they worked on a morning and afternoon--because there just was not enough space
to accommodate the kids. The fact that many of the people who were arriving to
work on the shipyards had never lived in an urban situation, even as modest as
Richmond. Richmond was a big city compared to--. Hundreds of people who arrived
in Richmond, some of whom did not even have toilet facilities at home in their
place of departure, and so there was a tremendous cultural gap between many of
the arrivals and this small community that was supposed to be so accommodating
to them. I can probably speak to different areas of difficulties. We were not
particularly plagued by this, because we were in the new community of Atchison
Village that was largely made up of people who had lived in this community, or
had come to work in advanced technology, such as various manufacturers in
Richmond. Incidentally, Richmond was a truly manufacturing city in those years.
It had the Standard Oil Refinery, large Rheem Manufacturing; a very large
American Standard facility, one of which they made bathtubs, at another of which
they made basins and fixtures; and the Pullman car plant in Richmond, one of the
largest in the country, where they maintained Pullman cars, and during the war
refitted as troop trains. These people were already in the community, and you
can imagine the competition, or the attitudes between these industrial workers
and the type of farmer or person from other fields coming in from Oklahoma,
Tennessee or Missouri. There are many stories on where these frictions occurred.
But, I think it&#039;s understandable, considering the kind of community Richmond was
before this huge responsibility was imposed.

RIGELHAUPT: You just mentioned some of the frictions with lots of people coming in. Could
you describe a little bit more where some of those frictions took place and what
they looked like?

HARDISON: Well, for example in housing. There were several small contractors who made
their living building houses--a few duplexes, small private housing. They were
all rather reluctant to market those properties to either investors who might
rent them to a shipyard worker, or to a shipyard worker that could put down
enough to purchase a property. I really believe that these local businesspeople
thought that when the war was over they would return to--essentially--normal.
That was in some ways encouraged by positions that Mr. Kaiser took himself, when
of the four shipyards he gained Maritime Commission&#039;s approval and budget for a
permanent facility. And Mr. Kaiser, on several occasions, indicated that after
the war there would be a modest shipbuilding industry in Richmond, which would
have been very easy for the community to absorb.

It was Shipyard Number Three, which had dry docks. That did not happen, as when
the war was over, Mr. Kaiser found that there were surplus ships all over the
world, including Victory ships, Liberty ships, and even larger cargo
vessels--like our C4s we&#039;d been building--so the market for a substantial
shipbuilding industry in Richmond faded. There again, the hopes and, you might
say, the energies of the community were directed towards normalcy after the war.
And that is a whole story in itself of how first they didn&#039;t have enough housing
and then after the war, the community, with its agencies, particularly the
redevelopment agency, made agreements with the Maritime Commission that
permitted it to demolish virtually all of the wartime housing.

There were just a few units left which were all built under a different program
from Atchison Village, which was to be retained. But to illustrate the desire of
the community to get rid of as much public housing as possible, the Housing
Authority made arrangements to see Atchison Village to its tenants who formed a
private condominium group. That&#039;s because the Authority just wanted to get away
from public housing. But people were still around, living in very difficult
situations after that public housing was demolished. My firm was the first one
to have an opportunity to design a post-war housing project. It would be called
Easter Hill Village. That&#039;s a whole story in itself. I&#039;d become licensed in
1948, and I received several major projects in Richmond in my early years as an
architect. But the first two major public projects was Easter Hill with the
Richmond Housing Authority in 1950, and the West County Court Building on
Thirty-seventh Street. So that&#039;s where I started my postwar experience of
helping the town convert to normalcy, which it really wasn&#039;t enjoying at the
time the war ended.

RIGELHAUPT: Could you talk more about your firm and anything you designed that&#039;s in
Richmond, from schools to housing, to courthouses. How you would sort of discuss
your experiences there?

HARDISON: Well, when the war ended--. In fact, about the middle of 1945, it was evident to
all of us in our production drafting department that there were not going to be
any more ships built, and they were not revising ships any more, so obviously
our department was being phased out, just as were the shipyard workers at each
yard. As the keel of the last ship would be laid, then they would start laying
off shipfitters and welders and the burners and so forth. The same thing
happened in our department, which actually came earlier because we were the ones
that did the drawings before the work was done. So it was obvious I had to start
thinking about what I was going to do with my future, and we had been very
fortunate to have been deferred from military service during those years--and
I&#039;m very appreciative of that opportunity--but we also, as did all of us who had
graduated in my class, had difficulty during those war years of relating to architecture.

So I was looking forward to getting back to it, and I left the Kaiser
organization in December &#039;45. This was well after the war was over but they were
still just finishing up the last C4s. Two others George Rhoda and Ted Moist, all
three of us in the same department there at Kaiser, and all three of us were Cal
guys, and decided we would start a design firm in Richmond. There was only one
architectural firm in Richmond, and the architect was very ill, and
unfortunately died, I believe in 1946. So it was a small community with
virtually no architects. It looked like it would be an opportunity for us to do
work in Richmond.

So we rented a little storefront office on Twelfth Street, and proceeded to
receive interest from a lot of different sources--not much of any money, but a
lot of opportunity to think about postwar work. The city was desperate for
everything from new stores to public buildings, schools, and just virtually
everything. So the opportunities were there if we could just get the work. Some
of the earliest work, for example--one of the proudest things in Richmond--the
Richmond Arts Center, was getting ready to build--. As part of the Civic Center
designed by the prominent San Francisco firm of Flueger &amp; Flueger. The lady who
headed the Richmond Arts Center organization, before there were any real
buildings, Hazel. Salmi, asked me if I--our firm--would do a sketch of the Art
Center how that might be incorporated in the Civic Center complex. We did a
sketch, which was given to the Fluegers, and the arts center was incorporated
almost identically to our layout, which still exists. It was added as a wing to
the auditorium, and is one of the most prominent nonprofit organizations in
Richmond. So that was one of our first little opportunities, but I don&#039;t think
we received anything for it. Maybe they paid us for the prints or something.

Then the Chamber of Commerce said, &quot;You know, we haven&#039;t changed a store around
here all during the war, for five or six years, so how about doing something
that would show how we could--.&quot; They decided on some kind of a program to get
the business community to get involved in a seminar on how a business block in
Richmond might be remodeled. So we took pictures of one city business block on
Macdonald Avenue, between Eleventh and Twelfth Street, and redesigned the front
of every store. This was in the years when aluminum was just coming into use,
and companies like Kawneer Company created great details of aluminum that could
be used on storefronts, and neon was also getting into play.

So we had a lot of fun doing a series of stores. We didn&#039;t change any of the
dimensions of the stores-- just their frontage. It was very well received. There
were a lot of merchants who were interested in moving ahead on remodeling like
that, and we got a few jobs out of it. Remember we were not licensed and only
allowed to be called &quot;designers&quot; limiting our work to remodeling houses and
non-structural things. Well, when I got my license we considered whether to
continue as partners. For a while I practiced alone, then Ted Moist joined me.
Mr. Rhoda had found an opportunity in Monterey, and went to that community,
where he became a very prominent architect. So anyway, for a number of years, it
was &quot;Donald Hardison and Associates&quot; and under that firm name, our first real
jobs were the First Presbyterian Church, which was relocating from downtown to
out on Barrett Avenue; and the YMCA, which asked for a very unusual plan. They
wanted to join with the YWCA in a building, which would be known as the Memorial
Youth Center, honoring those in the community lost during World War II. We got
the job in &#039;48 and completed it in 1950. In 1950, the big opportunity for
designing government work, which I mentioned, was the Easter Hill Village
project, which was a project of the Richmond Housing Authority. Then the County
of Contra Costa was planning a court building, and we were interviewed for that.
And I may say, that in both of those opportunities, there were five votes to be
cast and we got three out of the five--but that did it. It took us a while to
obtain school work even though I was well acquainted with the longstanding
superintendent, Walter Helms. It would be two superintendents later before we
really had an opportunity to design a number of schools, including Richmond High
School, which was quite a new concept in terms of circulation. It had a huge
mall as part of the central activity area for the students, which included a
cafeteria and library. We also did a number of elementary schools, a junior high
in Berkeley, and a swim center in Berkeley.

RIGELHAUPT: Excuse me, I&#039;m going to change the tapes.

HARDISON:  Sure.

RIGELHAUPT: Okay, the audio&#039;s back on. Okay, so you were talking about designing Richmond High.

HARDISON: Richmond High came later in our experience with schools, and that was very
interesting because this was during a time that the district felt that they
wanted to change the manner in which the teaching process was done, and they
wanted a school to reflect that. This involved what they called &quot;team teaching&quot;,
in which each classroom was to have two teachers, and they had respective roles
that they would work out between them. Instead of having enclosed classrooms,
with the usual door, they wanted the classroom open to the corridors. So you
could actually walk down a corridor and look in and see the activities in each
classroom, including any music or sound or anything that was going on. Also,
because Richmond was already becoming a troubled city in terms of vandalism,
they didn&#039;t want any windows. And thirdly, the original high school was a very
attractive building, which was affectionately held by all those who had
graduated from the school. It was a brick building with terracotta columns, and
it was just a handsome traditional school. It had been designed, of course, for
natural ventilation, whereas the new school was air-conditioned and--I&#039;ve
already mentioned--no windows.

Well, the first thing that I did was to talk them into having very minimal
windows, just so that you&#039;d know whether it was rain or shine outside from each
classroom. While this was accepted by the school board, it wasn&#039;t long after the
school was built when they even covered those windows up with plywood just so
that the vandals wouldn&#039;t break the glass. The school was a very simple design.
I wouldn&#039;t say that it would have matched the work of Frank Lloyd Wright or Le
Corbusier, but it was very clean. And it was liked by some people, and virtually
hated by others, particularly the traditional teacher, who not only liked the
old school appearance, but liked the idea of being able to close his/her
classroom door and have the privacy of teacher and students. Whereas that
opportunity was not present in the plan that was devised by the district--with
our cooperation, of course. To accomplish this new type of school, they actually
retired the former principal, David Gray, and called in a new principal who was
an advocate of the open classroom type of teaching. But there was a great deal
of discontent among the staff and so Richmond High, which I proudly boasted as
our finest architectural school job, really had its problems, and they still
exist today. There has been some remodeling to return to the traditional
classroom, but of course, nothing works, since it wasn&#039;t designed to work that
way. It was just not a very happy solution.

I&#039;m still very proud of what we did in designing the original, however. We also
did a number of, you might say, non-traditional elementary schools, one of which
was Grant School. It was because of the quality that resulted from that, those
very simple lines that impressed the Berkeley school board giving us an
opportunity on University Avenue to do a major addition to what was then called
the Burbank Junior High. It was subsequently renamed, because it&#039;s now a senior
high school for adult education. We also did the Berkeley swim center, which is
right behind it. That was very well received by the city of--by the people in
Berkeley. We also did a major junior high--when they were called &quot;junior
highs&quot;-- the Downer Junior High, which was west of the new Richmond High, was
really a very useful and practical, as well as handsome, school with colorful
panels part of the window fenestration. For reasons that have never been clear
to me, many years later, the District converted it to an elementary school,
claiming a shortage elementary schools.

But, as you know, elementary school requirements and those of the intermediate
school level are quite different. It&#039;s very unfortunate that they&#039;re using shop
space, for example, for conventional classrooms. My early respect for the way
the school was being used has been changed materially. Let&#039;s see, what other
schools have we done? Our firm has done numerous schools, including some in
Marin, and most recently--just shortly after I retired--our firm did the
Alhambra High School, just outside of Martinez. The firm has also done schools
in several other cities.

RIGELHAUPT: The housing project you did--the name has slipped my mind for the moment--

HARDISON: Easter Hill Village?

RIGELHAUPT: Easter Hill. Could you talk about your goals in designing that, influences, what
you hoped to accomplish with the set-up of the community, and when you did the project.

HARDISON: At the time that I received the commission for doing Easter Hill housing
project, wartime housing still existed throughout the community. There were
literally hundreds of units everywhere, within a few hundred feet or up to a
mile or so from Easter Hill Village, but the community was already requesting
that that such housing be demolished to make room for what they thought would be
normal development of the community. So Easter Hill was technically the first
housing done in the City of Richmond following the wartime housing that was, of
course, done in the early years of World War II. It was to be administered by
the Richmond Housing Authority, with funding from the federal government through
the Public Housing Administration, which it was called at that time. The goals
were to--a 300-unit project, which is sizeable--on an ideal site. So the first
assignment that I was given was to look at several locations within the
community that might be available for a project of this nature. It appeared to
me after reviewing a number that the site of Easter Hill, which originally was a
small hill where Easter sunrise services had been held on its summit, and that&#039;s
how it got its name. But during the early part of the war, the Kaiser people
needed--desperately needed--landfill material in order to create the site of
future yard number two.

So after tons of material were removed from the hill, a very unsightly quarry
brought down to grade level with ridges almost like a volcano around it. Of a
number I considered, this was the site initially recommended to the housing
authority, and they bought it, and were very interested in the concept. As a
young architect; this was a huge challenge in the housing field. Although I had
done homes, I had not done any multiple housing, and in reviewing where I might
gain consultant help to do the work, I was reminded that a fellow by the name of
Vernon DeMars had just arrived in Berkeley, with William Wurster, from MIT. to
be on the faculty of the architectural department. I called Vernon--we had never
met, and he came over and we looked at the site. He was very excited about it,
because he had considerable housing experience, both before the war and during
the war, with the Farm Security Administration. He had worked in their offices
for some time, and then at MIT he and a partner did a couple of very nice
high-rise housing developments.

I first engaged him as a consultant, but as we got into it, it became more and
more obvious that Mr. DeMars was bringing a good many of the novel ideas to this
project, and had also introduced me to Lawrence Halprin, a landscape architect,
who was responsible ultimately for designing the landscaping and, particularly,
suggesting how we could architecturally the huge boulders that were left on the
quarry site. Larry had the idea that they would make great compositions within
the project, and we could put plants around the boulders, and so forth. So I
bought that idea, and it became very much a part of the character of the future
Easter Hill Village. With regard to Vernon, I finally felt obligated to invite
him to be an associate, even though so ultimately all the work was done in my
offices, and I make virtually all contact with both the client as well as the
federal government. The firm became known, for that particular project as Donald
Hardison and Vernon DeMars, Architects Associated.

The project was unique in that, probably for the first time in public housing,
there was a very real effort made to create identification for family units. So,
not only were the apartments identified from one another by either offsetting
their floor plans so that they formed sort of a jagged pattern, but we often
changed color and materials of individual row houses, and then all the family
units--which were about, 95 or 96 percent, had designated yard space of their
own and fenced in so that they could plant a garden, secure their children, or
have a puppy dog. There was certain privacy provided for each family within the
unit. The street pattern developed also made it truly a neighborhood rather than
just a grid system, block pattern, which is the way the rest of Richmond had
been laid out. So that in that respect, Easter Hill Village, was laid out as a
custom community--in the same manner as Atchison Village, which we thought would
strengthen the relationships between the tenants. But in actuality, as the
project housed more and more very low-income--federal aided people, with many
single parent families--continued over a period of several years, the project
failed for the very reasons that we thought it would be successful.

Later, the police would claim that because it was a neighborhood, the crime that
was occurring there because the streets didn&#039;t lend themselves to either access
or egress. Once you got into the layout, you were sort of in a confined
neighborhood rather than in a block system where you can go any of four
directions. So the qualities that we felt were in the original project were
largely depreciated as time went on, and it truly became if not one of, probably
the major, crime centers for the handling of drugs. It&#039;s just because a very
serious problem. The early response to the project nationally was terrific.
During a special program for the hundredth anniversary of the American Institute
of Architects in 1957, which was funded by Kodak, &quot;Ten Buildings, in America&#039;s
Future&quot;, selected and photographed by a very prominent photographer. Included
were one Frank Lloyd Wright building, the St. Louis Airport, done by HOK
[Hellmuth Obata &amp; Kassabaum], and Easter Hill Village. We were very proud of
that. It was displayed at the National Gallery in Washington, which I visited.
I&#039;ve got a photograph of myself beside the beautiful exhibit, and we were given
other recognitions, published in Life Magazine and several professional
magazines The exhibit also traveled to Russia.

But in terms of the community and the police problem, it was a doomed
area--doomed village. Much to my sadness and shock, it looks today as though
virtually the whole project is going to be demolished and replaced by a
mixed-use, which will include some low-income housing and some--privately owned
houses. I maintain that the qualities for which it was originally designed still
exist, and Vernon DeMars fully agrees with me. He&#039;s ninety-five now,
incidentally, but he still is very sharp. Right now the community has already
designed what they hope to build there, and have not been responsive to my
suggestions that they could create home-ownership there by just converting some
of those four- and six-unit buildings to condominiums and there could be home
ownership and government rental units side by side. But they are seemingly not
interested in this, except that before they demolish the project, which is now
considered historic--it&#039;s been more than fifty years since we started the
work--an EIR [environmental impact report] must be developed to confirm that
everything has been considered before this demolition occurs. Part of the EIR is
a historical study and report, and historians have interviewed me and they are
very enthusiastic about the project, and do not understand why it&#039;s being
demolished. I have not seen their report. As required, it has been filed with
the state office of Historic Preservation and if it accepts the request of the
city, apparently, it will be demolished. On the other hand, if the office in
Sacramento decides that there is insufficient evidence that this historic
project cannot be maintained in a practical way, very remotely we may be able to
save Easter Hill. So that is the good news-- bad news.

RIGELHAUPT: When did Easter Hill open?

HARDISON: It was opened in 1954. There were 300 units. I believe that it was &#039;55 before
the last of the last units were occupied. But, as I said, we started working on
it in 1950.

RIGELHAUPT: And you mentioned that at some point--. Do you remember when some of the
problems you mentioned with Easter Hill started occurring?

HARDISON: Yes. Initially, there were no particular issues. The administration of the
housing authority, as was full understanding, wanted to have a mix of family
incomes. So there would be low incomes and some moderate incomes. But a
situation developed after the war when thousands of other units, were demolished
and the pressure from, not only the poor, but the minority community, became
tremendous to find housing. Initially there were a number of two-parent
families, I should say; both parents--but shortly after--when I say shortly, I&#039;m
talking about ten or twelve years--the national authority, which I guess was
still PHA [Public Housing Administration], or it might have been the successor
body, during Johnson&#039;s administration, urged that they not continue to balance
the incomes of the occupants, instead accept only the poorest. In so doing, they
inherited all the problems of those people. The kids were unsupervised a good
deal of the time, as usually the parents were working, and more often than not,
they were on federal aid, so that despite what the local authority believed in
the best in the interest of the neighborhoods, the order to house the poorest of
the poor, created inevitable social problems for the occupants. For twenty to
twenty-five years, our firm was in very close contact with the housing authority
and as problems occurred in maintenance--. For example, the wonderful boulders
that formed such great visual objects, created a problem because--, we never
dreamed that--kids would take such an interest in these boulders that they&#039;d dig
under them to make caves. Some boulders became unstable and so one of our
contracts was to stabilize the boulders, which we had assumed that once in the
ground they would stay there. But the kids loved to play around them. So we had
many remedial projects. For example, another minimum thing that was required by
the federal government at the time we designed it was, in the little laundry
unit, just off the kitchen sink, we had a laundry tray and room for a washing
machine, but no connections. In other words, federal standards had not permitted
it to be set up to use a modern day washer, so there had to be some plumbing
corrections. The original design would not allow doors on a great many of the
closets and cabinets. For example, in the bedrooms the wardrobes were not
covered with doors.

So, I guess, the tenants could put cloth over them, but it was just very
economically designed originally, all standards that we were required to use as
a guide during the design. So we were involved in upgrading. However, the last
project we did completely discouraged us and we said that we were no longer
interested in helping. Of a number of modernizations to be made, which were
badly needed, the Housing Authority decided that the most important thing to do
was to bar the windows to prevent intruders. In order to do this legally, very
elaborate hardware must be provided to allow a release that even a child can
activate in the event of a fire. If a child&#039;s in a room and there&#039;s a fire, we
had double-hung windows, originally, which they could very easily be opened for
escape. But when bars are installed over them, release levers must be very
carefully integrated into the interior so that a burglar or intruder cannot
release the bars, yet at the same time they must be easily released by a child,
in the case of emergency. It was just so discouraging to see this attractive
housing, which originally had different colors and textures on the outside,
having these black bars added. We just decided our firm didn&#039;t need that kind of
work, so we stopped serving the housing authority at that time.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you think some of the problems that occurred at Easter Hill were
representative of the problems that the larger City of Richmond faced after
World War II?

HARDISON: Very definitely. The only difference, I would say, is that whereas Easter Hill
was concentrated in a single neighborhood, accommodating a certain economic
level, in the City of Richmond as a whole--people were trying to maintain their
properties and had very good relationships with their neighborhoods. There were
isolated areas where two or three houses or more would have problems, but
basically the city housing was not bad. However, Richmond changed from a largely
Caucasian city, with many Japanese who had wonderful nursery systems, as well as
a few Afro-Americans during the years before the war. But generally speaking the
changes in this community during and after the war occurred because of the
differences in culture from where the people had originated as well as the
change in racial texture that virtually overwhelmed this small community.
Whereas there was a healthy downtown business district in Richmond when we came
to city, which extended well into the fifties, a combination of pressure from a
new minority community, together with some very unfortunate policies of the
redevelopment agency funded by the federal government, that allowed or
permitted--or encouraged, I should say--the demolition of commercial buildings
before there was any plan for their replacement. Downtown Richmond had some
major stores such as a large Macy&#039;s, and a multistory Penney&#039;s and a number of
other very good retail establishments. These were bought up by the redevelopment
agency, buildings were demolished, and vacant lots stood there for years. Under
those circumstances, the business community was not interested in putting
investment back into that area. Meanwhile, these price of, the value of, the
properties dropped so much that the newer community was able to purchase these
buildings, but many properties still remain vacant today, and there are still
vacant lots. The original business community them became interested in the newer
area, which became was land owned by the Standard Oil Company, which became the
Hilltop Shopping Center. And that was all new. It allowed a lot of flexibility,
and so first Macy&#039;s moved, then Penney&#039;s moved. Downtown Richmond was virtually
demolished by the policies of the redevelopment agency. Whereas communities of
Oakland have gone through a lot of the same problem. Oakland&#039;s downtown
buildings still exists and was not demolished. Also Berkeley has survived very
well, because of all its pre-war buildings which largely still exist on Shattuck
Avenue. So, Richmond has taken a beating as a result of this influx of a new population.

RIGELHAUPT: You mentioned the Japanese community in Richmond before the war. What do you
remember about after Pearl Harbor and in the months following, where
Japanese-Americans were interned? How do you remember Richmond reacting?

HARDISON: Well, I had a more personal recollection, that I really failed to cover properly
early on. One is that one of my first acquaintances and first friends that I
developed when I went to the University in 1934, was Shigego Richard Komatsu,
who was a freshman architectural student like myself. We got along very well at
Cal. In fact, we did a senior project together. He subsequently went to work for
a San Francisco architect. When Pearl Harbor struck he was--like all of us
devastated of course, but within a matter of just days after Pearl Harbor. He
and his folks, who lived in San Francisco, his dad was a painter--a painting
contractor--by profession or field--. All were forced to leave their home, and
subsequently his dad lost his business. I think they even lost their home, but
I&#039;m not quite sure what happened. I know that Shig, like myself, had Studebaker
Champion and he gave his car to a friend when he was forced to leave San
Francisco. He went on to do some very important service to the country during
the war, which made it all the more ridiculous that they considered the
Japanese-Americans such a hazard. Shig not only worked for a housing authority
back East, but actually invited to serve in the armed forces as a planner. To
this day, he can&#039;t understand how they could have encouraged that after they had
condemned him as being a threat to the nation. But anyway, our paths crossed
again after the war when he asked to be called &quot;Rich,&quot; and was again working in
San Francisco with Architect--Charles Strothoff. During the war Strohoff had
closed his practice and was actually the administrator of the Richmond Housing
Authority. So, Rich returned to work for him, but Strothoff was getting close to
retirement, and my firm was going strong. About 1952 or so I&#039;d had these jobs
we&#039;ve been discussing----so he agreed to come with me. First he was considered
an associate, but later he became a partner. The tragedy that I experienced with
him was that he wrote me some very sad letters during the war about how he just
couldn&#039;t understand it, and I&#039;d write back and say I couldn&#039;t understand it, but
I didn&#039;t know what I could do. I was working at Kaiser shipyards, I had no
influence or contact, and so I&#039;m very well acquainted with what happened to the
Japanese community. As Japanese families in Richmond, I was not acquainted with
any at the time. After the war, several prominent Japanese families that have
been here for years and owned large nurseries we got personally acquainted with,
both as friends, and customers, and we also became acquainted with some of their
problems. Mr. Komatsu brought into the office work for one of the nurseries, and
we did two major nurseries for them, Adachi&#039;s, one of which still exists in El
Sobrante. I should say that--typical, I guess, of their culture,--they are, with
few exceptions, amazingly uncritical of what we, what the government did. I know
that in their hearts they feel it, but the friends that I have are not activists
in terms of demanding, you know, retribution or something for their suffering.
So, I think the Japanese personality has a lot to do with the way they&#039;ve been
reintegrated into our community.

RIGELHAUPT: You&#039;ve really touched on a lot of the questions, so I don&#039;t have anything really
specific. I think this actually might be a good time to wrap up. So is there
anything you&#039;d like to add that you haven&#039;t said?

HARDISON: Well, I&#039;m a part of the local organization that&#039;s trying to help the National
Park Service with their new park. I&#039;m very enthusiastic about it. I have
information and recollections about several of their important sites, the most
important of which, I think, is Yard Number Three. However, the Ford Plant is
considered to be the place where the national park will have their visitors
center. My firm did a lot of work on that old building, a number of years
ago--thirty years ago, I guess--when the University had it and used it as a
warehouse and a facility for a number of different departments for both Berkeley
and at SF Med Center. So we&#039;re very pleased with the progress that&#039;s being made.
We have an awfully long way to go, and Judy Hart as the superintendent, is very
active providing the leadership that&#039;s going to be necessary. It&#039;s an unusual
park in that the sites all have to be maintained by others, than the National
Park Service. I&#039;m also very active in the restoration of the Red Oak Victory,
which was launched at Yard Number One, where I first worked at the shipyards,
and currently the Richmond Museum of History is looking for funding in order to
get the ship operational. It is destined to be one of the most valuable sites,
marvelous in the National Park Service.

RIGELHAUPT: Okay, I think we&#039;ll stop there.

HARDISON:  Okay.

[end of interview]</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>