<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00100711" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2015-12-29" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format>Unknown Date</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Josie Dunn | Interview 1 | December 29, 2015</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewer>David Dunham</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>lzhEUpUqUBg</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>DUNHAM:Good afternoon. I&#039;m David Dunham here with Josie Dunn on December 29,
2015, and we&#039;re very honored that you joined us here today for the Rosie the
Riveter/World War II Home Front Oral History Project.

DUNN: Thank you.

DUNHAM:We always start at the beginning, so what is your full name?

DUNN: My full name is Josie E.--initial E--you want my full name, right? [laughs]

DUNHAM:Well, whatever you want to give us. No stress.

DUNN: Okay, Beard. Beard. And then--

DUNHAM:Okay, B-E-A-R-D?

DUNN: That is correct.

DUNHAM:When and where were you born?

DUNN: I was born in Wilton, Arkansas.

DUNHAM:And when?

DUNN: On June 23, 1918.

DUNHAM:Can you tell me a little bit about your family&#039;s history and background,
going as far back as you--?

DUNN: Well, my mother came from Homer, Louisiana. That&#039;s where her parents
lived; that&#039;s where she was born, in Homer. And then her parents moved to
Arkansas, and that&#039;s where she met my father. And there were seven kids born to
that--siblings, those siblings.

DUNHAM:And you were the youngest?

DUNN: I was the youngest, yes, the youngest. And four months after I was born he
passed away, and we lost him.

DUNHAM:I&#039;m so sorry. And what were the circumstances? How did he pass?

DUNN: I think it was with--they call it TB, tuberculosis. That&#039;s what Mama
always said.

DUNHAM:So that must have been very hard then, for your mom.

DUNN: It was, very hard for my mother.

DUNHAM:Did you know your grandparents on either side?

DUNN: Yes, I knew my grandfather, but they tell me something about my
grandmother that I don&#039;t remember too well, but my grandfather was Jim Malone.
My mother&#039;s name was Malone, Josie Malone. That was her name. And then when he
moved her from Louisiana, that&#039;s when they moved to Arkansas, so my mother got
married in Arkansas.

DUNHAM:Do you know why they moved from Louisiana to Arkansas?

DUNN: No, I really don&#039;t.

DUNHAM:And then your family moved, shortly after you were born, to Oklahoma? Is
that right?

DUNN: Yes, when my father passed away, my grandparents had moved to Oklahoma.
When he passed away we didn&#039;t know his relatives, not too well, so then Mama
came to decide she&#039;d come out to Oklahoma with her parents. And that&#039;s where we
grew up from there.

DUNHAM:What was it like growing up in Oklahoma at that time?

DUNN: Oh, at that time! [laughs] I don&#039;t know at that time, but it had not been
too good, because she told me a lot of things about it. But I know growing up
myself in Oklahoma it wasn&#039;t too good for us, and I was so happy that we got a
chance to come up this way.

DUNHAM:Which was not till you were already an adult, that you got here?

DUNN: No, I was--after I graduated in 1936, then we came out here under the President--

 DUNHAM:Roosevelt.

DUNN: --Roosevelt, FDR, FDR regime.

DUNHAM:I want to hear all about that, and I don&#039;t want to have you suffer too
much through the difficult times of Oklahoma, but I&#039;d like to know a little bit
about what it was like growing up at that time. What was school like, or what
did you do when you were young?

DUNN: Well, we were--our school--all we had mostly was picking cotton, or
chopping cotton. People don&#039;t know the word chopping, what that means, but they
had to plant the cotton, and then when it grew up tall enough they get all the
weeds out and separate them to about seven inches apart on a row. It wasn&#039;t
being paid by the hour; you were paid by the day, by the job. The cotton would
grow about seven inches apart in a row. Most people they wanted, most workers,
they wanted to take two rows at a time to fill their sack up, you know, with
cotton. Then you&#039;d take it up to the scale, and the guy would weigh it and take
it to the gin later on and have it gin out, all the seeds removed and
everything. So my mother did that. She&#039;d always take us with her because I was
too young to stay home by myself, and she always took the family with us, you know.

DUNHAM:Did you have to do that work at some point too?

DUNN: Oh sure, sure! [laughs]

DUNHAM:How old were you when you started?

DUNN: Oh, I must have been about two years old.

DUNHAM:Oh my God!

DUNN: They had these long cotton sacks to fill the cotton in, so she&#039;d take me,
and then when I&#039;d get tired she&#039;d put me on the sack along with the cotton and
pull it, which was very stressful for her. But anyway, that&#039;s what she had to
do. So the kids, her kids, my siblings, weren&#039;t old enough to help her because
they were too young. First was the two girls. They were the oldest, then Mama
had a set of twin boys and then the rest of us, three girls after. So that&#039;s how
it ended up.

DUNHAM:Were you able to go to school at some point later?

DUNN: Oh yes, we had a school called--a segregated school actually--called
Dunbar. Now, it was called Dubois first. So we graduated from Dubois, which was
seven miles south of Muskogee. It was called Summit, a little place called
Summit, Oklahoma. That&#039;s where I went to school. But like I said, we never did
see a segregated school--the segregated school was miles away from us, but we
never saw any white or anything--never segregated while I lived there.

DUNHAM:What was a typical day like for you, growing up, when you were a young
girl there, when you started going to school?

DUNN: It was beautiful. I was the youngest, and naturally I got all the
preferences from the family. [laughs] So it was nice. The school was--we had a
fairly good edu--but I didn&#039;t learn, they didn&#039;t treat me right on my math. I
should have gotten more math, because I never learned to add, only twos--I have
to say two times two is four, that was multiplication. For add I had to have two
numbers to add on, so I was doing pretty--but it didn&#039;t do as good as I should
have. But I could divide, do the division. And multiplication, I had that pretty good.

DUNHAM:Well, you&#039;ve certainly done well for yourself overall! So did you have
any time for fun when you were growing up?

DUNN: Oh yes, we had--but not too--when they came out with tennis--not
tennis--this thing you get on the ground and knock the holes through the little wire.

DUNHAM:Oh, croquet?

DUNN: Croquet, yeah. Yes, we had that. And at the school they had good slides
that we could slide down to learn to do that. But other than that, that was
about all that we had at that time.

DUNHAM:And what types of things did you eat growing up then, and did you learn
to cook from your mom?

DUNN: No, Mama couldn&#039;t learn to cook because she had to take care of the
family. Mama worked seven days a week, starting at five thirty in the morning.
She had to walk seven and a half miles to get to do a job at that time was
called a domestic. That&#039;s where she&#039;d go and work for a white woman. So she had
to do that. So she didn&#039;t have time to teach my sister how to cook. So I never
did fool around the kitchen.

DUNHAM:Were your grandparents able to help out then?

DUNN: No, no. They had moved to a little place we called Hall&#039;s Chapel, which
was about six miles west of us--I mean east of us, really, it was east. And then
I understand that&#039;s where my grandmother passed, and then my grandfather got
ill, so Mama had to bring him in our small house in Oklahoma, south of Muskogee.
And she took care of him until he passed away.

DUNHAM:I imagine your siblings had to help with his care too, since your mom--

DUNN: Oh yeah, my sister really, that was her job. One of my sisters, Annie Mae.
That&#039;s what Annie Mae had to do.

DUNHAM:How much older was your oldest sibling from you?

DUNN: I think my oldest sibling--was seventeen years, I think, between us.

DUNHAM:Okay, quite a bit.

DUNN: Yeah, that was Aunt Bessie.

GRANDDAUGHTER: This is 1901, right? She was born in 1901.

DUNN: Yeah, 1901, that&#039;s right.

DUNHAM:Can you describe the house you grew up in there?

DUNN: I didn&#039;t bring a photo. [laughs] I should have brought the photo of the house.

DUNHAM:Oh, you do have one?

DUNN: It&#039;s still there. So yes, it was a lovely--it was a beautiful home but it
was really peaceful. Mama didn&#039;t allow us to scuffle--you used to call them
scuffling, fooling around, and Mama wouldn&#039;t have it, because the boys were
twins and she definitely wasn&#039;t going to have that because she wouldn&#039;t be able
to control them if they got--that temper got out of control. So she brought us
through, and we always, as long as we can remember, we all--passed away with
love and affection from all of us.

DUNHAM:When you were a young girl do you remember what you wanted to be when you
grew up, if you will?

DUNN: I wanted to be a--[laughs] well, you wouldn&#039;t believe it, but I wanted to
take a--you know what the girls do now, learning to do, know how to do sports,
how to do--I can&#039;t think of what I wanted to do.

DUNHAM:To play sports or teach sports?

DUNN: Yeah, I wanted to be a sports teacher, the girl who came there--

FUKUMOTO: The PE/physical ed teacher?

DUNN: Yes, yes. But I didn&#039;t--you can see I didn&#039;t do it. [laughs] I didn&#039;t take it.

DUNHAM:Plenty else. Did you like sports growing up? Playing sports?

DUNN: Not too well. No, not too well.

DUNHAM:But you just envisioned doing that.

DUNN: But not too well.

DUNHAM:Did you go to church as a child?

DUNN: Oh Lord yeah, that&#039;s all we had to do, and we&#039;d go to school at a church.
There was no movies or anything in the little small town where we lived. We&#039;d go
to church and wake up in the mornings--on Sunday morning you went to Sunday
school from about 8:30 till 10:30. And after that you went to church. And after
church you went to what was called the NYA, National Youth Convention, for young
kids. So maybe it was from one--one from the other. And then by eight o&#039;clock at
night church service was over, you were home.

DUNHAM:The NYA, which was part of the New Deal/FDR? Oh no, that was later.

DUNN: No, no. I was saying the NYA was the--it was something in, something name
we had for Baptist people.

DUNHAM:It was another church program that afternoon.

DUNN: Yeah, it was a church program.

DUNHAM:I know you mentioned the National Youth Administration. When did that
come into your realm?

DUNN: That was in 1943.

DUNHAM:Oh, not till during the wartime.

DUNN: Yeah, after World War II started, that&#039;s when Roosevelt got this program
for us because we didn&#039;t have any jobs.

DUNHAM:So before that, when did you finish school?

DUNN: We finished school in February. I think it was February because--no, it
must have been September. But at that time we couldn&#039;t--the school was different
for white and colored. We had to work out until October before we could get
started. We didn&#039;t get to go in September. We had to go in October, a month later.

DUNHAM:Now, why was that? Because you weren&#039;t using the same facilities, right?

DUNN: [laughs] I never did find out.

DUNHAM:Did you have a shorter school year?

DUNN: No, it was all the same, only they--up in Muskogee where we went to high
school, better schools--they would go out in September, and we couldn&#039;t go until
a month later.

DUNHAM:Was it because you were working?

DUNN: Well, it probably had something to do, because when we worked out where
the people was growing the cotton, they were quite nice. The black people then,
growing cotton, we had to go out--they could send a bus in to pick us from
probably eight o&#039;clock that morning till after five o&#039;clock in the afternoon.
And then at lunch time they would give us a whole hour for lunch. So we&#039;d
get--we&#039;d mostly see lots of guys, because you had to pick a hundred pounds a
day to get whatever the salary was at that time.

DUNHAM:Not very much, I assume.

DUNN: Not very much. Now, {Abby?} could have told me that if I had thought to
ask her, because that&#039;s what was going on with her too where she was born.

DUNHAM:So were you doing that as a teenager?

DUNN: Oh, yes, yes, yes.

DUNHAM:Wow, and so you did that all through these extended summers?

DUNN: That&#039;s right, that&#039;s right.

DUNHAM:Did you do other jobs as a teenager, or was that the one?

DUNN: No, just the agriculture was all, that&#039;s all.

DUNHAM:So when you finished school in &#039;35--is that what you said?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Thirty-six.

DUNHAM:Thirty-six, sorry.

DUNN: Thirty-six.

DUNHAM:Then what did you do?

DUNN: Well, I went--in the meantime my school that was Dubois had changed and we
had lost our credentials, or whatever you call it. We couldn&#039;t--if you stayed
there, because you had to--you wouldn&#039;t get any credit for the classes or
anything. So then I could go to Muskogee and get credit, so that&#039;s when I went
to Muskogee. I didn&#039;t know how in the world I was going to get there, but Mama
helped. And Mama was always raising her garden and helping people that come, so
Mama said--well, we didn&#039;t have but one car in the neighborhood because the guy
was a World War I serviceman, and he would help you to go to get to town or
whatever you need to do.

DUNHAM:He was an African-American serviceman in World War I?

DUNN: Oh, that&#039;s right, that&#039;s right, yes. So Mama happened to remember, Mama
said, &quot;Well, I don&#039;t know how I&#039;m going to get you a place to stay,&quot; because we
were seven miles from the school where I was supposed to go, so it&#039;s called a
Manual Training--MTHS, Manual Training High School. So Mama said, &quot;Well, I don&#039;t
know how I&#039;m going to get you there because we&#039;ve only got this one car in the
neighborhood, and this man, we don&#039;t know whether he can do it or not.&quot; So Mama
happened to remember one younger woman had moved into the town, and she had two
girls that was younger than myself, and Mama used to always give her chickens
and give her eggs, or whatever. So this girl had remarried and moved to
Muskogee, and Mama happened to remember, she said, &quot;Oh I think,&quot;--I can&#039;t even
remember the girl&#039;s name right now. So anyway, Mama called, and so she said, oh
yes, that I could come and stay with her. So that&#039;s how I got to finish high
school, by going and staying with her in her home there.

DUNHAM:So what was that like?

DUNN: Oh, that was beautiful! She didn&#039;t have enough room, but she set up an
extra bed for me with the two girls, but we made it real good.

DUNHAM:And what was the Manual Training High School like? How was that?

DUNN: It was pretty good. It wasn&#039;t too much different from Dubois. But it was--

DUNHAM:Was it supposed to have technical training?

DUNN: Yes, yes.

DUNHAM:Was there something, a particular trade you were learning?

DUNN: Yes, I was learning to sew, and that was what I wanted to do. When I came
out here to Washington, at first I went to sew--to Boeing and tell them I wanted
to take sewing. At that time they was making covers for the airplanes, and he
said, &quot;No, we don&#039;t hire blacks for that.&quot; Because certain jobs we couldn&#039;t get.
There were certain jobs--

DUNHAM:So they were hiring those, but they would only hire white--

DUNN: Yeah, I didn&#039;t get it. So my sister, my second oldest sister came out, and
right away she got--they hired her. I guess they had changed deals, so she got
to work in--that was Etta. She got to work--

DUNHAM:Was that a couple years--how long after you had asked?

DUNN: Oh, I figure that must have been a year and a half, almost two years.

DUNHAM:And when did you first come out here?

DUNN: I came in &#039;43, 1943.

DUNHAM:So what happened in the years between when you went to the Manual
Training High School in Muskegee--?

DUNN: Muskogee.

DUNHAM:Muskogee, I&#039;m sorry--and &#039;43.

DUNN: Well, let me see, what did happen? [laughs]

DUNHAM:Did you find work doing sewing or something in Oklahoma?

DUNN: Oh no, there was no work there unless you went to the cotton field or something.

DUNHAM:There was no work there. So did you stay in Oklahoma all those years?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Dad happened.

DUNN: What?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Dad happened.

DUNN: Oh! Oh yes, yes, sorry.[laughs] Oh yeah, that&#039;s true. [laughs] I was so
happy I could get him here, because I didn&#039;t know what he was going to do for a
job, anything. When I got to Boeing and we got along real good, you know salary
and everything we got--so when he got to be about sixteen--I don&#039;t remember
about what age he started. And Boeing was hiring from fifteen to twenty-three, I
think, at that time. So he said, &quot;Mom,&quot; he says, &quot;I think I&#039;m going to--I think
it&#039;s time for me to look for a job.&quot; I says okay. He says, &quot;I think I&#039;ll go to
Boeing.&quot; I said, &quot;No, honey, don&#039;t go to Boeing, because Boeing doesn&#039;t treat us
right.&quot; There are certain jobs, I think, that at Boeing you couldn&#039;t get if you
was of color. Because I didn&#039;t ever get into the union until 2008. I got a
picture in there--[laughs]

DUNHAM:Long after your retirement.

DUNN: I&#039;ve got a picture with this girl right here, Jerri, that showed us how
to--she got us in there.

DUNHAM:This is the letter they sent you?

DUNN: Yeah, I&#039;ve got that too. And this is a picture where we first, when we
went there, 2008--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh, yes, yes, yes. Probably am not going to--no, of course not.
[looking at pictures and speaking with David]

DUNN: So at any rate--

GRANDDAUGHTER: I remember this.

DUNN: And that was 2008 when they sent me a letter.

DUNHAM:Two thousand eight, but you&#039;re not in this one?

DUNN: No--oh, yes I am! I&#039;m there with the cane.

GRANDDAUGHTER: No, no, she&#039;s in this one. Sorry, I was saying I was there that
day, but of course it was the people who were there.

DUNN: I&#039;m the one with the walking cane in front of me there.

DUNHAM:All right, we&#039;ll take a shot of that later. So that was in the fifties by
the time he became old enough to work then? Because he--when was your son born?

DUNN: In--where was your daddy born? [laughs]

DUNHAM:Back in Oklahoma?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Where he was born, yes. But he was born in &#039;37.

DUNHAM:Thirty-seven, okay. So that must have been challenging to have
a--[background whispering about taking a still of one of the documents] Yeah,
keep it out, and we&#039;ll--

DUNN: Yeah, he was the first grandson in the family. He was--it turned out that
her family didn&#039;t have a son, have a girl--they had girls. Mama always had all
girls. So he was the first grandson born into the different families, plus his
dad in my family.

DUNHAM:Where were you living when he was born?

DUNN: I was still living in Muskogee.

DUNHAM:With the same family?

DUNN: Yes, we had gotten married and moved to Muskogee, Oklahoma.

DUNHAM:So then you were busy raising your son, I take it, then.

DUNN: Yes, but my son and his dad--we didn&#039;t get along too good.

DUNHAM:Oh, I&#039;m sorry.

DUNN: Because my husband was a, he was a--I guess you&#039;d like to call it--I don&#039;t
how you call Mark! [laughs] He liked to keep up with the times and everything,
but like he started to smoke, which wasn&#039;t too bad. Then he started to drink
liquor, and that wasn&#039;t too bad. But then he thought he&#039;d learn to--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Gamble.

DUNN: Gamble, and that didn&#039;t work out. I couldn&#039;t do that. So we separated, and
he went to California, and I stayed on in Summit.

DUNHAM:You stayed on where, sorry, in--

DUNN: In Summit, Oklahoma. I stayed on in a little town called Summit.

DUNHAM:So how did you make do as a single mother then?

DUNN: Well, I did fine because my mother was helping me, and she wasn&#039;t the
age--she wasn&#039;t on Social Security--she wasn&#039;t at old age yet, but she worked
and raised a garden, and she raised chickens. And she had a hog that she would
kill every year and hang him up in the smokehouse and get him ready to eat.

DUNHAM:Had she come to Summit, or how far was she?

DUNN: No, no, no. I always said &quot;Lord, give me a job that I can take care of
her,&quot; because she was such a hard-working girl. And so finally when Roosevelt,
FDR opened a way they told--somebody told me. I don&#039;t know who--I didn&#039;t ever
talk to him, but somebody told me he said, &quot;If you go to,&quot;--first they said to
Wichita, Kansas. He said, &quot;We will give you a job and you can support your
mother doing this job.&quot; I said, &quot;Well, I&#039;ll do that.&quot;

So I took the job in Wichita, Kansas, and then I got there, but Boeing didn&#039;t
have any openings. And I got there, and they said, &quot;Well, no, we don&#039;t have any
openings, but if you go to Washington, you can get to go to a shipyard, Todd
Shipyard, as a welder.&quot; I said okay. So I came over to Todd and found out--I saw
that all that water out there and everything and said, &quot;Oh no, I can&#039;t go. I
can&#039;t do that.&quot; &quot;Well, if you can&#039;t do that sort of thing we can do, so you can
go back to Boeing in Washington.&quot; Now, that&#039;s all they said, in Washington, you
can go to Boeing. I says, &quot;Okay, I&#039;ll do that.&quot; So when I--because Boeing, they
set up a place that we could have as protection, a house, dormitories and stuff.
So I said, &quot;Well, I&#039;ll go back to Boeing,&quot; and I came back, that&#039;s the year I
came back to Boeing.

DUNHAM:So can I ask--so had you already been in Seattle for a while? You were in
Seattle for a while?

DUNN: No, I was in--where was I? I came to Wichita, Kansas.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I think Todd is Bremerton?

DUNN: What?

DUNHAM:Oh, Bremerton?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Is Todd Bremerton?

DUNN: Yeah, I was supposed to start to work at Todd Shipyard as an acetylene
welder, and I had to have my helmet and my--

DUNHAM:Did you do that job for a little bit?

DUNN: No, I didn&#039;t do it, period. I bought all my equipment and everything, but
I never used it.

GRANDDAUGHTER: She was saying she saw all that water.

DUNHAM:Yeah, the water. I got that. My wife is that way.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Now, Grandma, you had started telling--there&#039;s a cute story about
when they first told you where you were going, and they said Washington.

DUNN: In Washington.

GRANDDAUGHTER: You thought you were going to see the president. [laughs] So I
was wondering if you could tell that one.

DUNN: No, the person that was in charge of us when we was living in the rooming
house, as a caretaker--so we told her, we said, &quot;We don&#039;t have a job here in
Kansas. So they said we can go to Washington.&quot; Okay, so we went and told her,
and she says, &quot;Oh, I hate to lose you girls, but you&#039;re going to see the
president! You&#039;re going to see the president!&quot; [laughs] Naturally, that&#039;s what I
wanted to do, because he had done so much for us getting us out of poverty, you
know. So we went back the next day, the guy said, the instructor said, &quot;Well,
you have to find out whether your caretaker will let you guys go.&quot; So I went
back, and I told my caretaker. Her name was Mrs. Grabberly. I said, &quot;They say we
can go to Washington.&quot; And she said, &quot;Oh my God! You guys are going to see the
president! You&#039;re going to see the president!&quot; And we said yes, so we thought we
were going to see the president.

So the next day we went back and we told our instructor this, &quot;Yes, we&#039;ll go.&quot;
He says, &quot;Well, I want to show you something.&quot; He had a billboard there with the
calendars and the states and everything. And he says, &quot;Now, here&#039;s where you&#039;re
going. You&#039;re over here in Kansas, so you&#039;re going to go all the way over to
Seattle, Washington.&quot; It&#039;s something to live with six such young girls. And one
of the girls said, &quot;Oh, that&#039;s the end of the world! That&#039;s the end of the
world!&quot; So we went back, and we told Mrs. Grabberly that&#039;s what was different.
We weren&#039;t going to see the president, we was going to Seattle, Washington.&quot; So
anyway, so she let us go though, but that was so funny. We all thought we were
going to see the president. [laughs]

DUNHAM:You&#039;ve mentioned the president doing a lot to help you get out of
poverty. Aside from the eventual job you got in Seattle, were there other ways
in which the New Deal or the Youth Administration was helping your family or
others that you knew of?

DUNN: Well, they sure helped me, because his wife Eleanor, she was really 100
percent with her husband, and so they determined that something had to be done
for us as a group. So she said you know that I want you guys to go and do the
best you can. And so that&#039;s what we did. I don&#039;t know if anybody in our
group--of course I&#039;ve misplaced all of them except the girl that you like, Eva.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Eva, yeah.

DUNN: I misplaced all--that&#039;s the only one.

DUNHAM:Eva Vassar?

DUNN: I don&#039;t know what happened to the other five girls. But we was the only
two that I know that came here to Washington together. But her son got--what
happened to her son? He died. At any rate, I was going to bring a picture of him
but I didn&#039;t. He got in there, and he really did a lot to help the black people.
He would go out. They sent him out to different states to recruit black kids and
he did a beautiful job with that.

DUNHAM:This is later? Eva Vassar&#039;s son?

DUNN: Yes, Eva Vassar&#039;s son. His name was--what was that baby&#039;s name?

GRANDDAUGHTER: I don&#039;t really remember. Does it start with an R?

DUNN: His dad was Tommy, his name was T.J., T.J.--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh, you meant T.J.!

DUNN: T.J., yeah. T.J.

DUNHAM:Was he recruiting for the government or other--?

DUNN: No, for this company, the school--what was this--like where you could have
gone to school.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh, Lakeside.

DUNN: Lakeside. Yeah, you could have gone to school there, because he--but he
really helped a lot of black kids to get going.

DUNHAM:When you went to Kansas and then Bremerton and ultimately Seattle, was
your son with you through those travels?

DUNN: No, my mother had to--when we left to come out here, my sister, she had a
daughter that&#039;s three years older than my son. So I came out here and I got
hired, and then I told her to come on out and we&#039;d work together with Boeing,
because I was already working with Boeing. So she came on out. I&#039;ve got a story
about that too, but I didn&#039;t bring it. And she came on out, and then we sent
back and got Mama to bring our kids with her. So Mama gave up her house and
everything and came on out here with us.

DUNHAM:Oh, she moved? Your mom moved permanently out here too?

DUNN: Yes, yes, yes, she did. She passed away out here.

GRANDDAUGHTER: She basically brought her--many of her family, if not the whole family.

DUNN: Yeah, the whole family finally ended up out here.

DUNHAM:So what was your initial impression of the West Coast and Washington?

DUNN: Oh, I loved it. I loved the weather, and that&#039;s one reason I wanted my
mother out here, because it really would get cold in Oklahoma. But I loved the
weather out here, and I&#039;d send back and get her and get the whole family out
here because of the weather. And they all got jobs--most of my relatives, a lot
of them went to Boeing. Some of them went to--my brothers went to the shipyard,
so anyway, so it really worked out good for that. In fact, all my relatives now,
in Washington, was that group that I brought out here with me.

GRANDDAUGHTER: You were telling me that they came out here, but a few of them
went back because they didn&#039;t like the rain or something out here, I guess. Was
that right Grandmother?

DUNN: Well, they had reasons to go back.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh, okay.

DUNN: Hattie Mae was more Caucasian, my brother&#039;s wife--because she was all a
black person, but she could have passed for being a Caucasian. So that didn&#039;t
work too good with my brother.

DUNHAM:That was more of a problem here, you&#039;re saying?

DUNN: No, between them. After she got there and the people started thinking she
was Caucasian instead of with--

DUNHAM:Oh, so they separated, you&#039;re saying.

DUNN: Yeah, and then he decided he wasn&#039;t going to stay and go through all of
that, and she wanted to stay--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Yeah, but they were still together as--till they passed away, I think.

DUNN: She wanted to stay, but my brother said no. And so they went back to
Oklahoma and built them a house and all, then they got--because they saved their
money. They worked here.

DUNHAM:Was that an issue of here being more integrated, versus in Oklahoma, and
so somehow--?

DUNN: I know that could have been, but it didn&#039;t have anything to do with me.

DUNHAM:Can you tell us about your initial experiences at Boeing? How you got the
job and what your training was and your first days.

DUNN: Well, when I got here, at Boeing, there was no books and nothing telling
you about how to rivet or anything. We had--it was called a rivet instructor. He
was a man, and so he&#039;d each--take you to the tool room and show you the tool
room, and show you how to choose your things. The first thing you needed was a
rivet gun, and that was pneumatic, on air. And then take you to get an electric
motor, drill motor. You had to learn to do that, because a lot of things you had
to--if the mechanic didn&#039;t do it right you&#039;d have to get back.

And then you had to learn to read blueprints. That&#039;s one thing that you really
had to know, what a blueprint was. And so most of the girls here would go out
and take an extra blueprint training. Because they&#039;d give you a class on the
job, but we mostly had had groups where you could go out and sign up and do
that. So most of us, that&#039;s what we did. But the mechanics is the one that
really--they had to know the blueprint, how to drill, how to start the job from
scratch, and then maybe we had to--by knowing blueprints we could find out--it
should have been a hole here; it&#039;s not there. And don&#039;t rivet until you get that
hole in, because otherwise you&#039;ll have to tear everything apart and come back to
get that one rivet role that was missed. But at any rate, it was beautiful. Oh,
it was beautiful.

DUNHAM:So if the mechanic made a mistake did you have to send it back?

DUNN: Yeah, you have to show it to your instructor. Either you could take it to
the guy that--the inspector--not the inspector, the--

DUNHAM:The foreman?

GRANDDAUGHTER: The supervisor?

DUNN: No, no. The one that okayed the job, okayed the stack to let you know that
the job was okay, and it had his name and everything on there to make sure you
did it right. Oh, what did you call that guy--he was--I can&#039;t think of what his
name was.

DUNHAM:So not a foreman or inspector?

DUNN: No, it wasn&#039;t. No, he&#039;s the one that had to pass it before you
could--sign--before he could pass it he has to inspect it.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I can almost see it. Same thing.

DUNHAM:All right. And so what was the makeup of your work force? Were they a mix
of African American and white? Any other ethnicities?

DUNN: Well, they was all mixed up, but the white thing--the blacks couldn&#039;t be a
part of the union. We couldn&#039;t be a union; we could work on a permit.

DUNHAM:So what did it mean that you couldn&#039;t be part of the union? What were the
impacts of that?

DUNN: Well, the only thing is that you couldn&#039;t--well, I will tell you the
truth. Every time they got a raise, even though you wasn&#039;t in the union, they
would--you&#039;d get a raise.

DUNHAM:You did still get the raise.

DUNN: Yes.

DUNHAM:But did you not have union protections?

DUNN: No, no protection. No protection, no.

DUNHAM:Did you make the same money as your--?

DUNN: As far as I know, but I was the only A woman riveter in the plant. But
there was white mechanics, A mechanics. And what we would do, we would--they
liked to play a--bet on your check, the number of your check, and so if you was
going to win, or what would be the winner. And that was the way that I could
find out. They said that the A mechanics and the A riveters got the same pay. So
what I could do, when they want to see did I play or win the lotto, you know
where the lotto--where you put your checks together and the person who got the
highest number on your check, they would be the winner and you would collect the
money. So the only thing I could find out, because they always told me we got
the same, when the boys come to check my check, to see if it was the same amount
as they was getting. That&#039;s the way I found out that it was--so I never did find
anything wrong with that. I think we did get the same amount.

DUNHAM:I haven&#039;t heard about this lotto game with the checks, so could you--so
this was a little mini-gambling thing?

DUNN: [laughs] Yes.

DUNHAM:So how much was at stake for that?

DUNN: I very seldom played in it though.

DUNHAM:But you just--it was based on your check--not the check amount but your check--

DUNN: On your check number.

DUNHAM:Whoever had the highest--?

DUNN: Number, yes.

DUNHAM:Winner take all, for something?

DUNN: Yes, you&#039;d win.

DUNHAM:Did everybody play that?

DUNN: Yeah, they&#039;d go around and beg you to play or to be a part.

DUNHAM:But that allowed you to see that you also made the right amount.

DUNN: Made the same. Because they claimed the A mechanics and the A riveters got
the same rate of pay.

DUNHAM:Did you work your way up to A riveter?

DUNN: Oh yes, oh yes, yes. Sure did.

DUNHAM:Do you remember what your starting salary was?

DUNN: My starting salary was fifty-two and a half cents an hour.

DUNHAM:That was day shift?

DUNN: That was day shift. Yeah--well, on second shift you get ten cents more on
the hour.

DUNHAM:Did you stay on day shift?

DUNN: Oh, well you couldn&#039;t. You had to trade off. If somebody, like a family
man, had a family or something, if he wanted to be at home with his kids or
something, then he&#039;d want a day shift, and then maybe I&#039;d have to go to second
shift. But I didn&#039;t mind it because I was getting ten cents extra!

DUNHAM:You get more money, okay. And this is before your sons come out west.

DUNN: Oh yes, oh yes, yes.

DUNHAM:What year did he come, your mom and all, and he come out? Or maybe there
were different times?

DUNN: Nineteen--what time was that, Jerri?

GRANDDAUGHTER: I&#039;m trying to think--1945 or 1946?

DUNN: Yeah, but he would probably tell us on this.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I think he came out when he was six.

DUNHAM:After the war was over?

DUNN: I&#039;m sure he told us in here.

DUNHAM:Oh, is that a little bio of his?

DUNN: Yes, his, yes, he says--

GRANDDAUGHTER: According to what he says six, but that would put him right when
you came out here. Did he come the same year Grandmother?

DUNN: Yeah, he came the same year, but that&#039;s after Mama brought him out here,
you know. That must have been &#039;40.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Because you said &#039;43 was when you started. I just counted up and
&#039;43 would have--he said he was six when he came out?

DUNHAM:Yeah, well maybe Candice could--

DUNN: He said he was five--I say five, he said he was six, I say he was five.

GRANDDAUGHTER: But that&#039;s about right. Six is 1943.

DUNHAM:So pretty soon after you came out, and then your mom was able to take
care of him? Or was he going to school?

DUNN: Yeah, Mother came, my mother came out and--

DUNHAM:Was there any childcare, or was that not--?

DUNN: No, there was nothing here. We lived next door at Duwamish Bend. That was
just, a project just opened up, Duwamish Bend for poor people and everything.

DUNHAM:Could we take a look in here? Could we--oh, sorry.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I wonder who made that up now, who made this up--and I
wrote--there&#039;s one thing I started in there that&#039;s wrong. I still don&#039;t know
quite know what it&#039;s called, but working with the cotton is apparently not the
sharecropper. And I don&#039;t know what you--Grandmother, what did you call it when
you were working with the cotton? Because Dad got upset that I called it
sharecropping, and I just didn&#039;t--

DUNN: I think the woman wrote that up. She says sharecropping, and Mama never
did do sharecropping.

GRANDDAUGHTER: That was me. I&#039;m pretty sure I got chewed out for putting that in
there, and I&#039;m really embarrassed now. I just thought that&#039;s what that was called.

DUNN: That was okay. No, we didn&#039;t get--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Was it just picking cotton, or was there a name for it?

DUNHAM:Because you were just day laborers?

DUNN: That was doing practically--mostly the men, because the men had to do all
the plowing, and you don&#039;t do that, weaving the cotton. The women could come out
there and chop the cotton, get all the grass out and everything, and got the
cotton ready to grow up.

GRANDDAUGHTER: See, I didn&#039;t understand that when I put--somebody asked me what
they did, and I don&#039;t know; I kind of thought that&#039;s--

DUNN: That girl, that girl told you to put that in there. What was her name?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh Lady--we called her Lady Di. Now I remember it. She&#039;s the one
who made this up, somebody I was getting my hair done by, her mother, and she
worked with this kind of stuff. So yeah, she asked me, and I had this idea in
mind that it was all the same thing, Grandmother. That working the cotton was--I
didn&#039;t know about the plowing and the--

DUNN: Yeah, no, a sharecropper, what they would do, they&#039;d work those guys and
they&#039;d do all the farming and everything. And most of the men wouldn&#039;t take
a--wouldn&#039;t write nothing down to show that they were working. Or maybe they&#039;d
go to the grocery store some, and they wouldn&#039;t even ask for a receipt. And
they&#039;d come back, and then at the end of the year they wouldn&#039;t get any credit
for all that work they had done, and the guy--a lot of people, a lot of black
men lost their living by fooling around with those type of people, the
sharecroppers. So anyway, no, so it didn&#039;t work out.

[sounds of paper rustling] I think I&#039;ve shown this before, my--

DUNHAM:Yeah, the calendar, your calendar. Yeah, it&#039;s great.

DUNN: I think--the calendar, yes.

DUNHAM:When you first got to Seattle you were talking about where you lived.
It&#039;s kind of like a barracks, or something, with a guard? What was that? Katie
Burks was describing, when she first came, something along those lines. Where
did you first live when you got to Seattle?

DUNN: In the dormitory. Boeing had a dormitory.

DUNHAM:Were they guarded?

DUNN: I don&#039;t remember, to tell you the truth. I don&#039;t remember.

DUNHAM:She also talked about going with chaperones to USO--did you do any of
that type of thing?

DUNN: Very little, because I had my son to take care of, you know, and everything.

DUNHAM:So did you stay at the dormitories very long?

DUNN: No, that&#039;s when the Duwamish Bend projects opened up, and then we could
get a place there. But I made a mistake--

DUNHAM:What was it called?

DUNN: I made a mistake, I did not--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Duwamish Bend.

DUNN: It was a project, a government project.

GRANDDAUGHTER: And this was real close to where Boeing was. It was almost the
neighborhood they call Georgetown. It&#039;s pretty much in that area.

DUNHAM:Was it a segregated area?

DUNN: I didn&#039;t ever work there, but there was a--they called it--the Red Barn
was across the street from there. That was the Red Barn.

GRANDDAUGHTER: He&#039;s asking if it was segregated.

DUNHAM:I asked you if the neighborhood you moved to was segregated.

GRANDDAUGHTER: It was primarily black. She said poor, but--were there some white
people living there, Grandmother?

DUNN: Oh yeah. We was all poor enough to be in there. The only difference, the
only difference was maybe a little kid, about the same age as my son. And every
time my son--we lived on one row of the houses, and he lived across the street
over there. He was about the same age as my son, but every time my son would go
out to play he&#039;d come out there and he&#039;d try to beat up on my son. And my son
wouldn&#039;t do anything. I&#039;d say, &quot;Well, why didn&#039;t you hit him back?&quot; &quot;I didn&#039;t
want to hurt him.&quot; I said, &quot;Well, he hurt you. You hit him back.&quot; So one day my
little niece, she was about two years older than Benjy, Tiny--so I said, &quot;Tiny,
when this guy come out,&quot; I said, &quot;Ben go out to play.&quot; I said, &quot;You don&#039;t say a
word. You just walk out and let Ben know that you&#039;re there.&quot; Because this guy
would always tell him, &quot;We&#039;re rich, we&#039;re rich.&quot; But the only difference, his
dad worked for Boeing, but this guy was in--he could always wear a white shirt,
and he could always dress up. And so Ben said, &quot;Mom, are we rich?&quot; I said, &quot;No,
we&#039;re not rich, but we&#039;re not exactly poor either.&quot; And I&#039;d hear Ben telling
people, &quot;We&#039;re not rich, but we&#039;re not exactly poor.&quot; So at any rate, so this
time the guy came out, and Ben was out there. He came over there, and he started
hitting on Ben. So they look and saw that his cousin was there, so boy, when he
saw Tiny was there boy, he went into that guy and just beat him up. So that was
the last of that. That guy never did bother him anymore.

DUNHAM:You mentioned that growing up you didn&#039;t encounter white people at all.
So what were your first experiences with white people?

DUNN: Never noticed a difference, I didn&#039;t. I knew I was there to make a living,
that&#039;s why I came out, and I wasn&#039;t going to let no color, nothing, keep me from
working. So no, but people, in my group, they was really good. It was absolutely
no problem, because they--by not being a member of the union, and Boeing went on
strike in 1948, not--but the union. And I was out for six months. By this time I
had remarried--Clarence Dunn. Anyway, but Clarence was just out of the Army
himself, and he got along real good with the supervisors and everything. But the
minute Clarence got there he wanted a car. &quot;We&#039;re going to get a car; we&#039;re
going to get a car.&quot; I says okay. So I didn&#039;t mind helping him, because he would
really share his money, anything that he had with me and the baby. So I says
okay. So we started pooling our money together. Clarence went to Boeing also.

DUNHAM:This is your second husband?

DUNN: Yeah, my second husband. Then when Ben went to Boeing--I mean when he was
talking about getting a job, he said, &quot;Mom, so I think that Boeing&#039;s just done
really good to us. I think I&#039;ll go and apply for a job.&quot; And I said, &quot;No, Baby.
I don&#039;t want you to do that. That&#039;s because Boeing is really not any friends of
us. I&#039;d rather you do a government job, something like that.&quot; So that&#039;s when he
went into the IRS, and that&#039;s when he went to--

DUNHAM:So he took your advice. You mentioned the strike in &#039;48. Can you tell us
about the strike in &#039;48?

DUNN: There wasn&#039;t much for me to talk about it, because I&#039;d tell them no. They
wanted me to sign up. I said, &quot;No, I can&#039;t do that, because you say I&#039;m not a
member, and I&#039;d have to work on a permit, so I can&#039;t do that.&quot; Then they tried
to talk me down, and I wouldn&#039;t change. So then they called me a--

 DUNHAM:Scab?

DUNN: Scab, yes. [laughs] But most of the guys, even the guys, they said, &quot;Well,
I don&#039;t blame you. We don&#039;t blame you for not coming into the union.&quot; So I
thought, no, I couldn&#039;t do it.

DUNHAM:So that was the first time they were actually truly inviting you, is when
it served their purposes?

DUNN: That&#039;s right, that&#039;s right. So I told them no, I couldn&#039;t do it. So at any
rate--then they tried to--they called me a scab and everything, to make the
other people think that I wasn&#039;t doing them right, which I knew wasn&#039;t true.

DUNHAM:Did you face any backlash beyond that then?

DUNN: No, not really. The only thing--later on when the supervisors started
watching the payment on your check, you know how much the amount was. I just
started working all overtime and everything, and they would start looking at my
check and how much money I&#039;d make. Because I&#039;d work every time--working
overtime, sometimes I was working five days, seven days a week, plus on regular
time, time on overtime you got time and a half. On the graveyard shift you got
the full--{three?} work. And then I started doing all that, and my checks
started getting pretty big. So the supervisor, well, he never did respect the
women. No way. All these women wasn&#039;t--they upset him.

It didn&#039;t happen till he--at that time, the women--you couldn&#039;t be a husband and
wife deal. They wouldn&#039;t let you work together like that. So somehow or another
his wife came out there, and he hired her to work for him up there with me. But
she didn&#039;t know how to rivet, so I had to teach her how to rivet, you know. So
naturally we&#039;d talk, and she would tell me things about him and the way he was
treating her and everything. And this guy, the supervisor, was afraid that I was
getting too much information on him. Because I would never talk about anything.
That&#039;s why he really wanted to get rid of me, because he figured I would
know--because see, they married, they got an extra child while she was working
with me, and she&#039;d tell me all about what was going on with them and the way of
taking care of the kids and all. So he knew I knew a little bit too much.
[laughs] He figured I--I guess that she would tell him what we had talked about.
So he really didn&#039;t--he really wanted to get rid of me.

And so when we&#039;d go to meetings, the shop meetings, about three or four times a
month. And when I&#039;d get there, he said, &quot;Well, we&#039;re going to start with
seniority.&quot; And nobody in my area had as much seniority as I did. And he said,
&quot;We&#039;re going to start with seniority.&quot; Then he says, &quot;When it comes to vacation,
who wants to be first?&quot; I wouldn&#039;t say anything, because I knew I needed more
than a month to go from Oklahoma to--because my husband was going to try to
drive instead of taking the plane because he wouldn&#039;t take a plane, and he
wouldn&#039;t take a train. He came out on the train, and he said he was sitting in
there and he could look and see the engine and the caboose, and it was such
a--he wouldn&#039;t take a train for nothing. Then we got a car. He was the first one
that got a Buick car in 1948, and we got a Buick car. And then he would drive
all the time. But he said it would take us about a whole month to go and come
and have any time to spend with my mother. So then--so he got the car.

DUNHAM:What was the outcome with Fred, your supervisor that was trying to get
rid of you?

DUNN: Because he just didn&#039;t want me to make--when you look at the check and see
how much, see how much my check was.

DUNHAM:But he didn&#039;t have a way to get rid of you.

DUNN: No, he couldn&#039;t. And I asked the other supervisor if there&#039;s work to be
done, overtime and something, they&#039;d come--you&#039;d see them coming with this thing
in their pocket to write the names of people that was going to work overtime.
And I didn&#039;t have to worry, because I knew they were going to come to ask me to
work. So the stopped asking me to work overtime, and he says why he did that
because they have these young boys that just started a family, and they needed
the overtime. So I went with that. So then when he said that, I knew I had
supervisors, that I could go to them and get overtime. And so one day I came in,
and he hadn&#039;t asked me to work overtime. So I came in there and--with my toolbox
and everything--and he said, &quot;Oh, I didn&#039;t know you were here.&quot; I said, &quot;No, I&#039;m
sure you didn&#039;t.&quot; Because I&#039;d just--. So then he went and told the supervisors
to ask him first if I could work overtime, because he probably needed me on the
job. But see, we knew that wasn&#039;t true. So at any rate, I think I left that
rascal there when I retired. I can&#039;t remember his name anymore. But he
definitely didn&#039;t want me to make that extra-time money.

DUNHAM:Can you tell us about the end of the war? Do you remember V-E Day and V-J
Day and where you were then?

DUNN: Yes, I was at Renton, working at the Renton Plant 304, something like
that. So we heard about--the president had died, the owner of the Boeing plant
had died, Mr. Boeing himself. So they gave us a few seconds, maybe less than a
minute, to respect the fact that he&#039;d gone--his son just died a year or so ago.
I remember, but I don&#039;t think I wrote it down. But at any rate, but so, yeah,
but we got to go out there, and all of us went out together in our different
areas and we waited for the ceremony and everything. So it worked out okay. So
then when it came to opening up the 747 and Renton got picked--one of those
pictures may be there somewhere. Yeah, we went out there, and this was done in
final assembly on the B-17s. We went out there and we all met, and they
congratulated us and everything. So that was really a beautiful site to see,
I&#039;ll tell you. It was really beautiful.

DUNHAM:At the end of the war a lot of people were laid off, right? Were you able
to continue working?

DUNN: I worked right straight on through.

DUNHAM:How were you able to? Do you know? Was that seniority?

DUNN: Because I had supervisors that appreciated my work. I know one name is
Richard Sherman. I often wonder what happened to Richard Sherman. We called him
Slim. I don&#039;t know what happened to Slim. And I had other supervisors too, that
liked my work and everything. So I know if this guy didn&#039;t want me to work for
him I knew I could go to other supervisors, that I would have no problem getting
a job.

DUNHAM:Since a lot of people did lose their jobs do you know was there any complaining?

DUNN: I don&#039;t really know. To tell you the truth, I don&#039;t really--right now I
wonder where did these people go that we used to work together. Like you talk
about the Rosies. I don&#039;t remember when--well, one girl, I know she fell off,
when they started putting wooden boards to separate the planks so you could get
in there and work below and everything. So she told me she fell, she fell and
hurt herself. I didn&#039;t know that. I didn&#039;t even know what had happened.

DUNHAM:Did you know of any other injuries? What was health care--or did they
have facilities on site to deal with injuries?

DUNN: Not that I know of. But I know if you had a headache or anything, you
could go to the dispensary. They&#039;d have a little cot there if you needed to
rest, or give you an aspirin or something. If you needed a way home, if you
didn&#039;t have a way home, Boeing would see that you got home. I never had anything
to argue about Boeing, because what they let the union do. They couldn&#039;t say
that they didn&#039;t know that that was discrimination, because it showed you on the
paychecks, you know? Whoever made the finance, he should have known that an A
riveter and mechanic was getting different pay. So that&#039;s why I thought about
Boeing, and really said they knew more of what was going on than they said.

DUNHAM:So there was discrimination in the pay?

DUNN: No, not that I could see.

DUNHAM:So in what regard were you saying there was discrimination?

DUNN: I mean when a mechanic and I would put our checks together, well there was
always the same, only maybe I had worked more hours than they did. And that&#039;s
what the amount on the check showed up, but the pay, the rate of pay was the
same as far as I could see. I never did see anything with there being
discriminated against there.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Were you thinking about the union discrimination?

DUNN: Yeah, the union. That&#039;s why I said I know Boeing had to know. The finance
guy had to know when he made those checks out, that you&#039;re supposed to be an A
riveter /A mechanic--he should have known. I know he knew what the difference
was, but Boeing never did say anything about it or know anything about it.

DUNHAM:Were there other challenges between men and women or between the races,
especially early on? Maybe you didn&#039;t experience first hand but that you
observed or heard about, of just tensions?

DUNN: No, because the women I worked--especially the older women, it was all
white women. There was no black women in there--and no black men either.

DUNHAM:But were there white men in your group?

DUNN: Oh Lord, yes! There was two older men when I first went there that gave me
something to take--one of them was named Merv. Merv was a beautiful person. But
another guy, I don&#039;t even remember his name, but he didn&#039;t like black people.
And he&#039;d always call us scabs and everything. But Merv, he was--if Merv knew I
had a plant or something that I liked, that he would tell me about, he&#039;d bring
me a plant and leave it outside at the gate for when I came out. I could just
show him what I had to bring, and he would--but he was a beautiful person. But
he knew that this other guy didn&#039;t like black people.

DUNHAM:So the other white racist guy, did he do things worse than name-calling?

DUNN: Well, I don&#039;t ever remember him calling me any names, but he just--I had
to do riveting for him but he never would be friendly or anything. So I don&#039;t
know. I don&#039;t even remember his name. But so far as the women, the white
women--they was right in there 100 percent.

DUNHAM:Were they mostly local, or were they from the South or all over?

DUNN: I don&#039;t remember where they were from. I know they lived in Auburn or
around Kent or some places like that, where they came from.

DUNHAM:And did you know, during the war years, any Japanese American, or Italian
or German Americans?

DUNN: Yes, one thing about there--when you went, there were so many dwarfs,
little people. Oh my God, I&#039;ll tell you; it was just really crowded. One guy
said he used to see them coming there, that worked at Boeing. He&#039;s passed on
now. He worked there too, but he said he used to see them coming in truckloads.

DUNHAM:Was that because they couldn&#039;t be in the military?

DUNN: I have no idea, I just--

DUNHAM:And/or they were especially suited to work there?

DUNN: I just missed them in the company, and I was wondering what happened. The
only short man was left, he was working in the bar room, where you&#039;d have the
bucking bars to--and we called him Shorty. I don&#039;t even know what Shorty&#039;s name
was. But Shorty, he definitely didn&#039;t like black people. We&#039;d go there, and then
when the whistle would sound, the boy would want you on your job. You had these
iron tables, and he&#039;d want you to make a noise which let you know that you was
ready to go to work. But this guy, if you had to have a bar or something, he
would hold you there, fooling around, until after the whistle sounds, because
that&#039;s going to make you late getting back to your area.

DUNHAM:Oh, in trouble.

DUNN: Oh Lord, he was--

DUNHAM:Did he do that to everybody? Or just to--?

DUNN: To mostly black people.

DUNHAM:And was there any way of complaining or letting a superior know about
something like that?

DUNN: Well yeah, I told my supervisor, but--so he said, I said, &quot;What I&#039;m going
to start doing instead of turning my tools in that I need, I&#039;m going to hold
them out until after the whistle sounds and let you know that I&#039;m really here on
the job.&quot; And then I&#039;d take and make a lot of noise with my buck and my rivet
gun on the table [making machinery sounds], you know, and they&#039;d hear all that
noise. But he was something else. But he definitely would try and get you in
trouble by being late. But he was being paid an hour earlier to be there, so if
we were there early we could come on and get our tools, but he&#039;d do something to
keep you from being, from making you be on time. So at any rate, they had a lot
of trouble about that, but I don&#039;t think they ever solved it. And the way I
solved it is holding my tools out that night, the evening before the morning.
And then when I&#039;d get to work that morning, shoot, I just take my tools out of
my toolbox and go to work. And he--

GRANDDAUGHTER: I was thinking, Grandmother, one thing you told me about the
dwarfs, the short people, where they were useful--I&#039;m trying to remember if it
was the wing or the tail section or something like that. That&#039;s where--because
most everybody else couldn&#039;t get in there. It was too tight quarters.

DUNN: That was downstairs in final assembly, 303, where they made the wing
section. And boy, until you get in there, that you couldn&#039;t--they had to send an
extension light in there for you to see, and half the time you couldn&#039;t half see
where the rivet is going, where you&#039;re supposed to put the bucking bar and all
of that, you know. I did it once, but I said, &quot;God, if you let me get out of
here alive I will never do that again.&quot; [laughs] I couldn&#039;t handle it. So of
course I knew I had no trouble, because the supervisor--I could ask any of my
supervisors. They would want me to come and work for them, especially that Slim,
that Slim we called Richard Sherman. He was--oh, I could do no wrong with
Richard Sherman.

DUNHAM:You mentioned the Rosie-the-Riveter types. Did you identify then or now
as a Rosie the Riveter? Or did you feel that that was a separate--the white
women, if you will.

DUNN: No, well, but by us being the same complexion, we&#039;d always stick together.
But I just don&#039;t know when they left, when they all left. Because I know I can
remember the girls that really ended up with me. Well, we didn&#039;t really, really
work together when they left as the Rosies. Katie and her sister and all--I knew
they were there, but I don&#039;t know when we got separated. You could easily do
that by going to a different area. They sent me in--and maybe I&#039;m in Area Four
on the same balcony, Area Four, and they might have been in Area Five or
somebody like that, or a different supervisor.

DUNHAM:Did you come out at the same time as Katie and her sister, the group of six?

DUNN: No, I don&#039;t--

DUNHAM:No, it was a different group.

DUNN: I don&#039;t know. I came out in &#039;81, but I never heard Katie&#039;s--

DUNHAM:No, I meant when you first came on the train out--

DUNN: No, it wasn&#039;t Katie--Eva, and the two other girls was really too young.
They shouldn&#039;t have been hired.

DUNHAM:Were they able to be hired even though they were too young?

DUNN: Yes, yes, but I don&#039;t know what happened to those girls.

DUNHAM:Did you have a sense of patriotism while doing this work? I know it was a
great opportunity to be able to help with your family and son and all, but how
did you feel in regard to that?

DUNN: Oh, that was beautiful, because I had already prayed for the Good Lord to
give me a job that I could do something for my mother, get her out of some
poverty. And it was beautiful. I really enjoyed what happened to my family, yes, indeed.

DUNHAM:I&#039;ve heard that aside from some of the challenges and with the union that
there were other de facto segregation or Jim Crow segregation around Seattle at
that time still. Did you encounter that?

DUNN: The only thing I knew was about the--all I know, we all went to the same
church or something like that. But other than that, I can&#039;t think of anything
that being--well, the department stores, that was different. You didn&#039;t get a
job, being a black person, in the department stores and in the cafeterias and
places like that. You didn&#039;t eat--

DUNHAM:Couldn&#039;t get a job. What about as a consumer? Were there places that you
felt you couldn&#039;t go or knew not to go?

DUNN: Well, yes, there especially at the--as I&#039;ve said, the department stores.
You didn&#039;t have to wonder, because they&#039;ve got a sign. White Only or No Colored.
They had all those signs was out all over.

DUNHAM:To even go into the stores?

DUNN: To go in, yes indeed. If you went--and you couldn&#039;t try on clothes and
nothing. You couldn&#039;t do that in the department stores, and you couldn&#039;t work in
the grocery stores, nothing like that. They&#039;d take your money, but you--you
know, but--[laughs]

DUNHAM:So over time, do you know, were there specific movements to try to change
that, or do you know how long it took before those things changed?

DUNN: No, I really don&#039;t. Well, I know--I start not spending with them. I knew
where to spend my money, and I wasn&#039;t going to spend much money, at any rate,
because they always called me a miser, a miser you know! [laughs] But no, it
really was different.

DUNHAM:And what about housingwise, if you moved. I don&#039;t know how many places
you&#039;ve lived, but I&#039;ve heard that it could be very challenging for African
Americans to rent or buy.

DUNN: When I lived in Duwamish Bend they had just started this new project for
low-income people and black people. So then--well, they told us when we went
there we could only stay so long, because the place was going to be torn down.
And so we had to start looking for a place to--but there was no places that they
wanted black people. They wanted your money, but they didn&#039;t want to hire you,
give you a place to live. So then I started looking for a place to buy, and my
husband was a veteran, Mr. Dunn. He was a veteran, he says, &quot;Well, so we can use
my federal deal.&quot;

DUNHAM:Use the GI Bill?

DUNN: The GI Bill. But we never did, because everywhere we went you couldn&#039;t get
a place. So we finally, he&#039;d take me way out to Auburn and places like that. He
says, &quot;This one, this one, do you want to do--.&quot; And I said, &quot;No, because I
don&#039;t want to be out here, because you&#039;ll be driving your car in town, and me
and the baby would be out here stuck somewhere and can&#039;t get--,&quot; because they
don&#039;t like us out here in the first place. So no, I wouldn&#039;t accept that. So no,
he never did use {________?} for housing. No, we didn&#039;t have to do that.

DUNHAM:Were you able to buy?

DUNN: Oh yes. We all put our money together. He put his money there; Ben, my
son, put his money there; and I put my money there. And we all worked as a
group. It wasn&#039;t this is mine, this is yours. So we all--that son of mine he was
something else! [laughs] He was something else, at any rate. And he still treats
me the same way now. That boy is something else, I tell you.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Hey Grandmother, I was going to ask so how did you get to the
Central District? I heard there was only two places to live. I don&#039;t know if
this is the same time, but Duwamish Bend or the Central District, was the only
place they would let black people live. Is that how you guys ended up in the
Central District?

DUNN: Well, no. The way I ended up in the Central District, I knew time was
running out, that they was going to do away with Duwamish Bend project. So I
went and told them, well, it must be time for me to leave now, to find a place.
I had never paid any attention to her, because I just stayed there on Fourth
Avenue South, where the project was. And she&#039;s saying to me, &quot;Well, one
thing--why don&#039;t you go to Twenty-Second and East Union? You&#039;ll find some places there.&quot;

I didn&#039;t know where that was, so I took the bus. So I said the first colored
person I see I&#039;m going to ask them about a place. So I saw a young girl on the
street and I asked her and she says, &quot;Well, I don&#039;t know, Sister, but I&#039;m living
and a woman&#039;s got an extra--they&#039;ve got two bedrooms, and if you don&#039;t mind we
can share the one bedroom together.&quot; I said, &quot;Well, okay.&quot; She says, &quot;Well, now
you go, but don&#039;t tell her I told you.&quot; I said okay. So I went and knocked on
the door and the woman came and I told her I was looking for a place to stay.
And she said, &quot;Well, I&#039;ve got an extra bedroom. Not extras, but I&#039;ve got a girl
living in there. If you guys don&#039;t mind sharing the same bedroom, you can stay.&quot;
So I sat there a while and pretty soon the doorbell rang, and I figured it was
this girl that I had talked to down the street on Madison. So she came in, and
she introduced herself and everything. And the woman said, &quot;She&#039;s looking for a
place to stay. See, but I told her I&#039;ve got the two bedrooms, one empty. So if
you guys want to take, she won&#039;t mind sharing.&quot; I say, &quot;Well, that&#039;s okay.&quot;
Because I didn&#039;t know anyplace else to go, at any rate.

So we lived together for a while, but I don&#039;t know what this girl did. She
didn&#039;t work at Boeing, but her name was Virginia somebody. But we stayed there,
and then about that time the project opened up, so I moved out. I stayed there
about two months, and by then the project opened up, and then I went and signed
up for the project, which was Duwamish Bend project, and that&#039;s where I stayed.

DUNHAM:Until sometime after the war when they--or how long after the war was it
kept open?

DUNN: I stayed there until &#039;53, till &#039;53.

DUNHAM:With your husband and son?

DUNN: Yes.

DUNHAM:And from there--?

DUNN: We tried to find places to buy, and one woman was working for the
government in housing, so I called and asked--somebody, a guy who&#039;s working at
Boeing had told me a place out there on the South End, and I was asking. She
says, &quot;You don&#039;t want to be out there. That&#039;s where the darkies live.&quot; [laughs]
And I didn&#039;t say a word. I should have turned her in to the housing project,
because she was working on a government job.

DUNHAM:Was she white?

DUNN: Oh yes, she was white. I know she was white, because she wouldn&#039;t have
said that, you know.

DUNHAM:Were there any African-American realtors?

DUNN: Oh yeah, there was quite a few, but the Central Area was built up mostly
of Germans and these other people. I can&#039;t think of who they were. But at any
rate, we got a house in the Central Area; it changed to Central Area, because
most of the black, just black people lived in that, because a lot of people was
Jewish, and I think they were moving out as fast as they could when we started
moving in. But it worked out okay.

DUNHAM:Has that neighborhood changed over the years?

DUNN: Oh yes, it&#039;s mostly white now. They&#039;ve all--just about every place you see
that used to be black, white people live there now. So, anyhow.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I think around 14 percent of the black people are left, as far as
owning homes, Tom told me it was down to 14 percent.

DUNN: I&#039;m sure that&#039;s true, because the banks wouldn&#039;t--

DUNHAM:And that&#039;s where you still are?

GRANDDAUGHTER: Yeah, that&#039;s where my grandmother is still living.

DUNN: The banks wouldn&#039;t let you. They red-lined us, wouldn&#039;t let us have a loan
or nothing. We didn&#039;t have to depend on them, you know.

DUNHAM:So you didn&#039;t need a loan? You were able to pool your money together and
buy it outright?

DUNN: We didn&#039;t need a loan.

DUNHAM:But that was the only way. Well, I know you talked about the one trip,
you&#039;d have to get a month off to go back to Oklahoma. Did you visit Oklahoma
much, and what was it like when you returned there?

DUNN: No, I tried to go once a year--once every two years. And Clarence--he
loved to drive, the old man. Clarence loved to drive, that&#039;s the only way we
were going to get there. He had to drive. He wasn&#039;t going to take an airplane,
because he knew that&#039;s where my money was coming from.

DUNHAM:What was it like when you visited Oklahoma then? Did you ever think about returning?

DUNN: Oh Lord, no! [laughs] Plus I&#039;ve got Mother and my family out here.

DUNHAM:You had some family still there, yeah?

DUNN: I&#039;ve got--yes, I&#039;ve got in-laws--no, I&#039;ve got who&#039;s that child--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Norman?

DUNN: Norman&#039;s niece. Yeah, my brother--that&#039;s Hattie Mae&#039;s daughter. Yeah,
that&#039;s her. And then I&#039;ve got some Maloneses, my family of Malones is still
there, my mother&#039;s grandmother&#039;s people. But other than that, no, Lord.

DUNHAM:I don&#039;t want to take up too much more of your time, but I was curious;
you said Clarence served in the military?

DUNN: Yes.

DUNHAM:What branch of the military? Do you know what he did?

DUNN: Army.

DUNHAM:Do you know where he served?

DUNN: He was overseas--I don&#039;t know right now, but anyway, Beth&#039;s got all that information.

GRANDDAUGHTER: I used to think he drove for General Patton. I thought that&#039;s
where the--

DUNN: Oh yes, it was Patton. Yes, he was doing Patton&#039;s--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Dad said that was wrong. That&#039;s all I know.

DUNHAM:Was he in a segregated unit?

DUNN: Oh Lord, yes. You should hear him talk about some of that.

DUNHAM:Did you hear about the Port Chicago explosion down in California in 1944?

DUNN: Yes.

DUNHAM:You heard about it at the time?

DUNN: No, no.

DUNHAM:Not till years later, okay.

DUNN: I knew in Tulsa, Oklahoma, because they had a race riot there in around
1921 or something like that. It was a big race riot there. The blacks had always
bought a lot of land and everything in Tulsa, and they had a big race riot
there. And a lot of--more of the black got killed than whites in Oklahoma. But
in Muskogee I never heard of anything. If they did, they kept it on the quiet,
what was going on.

DUNHAM:Is there anything else we haven&#039;t asked you about today that you&#039;d like
to share with us?

GRANDDAUGHTER: I&#039;m thinking about the left-handed screwdriver. [laughs] I always
think about that particular thing.

DUNHAM:What&#039;s the left-handed screwdriver?

DUNN: Oh, the guy that was helping me or was teaching me--he wasn&#039;t teaching me,
but anything--the women would tell us and tell you about what those white guys
would try and pull on you. &quot;So now you be careful. When you go up there they&#039;re
going to tell you to go get him a left-handed screwdriver,&quot;--or left--. Anything
you use a left hand for. I went up there, but she had warned me, and I knew not
to go up there and ask for--but see what they&#039;d tell you, &quot;Go up there--.&quot; Most
of the tools are right-handed, you know, and they&#039;d tell you to go up there and
ask for a left-handed screwdriver or something, or a left-handed pair of pliers
or something, you know. But she had me knowing about all that before I made a
fool of myself.

DUNHAM:Who was that that let you know?

DUNN: That&#039;s a friend of a white woman that worked there. Boy, she really helped
me, like when my mother would get ill I&#039;d have to use my vacation or something
to take care of my mother because she wasn&#039;t feeling that well. That morning I
wouldn&#039;t leave her, and I&#039;d call and tell them I wouldn&#039;t be in. But she&#039;d say,
&quot;Now, they didn&#039;t tell you about you could get care that can help, people to
come and spell for you that day and take care of your mother.&quot;

DUNHAM:Oh, Boeing would provide that?

DUNN: Boeing--no, the legal stuff--the government. So she&#039;s the one that told me
that. I didn&#039;t know. Nobody would--Boeing didn&#039;t tell me. Nobody told me but her.

DUNHAM:Did you utilize that service?

DUNN: Oh, did I ever! Yes, because I already had plenty vacation and plenty
stuff that I can use, working a lot of overtime you know, you get paid for that.
So no, I always had enough to do it. So if Mama didn&#039;t feel good that morning
I&#039;d say, &quot;No, I&#039;ll stay here with you.&quot; Or if she was ill the night before, so I
knew I wasn&#039;t going to go to work the next day. So it really worked out. She
really helped me to do a lot of things that I didn&#039;t know about, that have been
beneficial to me.

DUNHAM:How did your mom adjust to Seattle?

DUNN: Oh, Mama loved it. Mama said, when she got here, that she didn&#039;t know that
you could have ice cream any day you wanted and as much as you wanted. [laughs]
And pies and things--she thought, oh, that was for holidays. But Mama said she
found out she could have that every day of the week if you wanted it! [laughs]
Oh, Mama loved it, Mama really loved it.

DUNHAM:How fortunate that you were able to bring her here. Yeah, go ahead.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Do we have time for one more--my dad wanted me to slip this one--.

DUNHAM:Oh please! I have time. I just don&#039;t want to wear you guys out.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Bandanas, the Rosie-the-Riveter bandanas. Something about the bandanas.

DUNN: Oh yeah, they started--oh, here&#039;s one. It was supposed to have been on
sale, but we could never find this card. They never did print it out, and see
the women wearing their bandanas? So they came and made us use--going with the
hair free you know, hair and everything, and a motor, an electric motor, you&#039;d
put a drill in, and it started to catch your hair and you&#039;d snatch it out. So
they came and told us all we had to wear the bandana. So a lot of colored
girls--we don&#039;t need no bandana, because we don&#039;t get hair, long hair. I said,
&quot;Well, don&#039;t be no fool, because can get--you put a long drill in that motor,
because you can&#039;t do it.&quot; So they finally agreed with me, so we went to the
bandana like the white girls did, like all the girls did, had to wear a bandana.
And they started, you know, this year, they have come back some material, the
same material. And they made us bandanas--well, not bandanas, made us more like
scarves. I&#039;m going to see if I can find some material and make me a bandana. But
these are just like a scarf you put on your head. But those black girls really
did! They did, but we didn&#039;t need a bandana. [laughs]

DUNHAM:Do you remember seeing the Rosie-the-Riveter campaigns and information
during the war years?

DUNN: No, to tell you the truth I didn&#039;t know about this until 2000--from a girl
that works with the--she told me last month that she had retired. Her name is
Sherry, Sherry--do you remember Sherry&#039;s last name? Right now I can&#039;t think--

GRANDDAUGHTER: I&#039;m not sure about a Sherry. I&#039;m not familiar with that name.

DUNHAM:Was she a co-worker?

DUNN: No, she works for the government on the projects and things like that, you
know. She was working for the Central Area where we met, and she told me she had
retired in the last year.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Not Jo, you&#039;re not talking about Jo?

DUNN: Jo, yeah, Jo Sh--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh sure! That&#039;s where you&#039;re getting that. I think her last name
is Scherer.

DUNHAM:Oh, last name, okay.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Because her first name is Jo.

DUNN: Jo, yes, Jo.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Okay, I was trying to figure out Sherry.

DUNN: She was the one who told me--she was working at that {Century?} and I
looked out and I said, You know, I believe that&#039;s a woman that&#039;s got that job.
Because at that time women and men were all wearing the same--you couldn&#039;t tell
who was who. So I went and asked her, &quot;Is this your job?&quot; She says, &quot;Yes, why?&quot;
I said, &quot;Because this is what we worked so hard for, to get women doing the jobs
that men would do.&quot; And she said, &quot;Yeah.&quot; So she said, &quot;But I want you to come
to the meeting. We&#039;re going to have a meeting up at the center up on Capitol
Hill. Will you come?&quot; I said, &quot;Yes, I&#039;ll come.&quot;

And so I got up that morning. It was raining, and my husband had just passed but
it was a few months ago and had bought--he had a new car. So I said, &quot;Well, I
don&#039;t know how to drive.&quot; So Ben suggested that I get the guy that lived in one
of our apartment buildings at that time and ask him to bring--so he&#039;s the one
that carried me, that Mr. Jones. He&#039;s the one that carried me up there. And it&#039;s
the first time I heard about Rosie the Riveter. And we got there, and I told
that girl, I said, &quot;Well, listen, from now on we&#039;re going to have to work to
give women a job. You let them know that they can be workers like the men--can
be carpenters or anything that the men do.&quot; That&#039;s why we&#039;ve got taxi drivers in
Duwamish Bend. They had their own taxi cars, and they got to be taxi drivers.
Before them we didn&#039;t have any black taxi drivers or anything. So at any rate
she&#039;s the one that got me started. So she&#039;s kept--every time they have something
she&#039;d call and ask me to come, and that&#039;s when I&#039;d go. And that&#039;s when I first
went there they told me about this card, but they didn&#039;t make this card.

DUNHAM:Oh, the Washington Women in Trades.

DUNN: We tried to find it, and nobody had it. You go to the post office, and
nobody had it. So you can see--and that was the only one I ever got too. I never
did get another one.

DUNHAM:Well, what are the messages that you convey and that you want future
generations to know about your experiences from World War II and beyond, that
you continued in the so-called men&#039;s work at the time?

DUNN: The main thing is don&#039;t give up because somebody say you can&#039;t do it. You
can do it if you try hard enough. And to take care of your money. Don&#039;t go out
and spend just to be spending. Don&#039;t do it. You always save something for a nest
egg, and that way you don&#039;t have to really depend on a man or anything for your
living, because you can make your own living and do that, because I know I never
would have done as well if I hadn&#039;t had something to go on for myself. And I
appreciate what Boeing did for me. I never had any complaints, because I didn&#039;t
mind working, and if I got a chance to make extra money working overtime or
anything like that, I&#039;m there 100 percent for it, and I never had any problems
with the supervisors, anything. Sometimes they&#039;d ask me to do jobs, and if it&#039;s
too heavy I&#039;d say, &quot;No, no, no. It makes them heavy.&quot; They&#039;d say, &quot;Well, don&#039;t
you worry, if you need some help you&#039;re going to get some help.&quot; And they would
send people to help me with the job. There are some heavy jobs out there, you
know, there are some heavy jobs. So at any rate--I don&#039;t know, it
just--everything worked out real good for me. I can&#039;t complain.

DUNHAM:And what does it mean to you now to have your wartime, and beyond,
contribution recognized?

DUNN: Well, it makes me feel good, but I don&#039;t--it&#039;s just--I figure it&#039;s just
luck that got me going. And I thank the president every time I hear his name or
think about him, because he and his wife really did fix it for us to--especially
for the women. Before he--most of the black women didn&#039;t have any jobs, and he
saw that we was going to get help, and they really did strive hard to help us
black girls. Because not only black, a lot of white has benefited from it too. A
lot of white girls have benefited from it too. So I&#039;ve really been well blessed.

DUNHAM:Is there anything else, Jerri, from you that we didn&#039;t cover?

GRANDDAUGHTER: I can&#039;t think of anything.

DUNHAM:Is there anything else, anything else Josie, that we--any last thoughts
you&#039;d like to share with us today before we close?

DUNN: Well, I&#039;d like to praise the girls that really got in there and helped me
to get this thing going. I didn&#039;t do it on my own. One of the girls here--this
girl here--{Katherine ________?} wrote that. She said that she worked at
the--Boeing&#039;s first place there in Seattle. I didn&#039;t work there at the--what is
the name of that place? The house, Boeing&#039;s first house.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Plant Two?

DUNN: No, across the--from Duwamish Bend. The red, red--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Oh, that red barn?

DUNN: Yeah, the red barn. She said she worked there, but I didn&#039;t. But when I
was there it was just a red barn, just standing over there by itself. I never
saw anybody working or anything, so I don&#039;t know--but at any rate, but Boeing
has really been good to me, I&#039;ll tell you. I have no complaints. It&#039;s the union
that did us up, but Boeing let the union do that, because I know they knew that
the union wasn&#039;t treating us right. But at any rate--

GRANDDAUGHTER: She got this--when she said they recognized her in 2008--a little
while ago, about almost a year ago you got that certificate in the mail. They
had it rolled up, and it was protected, rolled up in the post office, and she
got a certificate for her seventy-five years. I guess it&#039;s kind of--they call it
seventy-five, I guess from the time when she was working for the war up through
then--I guess they had an anniversary with that. Is that it?

DUNN: Yeah, this is it.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Yay! I was wondering about that.

DUNHAM:Okay, we&#039;ll take a shot of that.

GRANDDAUGHTER: And I do have a final thing to say.

DUNHAM:I don&#039;t know if we can take that out. We can look at that. [sounds of
papers rustling] Okay. Maybe we can take a still of that. Does it--

GRANDDAUGHTER: [reading] International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers.

DUNHAM:Is there anything that formally recognized the discrimination of not
including--because these just reference so many years, or what have you. But do
they ever acknowledge--?

GRANDDAUGHTER: In 2008 they gave them a rose or something, and there was, at the
union hall there was a--I don&#039;t know if it was called a reception or a banquet,
but when they honored them at the reception--Grandma, do you remember at the
reception if--his question is did they say, did they recognize the
discrimination that they did at that time?

DUNHAM:Did they acknowledge not including you--?

DUNN: They never--

 DUNHAM:Okay.

DUNN: I&#039;ve never--

GRANDDAUGHTER: Because I thought they must have if they were finally going to
say they were part of the union. But--oh yes!

DUNHAM:[looking at documents] Right, that&#039;s the group, yeah. So you wanted to add--

GRANDDAUGHTER: I think my thoughts are--and Grandmother, I&#039;m so grateful to you
for your decision to take up on the president&#039;s idea, or their suggestion to
come up here, because every time I think of Oklahoma and hear on the news the
things they do, I&#039;m just--I feel so blessed that I&#039;m not down there. And if it
wasn&#039;t for her decision to be here--I&#039;m born and raised here. And I--this is the
only experience I know, and I love Seattle. I&#039;m proud of having lived here and
still living here. This is all because of my grandmother, and all the things you
did, I&#039;m so proud of that--of you, Grandmother.

FUKUMOTO: Absolutely.

DUNHAM:Yeah, that&#039;s very well said.

FUKUMOTO: You should be proud.

GRANDDAUGHTER: Proud to be a rosebud.

DUNHAM:Yeah, yeah, no, not at all. Yeah, I just wanted to thank you again,
Josie, today, for joining us and for sharing your very inspirational life, your
perseverance against a lot of significant challenges. So thank you.

DUNN: Well, thank you very much for the invite.

DUNHAM:Our pleasure.

[End of Interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>