<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00100762" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2011-08-12" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format>Unknown Date</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Georgia Sadler | Interview 1 | August 12, 2011</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Georgia Sadler</interviewee><interviewer>David Dunham</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>mEXiX1FVPco</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>DUNHAM: Okay, it&#039;s August 12, 2011, and I&#039;m David Dunham with the Rosie the
Riveter World War II Home front Oral History Project, and I&#039;m here in Chula
Vista, and can you tell me your full name and date of birth?

SANDLER: Georgia Wreyford Sadler, born February 17, 1924.

DUNHAM: Okay and where were you born?

SANDLER: Rochester, Texas.

DUNHAM: Can you tell me a little bit about your family background, your
grandparents, where they were from?

SANDLER: My mother&#039;s parents was from Tennessee, and she was born in Oklahoma,
they had moved, and there was nine children. She was the second from the
youngest, three brothers and six girls.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: My grandfather was a farmer, my dad was a farmer. My dad was born and
raised in Arkansas. He was born in the 1800s and fifteen years older than my
mother. I have three brothers, but no sisters, although I asked for a sister
every time I could think of it.

DUNHAM: Where did you fall?

SANDLER: What?

DUNHAM: Where did you fall, did you say, were you the oldest or youngest you say?

SANDLER: I was the second.

DUNHAM: Second, okay.

SANDLER: I have an older brother and the two younger ones.

DUNHAM: So did you grow up on a farm?

SANDLER: I did, and I worked on that farm, too, right alongside my brothers and
my dad, and didn&#039;t do a whole lot of cooking, I did some until I got burned
(with hot grease that spilled down my right leg).

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: After that I didn&#039;t like to cook.

DUNHAM: Oh, I forgot, you were maybe going to take your glasses off, I guess,
before the photos.

SANDLER: I&#039;ll put them back on.

DUNHAM: It&#039;s not a big deal, but if you&#039;d like--

SANDLER: I&#039;ll put them back on because we didn&#039;t want the glare. That was to
read the paper.

DUNHAM: So what kind of farm? What did you grow or what animals--?

SANDLER: We raised cotton and feed for the stock and such as that.

DUNHAM: So what was a typical day like on the farm growing up?

SANDLER: Oh, getting up early, milking the cows, feeding the chickens, feeding
the hogs and horses, if there was any sheep, which there was once in a while
there was sheep, had a goat part of the time that used to butt me down (when I
was 3 or 4 years old).

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: Every time it got around me, the goat decided that I was a plaything
and butted me Mom said every time I got in the yard it got me.

DUNHAM: How did the Dust Bowl and Depression affect your family and the farm?

SANDLER: There were no jobs in the area except farming. As far as affecting my
immediate family, we didn&#039;t have money to buy a lot of stuff, but I never went
hungry. We raised our own meat. We had our chickens for food, as well as the
eggs. We had a garden. We had fruit trees and all the food that we ever needed.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: So I never went hungry.

DUNHAM: What about your neighbors and related community? Did some of them have
to leave the area or--?

SANDLER: Well, some of them did, and we had family that came in and lived in our
garage that had a dirt floor. It was only for one car. The wind blew through
every crack that was in there. Probably the rain came through the roof, I don&#039;t
know. But they had no other place to live.

DUNHAM: Yeah, where had they come from?

SANDLER: They lived in the area, but they didn&#039;t have a job and couldn&#039;t pay
rent. And my mom and dad had bought the farm just before the Depression started,
and they managed to keep the farm because the former owner gave them a little
bit of leeway. He knew if he didn&#039;t have them there, he&#039;d have somebody else
that couldn&#039;t afford it, so he decided to help, so they didn&#039;t lose their farm.
We was there from the time I was about four years old until I was gone from
home. We still have the acreage (10 acres). So the house was buried. It was
bulldozed and buried in the ground (about 12 years ago). I said the termites had
a nice feast.

DUNHAM: I guess so. When did you, do you remember when you first went to school?

SANDLER: I started when I was six.

DUNHAM: And what kind of school was it?

SANDLER: It was just a regular elementary school, first grade teacher, I don&#039;t
know whether she was quite rough or not, but to me it was a real eye-opener my
first day of school. We had one student that was so unruly, she hit him with a
paddle a few times and finally she broke it over his head.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: He was that unruly. That was my introduction to school for the first
day, so I had never had Kindergarten or anything else, and it scared me, and I
never did like school.

DUNHAM: Yeah, it didn&#039;t get better from there?

SANDLER: It didn&#039;t get better, then I had a couple of teachers that was not
primary concern with the education of a child. One of them studied his book on
how to raise hogs and how to raise chickens.

DUNHAM: Rather than teach.

SANDLER: He would assign us so many pages to read, and he got his little
pamphlets and set in the window behind me and either way I looked, turned my
head, I had his feet in my face every time I turned my head.

DUNHAM: Wow, what grade was that?

SANDLER: This was the fifth grade.

DUNHAM: What size were these classes, was it a relatively small school, or--?

SANDLER: It was a small school, so anybody that was in that town or in that
community went to the school. I don&#039;t know how many students that we had, but
when I graduated from high school we had just over forty students in my class.

DUNHAM: Okay, what did you do for play or social growing up or--?

SANDLER: Oh, at school I loved to be on the swing, and we had a slide part of
the time, but we could seldom use it. We had a bar that we could tumble over and
over and over and over on that, and seesaw, and that was all a novelty back then
because you didn&#039;t have those at home.

DUNHAM: Did you grow up with a religious background?

SANDLER: I went to the church every Sunday.

DUNHAM: What church was it?

SANDLER: It was a Baptist Church, but it was not a Southern Baptist Church.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know the full difference in it, but there is a difference in it
I understand.

DUNHAM: Okay, what was high school like for you?

SANDLER: High school was really good. I enjoyed the home making classes. I took
that for two years. And I was in gym classes. I played volleyball and
basketball, played softball. I was in the pep squad.

DUNHAM: Was basketball the style where you stayed on one end or the other, yes,
okay. Do you remember which end you were on or--?

SANDLER: Well, it was in a certain position, and I forgot now what position it
was. You couldn&#039;t cross the half-way point.

DUNHAM: Right, right, okay, so you played that through high school and enjoyed
sports, and then how was it, was it shop or carpentry you did get involved in?

SANDLER: Well, when I was a junior in high school they opened up the shop class
for the girls, and there was five of us took the first year. Then two of them
graduated, so there was only three of us that took it for the senior year. The
first year we made a picture frame, we made a bookcase, we made a little cedar
chest, it was not made of cedar, but it looked like a cedar chest. Later on I
upholstered the lid to it.

DUNHAM: Oh, wow.

SANDLER: It&#039;s still got the same cover on it. The second year of shop, I made a
bedroom set out of birdseye maple.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: There had never been any of the boys that was in the shop, including my
brothers, never made but one piece of furniture.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: And I made the bed, a chest of drawers, the dresser and the stool for
the dresser.

DUNHAM: Wow, so you had exceptional talent there.

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know that it was exceptional talent, but the war started in
December of that year, and the teacher left and started working in Civil Service
in Amarillo, which gave me an extra period for working in the shop.

DUNHAM: Wow, okay.

SANDLER: I had a band teacher, was in the band, he left. So we had no more band.
I took advantage of that. They gave me an extra, well that was two extra ones,
and then we had a study period that we could go into the study hall and if our
grades were well enough that we didn&#039;t have to stay in that, we could go out and
do other things. I had four classes a day.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: Time for four classes, had no teacher.

DUNHAM: So, yeah, you had no more woodworking teachers, so you were doing this--

SANDLER: The woodworking teacher left, the band teacher left--

DUNHAM: So you were self-teaching at this point.

SANDLER: We were self-teaching, and I had gotten far enough along with the chest
of drawers and the bedroom set that I asked the teacher if I could make a
dresser. Now this was before Christmas, and he said, he laughed, he said, &quot;You
think you&#039;re so smart, he said draw up your plans. Oh, I told him I didn&#039;t want
the dresser that he was having the other students make. He said, &quot;Well, you
think you&#039;re so smart,&quot; he said, &quot;Why don&#039;t you draw up your plans and let me
see if I okay them. If I do, then we&#039;ll order the lumber for your dresser.&quot; I
got those done before he left in December and he approved them, and we ordered
the wood and we ordered the metal parts for the drawer slides and the rollers
and so forth, we ordered all of that, but by January he was gone. The drawer
glides did not come because they were metal; all metal was going toward the war
effort. I had the metal for the chest of drawers which had been ordered before
the Japanese bombed Hawaii, so I got to put the metal drawer slides in, and I
had to come up with a different type glide for the dresser.

DUNHAM: How did you do that?

SANDLER: I went to one of the department stores and pulled out the drawers and
looked at how they had the deals made, and found one that had wood glides in it
and did it like they did, so that&#039;s the explanation to my granddaughter, who has
the bedroom set as to why the dresser and the chest of drawers are not alike
inside. But the birdseye maple is very hard to work with. We only had a circle
saw, eight inch saw, or nine inch possibly, I&#039;ve forgotten exactly, an electric
drill and an electric sander, and all of the planeing or all of that work was
done by the elbow grease (with hand tools). We did it all the hard way.

DUNHAM: Now you say we, were you working as a group at this point?

SANDLER: No, there was other people in the class.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: The other two girls, the one that I showed you the picture of.

DUNHAM: Yeah, were they devoting their other free periods to--?

SANDLER: They did some of it, but I don&#039;t remember what one of the girls
finished up, it was told later that she made twin beds instead of the full size
bed, but I know the one that I showed you the picture, Janie Pointer. She and I
both made the bedroom set like the schoolteacher had. But the dresser that I
made I wanted a flat top instead of the top that was the three different I mean
pieces there, two different levels, and with a great big round mirror. I didn&#039;t
want the dresser like that, so I drew up my plans and the teacher approved them
as I said. It&#039;s one of a kind as far as I know out of that school.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well, that&#039;s great, that&#039;s wonderful that your granddaughter you
said still has it.

SANDLER: I gave it my oldest grandchild. The bedroom set in being used by my
great-granddaughter. I sleep on that bed when I visit them in Vacaville, Ca.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well backing up a little bit, I was wondering when you said they
opened the woodshop class to five girls your junior year, how did that come about?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know why they did it, but they just decided that the girls
could work in the shop.

DUNHAM: Okay, it wasn&#039;t something you or other had requested per se--?

SANDLER: No, no, it was just something the School Board or the teachers, I don&#039;t know.

DUNHAM: Okay, but it was fortuitous for you--?

SANDLER: It was available to us the junior year and the senior year. Now whether
they had it after that, I don&#039;t know because they didn&#039;t have a teacher for a
long time. I don&#039;t know whether they ever got another teacher in there.

DUNHAM: Yeah, and not a lot of shop classes today in a lot of high schools, too,
unfortunately, I must say.

SANDLER: It was one of the highlights of my high school.

DUNHAM: Yeah, and you were able to continue with that in a sense, but first let
me just ask you, you referred to it already, but do you remember when you first
did hear about the attack on Pearl Harbor?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t remember where I was. I was probably at church.

DUNHAM: So and aside from the various teachers who left, now they went to serve
is that, or did they--?

SANDLER: Well, one of them I understand went into the military, the band
teacher, he was young enough to go into, the shop teacher was an older man, and
he was not of age to go into the military, so he went into Civil Service. And he
was the shop foreman in Amarillo. The job that I went to. He notified us three
girls to come to work for him. I don&#039;t know if he ever said anything to any of
the boys. They probably went to the military.

DUNHAM: More so.

SANDLER: I think that&#039;s what happened, but he had us three girls come. Only two
of us was there at one time, though.

DUNHAM: Okay, how did that, so he contacted you about that opportunity--?

SANDLER: Yes, yes.

DUNHAM: And you were immediately interested I take it and--

SANDLER: Very much so.

DUNHAM: Yeah, and so what did it take to get started there?

SANDLER: A move from Rochester, Texas to Amarillo.

DUNHAM: Since I&#039;m not very familiar, how far is that?

SANDLER: Oh, I don&#039;t know how far it is, but a little bus ride.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

SANDLER: But I was looking for a job. After I got out of high school I worked at
the bank, my hometown bank for two months, and after I&#039;d been there six weeks I
was expecting to get paid for it.

DUNHAM: Sure.

SANDLER: I didn&#039;t have any pay, I was a bookkeeper. I didn&#039;t have any pay slip,
so I asked the manager when he got time to talk to me. As I went to work that
day, two men met me at the door, and I didn&#039;t know whether they were robbers or
what they were, but when I unlocked the door they went in the bank with me and
it so happened they were bank inspectors or something of the kind, and anyway,
there were some things going on I guess that wasn&#039;t proper, but when I got a
chance to talk to the bank manager, he said, &quot;Well, you&#039;re not going to get paid
until you work here six months.&quot;

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: For free.

DUNHAM: You mean you wouldn&#039;t be paid for those six months, that was going to be
a volunteer--?

SANDLER: You wouldn&#039;t get a penny for it.

DUNHAM: Wow, but that was not your, did you know when you first started there
did you have an understanding of how much--?

SANDLER: I understood that I would work six weeks without any pay, and then I
would start getting paid, and that wasn&#039;t pay day. That was when the bank
managers met me at the door. They weren&#039;t there for me, it was for something
else, but I happened to be the one that opened the door when they went in. When
they got through with talking to the bank manager or bank president of the bank,
I went up to him and asked him about where was my pay? He said you&#039;re not going
to get any until you worked here six months. And I went back and I got my key to
the bank and by that time he was busy again, and I handed my key to the
assistant manager.

DUNHAM: Okay, wow.

SANDLER: And I walked out the bank, I didn&#039;t even put in that full day. So I was
looking for a job when I got this notice to go to Amarillo if I wanted to. I
went to work there and worked for a year or more, met my husband there, and, of
course, he wasn&#039;t there very long, but--

DUNHAM: How did you meet him?

SANDLER: He was stationed there, going to school. I had a date with another
fellow in his squadron, and I had two roommates, and their boyfriends came in,
but my date had to work on, well, he was on guard duty I guess is what it was.
Anyway, he couldn&#039;t come in, and the guys were all in the same squadron and the
other two boyfriends asked him (Bob) to come meet Georgia. And he said, &quot;No,&quot; he
said, &quot;I&#039;m going down to celebrate my birthday.&quot; It was his twenty-third
birthday, the 24th day of December, 1942. So they talked him into coming by and
meeting me and that was how we met, and three and a half years later we got married.

DUNHAM: Well, back to the starting of the job, did you have to get any special
training or had you received all the training you need through all these
woodworking you&#039;d done--?

SANDLER: I just swished right in and started using those big saws and--

DUNHAM: So what were you making?

SANDLER: Making work benches and cabinets and things like that because it was so
early after the war that they didn&#039;t have all the things they needed in the
hangars to do the work they needed, so we was building things like that. And one
particular cabinet that I made had about I don&#039;t know twenty-four little
compartments in it, and I had to put doors on all those little compartments
after I got the cabinet made. And it was as big as well, at least half as big as
the entertainment center, so it was a good size. One person couldn&#039;t turn it
over and pick it up at all, so had to have help to do that.

DUNHAM: Yeah, I see, so were there physical issues and did you have any changes
relative to that, or was it, or course, you&#039;d grown up on a farm and had done
hard work and already done all this carpentry, so--

SANDLER: Did it all just like a man would, same job that the men was doing
around there.

DUNHAM: So what was the makeup of your co-workers?

SANDLER: There was a few men, but I don&#039;t remember now, that was in &#039;42, and
I&#039;ve had a few years, but there was a few men. It doesn&#039;t seem there was a big
crowd in the deal.

DUNHAM: Okay, and what about where they were from, and--?

SANDLER: Most of them were from the local area, Amarillo, as far as I know.

DUNHAM: Okay and the ethnic makeup was--?

SANDLER: The assistant to the teacher was a colored fellow, very nice man named
Hickey. He was real pleasant. He was no problem, we didn&#039;t see race. I&#039;m
surprised that we didn&#039;t because at that time you saw race, but he didn&#039;t show
any difference in one color from the other, in fact, I don&#039;t remember whether he
was the only colored fellow in there, might have been. But I&#039;ve always
remembered him as being very kind and patient really.

DUNHAM: Since he was the assistant he was one who might help you in certain--?

SANDLER: He would help you just a regular fellow.

DUNHAM: Okay, so how long did you work there?

SANDLER: I worked there for over a year, I don&#039;t remember exactly how long, then
I went to Oklahoma City and worked at Tinker Air Force Base.

DUNHAM: Did something specific happen that--?

SANDLER: Well, women didn&#039;t have many rights, and there was something said, but
it was not the black fellow that said it.

DUNHAM: By a male co-worker?

SANDLER: Male co-worker and I didn&#039;t want to work with that person any longer
from what was said to me. The pass made at me and--

DUNHAM: You what?

SANDLER: The pass made, and I wasn&#039;t interested.

DUNHAM: So how did you handle it, I know it&#039;s sensitive, but just--?

SANDLER: I just walked out.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: And I packed up my bags and went to Oklahoma City. I didn&#039;t transfer, I
just, I knew that there was another place up there that I could get a job in
Civil Service, so I went up there, it took me about a month maybe six weeks
before they could get me on out there (at Tinker Field), and I worked for the
Nabisco Cracker Company, and if you&#039;ve ever packed crackers in those little
boxes, your fingers bleed here and here. Because of your running your hands down
and that salt that&#039;s on the crackers, it just eats your fingers up.

DUNHAM: Oh, my goodness.

SANDLER: They didn&#039;t tell me to put tape around my fingers, but after that first
day I learned that you put tape around your fingers so that they didn&#039;t get
chewed up in salt.

DUNHAM: So did you go up there on your own?

SANDLER: Went up there on my own, found a place to live, and put in my
application at Tinker Field and got the job right away working wood work in
there. The job was completely different than what it was in Amarillo. We worked
on aircraft that the boys that was trying to learn to fly, when they had an
accident and knocked a hole in the wing or something like that, we repaired the aircraft.

DUNHAM: So you worked at Nabisco while you were waiting to get on there?

SANDLER: While I was waiting to get on.

DUNHAM: And its Tinker Field is that the town or is that the company.

SANDLER: That&#039;s the base (by Oklahoma City).

DUNHAM: That&#039;s the base, okay. And so did you get any special training then to
do repair of the planes--?

SANDLER: I got instructions, but that was just routine. If they had a hole in
the plywood that was over the wing, we would cut that out, make it square or
rectangle, whatever, and we had to do a 10 to 1 ratio on it. The plywood was
1/8th of an inch thick and we had to make at least a 10 times that to make the
repair smooth.

DUNHAM: Okay, and at this or your previous position did you join a union?

SANDLER: There was no union. (It was a Civil Service job.)

DUNHAM: What was the makeup at your co-workers at Tinker Field?

SANDLER: At Tinker there was several girls that worked in that area, but they
didn&#039;t always have the training, they didn&#039;t do the repairs of some of the stuff.

DUNHAM: They didn&#039;t have as much skill as you had, as much background in--

SANDLER: There were several men that had the skill like I did, and we did the
repairs, I wasn&#039;t the only girl that did it. But we had one or two that just
they never could get it right.

DUNHAM: So what did they do, did they last?

SANDLER: Well, I think they transferred.

DUNHAM: What about fraternization between men and women there, were there any,
did you have any more problems there, did others, was there kind of, in the work
force there?

SANDLER: Well, the foreman on the job and several of the people, men and women,
it was in the shop area there, instead of standing there and talking during our
lunch break, and I don&#039;t know why that I had picked up my claw hammer and I had
it in my hand, maybe I started back to work and we walked in, I don&#039;t remember
now, but we was talking about people going to Kansas on TDY and getting per
diem, and I said, &quot;I&#039;d sure like to go up there to Kansas and get some of that
extra money. I could use it.&quot; And the foreman said, &quot;Let me feel in your pockets
and see if you&#039;re a man.&quot; I don&#039;t know what happened other than I swung my
hammer at him, and if he had not dodged that hammer, I would have hit him on the
head with it. But I didn&#039;t know that I was swinging it. It was just a reflex.
But I just thought that I needed to get out of there if he&#039;s going to make that
kind of statement.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: So I went over to another department, and it was a tool crib.

DUNHAM: So this is in Oklahoma that this happened.

SANDLER: Oklahoma City. But I didn&#039;t go for that feeling in your pocket.

DUNHAM: No, of course not, no. Yeah, I wonder if you had stayed there that one
swing of the hammer might have, or hopefully it did have a positive impact on him.

SANDLER: I hope it had an impact on him.

DUNHAM: But it&#039;s unfortunate there was any other recourse you could take. It
wasn&#039;t in same in Amarillo where there was--

SANDLER: I don&#039;t think you could have ever done anything. The men had privileges
that women didn&#039;t have.

DUNHAM: Yeah. Did you see other women who sort of either succumbed or played
along to those type of things?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know, I don&#039;t know what they did. I saw the women at work, and
that was all. One thing that some of the men did do, we had mice in the
department, you could move some of the lumber. It was leaning up against the
wall, and you&#039;d find a bed of mice, and there&#039;d be little tiny baby mice, and I
noticed that the men would come along and tap the woman on the shoulder, and
she&#039;d look around and see that mouse up there on his shoulder, and there all
kinds of screaming going on, and I was running an eight inch saw, circle saw,
and they came up and tap me on the shoulder and I look around and I said, &quot;Oh,
let me have it. It&#039;s so cute.&quot; I blew the wind right out of their sails. They
never did come back and bother me anymore about putting a mouse on my shoulder.
But they got those girls repeatedly. But whenever I said, &quot;Oh, it&#039;s cute. Let me
hold it.&quot; And I didn&#039;t want to hold it any more than they did, but telling them,
&quot;Let me have it,&quot; took the wind out of their sail.

But things like that happened, but you didn&#039;t pay much attention to that. I did
have one fellow that came up and goosed me in the ribs when I was standing there
with the saw running in both hands out by the blade, and I knew not to move my
hands, and I just squatted down to get away from him, just squatted down as low
as I could. Then I finally moved one hand and turned the motor off. And I turned
around and I said,&quot;If you do that again, I&#039;ll kill you.&quot; And this was just a
reflex. You don&#039;t fool with people when they&#039;re running machinery.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well aside from the blatant harassment, were there any injuries
that did come of any of those type of things or other injuries?

SANDLER: No, there wasn&#039;t anyone that got injured, but it could have happened so
easily, but I was prepared for it I guess mentally, I was prepared for it and
that&#039;s why I didn&#039;t jerk my hands into the blade or turn loose of the wood. If
you&#039;d have turned loose of the wood, it could have flown back and hit you in the stomach.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well, there&#039;s so many things that could happen there, wow.

SANDLER: One of the things that I did one day or two days, the ribs that go into
the wing of an aircraft, if you know what I&#039;m talking about, when the aircraft
is made, it has a round leading edge, and there&#039;s inside there&#039;s some ribs that
are kind of time consuming to put together, and we didn&#039;t do those, they came
out of a factory somewhere else and they was shipped to us. Well, a whole load
of them was shipped in there for the wrong planes. They wouldn&#039;t fit the wings
that we was working on, they did not send them back to the factory, they didn&#039;t
send them on forward where they could use them, I spent a day and a half or two
days sawing those up so they could be buried in the place on the base where they
buried things. They didn&#039;t want to put them in there whole. They didn&#039;t want to
burn them, so I sawed them up.

DUNHAM: Why was that, that they?

SANDLER: So that the enemy could not get the pattern.

DUNHAM: Mm, okay.

SANDLER: That&#039;s what I was told. I don&#039;t know whether that&#039;s what it was, but
all of those every time I would saw one of those ribs, I think of the hours that
had gone into making these, the time consuming--

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: I worked on the B29 when they first came out. They did some alterations
on it. We did some of the floorboards, we did intake B valves is what they call
it, while the plane is sitting on the ground we did the cowling or something
going into the cowling. I can&#039;t remember the phrases; it&#039;s been too many years.

DUNHAM: That&#039;s okay, no; it&#039;s informative what you do remember.

SANDLER: We made these boards to fit in there to keep the sand out of the
engines, and this was something before the planes went overseas.

DUNHAM: So these weren&#039;t strictly repairs, then, these were manufacturing.

SANDLER: This was an alteration.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: For the B29.

DUNHAM: Okay, and what other planes did you work on, do you recall?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t remember, they were the training planes. All of them were the
training planes (except for the B29&#039;s). But we didn&#039;t have very many spars that
was the main deal in the wing. We didn&#039;t have very many of those to repair, and
certain men did the repairs on those.

DUNHAM: Do you know where the planes were going then, do you know, or--?

SANDLER: Just wherever they were teaching the boys to learn to fly. We didn&#039;t
get that, it&#039;s best not to ask questions, I forgot what this thing was now,
about asking questions, but you just didn&#039;t ask.

DUNHAM: Now in Oklahoma, aside from the continued sort of harassment, were you
considered an outsider having come from Texas, or were you close enough that it
was sort of were there other people coming from different places, too?

SANDLER: I didn&#039;t pay any attention to that, so I don&#039;t think that&#039;s what it
was. I think it was just that the foreman, he just had something to say and his
way of saying you can&#039;t go. I don&#039;t know what it was. I don&#039;t know, and I don&#039;t
know whether he had ever said that to the other women or not. But I didn&#039;t think
it was a proper thing for him to be saying.

DUNHAM: So when you shifted departments, what were you working on in the--?

SANDLER: One of the things that I did was big box of files came in, all sizes,
shapes, all type of different duty anything from a metal file to a wood file,
and some of them could be the same type file, eight inch or ten inch, twelve
inch whatever, and some of them could be real coarse, just all different type
files. I sorted those out and put them away accordingly. I don&#039;t remember just
different jobs with the tools.

DUNHAM: Okay, and did you like that as well, or was it--?

SANDLER: I hated it.

DUNHAM: Okay, so were you hoping to find another way to get back to doing more
hands on work--?

SANDLER: No, I was hoping the war would come to an end. One thing that I did do
and I don&#039;t remember what it was when I was working there or when I was into
woodworking, but I think it was when I was in the tool crib. I showed movies for
the different places around the base for their lunch hour. I would take a
projector and the equipment, the screen and all, on a dolly about three feet by
six foot deal, it bounced around as you pushed it, and go from shop to shop at
their lunch hour and have a movie that the government had picked out.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: And showed that for their entertainment there so they get their mind
off of the war or whatever, the family, most of us had family that was in it. It
was just some entertainment, but I got to do that for quite a few months.

DUNHAM: So you learned to run the projector and--?

SANDLER: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: So do you remember any of the movies that you showed?

SANDLER: Oh, gosh, no, no. Most of them were government movies. But it was
trying to get your morale up is what it amounted to.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure. Was there other lunch time entertainment, like music or--?

SANDLER: They probably had it, but I wasn&#039;t involved in any of that. The base
newspaper called me into their office one day. I got a notice to report down at
the paper, and I had no idea why. They said we understand that you have a
fiancé that&#039;s a prisoner of war in Germany. I said, &quot;Yes.&quot; They said, &quot;You&#039;ve
got a brother that&#039;s a prisoner of war.&quot; I said, &quot;Yes.&quot;

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: They said you&#039;ve got a cousin that&#039;s a prisoner of war, they&#039;re all in
Germany. I said, &quot;Yes.&quot; Anyway, we talked about this and so forth and they had a
big write up, I say big, it was about four inches, five inches space in the
paper about me doing my patriotic duty for the war effort and that I had family
that were prisoners of war.

DUNHAM: How did you find out about each of them being prisoners of war?

SANDLER: The families was notified.

DUNHAM: Which of those was first?

SANDLER: My in-laws were the ones that were, future in-laws was notified. I went
up to visit with them twice during his time he was a prisoner of war.

DUNHAM: Where did they live?

SANDLER: It was in Maryland. He was born in England, but he came to the states
when he was about six months old. (Ellis Island in August, 1920)

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: So he knew nothing but the United States, although he didn&#039;t get his--

DUNHAM: Citizenship?

SANDLER: Citizenship papers until after we was married and had one child. Jo Ann
was born. He got his papers through Oakland, went into Oakland and got it for him.

DUNHAM: So had you been corresponding with him before he was captured--?

SANDLER: Yes, but the mail was very slow, probably took two or three months to--

DUNHAM: Had you already met his parents before then?

SANDLER: I hadn&#039;t met his parents at that time.

DUNHAM: So what was that like when you first met them?

SANDLER: It was very nice. The only thing that was surprising about it, and this
is when you rode buses to different places, and I had heard that if you rode
Greyhound buses you might stand up from California to New York. You might never
get a seat on it. Anyway, the Trailways guaranteed you a seat when they sold you
a ticket, so I went Trailways everywhere I went on bus, I went Trailways, if the
Trailways went there, and they did most of the time. But I got to the bus
station in Hagerstown, Maryland, and everybody got off the bus, and I&#039;m waiting
for the in-laws because they said they&#039;d be there at the bus, and I&#039;m waiting
and there&#039;s people standing around and I see this couple over there and they&#039;re
looking around, but they&#039;re not coming to me, and I&#039;m not going toward them, and
finally I got up nerve enough and I went over and asked if they were the
Sadlers, and they said yes. Then when we got to talking, Bob&#039;s mother said he
told us you was a redhead. That&#039;s why we were standing back, just waiting to see
the one that was red haired, and you don&#039;t have red hair. I said, &quot;Maybe it&#039;s
red when I get out in the sun.&quot; Sure enough they was a little bit of looking
whenever we get out in the sun, but I didn&#039;t see it myself because I don&#039;t carry
a mirror around looking at my hair whenever I go outside, but there was a little
bit of a red cast, and he had told about the redhead. So they was quite
surprised that I had brown hair. But it was very good meeting them and everything.

Things were hard to get, clothing was hard to find sometimes, especially in the
size you wanted, and when I think it was my second visit out to meet them, my
future father-in-law was running short of his underwear, and he wore the boxer
shorts at that time, I don&#039;t know whether they had jockey shorts or not, and she
said something about his underwear wearing out she said I hope this thing clears
up soon or they get to making more underwear. I said, &quot;Well, I can make some for
him.&quot; They both brightened up. You can? I said, &quot;Well, I&#039;ve got a sewing
machine.&quot; I had a sewing machine. The next door neighbors got a sewing machine,
and she&#039;ll loan it to us. We can go down to Miss Tucker&#039;s and get her sewing
machine, or you can sit down there and sew it, one of those big models, you
know, the floor model. So I got the material and I took a pair of his old short
and took them apart for the pattern, and I went down there, and I made him six
pair of shorts. They were blue and they were green and they were white, they
were all solid colors, they had been washed and it was a soft material. That man
was so thrilled to get that six pair of shorts, he thought he had died and gone
to some kind of Heaven with that because he just about had his backside hanging out.

DUNHAM: Wow. What kind of information did you have about your fiancé and other
family members who were POWs?

SANDLER: Didn&#039;t get much information. He was permitted to write a post card. I
don&#039;t remember every so many months, but if there was anything in it that the
Germans didn&#039;t want published or whatever, or if it was something they didn&#039;t
like, they&#039;d black it out. And when I wrote to him I had to be careful what I
was saying in that because you didn&#039;t want to say anything, loose lips sinks ships.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure. Well, when your daughter was starting to tell of when he was
ultimately released, can you share that story?

SANDLER: Some of the pictures that was drawn by Roy Butler, who died last
November I believe it was, he and my husband decided to trade, my husband traded
him a little bit of the food ration when he had it, extras, for the pictures Roy
drew, because Roy was, he would have given the pictures to anybody willingly
anyway, but since food was short, he took advantage of it, not advantage of the
people, I don&#039;t mean that. But he decided he had a talent and he would get a
little more food. The German rations were very slim, the German bread, had you
ever heard of the German bread?

DUNHAM: I don&#039;t think I know it well.

SANDLER: The Americans called it sawdust bread.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: It had sawdust in it. It had maybe a little bit of flour or wheat of
some kind, it had grass ground up in it, it had sand in it, it had gravel in it,
and there was a recipe for it, I don&#039;t know where it is, I&#039;ve got it someplace.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: But it was not very appetizing, but some of the food that they had in
the soup that they had was dehydrated cabbage and it was in brick form and he
said, &quot;We would soak it overnight in a tub of water and skim the worms and the
bugs off of it, and then put it on to cook and before we ate it, we&#039;d skim the
bugs and worms off of it, and then we decided if we left the bugs and worms in
it, that it was nutrition.&quot; And he said, &quot;We&#039;d pick out a spot on the wall, and
we would watch that spot on the wall, never look down in our dish because if it
we did, we couldn&#039;t eat it, eat the bugs and the worms.&quot;

DUNHAM: Yeah and where were they?

SANDLER: It was in Germany, well German prisoners; he was near Krems, Austria,
Stalag 17B, the one that William Holden&#039;s movie was about. My brother was in an
officers&#039; camp, and my cousin was also. They were pilots. My husband was on a
B24, and my brother and cousin was pilots in B17s.

DUNHAM: Were their experiences very similar as far as--?

SANDLER: They didn&#039;t have it as rough as the enlisted men did, but the people
that was on an aircraft, the Germans respected them more than they did the
ground pounders, the Army personnel, and they were treated better than the Army
personnel, same rank maybe, but they didn&#039;t have it as bad.

DUNHAM: How did your fiancé come to be released?

SANDLER: The Germans were losing the war, and the Russians was coming from the
East, and the Allies, American Allies were coming from the West, and the German
guards didn&#039;t want to be taken prisoners by the Russians, so they put them on
the march, and this was in the winter time, the coldest winter they had for
years, and marched them for several days, and then they met up with the
Americans. But they could walk off away from the guards and try to get food from
the German people, try to trade with them, and a little bar, a little piece of a
bar of soap was something that the German women really wanted, and they could
get an egg or two or chicken leg or something, I don&#039;t know maybe they could get
a whole chicken with a bar of soap. When they got bars of soap, in the Red Cross
parcels, they did cut it up when they found out they was going on a march. The,
what was I going to say about it, I don&#039;t remember.

DUNHAM: Well, how long a period of time was that from when the Germans sent them
on the march to when they met--?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t remember how long it was, but it was several weeks, but they
marched day and night, they slept outside most of the time. Once in a while
they&#039;d come to a farmer&#039;s barn where they could go in and get out of the
weather. But the weather was well below zero in some of the times I think when
they was out. But it was not a pleasant--

DUNHAM: No.

SANDLER: The barracks they was in, the beds were three high, bunk beds, but they
only had one or two blankets, and sometimes they would sleep together for the warmth.

DUNHAM: Sure.

SANDLER: The tobacco companies from America might not try to furnish food for
the prisoners of war, but they furnished cigarettes. They saw to it they had
cigarettes. My husband didn&#039;t smoke until he was a prisoner of war, and he said
it kept him from being hungry a lot of times, took your mind of wanting to put
food in your mouth. So he came back smoking, and he smoked for about ten years
when he gave it up.

DUNHAM: Did you ever smoke?

SANDLER: I never had a cigarette in my mouth, never.

DUNHAM: Was there a lot of smoking back to the places you worked, though?

SANDLER: Oh, yes, yeah. The first woman that I saw smoke I was up around, she
was a beautiful woman, had beautiful grey hair, but when I saw her put that
cigarette in her mouth, it&#039;s surprising how ugly she turned to me because I
didn&#039;t think women should smoke. Of course, that&#039;s up to them the matter
themselves, but back then I was down, I guess, and just didn&#039;t think that a
woman should smoke.

DUNHAM: Did your father smoke?

SANDLER: No, he dipped snuff, but he didn&#039;t smoke.

DUNHAM: Okay and your mother obviously did not.

SANDLER: Oh, she didn&#039;t like any part of it, although her mother dipped snuff.
(My grandmother lived to be 102.)

DUNHAM: Oh, yeah? Was there thinking of rationing here and with cigarettes and
other things, and what are your memories of rationing? Of course, you weren&#039;t
looking for cigarettes, but were other people, I&#039;ve heard of prizes for
cigarettes and bartering and all kinds of things.

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know that I was ever short of anything as far as food or
whatever during the war, and I didn&#039;t use my sugar coupons and my mom and dad
didn&#039;t need them, so I gave them to my future in-laws. They were from England
and they liked their tea, and they needed the sugar for their tea, and they were
very happy to get those sugar coupons. I didn&#039;t have a car, so I didn&#039;t need gas
rations. About the only thing that I might have got short on is shoes, and I
managed without having to use coupons.

DUNHAM: Did you make something, or--?

SANDLER: No, I had a pair of shoes that lasted me. I always took care of
whatever I had, so--

DUNHAM: Did you live close to your work, or how did you get to and from work?

SANDLER: I went on the bus. In Tinker Field, no, no, no, back that up, Amarillo,
they opened up some rental deals on the base for the civilians, I guess we&#039;re
all singles. There was four of us girls rented one of the units, and each one of
us had a little cubbyhole not much bigger than a single bed. We could get off
the single bed and stand at the side of it, pull the drawers on, but that&#039;s
about all. And we had a little kitchen and small living room and one bath for
the four of us. We lived there on the base, and we had a room, building, little
building out in front of this unit where there&#039;s a lot of these buildings like
that. There was one place for us to do our laundry by hand, and you had to take
your laundry (back to your room), you didn&#039;t want to hang it up outside, took it
inside your living quarters and hung your laundry up across your bedroom on your
space in there, let it dry, and then you ironed it. But we didn&#039;t have to use
the bus, we just walked around the base, so that made it really nice. No
civilians that was not employed with the military didn&#039;t get to live out there, so--

DUNHAM: Was housing scarce in either Amarillo or Tinker&#039;s Field?

SANDLER: It was bad, especially in Amarillo. There was three of us that lived in
a single room in a motel, and it was full of people that was working at the base
that was in this motel.

DUNHAM: Was that before you got the space on the base?

SANDLER: Before we got out there, yes. We had one bathroom, and all of us in the
whole motel was trying to use that bathroom at the same time in the mornings.

DUNHAM: How many people were at the motel?

SANDLER: Oh, gosh, I have no idea. It wasn&#039;t a big space, but I would say it
covered at least an acre, and the bathroom and the showers were out there in the
middle of it. We had a wash basin in our room so we could brush our teeth, we
could wash our face and hands, but if you wanted to shampoo your hair and take a
full bath, you had to try to get out there and stand in line if it took that.
But then we moved across the street into an apartment deal, and we had a little
bit larger room, and there was three or four of us in that area. But you crowded
up; you could put cots in instead of the single beds or double bed whatever.

DUNHAM: In Richmond where there was a tremendous boom, went from 20,000 to
120,000 within four years with the shipyards and all there, there was tales of
people sleeping in the movie theaters, the bowling alleys and all kinds of
places like that. Was there anything like that happening in Amarillo?

SANDLER: If there was, I didn&#039;t know anything about it. I lived out closer to
the base. I didn&#039;t have to go across Amarillo and lived in the main part of
Oklahoma City. (We carpooled to and from the base.)

DUNHAM: So when you got housing on the base, had you applied for that
specifically or how did that come through?

SANDLER: I think you did have to apply for it. I don&#039;t remember.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: I know as soon as you heard about something, you put your name in.

DUNHAM: Right.

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know whether you got in there before they opened or what; I
don&#039;t remember just how it was.

DUNHAM: Okay. What was the sort of social life? What did you do during your off
work hours in either Amarillo or--?

SANDLER: Mostly sat around and talked about what went on through the day because
it was the girls that I worked with, and there was some that was married, but
the ones that was with me, we were all single, just out of high school, and we&#039;d
have dates once in a while and things like that.

DUNHAM: What would you do on a typical date?

SANDLER: Oh, the guys liked to go to the bar. The one and only time that I was
ever going to the bars was when I was dating back in the early part of the war.
When I got to Oklahoma City I didn&#039;t do that. I had an aunt and an uncle lived
in Oklahoma City, and I was close enough to them that I could go visit with
them. My uncle worked at the base, and when I would see my uncle come in to my
department I knew he was bringing me a piece of homemade apple sauce cake. Oh,
man, that was to die for.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: My aunt made the best cake, and I enjoyed that cake. Every time I saw
him I knew that&#039;s what he was bringing me.

DUNHAM: Did you learn how to make that?

SANDLER: You better believe I did, still got the recipe for it, too.

DUNHAM: Wow, wow, that sounds great. Were the shifts again at both kind of
places you worked were there multiple shifts, or just day shifts, were there
graveyard and swing shifts?

SANDLER: I think they worked around the clock.

DUNHAM: Did you always work the day shift?

SANDLER: Yes, I did.

DUNHAM: Okay. Did you hear anything about the swing or graveyard shift
particularly, or if you came in on the day shift, were things--?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t think that they worked in our department. They worked in other
departments, though. In order words, I heard about swing shifts and so forth,
but the part that I worked in, in the Civil Service, was strictly daytime.

DUNHAM: Now, you left Amarillo abruptly, did you stay in touch with your
girlfriends there?

SANDLER: Yes, I did.

DUNHAM: Okay and they stayed on there--?

SANDLER: They stayed on there until after the war, and then one of them stayed
on for I think about a year. She didn&#039;t come to work when I did. She was not
there when I left. She came in later, so I don&#039;t know what she was doing. We was
not that close as the other girl and I was.

DUNHAM: Okay, I&#039;m going to pause here for a minute and change the tape if that&#039;s
okay, and we can--

SANDLER: You mean I&#039;ve talked for an hour.

DUNHAM: Just about.

DUNHAM: So this is David Dunham with Georgia Sadler, and this is Tape 2 on
August 12, 2011, and I think we&#039;ve talked a little bit already about some of our
husband&#039;s prisoner of war experiences, but you were just telling me, you could
tell me the story of how he was captured.

SANDLER: They was on their second mission out of England, and they had dropped
their bombs on Germany and was on the return journey and the bomb bay doors was
still open on the aircrafts, and the plane that was next to my husband&#039;s must
have been hit by flack, the pilot was probably killed, but it dropped down and
ran into their plane, cut the wing off of it, and my husband&#039;s plane turned
upside down and he and the radio operator were the only two that managed to get
out. My husband was a top gunner, and he had to back out of his cubbyhole and
didn&#039;t find his parachute and get it on, and he couldn&#039;t get it fastened on both
sides, only one side of his parachute could he get fastened up, but by the time
that he had done this, they were so close to the ground that he looked out the
bomb bay doors and he knew if he didn&#039;t jump then, he wasn&#039;t going to make it.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: So he did jump, and he said he glanced back over his shoulder and saw
that somebody else was coming out. It turned out to be the radio operator, but
he didn&#039;t know at that time that they were the only two survivors from his
plane. The radio operator broke both legs above the knees. He hit the tail
stabilizer. But my husband just buried in the ground up to his ankles in the
dirt and hurt his back and his spine, and he suffered with that, but he never
complained about it very much, but that&#039;s what put him in the POW camp.

DUNHAM: Do you know how long until they were found?

SANDLER: Oh, they got him right then and there.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

SANDLER: When he hit the ground he said the farmers, men and women, was coming
with pitchforks and shovels, any kind of farm equipment, coming after him. He
said if it hadn&#039;t been for a German military base close by and a Lieutenant and
his assistant came out and waved their guns at their own people. He told them to
back off, and they took him to the military base, and that&#039;s all that kept him
from being killed after he got on the ground.

DUNHAM: Right and this was in &#039;43?

SANDLER: This was in November. (November 13, 1943)

DUNHAM: And he was a prisoner until the end of the war.

SANDLER: Yeah, in &#039;45.

DUNHAM: Is there anything else you wanted to share about your husband&#039;s
experience, or--?

SANDLER: No, at the moment that&#039;s all I can think of--

DUNHAM: Okay, if there&#039;s something else you wanted to add, and I know how your
daughter Jo Ann told me about another, I&#039;m sorry, I forgot which, was it your
granddaughter who&#039;s made a short video?

SANDLER: Yes.

DUNHAM: So, it would definitely be interested to see that as well. Well, back on
the home front with you, so you just to get the dates right, you went to
Amarillo in fall of &#039;42?

SANDLER: Amarillo.

DUNHAM: Amarillo, sorry. In the fall of &#039;42 and about a little over a year later
to Oklahoma--

SANDLER: Oklahoma City.

DUNHAM: And so then you worked there for about two years?

SANDLER: Until the end of the war.

DUNHAM: So you had been transferred to the tool department after having to deal
with an--

SANDLER: But I don&#039;t remember working too much in the tool department, that&#039;s
where I must have gone into showing those films and doing things like that.

DUNHAM: So that primarily, what other kinds of things were you doing then, were
you kind of working independently, or--?

SANDLER: I was probably working with something besides the files. I&#039;m talking
about the files--

DUNHAM: Yeah, yeah, yeah, the big metal files, you sort of--

SANDLER: The tools.

DUNHAM: But you were showing the movies, and do you remember what else you might
have been up to, or--?

SANDLER: No, no, no.

DUNHAM: Okay, but it wasn&#039;t as much fun as working on the planes.

SANDLER: Oh, I just enjoyed doing woodwork. That was my hobby, and I would still
have been doing it if I&#039;d a had all the tools and the space and everything after
I got married. I taught my husband how to work on buildings and so, we built a
room on a trailer that we had pulled to St. John&#039;s, Newfoundland, and put a room
onto the front of the trailer so we&#039;d have a closet big enough to hang a few
clothes in because the closet in the trailer is only about this big a square,
and you can&#039;t hang many coats in that, much less the clothes you&#039;re wearing. So
we built this room in front of the trailer and then we built one off the back
door of the trailer later on so I could have a washing machine and hang my
clothes in the room to dry.

DUNHAM: And where was this, and how did you get there?

SANDLER: St. John&#039;s, Newfoundland.

DUNHAM: And what took you there?

SANDLER: He was military, and that&#039;s where the--

DUNHAM: Okay, and what was that like?

SANDLER: Wonderful.

DUNHAM: Was this just after the war in late &#039;45 or &#039;46?

SANDLER: It was in 1955.

DUNHAM: Oh, &#039;55, okay so a few years or a number of years later, okay. What
about at the end of the war, how did you leave your job? Were you--?

SANDLER: I just resigned and made a trip to Maryland because I&#039;d heard that my
husband&#039;s camp had been (ringing), you want to start that over?

DUNHAM: Okay, may I pause for a, okay, we&#039;re back on, we had a telephone
interruption. Go ahead, you were saying about when you resigned from your work?

SANDLER: I went to Maryland to be there when he got back home, but he didn&#039;t
want to be on the troop ships with all the many, many people coming back at the
same time. The bed was occupied for twenty-four hours a day; we had three people
assigned to the same bed on those troop ships coming back. One person had it
eight hours, and one person eight hours, the next person, and he didn&#039;t want to
do that so he waited since he was from England, he decided that was a good
opportunity to visit with some of his family over there. So he took a couple of
weeks off and visited with his family, and he came back on I believe the Queen
Mary, the Queen Elizabeth or the Queen Mary, one or the other of them that was
used as a troop carrier at that time.

DUNHAM: How was his health after the ordeal he&#039;d been through?

SANDLER: He was in fairly good health for what he&#039;d been through, eighteen
months of lack of food and nerve wracking deal. He never knew from day to day
whether he was going to be alive tomorrow or not. But it showed some through the
years, but one thing that all, is the way I understand it, all prisoners of war
families have found out that their husband or their sons or whatever did not
talk about their experience unless it was with another prisoner of war. And when
two of them got together or two or more got together, then they talked about
their experiences, and that happened with my husband and my brother. And my
children and his children were grown and married, and my brother&#039;s children had
never heard their dad talk about his POW experiences until Bob was with him. And
they said, &quot;Dad, why didn&#039;t you ever say anything about it?&quot; He said, &quot;Well, I
didn&#039;t have anybody else to talk to about it that knew what I went through.&quot;

But Bob had talked a little to our children about it, not a lot, and he hadn&#039;t
talked to me about it a lot until we got into a former prisoners of war group,
it&#039;s a national group, and when they&#039;re together that&#039;s all they do is talk
about their experiences.

DUNHAM: And you were present for that--?

SANDLER: The wives in that organization had as much power to hold office as the
man does, they&#039;re equal.

DUNHAM: So what was it like hearing about those experiences?

SANDLER: It was really interesting, and some of them would have one thing to say
like the ones in Japan, their experiences were rougher in some ways, they were
beat up more, their life was really on the edge I guess you&#039;d call it because
you never knew for sure from minute for minute what they were going to do to you
over there. It seemed like the Korean and the Vietnamese prisoners of war really
had it bad too, but you get a group of them, and they&#039;ll tell you about it.

DUNHAM: Had your husband experienced nightmares or anything that you&#039;d observed
that you thought might be related?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t think he had nightmares, I really don&#039;t. He seemed to sleep
good most of the time, which was I think a good thing.

DUNHAM: Well, so when he got back on the Queen Elizabeth or Queen Mary, how were
you reunited?

SANDLER: He came to his parents&#039; house and I was there. I quit my job when I
heard his camp had been rescued.

DUNHAM: Now when you quit your job, were there layoffs or a lot of other people
quitting, or what was kind of, do you know what the status--?

SANDLER: I didn&#039;t stay there to see.

DUNHAM: You had your own--?

SANDLER: I had my own--

DUNHAM: Yeah, just curious.

SANDLER: Yeah, my own thing to do.

DUNHAM: So, then what happened when you reunited? Set a date?

SANDLER: He was shocked that I was at his parents&#039; house because he hadn&#039;t
realized that I had been up to visit them twice. He knew I&#039;d been up there once,
but he didn&#039;t know I&#039;d been there twice and didn&#039;t know I made his dad&#039;s
underwear. But anyway, the morning that he got home, she and I were still in bed
asleep and I heard a car pull up in front. He had to take a cab from Hagerstown,
Maryland, out to his home. (His father worked there and Bob stopped to see him
before taking the cab on home -- about 25 miles away.)

I heard this car and car door or something, anyway, I jumped up and looked out
the window and I thought it was him, so I got my clothes on instantly, went to
his mother&#039;s room and yelled, &quot;Bob&#039;s here.&quot; And she got out of bed, and when Bob
got to the back door getting his suitcases and all out of the car, and then when
I got to the back door, I opened it for him, and the first thing he said was,
&quot;Joe, Joe.&quot; And I kind of looked behind him and, &quot;Joe?&quot; I&#039;d never been called
Joe in my life. And he said, &quot;I&#039;ve called you Joe all these years, all these
months over there in prisoner of war camp.&quot; He said it was just short for Georgia.

It dawned on me that all the time that I had been working Civil Service, when I
signed off a project I put Geo, and it can be pronounced Joe. In fact, to find
out if any of the crew member&#039;s families had heard what had happened to him, I
wrote to every one of them and got a letter back from them, and it was always to
Mr. Wreyford, Mr. Wreyford. My name was Wreyford, but it was Miss instead of
Mr., but I signed it Geo, they figured it was George. So I had to correct that,
but anyway, we all had the same information. But I did get in contact with all
of the crew members&#039; families, but all of them had been killed except this one.

DUNHAM: Did the radio man survive?

SANDLER: Yes, he survived. But he died not too many years later. But as far as I
know, my cousin that was a prisoner of war lived for a number of years, and my
brother is still alive. He is eighty-nine in December.

DUNHAM: That&#039;s great.

SANDLER: He still has a garden.

DUNHAM: Well, you said you were out in your garden yesterday, right? So, that&#039;s
great. And your other two brothers did they both serve?

SANDLER: My brother just younger than me was in the Navy, and he did not stay in
the military. My husband and my brother, oldest brother, stayed in the military
and retired, but this one got out of the Navy as fast as he could get out. He
had a real experience that was not pleasant.

DUNHAM: Do you know what the nature of that was?

SANDLER: Yes, they was near some island and he and some of the guys were put out
in the water up to his shoulders and then stayed there for about I don&#039;t know
between eight and thirty hours, something like that, in the water. And just
standing in the water.

DUNHAM: As a result of a mission, or as a test of some kind?

SANDLER: No, they was out there trying to keep any activity from the Japanese
coming back into the island. But he said that setting out there like a fish and
all, and he said he wouldn&#039;t go for that, so he got out of the Navy. But my
youngest brother was too young to be in the military. He did serve in the
occupational forces in England after the war, but it was immediately after
because, well, let&#039;s see, when did the war, it was--?

DUNHAM: Forty-five?

SANDLER: Is what?

DUNHAM: Forty-five?

SANDLER: What month?

DUNHAM: Well, VE Day is May, VJ Day was August, September.

SANDLER: Okay, he graduated that year, like I graduated when it started.

DUNHAM: Did they get some more teachers in the intervening years of that school,
or do you know what it was like?

SANDLER: I don&#039;t know, I don&#039;t know, I never kept track of it. I didn&#039;t like my
home town, I didn&#039;t like anything about it, and if I could have moved away from
there when I was six or eight years old, I&#039;d have been out of there. But,
anyway, my youngest brother got out of high school, immediately went into the
military, occupational forces.

DUNHAM: Okay, now can I ask if you don&#039;t mind to go back to the beginning just
about your home town and that feeling you had, what didn&#039;t you like about it?

SANDLER: I think a whole lot of it resulted from that teacher.

DUNHAM: The first day of school.

SANDLER: The first day of school, and just being frightened about, and it made
me dislike school.

DUNHAM: Do you remember what happened to that boy; did he stay in your class?

SANDLER: He lived around there, and I don&#039;t know whether he&#039;s still alive or
not. Last I heard he was still giving the sheriff trouble. He and the sheriff
got into some kind of altercation, and he bit one of the ears off of the sheriff.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: So he was a real decent little SOB.

DUNHAM: I guess so.

SANDLER: He was in trouble all of his life.

DUNHAM: At least we know the first day of school beating, that didn&#039;t help.

SANDLER: That didn&#039;t help any, no.

DUNHAM: Whether or not something else would have, we&#039;ll never know.

SANDLER: Yeah, he had a sister that was real nice. He had other brothers that
was not in trouble. He was the only one in the family that I know of that was
always in trouble.

DUNHAM: That teacher, was that just first grade, or was that several years for
that one teacher who was so--?

SANDLER: That was first grade is all we had her.

DUNHAM: Did you manage to avoid her paddle, or--?

SANDLER: Oh, I never got the paddle.

DUNHAM: Yeah, okay.

SANDLER: I never got the paddle, no.

DUNHAM: Okay. Now did your parents stay there all their lives?

SANDLER: Oh, yes, oh, yeah, stayed there all the time. My dad was, he passed
away while they was living there, and Mom stayed there for several years,
seventeen, eighteen, I don&#039;t know, maybe twenty years after he passed away
before she moved. My brother that was in the Navy built her a house in
Weatherford, Texas. My mom was short. He built it where the counters were low so
she could be comfortable, it was convenient for her.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: He had a bar that was low for her to sit there at the bar. She always
wanted a heater of some kind so she could back up to the heater and get her legs
warm. She said, &quot;My legs are always cold, have always been cold all my life, and
if I ever get what I want,&quot; this is a wish list for years and years, &quot;I want a
heater that I can back up to and get my legs warm.&quot; And he put it in for her.

DUNHAM: That&#039;s nice for her. That&#039;s a great son. So you and your brother were
gardeners, and did you participate all the Victory Gardens during the war, or--?

SANDLER: Oh, we didn&#039;t have any place.

DUNHAM: Where did you and your husband first go when he got back, or how soon
did you get married after--?

SANDLER: Well, that&#039;s one thing that I didn&#039;t cover earlier isn&#039;t it? He got
back from his visit with his relatives in England, and he wanted to get married
on Friday the 13th, and I balked on that. I said, &quot;Let&#039;s make it on Saturday,
the 14th, and that&#039;s what we did.

DUNHAM: Because 13 had been his lucky number, though, is that right?

SANDLER: Had been, yeah. He used to aggravate me to, &quot;You wouldn&#039;t get married
the day I wanted to get married.&quot; I said, &quot;Well, sorry about that.&quot;

DUNHAM: Well, it turned out well.

SANDLER: It turned out well, fifty-nine years.

DUNHAM: Wow, that&#039;s wonderful.

SANDLER: Was when he passed away.

DUNHAM: So you got married on Saturday, the 14th of, in forty--?

SANDLER: Of July. (1945)

DUNHAM: Okay, of, okay, great, and where did you first settle or go or--?

SANDLER: Well, we was in Maryland for a while after he got out. We stayed in
Texas for a little while, and then he decided to go back into the military, but
while we was in Maryland we run a little country grocery store, and had a little
one. Well, she (Jo Ann) was born in Texas, but we went up there shortly after.
Got back to Texas and helped my mom and dad run a help yourself laundry for a
few years, a few months, I don&#039;t know whether it was years or not, but not too long.

DUNHAM: You were having to withstand your home town those years.

SANDLER: Staying in my home town, and we got out of there right away. He went
back into the military, and from there we was at different bases. He went to San
Antonio to get assigned to a permanent station, and one of the places we went to
was Fairfield, California. The base at that time was Fairfield Suisun Air Force
Base. After General Travis was killed in an aircraft accident, they named the
base after him. This was in 1949 when we was there. He was assigned to Japan and
was there when the Korean War broke out, and the day it broke out he was sitting
in the airport in Tokyo waiting for a plane on emergency leave. Our son was born
(June 16, 1950), and they didn&#039;t expect him to live. We had lost a baby between
him and Jo Ann, so my doctors started working with the Red Cross to get him back
to the states, and I didn&#039;t know that they was doing this at all. My son had to
stay in the hospital for two weeks after he was born, and the day that I picked
him up from the hospital, my mom and I went over and picked him up from the
hospital, Bob came in and Dad had to go up to a town about twenty miles north
and pick him up and I didn&#039;t know then that he was coming in. But, anyway, the
Korean War broke out while my husband was sitting in the airport in Tokyo. He
was about two hundred and fifty-some on the list, and when the war broke out, I
don&#039;t know, twenty-five or thirty something on the list. Anyway, he got out on
the next aircraft, and got back to the states and he never did have to go back
to Japan. What he brought with him in his little duffel bag is all he ever got,
never did get his clothes, any items that he had in Japan, never received a thing.

DUNHAM: Why was that, do you know?

SANDLER: They never sent it to him. They just, I guess they were busy at the
base that he was assigned to they was busy sending fellows over to the Korean
War, and didn&#039;t have time to fool with something that wasn&#039;t that important. But
my husband was assigned to Ft. Worth base there and went from there to El Paso,
from El Paso to Wichita Falls, from Wichita Falls to St. John&#039;s, Newfoundland,
from Newfoundland back to Travis Air Force Base, and then from there he went to
the Philippines. I joined him over there after ten months. We got assigned to
Japan from the Philippines we went directly to Japan, assigned to the same base
that our daughter and son-in-law was at. We bought a house on the base, first
place that I&#039;ve ever seen that you could buy a house on base, and it was next
door to Jo Ann and Joe, walked out our front door into their back door.

DUNHAM: So what years was this?

SANDLER: This was in, Jo Ann, what year was this?

JO ANN: Sixty-six.

DUNHAM: Okay, and is this is Okinawa or--?

SANDLER: That was in Japan.

DUNHAM: In Japan, okay.

SANDLER: Tachikawa, Japan. (35 miles out of Tokyo)

DUNHAM: Okay.

SANDLER: So she and I made trips to Tokyo and enjoyed that being with her and all.

DUNHAM: Because you had not gone to Japan the first time when you had young--?

SANDLER: No, no, he was over there by himself. Jo Ann and I went to Hong Kong
together and had quite an experience with that and got back and our first
grandchild was born while we was there in--

DUNHAM: So how long were you in Japan, you bought a house there?

SANDLER: We spent thirteen months there.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay. And what was that like overall, did you enjoy it?

SANDLER: It was nice. I think it would have been nice without Jo Ann. Having her
there with us made it so much better.

DUNHAM: Did you learn any Japanese while you were there?

SANDLER: Oh, not a thing.

DUNHAM: Not a thing, okay. And you&#039;re pretty self-contained on the base, too, but--

SANDLER: They, the people in town, they would talk to you when we would take the
train into Tokyo, if we was standing around looking at the signs wanting to know
where to go, which direction to head, some Japanese would walk up to you and
say, &quot;May I help you?&quot; speaking just like you and I, so they were very helpful,
very friendly.

DUNHAM: That reminds me back during the war were you aware of any, and, of
course, it&#039;s much more common out here, but of any Japanese, German or Italian
Americans who during the war years in either Texas or Oklahoma?

SANDLER: No, no.

DUNHAM: Okay and what about were there any Native American workers that you knew
of at any of the places, or much Native American population?

SANDLER: No, not that, I don&#039;t remember any that was there.

DUNHAM: Just one other thing I think kind of from a related project that we do,
but had you heard of the Port Chicago explosion up near us between Concord and
Pittsburg there, there&#039;s a Port Chicago Naval magazine?

SANDLER: I probably heard of it, but--

DUNHAM: It was July 17, 1944. It was where over 300 men were killed there, and
so we&#039;re doing an oral history project related to that as well, kind of focusing
on that area, so just curious.

SANDLER: We probably heard of it, but--

DUNHAM: Those in the Bay Area that we interview, most of them, many of them felt
and/or heard the explosion from all over the Bay Area because it was a
tremendous explosion of two munitions ships that were loading, and, of course,
first people thought it was an attack, which was long feared on the West Coast,
but it turned out that it was this munitions explosion that had happened there.
But, okay, well, I just wanted to check about those.

SANDLER: Well, we didn&#039;t have the communications then, no TVs that&#039;s for sure.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure. Did you listen to the radio much during those years?

SANDLER: I was going to say most of us didn&#039;t have radios, well, we could have
had them but--

DUNHAM: When you had those lunch time movies did they have newsreels with them?

SANDLER: Yes, a lot of times that was one of the things that was shown.

DUNHAM: Now did you have to put those together at all, or were just playing
them, they came ready to go.

SANDLER: No, they were all ready for them to show, but I enjoyed them and the
people appreciated it, and they&#039;d come up and say, &quot;Thanks,&quot; but I pushed that
little cart all over the base. People see me coming and, &quot;Hi, there, we saw you
last week,&quot; or whatever it was and--

DUNHAM: Did you have popcorn or other treats?

SANDLER: No, no, no, no. They had their lunch break and that&#039;s what--

DUNHAM: Yeah, you mentioned when you got to St. John&#039;s, Newfoundland, that you
did some work, added on to the house and showed your husband how to do some
things. Had you been able to do much other work like that through the
intervening years or since?

SANDLER: We had been a little bit, but this is the first time he had really
built any room, but trailers were only eight feet wide, and this was one was
eight feet wide and forty feet long, and this is outside measurements, it&#039;s not
the inside measurements, and we had two children. That&#039;s a little bit crowded.

DUNHAM: Yeah, yeah.

SANDLER: You don&#039;t have much room in there that in--

DUNHAM: Did he appreciate the skills that you had?

SANDLER: Well, I think he did. The only other time he had tried to do anything,
it kind of crashed, but he learned enough, we improved on it.

DUNHAM: Okay. Were you able to do any of that kind of work, other examples, were
you able to do that, or other outlets for that passion you had?

SANDLER: We put up a patio one time, and then we&#039;ve helped do things around. He
built a room on the, enclosed I should say a patio in our last house that we had.

DUNHAM: Did you ever wish for more kind of opportunities for that kind of work or--?

SANDLER: After he began to learn how to do the things, he wished that we had
more tools so he could do more things, and we did put up a 12 x 24 shed, our
storage deal or space for working in the backyard of our last house. He had
quite a few tools that he&#039;d get out and tinker, but as far as building anything,
we didn&#039;t need anything, and--

DUNHAM: Okay, okay, and you weren&#039;t tinkering so much with the tools in those days.

SANDLER: I had other things to do. I had grandchildren at that time.

DUNHAM: Of course. How long were you in Newfoundland?

SANDLER: Three and a half years.

DUNHAM: What was that like? Cold--?

SANDLER: It was cold, but it was wonderful, wonderful. In fact, Jo Ann and I had
planned to take a trip up there, and we would have left two days from now. We
was going to leave the 14th, and I didn&#039;t have a passport book. I have a
passport card, but I didn&#039;t have the passport book, and we happened to think of
it before we made any reservations, so we had to cancel our trip because if you
go up there this time of year, you might have nice weather, and about two more
weeks would be the end of the good weather. You&#039;ve got winter.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: You blinked your eyes, and you&#039;ve got cold weather again.

DUNHAM: What did you particularly like about it up there?

SANDLER: The people, for one thing, and the scenery and it was just a pleasant
experience all the way around, the NCO Club did things for the personnel that I
have never heard of other NCO Clubs doing.

DUNHAM: Like what?

SANDLER: We could go out, eat out there, on Sundays for a dollar each for Bob
and I, fifty cents for each one of the children, so for three dollars we could
have a lobster dinner or a steak dinner or whatever.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: They had five different meat courses that you could have, and it was
the same price for all of them. On Thursday nights the buffet was free, and they
had the same things they had on Sunday which you paid a dollar for, you could
have your lobster, your steaks, your roast chickens or whatever, you could have
all that, and we played bingo and we won. Nearly every week we&#039;d win in bingo.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: And that was really nice when you looking at bingo. Sometimes we win
two or three times at night.

DUNHAM: Wow. Did they have live music, did you experience traditional--

SANDLER: You could go to the dances, or you--

DUNHAM: Celtic music up there?

SANDLER: You could just listen to the music, they entertain the children, they
had parties for them, they gave away all kinds of toys, just did everything for
the whole families.

DUNHAM: Are you hoping you might be able to go try for next year then, get your
paperwork in order?

SANDLER: We&#039;re still planning on a trip; I don&#039;t know whether it would be next
year or not. We still have friends up there.

DUNHAM: Oh, that&#039;s wonderful.

SANDLER: And one couple had seventeen children. (The Burke family)

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: One had died in infancy, but they raised sixteen.

DUNHAM: Was this a Navy family, or a local family there?

SANDLER: No, it was a local family up there, and we had made arrangements to see
her when we&#039;d get out there and some of her children, but next year she&#039;s having
a family reunion, they have one every five years. NOTE -- We did get to take our
trip to Newfoundland last summer and joined the Burke family for their reunion.
There were over 100 people in attendance. My daughter, Jo Ann, my granddaughter
and great-granddaughter were also able to join me. We had a fabulous time and
were greeted like long-lost family even though we hadn&#039;t seen them since June, 1959.)

DUNHAM: How many must that be?

SANDLER: All of them come unless they&#039;re sick--

DUNHAM: Yeah.

SANDLER: But they have two weeks that they&#039;re together. They&#039;re spread all over
Canada, and there&#039;s one son that&#039;s in Indonesia, and he and his family come to
the reunion, so we may get in on the tail end of that or may get there quite a
bit earlier. We don&#039;t want to get there and have her tired when they get there.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure.

SANDLER: So we don&#039;t want to interrupt their party.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well, that would be great. I would like to go up there sometime.

SANDLER: If you like to fish, if you like to hunt, that a fisherman&#039;s or
hunter&#039;s paradise.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well, those aren&#039;t my fortes, but I just I still like the idea of
getting up there, but I&#039;m interested in the traditional music and just--

SANDLER: We could look out our back window to our trailer and see the icebergs
in the harbor, or in the ocean.

DUNHAM: Wow. Is there anything you wanted to suggest we talk about Jo Ann, as
we&#039;re close to wrapping up, I think but and you as well, Georgia, if there&#039;s
anything in particular you wanted to make sure you mentioned?

JO ANN: Nothing that I can think of.

SANDLER: The only thing that I might not have mentioned when my husband&#039;s plane
went into the, or was hit, it broke off the wing, and the plane flipped up, but
it went into a spin upside down, so he was very fortunate to be able to get out.
Probably the pilot and co-pilot was killed by the propellers from the other
plane coming in and hitting the cockpit. And there was two survivors out of his
plan and three out of the other plane.

DUNHAM: And how many would have been in the plane total?

SANDLER: There would have been nineteen, total.

DUNHAM: Wow.

SANDLER: One fellow was missing out of Bob&#039;s crew. He was sick, and he didn&#039;t
go, and I don&#039;t know what position he was in, but I&#039;m sure it was a gunner.

DUNHAM: Well, is there anything just sort of in reflecting on the war and how it
fits into the story of your life that you just, is there anything else you&#039;d
like to share today?

SANDLER: It got me out of Rochester.

DUNHAM: It did, already went back a few times, but it showed you the way out.

SANDLER: I went back a few times, but, yeah, it showed me the permanent way out,
but it was nice really. I don&#039;t mean the war was nice, getting out of Rochester
was nice. But I can&#039;t think of anything else, and when you leave, I&#039;ll think of
several things.

DUNHAM: I was sure, and as I said, we will send you the transcript. We like to
get it all recorded, but you&#039;re welcome to send some additions or clarifications
as we do that, but well, I think it was clear, maybe you are getting that
opportunity already for your work, woodwork classes, but it was great that you
were able to do that a little more through the war years and work on the planes
and other things that you did. It seems like it fulfilled a passion and skill of
yours, and also was certainly a great aid, and you met your husband. Of course,
that was the best part of the gifts, too, about getting out of--

SANDLER: He was in school in Amarillo at the time.

DUNHAM: Yeah, yeah, so that was the good thing about Amarillo because it didn&#039;t
seem like it was all good either, but there was that.

Well, I think we&#039;ll close for today then if that&#039;s okay with you.

SANDLER: I can&#039;t think of anything else.

DUNHAM: Yeah. Thank you very much for participating. I think this was a great
contribution to our project.

[hEnd of Interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>