<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042299" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2002-10-25" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Sal Chavez | Interview 3 | October 25, 2002</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Sal Chavez</interviewee><interviewer>David Washburn</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url></media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Born and raised in Santa Fe Railroad housing off lower Macdonald Avenue in Richmond. Chávez worked for local industries, such as the Santa Fe Railroad, American Radiator and Standard, Filice and Perreli Cannery, and Kaiser shipyards. During the war he served with the US Coast Guard, and later started a career as a barber. His interview offers a unique perspective into the history of Richmond's longtime Mexican community. Discusses: life of the employees of the Santa Fe Railroad, Mexican culture in Richmond, social relations (dating) in Richmond schools, race relations.</description><rel /><transcript>WASHBURN: Yesterday we stopped when we were talking about when you first started
working on the shipyards. You said you only worked there for a month, but people
are real interested in it because it was such a big event for Richmond.

CHÁVEZ: I worked there for about three months, then I went into the service. I
joined the service because I knew that eventually I was going to get drafted. So
I said, Well, what pay do you want, the army or the coast guard? I said I want
to sign up for the coast guard. So I signed up and I didn&#039;t have to go in the
army. I went in &#039;42 and I got out in &#039;46.

WASHBURN: You told me that yesterday; I remember that. What we didn&#039;t get to
talk about is you said you knew people from down the neighborhood and Richmond
where you lived who worked at American Standard, who worked at Santa Fe
Railroad. Worked at the Pullman.

CHÁVEZ: Most of them were from North Richmond. Most of them were from Richmond
that worked in the Santa Fe.

WASHBURN: Did you know folks that also worked in the shipyards?

CHÁVEZ: No. Well, I know a lot of girls that went and worked as welders. But I
don&#039;t know them by name, it&#039;s been so long.

WASHBURN: You said that working at the Santa Fe and American Standard you knew a
lot of folks from your neighborhood. How would you compare that to working at
the shipyards?

CHÁVEZ: Well, when you worked for American Standard you had three shifts. You
were working around the clock. And you didn&#039;t have the chance to talk to nobody.
You used to go in at five o&#039;clock in the morning and get out at eleven, went to
bed, sleep. It wasn&#039;t that you think, &quot;Oh, they&#039;ve got a lot of people.&quot;
Everybody went home. We were tired. Maybe to the store, but you never had
gatherings all the time. You know what I mean? Cause half of the time a lot of
guys worked and all that. The only time, maybe like if somebody had a baptism,
and then they have a little party and that&#039;s it. Then those dances, it was that
they had--like I told you--for the September 16 and the May 5.

WASHBURN: Oh, I understand all that. What I&#039;m trying to get at, is how many
people you knew who worked at the shipyards. Like, when you arrived there, did
you have friends?

CHÁVEZ: No, you had them from all over. The friends you had went to work. A lot
of guys were going to school, then went to work. Just like me. I don&#039;t know how
you&#039;ve got it figured, but we didn&#039;t see too many guys. Maybe you saw guys that
you went to school with or around your neighborhood, but the rest of the guys
were from Richmond, but la planta baja. You know what I mean? [laughes]

WASHBURN: That&#039;s where you lived, it was called la planta baja?

CHÁVEZ: That&#039;s where we lived. We all lived out there, from Second Street down.

WASHBURN: How do you translate la planta baja? That&#039;s &quot;the plant below?&quot;

CHÁVEZ: La planta baja means that you&#039;re down. Down at the bottom of the totem
pole. La planta baja means you&#039;re down. It was just a slang word.

WASHBURN: Was it down meaning the neighborhood was down by the tracks or meaning
that the neighborhood was poor?

CHÁVEZ: No, no. You were down by the tracks. Most of the Mexican people lived
at Eighth Street, Second Street because they worked on the railroad and some of
them worked in the foundry, like I said. So that was it. Then some later on got
the good jobs. Like when the war broke out, a lot of them went to work for
Standard Oil. They quit the Santa Fe and went to work for the Standard Oil,
which paid them more money. That&#039;s what they did.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s also when the war broke out. They went to Kaiser and to
Standard Oil?

CHÁVEZ: Standard Oil.

WASHBURN: Just Standard?

CHÁVEZ: Mm-hmm. That&#039;s their name. That&#039;s what it was before. Standard Oil. I
know what you&#039;re thinking about. You&#039;re thinking about the American Standard.
The American Standard was a foundry.

WASHBURN: Right, that&#039;s what you called the foundry. [tape interruption] I&#039;m not
quite following you. You said that folks worked at the Santa Fe railroad and at
the foundry.

CHÁVEZ: No, at the railroads. They&#039;re called Ned Duran. You can keep on talking.

WASHBURN: When the war broke out, you told me, people quit their jobs at the
Santa Fe railroad and at the foundry and went to work at the shipyards.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, for more money.

WASHBURN: For money.

CHÁVEZ: That&#039;s right.

WASHBURN: So, what are you now telling me about the Standard Oil?

CHÁVEZ: Standard Oil didn&#039;t hire Mexicans, but then when the war broke out they
hired everything.

WASHBURN: So how do you know they didn&#039;t hire Mexicans? People tried to get jobs
there and they--

CHÁVEZ: Guys went to work out there my age, you know, at that time. I used to
go out there and try to get a job at Standard Oil and they wouldn&#039;t look at you.
They wanted blacks or whites. But then during the war, they were hiring
everybody, kind of. We&#039;re talking about the Standard Oil. They didn&#039;t hire--.
The only time they hired was when the war broke out, then they hired everybody.

WASHBURN: And that includes blacks?

[At this point, someone else in the barbershop contributes to the discussion.]

DURÁN: They didn&#039;t hire me, even after I got discharged I couldn&#039;t--.

CHÁVEZ: Even some of the persons that worked on the railroad, they quit the
railroad to work for the Standard Oil.

DURÁN: You know why they didn&#039;t hire me?

CHÁVEZ: Why?

DURÁN: Because of my disability.

CHÁVEZ: Really?

WASHBURN: Hmmm.

CHÁVEZ: I met him in the army hospital.

WASHBURN: How are you doing? I&#039;m David. Nice to meet you.

DURÁN: Pleasure. Ned Durán.

WASHBURN: Nice to meet you, Ned. David.

DURÁN: David?

WASHBURN: Yeah. Just interviewing him about Richmond and some history. He knows
a lot about the--.

DURÁN: Oh, he was born and raised here. I&#039;ve been here since &#039;45 only.

CHÁVEZ: He knows quite a bit about Richmond too.

WASHBURN: You know quite a bit too? Where did you move to when you moved into Richmond.

DURÁN: I came from Colorado. I got discharged from Fitzsimmons Hospital and I
came over here. I lived--was raised and born--in Colorado.

WASHBURN: Was your family in sugar beets over there?

DURÁN: No, my mother was a clerk. She worked at the--She was a postmistress
when I was born. First one in a little town, and she worked at the department
store. She graduated from some school in Albuquerque, because when she passed
away--. She was 104 years old in 1986 when she passed away.

WASHBURN: Wow! Good genes, strong genes.

DURÁN: My Dad was-- I was five years old when he passed away. He passed away in
1919. I was born in 1917.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s great. I&#039;m asking him about the Mexican-American community in
Richmond, and he was just saying people called that area &quot;la planta baja.&quot;

CHÁVEZ: La planta baja was at the end of town. They used to call the--I told
you, &quot;section house&quot;, they called that section house, but then they nicknamed it--

DURÁN: Santa Fe yards.

CHÁVEZ: No, no.

DURÁN: Those homes there. Started working there. Then I told my wife, I&#039;ll get
a part-time job for Christmas help. Cause I already knew about it. So they gave
me a part-time. Then it started raining like hell, so my job as a carpenter was
gone. So the only one had was the $1.71 I had since then as a Christmas help. I
told my wife, &quot;No, I&#039;m going to go back to the post office. It might be a little
check, but it&#039;s steady, you know.&quot; So, I went back.

CHÁVEZ: People that lived in the town--

WASHBURN: That&#039;s what I&#039;m finding out. I&#039;m trying to write a little history of the--

CHÁVEZ: The guy started working for the city. It was hard, because they
wouldn&#039;t hire you. I&#039;m being honest. Because you were Mexican. That&#039;s why they
wouldn&#039;t hire you.

WASHBURN: Who wouldn&#039;t hire you?

CHÁVEZ: The Standard Oil wouldn&#039;t even hire you either.

DURÁN: During that time, I think, the city council was run by Standard Oil.

CHÁVEZ: Oh, really?

DURÁN: Sure. The city council was full of Standard Oil people. Politics. But
you know, there was Barrett and all them guys that were deal there. They didn&#039;t
hire-- Fact is, they didn&#039;t even hire blacks.

CHÁVEZ: Didn&#039;t hire anybody. During the war-- As soon as the war broke out,
they hired even the Indians that came from New Mexico. They brought them in boxcars.

DURÁN: That was Kaiser made of Richmond. Kaiser made Richmond. He was hiring
everybody. The shipyards were hiring everybody. Kaiser hired all of them guys
from Oklahoma and everything that came here and worked. Blacks, everybody. Women.

CHÁVEZ: Women welders.

DURÁN: Sure, welders, burners, and everything they had there. My wife worked at
the gas rationing board in the Yard Two.

CHÁVEZ: Rationing?

WASHBURN: That&#039;s interesting. You said that Standard Oil wouldn&#039;t hire Mexican
people before the war.

CHÁVEZ: Honest. Ask anyone. You can ask anybody, old-timers.

WASHBURN: Were there any other businesses that wouldn&#039;t hire Mexicans either?
Like Pullman or something like that.

CHÁVEZ: No, Pullman hired. They had a lot of Mexicans.

DURÁN: I think so. I don&#039;t know a thing about that though.

CHÁVEZ: Like the Sante Fe hired them, and everything.

WASHBURN: And the foundry hired too?

CHÁVEZ: Oh, yeah! That was hard labor. Nobody wanted to go out there and work.

DURÁN: I tell you something else. When I joined the army in 1940, I joined the
First Cavalry Division, and they come and said, &quot;Oh, look at the shit-eaters
coming in.&quot; That&#039;s what they used to call us. And they used to go to Texas, like
that, and you could see on the restaurants, &quot;No dogs or Mexicans allowed.&quot; And
we were in the army, man! So I told one kid, I says, &quot;How long you been in the
army?&quot; He says, &quot;About three or four years.&quot; &quot;Couple of years they&#039;re going to
take orders from us. We&#039;re going to show you how to ride horses and stuff like
that.&quot; And it&#039;s true. A bunch of us made corporals. We overlooked, you know.

CHÁVEZ: They didn&#039;t let you in. [people talk over each other]

DURÁN: They saw that you was a better soldier than anybody else there.

CHÁVEZ: I went to Mexico when I was just a kid. I was going to grammar school,
Peres School, and I remember that we had a stop in Texas, El Paso, and then
wait--my father worked for the railroad, so they give you a pass--passage for
the whole family--but you had to be there ten years before you could be eligible.

DURÁN: See, back home, there wasn&#039;t anything like that.

WASHBURN: What were you going to say about Texas?

CHÁVEZ: So then what happened was that you had a sign in the toilet, and I went
in there, and when I got out, everybody kept looking at me because what it said
was, &quot;No blacks or Mexicans.&quot; I didn&#039;t give a shit because when you gotta pee
you gotta pee. [laughs]

DURÁN: That&#039;s right. One time I went to CC camps--

CHÁVEZ: You went to CC camps too. So was my brother.

DURÁN: I was at CC camps at Estes Park in Rocky Mountain National Park in
Colorado, north of Denver. This kid and I decided to go in to Denver, so we
started hitchhiking, and we stopped in Longmont. That&#039;s where I was born,
Longmont, Colorado. We went to this restaurant and we had dinner. So we rented a
room, and next morning we got up and went to have breakfast. We walked in there
and the waitress said, &quot;Sorry, we can&#039;t serve you.&quot; We say, &quot;Why?&quot; &quot;Cause you&#039;re
Mexicans.&quot; I said, &quot;You served us last time. What do you mean &#039;Mexican&#039;? We were
born and raised here. I was born here in this town.&quot; Then she called the
manager. I told the manager, &quot;You know something, I was born in Longmont, but if
that&#039;s the way you treat people, I condemn this damn place.&quot; They served us. But
there were a lot of things. In northern Colorado especially because we were from
southwestern Colorado. That&#039;s where all the Hispanics are from.

CHÁVEZ: You&#039;ve got a big sheep ranch. How many sheep?

DURÁN: My stepdad&#039;s brother had ten thousand head. So, when I was a kid, I
spend most of my time in the mountains during, after shearing time.

WASHBURN: What kind of sheep?

DURÁN: Regular. Rambouillet. Mixture--rambouillet and the regular sheep.

WASHBURN: It&#039;s interesting that you guys say that. From what you&#039;re saying,
there was a lot more racism in Texas and Colorado.

DURÁN: Oh, yeah. You bet there is! You know the reason why? Because all them
people are fighting the Alamo yet.

WASHBURN: You mean they&#039;re still fighting it. They&#039;re still bitter.

CHÁVEZ: [laughs] Are they?

DURÁN: Sure, that&#039;s the whole thing there. That&#039;s why the Mexicans--

WASHBURN: It&#039;s deep in the--

DURÁN: Well, they were raised to hate Mexicans like that. Especially the
old-timers. You know, what they--

WASHBURN: So how would you compare those times in Texas, to what it was like in
Richmond? What was the discrimination like in Richmond?

DURÁN: I didn&#039;t--I haven&#039;t--had no discrimination.

CHÁVEZ: We didn&#039;t have no discrimination. But, you know, even though you didn&#039;t
have any, but you stuck to yourselves.

DURÁN: Oh, yeah, we stuck to ourselves. Especially in the post office. You mix
with people, you know.

WASHBURN: You did mix?

CHÁVEZ: That was in the later years.

DURÁN: In later years.

WASHBURN: Yeah, I&#039;m talking about in the forties and fifties and stuff like
that. So you&#039;re saying in Richmond you never saw those kind of signs, like &quot;No
Mexicans in here,&quot; &quot;No blacks in here&quot; and stuff like that?

CHÁVEZ: A lot of guys said that they were over in Georgia and in the line that
says &quot;No dogs or Mexicans.&quot;

WASHBURN: It&#039;s kind of a simple question, but why do you think it was different
here in Richmond here than in Texas? I mean, they were raised to hate people in
Texas, like you said, but why don&#039;t you think there was any of that stuff. There
was more discrimination--

DURÁN: I don&#039;t know. There was less discrimination here, I think, than in
Texas. But a lot of places, like Colorado, the discrimination is mostly northern
Colorado. Not in southwestern Colorado where all the Hispanics and people were
there. Cause most of these people, their ancestors migrated from Florida down
the peninsula, like-- Remember, the guy that was looking for the seven cities of
Cibola. Migrated from Florida over there to--. Fact is, they were Spanish,
Portuguese, and everything. Where I come from, I think, most of the--because my
mother was half-Portuguese, half-Spanish. So most of the people, like from where
we&#039;re from, I think, were mostly Portuguese. Because we don&#039;t--like me, &quot;Do you
have any relatives in Mexico?&quot; &quot;No.&quot; Not that I know of.

CHÁVEZ: My relatives are all dead. On my father&#039;s side, they&#039;re all dead. My
mother&#039;s are all dead. I went to Mexico three or four times when I was growing
up. My brother-in-law&#039;s family. I went there three or four times so they got to
know me, so that if his parents already gone--. But, the kids, they knew me.

DURÁN: Sure. Like, I dunno. I was at the Melody Bar one time, when I got out of
the post office, some guy was saying about Mexicans, you know. I says, &quot;Hey,
what nationality are you?&quot; &quot;Oh, I&#039;m Scotch.&quot; I said, &quot;Well you&#039;re a mexican.
That&#039;s what &#039;mexico&#039; means--&#039;mixed blood.&#039; You&#039;re a mexican.&quot; &quot;No, I&#039;m not.&quot;
&quot;Yes you are. You&#039;re mixed blood. What do you think &#039;mexico&#039; means? &quot;Mesclado&quot;
All right? &#039;Mexico&#039; means &#039;mixed blood.&#039; [chuckles] I tell him about it. Gave
him a history of Mexico, the little bit I know.

WASHBURN: So there wasn&#039;t the kind of outright, the signs that you saw in Texas--

DURÁN: Oh, no, no.

WASHBURN: --but still people like Standard Oil wouldn&#039;t hire Mexicans, though.

CHÁVEZ: No.

DURÁN: Underneath. Very quiet-like, you know.

WASHBURN: What?

DURÁN: Like they smile at you and underneath they--

WASHBURN: But in Texas they won&#039;t even smile?

DURÁN: They don&#039;t even smile. They just come out with it: there are no dogs or
soldiers allowed.

CHÁVEZ: Soldiers? You say, &quot;I&#039;m fighting for your country.&quot;

DURÁN: Mexicans. No Mexicans or dogs allowed.

CHÁVEZ: Then after, now, they don&#039;t give a shit, huh.

DURÁN: After the war broke out, man, we were the most popular people in Texas
and all over the place. Soldiers. Look at the 36th Infantry Division. All the
Mexican people got most of the valor medals. Silver Star. That&#039;s the big one.
Medal of Honor. The 36th Infantry Division and the 45th Infantry Division were
all Texans and Okies. Oklahoma and Colorado and all them places. Another example
is the 445th Regimental Combat Team. You don&#039;t know what that is.

WASHBURN: No, I don&#039;t know.

DURÁN: That&#039;s Japanese.

WASHBURN: Oh, four-four-two. Yeah, I know about them. Served in Italy, right?

DURÁN: What did they do? They served in Italy. Tops.

WASHBURN: They came out and saved some whole infantry by doing some real brave acts.

DURÁN: Sure, what did they do here? Some of them kids joined the army from the
encampment. That&#039;s the one thing--

CHÁVEZ: They took them out of the camp.

DURÁN: Yeah, they joined.

WASHBURN: That was wrong.

DURÁN: That was wrong, very wrong.

CHÁVEZ: They shouldn&#039;t have taken them, huh.

DURÁN: Do you know why they took them? The 442nd Regimental Combat Team, they
call it the &quot;Purple Heart Team.&quot; That was the most decorated regimental combat
team in the army. And they&#039;re all Japanese.

WASHBURN: They were real brave.

DURÁN: Sure, they exhausted the people. And [Daniel] Inouye is a senator from
Hawaii. A lot of guys from Hawaii that are senators now. Look at another thing.
Look at the Apaches. Arizona and all them guys. In the South Pacific. You know
what they did?

WASHBURN: There&#039;s a movie about this, right?

DURÁN: They had their code. That&#039;s why the Japanese and people didn&#039;t
understand the American code. Private code. The Apaches were using their own
language. They didn&#039;t know what the hell was going on. You read the thing about that?

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve heard about that. Actually, there&#039;s a movie that just came out
about that. I thought it was the Navajo.

DURÁN: &quot;Whispering Sands.&quot; They&#039;re Indians, that&#039;s right. Southwest Indians.

WASHBURN: Southwest Indians, yeah. That&#039;s interesting. But why do you think, I
mean, Standard Oil started hiring Mexicans during the war, but what changed
after the war?

CHÁVEZ: Well, they just kept on hiring.

WASHBURN: So that&#039;s when it started.

CHÁVEZ: They kept on hiring everybody. That&#039;s it.

DURÁN: They were short, too.

WASHBURN: They were short.

CHÁVEZ: We did a lot of hiring at Santa Fe. A lot of hiring. They wouldn&#039;t let
nobody--. They even brought those Indians, from where? Remember they had that
old Santa Fe camp?

WASHBURN: New Mexico.

[everyone talks over each other]

CHÁVEZ: They had God Darn hair in a bun. You know how they usually have it. I
thought, &quot;Jeez, what&#039;s that?&quot; They all lived in the Santa Fe camp.

DURÁN: I think those were a bunch of--. They were different Indians, maybe Hopi Indians.

WASHBURN: I actually read something about it, Laguna Pueblo.

CHÁVEZ: They lived across the tracks. Old {Chiteewa?} was a good friend of mine.

WASHBURN: An Indian guy or gal? Was it a guy?

CHÁVEZ: It was a girl.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s nice.

CHÁVEZ: Jesus Christ, man. They had the Indian camp. You should have seen when
they had their parades in Richmond. Man, they got on all their war robes, and
man they could--. Especially, one of them was a chief. Man, he&#039;d do the Indian
war dance up and down the avenue. Man! The guys would say, &quot;Slow down.&quot; He was
getting too--

WASHBURN: Too animated or too excited?

CHÁVEZ: He was real fit, boy.

DURÁN: In Colorado the Indian was Comanches. Prairie Indians. That&#039;s it.

WASHBURN: What parade was that you&#039;re talking about?

CHÁVEZ: They had their parades, a long time ago. They had the memorial parade,
Fourth of July, all that kind of thing.

WASHBURN: Those Indians would participate?

CHÁVEZ: They all used to go out there and they&#039;d participate. They came out
there, especially that chief.

DURÁN: They still do.

CHÁVEZ: He had on the God-darned feathers. But he got carried away and then I
guess he thought he was ready to go on the warpath. [laughs] I guess he got
carried away, you know.

WASHBURN: So did any of the Mexican folks participate in the parade too?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, they were in the parade. I used to be one of them who used to be
in the parade. I had a beautiful horse. I owned two horses in my life, and they
were both stallions. I used to love stallions. I used to love to ride horses.
Both my horses were top of the line. They used to pick up their legs and, I
mean--. Studs, you know what I mean, you could see the big balls hanging on them.

WASHBURN: And you used to ride that in the parade?

CHÁVEZ: Oh, yeah, I used to ride them in the parade. I used to hear, &quot;Don&#039;t get
that stallion close to me.&quot; I said, &quot;He ain&#039;t gonna do nothing to you.&quot; They&#039;d
be afraid of the stallion. He&#039;d be so proud, big old eyes.

WASHBURN: So why would they have you ride the horse in the parade rather than
somebody else?

CHÁVEZ: Because I asked if I could ride. I asked if I could ride, and they
said, &quot;Sure, come on!&quot; But that&#039;s lately, here. It wasn&#039;t like before. You know,
before, you had a lot of the American Legion or--. That&#039;s all you saw, Mexican
guys in the American Legion.

WASHBURN: So when are you talking about when you used to ride the horse?

CHÁVEZ: Oh, that was so long ago. Ned? Twenty years ago or more?

WASHBURN: Seventies and eighties and such?

DURÁN: Seventies.

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh. Used to go out there with a charro, and all that.

DURÁN: Dress up like a Mexican charro--

CHÁVEZ: I have over 300 trophies that I won.

DURÁN: --in a big old hat.

CHÁVEZ: I used to compete over there in Half Moon Bay, Redwood City. I bring my
horse way out there.

WASHBURN: Compete at doing what? High step? My mom has some horses, so I know those--

CHÁVEZ: They had classes. And you went to the class and the horse, you know.
Parade class. Ninety-one. I didn&#039;t want to be in a group. If I got the trophy, I
wanted it for me.

DURÁN: In the First Cavalry Division during peacetime, they used to have horse
shows. Equestrian riding. And I won a regimental-- I used to ride horses when I
was seven years old. Used to ride them bareback, you know. I won a regimental
ribbon, and then I went to division, and I won a division ribbon. I&#039;ve got them
at the house. I had third prize. First prize was red--

CHÁVEZ: Blue.

DURÁN: I mean blue. And second prize, red. White was the third prize one. The
judges were looking at me like that, see, and I had my horse going on around the
circle. And all of a sudden, I saw him and I started trotting and that put me
out. Used to ride bareback. I broke horses in remounts.

CHÁVEZ: In the course, you used to have to have a lot of remounts. They come from--

DURÁN: Nineteen forty, nineteen forty-one. From Reno they used to ride them a
little bit.

CHÁVEZ: We used to have them in a corral. They were delivered from New Mexico,
and they were--. You know, we used to jump on them Indian style and sometimes
they started bucking. Sometimes you&#039;d run and get with the rest of the horses.

WASHBURN: I understand why he rode horses, because he grew up on kind of a ranch
in Colorado, but why did you ride horses if you grew up here?

CHÁVEZ: There used to be a guy--a Mexican--{Nica Norvega} and he had two work
horses and then he had cows. He had them out in the old--where they had that
paint shop over there in North Richmond. He had them way out there, in the
fields. I used to go out there and help him. They used to have a regular {more}
with the horses. I used to go with him and help him. So what he used to do after
he come back from, you know, when he came back from where we were at to the
barn, he&#039;d let me ride the horse with a harness and all that while he was
pulling the thing. So when I got out there he says, &quot;Fine, take the harness off.
And just the bridle. And bareback.&quot;

DURÁN: That&#039;s right. I used to ride bareback.

WASHBURN: So how old were you when you started riding?

CHÁVEZ: I was just a kid. Just a kid.

DURÁN: I was seven years old.

WASHBURN: So you were riding horses from seven?

CHÁVEZ: I was even riding one in the service. I was in the coast guard mounted
patrol. I rode horses for about three or four years. No, three years.

DURÁN: Yeah, when the war broke out, the First Cavalry Division was border
patrol in Mexico. We were right in Columbus, New Mexico.

WASHBURN: When the First World War broke out?

DURÁN: Second.

CHÁVEZ: I used to ride on the beach. Sometimes some of the girls, &quot;Can I ride
the horse?&quot; I said, &quot;I can&#039;t let you ride,&quot; but I&#039;d put her on the back, on the
rump of the horse.

WASHBURN: So, Sal, when did you buy your first horse, then?

CHÁVEZ: I bought my first horse when I was just married. Fifty-some odd years ago.

WASHBURN: So in the late forties, huh?

CHÁVEZ: I bought that horse. I used to feed it myself, and then I bought--. I
used to feed it myself. Used to buy the hay and all that, then I got to know
this guy--he&#039;s a rancher, Tony {Forium?}. I used to go out and feed his cows and
all that kind of stuff. When I ran out of hay, I used to take a cord of bales.
But I used to help them every day, every day. So my horse had plenty of alfalfa.
And then, when he broke his neck, he was twenty-some odd years old. He broke his
neck. He still stood. I had him out here. He was out here and the end of the
{__} road. What happened was, he tried to jump a fence, or something, he broke
his neck. He was killed. I was without a horse for a long time, then I bought
another one, and I had him till he was fifteen, and then I sold him. I still got
my tack, I still got my saddle. Good bridles. Good bits. I also have a nice
Mexican saddle, which I&#039;m going to donate to the museum. [laughs]

WASHBURN: What museum?

CHÁVEZ: I was just kidding!

WASHBURN: [laughs] That&#039;s all right. When you first got here, did you look to
find some horses to ride when you first got here? No?

DURÁN: I couldn&#039;t ride any more because I had a brace on my leg, you see. I
enjoyed them. I enjoyed the cavalry. Because in 1942, they took our horses off,
away from us, and they sent us 1,000. They transferred a thousand of us
cavalrymen to activate the 91st Infantry Division in Medford, Oregon. I was one
of them. After I was breaking horses, they made a corporal out of me, you know.
I was corporal and I jumped to staff sergeant. So we were in the 91st Division,
that&#039;s where I hurt my--I tore my ligaments. My leg went over the wall on the
obstacle course. I still went overseas. I went to North Africa, and all around
Africa. That&#039;s where I got hurt again. Then from there they sent me back to the
States and they told me, &quot;You&#039;ll catch up with your outfit in Adriatic Coast of
Italy, eastern Italy.&quot; They sent me out there. They sent me to Fitzsimmons, not
Fitzsimmons, but Brigham City, Utah hospital. From there I got a transfer to
Fitzsimmons. Home town.

CHÁVEZ: Where&#039;s that? In Washington.

WASHBURN: No, that&#039;s in Colorado, huh?

DURÁN: Fitzsimmons? Denver. Brigham City was in Utah. So they told me, &quot;Sign
here.&quot; By that time, I was already a platoon sergeant. I was already Sergeant
First Class. They used to call them technica1 soldiers. I didn&#039;t want to get
out. I wanted to make it my army. I&#039;m glad I didn&#039;t, in a way, stay twenty years.

WASHBURN: Glad you didn&#039;t?

DURÁN: Anyway, so I kind of told them there once. &quot;Sign here.&quot; I said, &quot;What&#039;s
that?&quot; &quot;Your discharge papers, and this is your 30 percent disability.&quot; &quot;Okay.&quot;
So ever since then, I had--

CHÁVEZ: You got disability, 30 percent?

DURÁN: Yeah, first. Right off the bat. I was only drawing sixty dollars a month
then. And they gave me that brace, and I still had--. I had some operations on
my knee here in Oakland, where I met him, at the VA [Veterans Administration]
Hospital. That&#039;s where I had more operations, there.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, I saw him all the time. You and that blonde. Who was that girl
used to have--?

DURÁN: And then I was doing the post office and I was carrying mail, and I got
hurt again. Cartilage got out of it again.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve got a problem with my knee too. You get a re-occurring problem.

DURÁN: So anyway, I had about nine operations on it. The postmaster told me the
doctor at the Fitzsimmons hospital, at the VA hospital, told him, &quot;He can&#039;t
carry mail any more, it&#039;s too much on the knee.&quot; &quot;Well, all right. Write a
letter to the postmaster and tell him to change me to clerking inside.&quot; So he
did. I was a clerk at Richmond, then I went to El Cerrito, and I worked at the
El Cerrito post office, window clerk. Fairmont, that&#039;s where I retired.

WASHBURN: So you guys met in a VA hospital?

DURÁN: Yeah.

WASHBURN: In Oakland?

DURÁN: In Oakland.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s where the big one was?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh. Kind of hard.

DURÁN: He had a beard like, you know, Barabas. Have you seen Barabas. A beard
like that.

WASHBURN: I could tell. He seems like he can grow facial hair pretty well. Sal,
what were you doing in the hospital?

CHÁVEZ: Kidney.

WASHBURN: You had kidney problems? Hmm. So you guys stayed in contact after
being in hospital.

DURÁN: We stayed in contact after that, all the time.

CHÁVEZ: When I was there, remember that time they came in there for over a year
because they wanted to make sure that whatever I had wasn&#039;t going to go to the
kidney. Eighteen months.

DURÁN: I met you the first time I went up there. When I went the second time,
you were still there. I said, &quot;What are you doing here? Still here.&quot; And the
third time, there he was again.

CHÁVEZ: But, you know, I&#039;d get a pass every weekend. But then you know my
paycheck went up to 100 percent straight away. And do you know what 100 percent
was at that time? A hundred and thirty-eight bucks.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s a lot of money then.

DURÁN: I tried to get more than 100 percent. They gave me 40 percent. In 1989 I
finally had to have an artificial knee put in. So I have an artificial knee.
Then, ten years later, they had to do it again because a cushion in there wore
out. So I had to go through it again.

WASHBURN: When you lived in Richmond where did you live?

DURÁN: I lived right off San Pablo Avenue, called Huber Avenue.

WASHBURN: Did you ever know Polly Russell and MaryLou--no, MaryLou and Polly?
There were some sisters; they lived on Hubert too. I met some gals--she&#039;s a
Mexican-American woman from New Mexico. She married a guy name Russell. But I
don&#039;t know, what was her original--? Maybe it was Diaz.

DURÁN: Yeah, we lived at 52nd Huber Avenue, 5200.

WASHBURN: So, you lived in government housing?

DURÁN: Yeah, that&#039;s all there was there. Fact is, on Cutting Boulevard, right
there where that station is at now, there was a grocery store there. Lucky&#039;s
grocery store.

WASHBURN: I passed by it, yeah. So, how did you find housing there?

DURÁN: Well, I met my wife there. She used to live there with her cousins. I
came and stayed with my brother, and my brother lived in 4900 Cutting Boulevard.
He was working in the shipyards.

WASHBURN: Okay, so you came first to live with your brother?

DURÁN: And I came first to live with brother. Then, in the CC camps, when we
were young, I met a kid from Alamosa, Colorado, and I met him at the bar, Luiz
Club, you know.

WASHBURN: At Luiz Club? Where was that?

DURÁN: Right there, where Target is at. Right around there. Anyway, so I met my
wife through him.

WASHBURN: And then moved into her house?

DURÁN: I went around. I didn&#039;t care I wasn&#039;t married, anyway. But I saw her,
and I liked her. So I told her, &quot;Well, this friend of mine and I went to see the
priest, so you better come--.&quot; She was Catholic and I&#039;m not, see. She went up
there, and I told her, &quot;Well, we already saw the priest going to marry us.&quot;
She&#039;s being alone. We&#039;ve been married 57 years. But damn priest, do you know
what he said? &quot;Being that you&#039;re Protestant, and she&#039;s Catholic, your marriage
is not going to last a long time. &quot; But the other priest said, &quot;Send you back to
Mexico where you belong.&quot;

WASHBURN: He said that to you?

DURÁN: Irishman.

WASHBURN: The Irish guy said you should go back to Mexico?

DURÁN: Yeah. His name was McCarthy, Father McCarthy. From El Cerrito. Saint John&#039;s.

WASHBURN: Where did you guys get married?

DURÁN: Saint John&#039;s, right there. I says, &quot;What you want to marry for me?&quot; I
said, &quot;I want to marry right here in your study, that&#039;s all. I don&#039;t want no
church wedding.&quot; Because you had to take lessons and all that, marriage lessons.
I wanted to marry her, so I said might as well take anything. You know what he
told us? &quot;Better send you back to Mexico, where you belong.&quot; &quot;Well,&quot; I said,
&quot;I&#039;m more American than you ever will be.&quot; And then my friend told him, &quot;Hey, he
just discharged from the army. What do you think?&quot; So, anyway he wanted to just
beat him up.

WASHBURN: But he&#039;s a priest.

DURÁN: Yeah. He wanted to beat the hell out of us. So, anyway, we got married
and he said, &quot;Well, your marriage is not going to last.&quot; I says, &quot;Okay.&quot;
Fifty-seven years we&#039;ve been married.

WASHBURN: Did you ever go to church in Richmond?

DURÁN: Yeah.

WASHBURN: Where did you go?

DURÁN: We used to go to that little Perspiration church that used to be on
Cutting. Where was it? At Stockton? I think Episcopalian or Methodist. We used
to Methodist Church most of the time. She used to go with me, and I used to go
with her, you know.

WASHBURN: Where did she go?

DURÁN: She went to Saint John&#039;s. Catholic.

WASHBURN: Your brother came out here from Colorado too? How did he manage to
make his way out here?

DURÁN: My brother in my home town, he was a county assessor. And my other
brother was a policeman. And they both came over here after they--wait, let&#039;s
see, my brother wasn&#039;t county assessor. After he left here, he went as county
assessor. My oldest brother. And my younger brother, he was here, and he was a
guard in Yard Three.

WASHBURN: Security guard?

DURÁN: Yeah. So, when they went back home, my older brother got into politics
and got to county assessor, and my other brother, he was a policeman in my home
town. That was it.

WASHBURN: But how did your brother make his way out here to work in the shipyards?

DURÁN: Worked in the shipyards. I was in the army, so I don&#039;t know. They were
here, when I got out, already. They just migrated over here, I guess, because of
the jobs. My brothers, they worked in the mine up there. My hometown&#039;s in mining
country. Coal mining. They worked in the coal mine. They both did. They even got
that black lung. You&#039;ve heard of that?

WASHBURN: Oh yeah.

DURÁN: He got that.

WASHBURN: He was sick for a while?

DURÁN: Yeah. And he lived to be 92 years old.

WASHBURN: You&#039;ve got some strong genes in your family. A hundred and four. And ninety-something.

DURÁN: Oh, we have. On my mother&#039;s side. On my father&#039;s side, he was 47 when he
passed away.

WASHBURN: Your brother came out here to work in the shipyards.

DURÁN: Yeah, he worked in the shipyards.

WASHBURN: In what year, do you remember, when he came out here?

DURÁN: Nineteen forty-four, I think. Forty-three or forty-four.

WASHBURN: I was talking to Sal. Sal worked in the shipyards, but only for couple
of months. I was trying to figure out if--. I mean, I know the shipyards were so
big and there were so many, so many--

DURÁN: There were three shipyards, weren&#039;t there?

WASHBURN: Four, by the end. And there were so many employees there, but I was
trying to figure out whether-- I mean, you met Sal at the VA hospital, but if
you were at the shipyards, would people be speaking Spanish? Would you hear
Spanish being spoken?

DURÁN: We&#039;d speak Spanish and English, naturally.

WASHBURN: In the shipyards?

DURÁN: Yeah. See, our Spanish back home is way different from the Spanish--.
Fact is, I even took it in high school. I took Castillian Spanish. Because our
Spanish is not like Mexican Spanish. Castillian Spanish was always, what do you
call it, slang. Cause we used a lot of English words in our Spanish. Like we
say, &quot;the bus&quot; - we say &quot;el bus&quot;. Like we say, &quot;the track&quot;, &quot;el tracque&quot;, or the
train, &quot;el train&quot;. We didn&#039;t understand what it was. Ferrocarril and all that.
Automovile. Carro, we used to call them. And trucks we used to call truck.

WASHBURN: They do that still today, though. That&#039;s common here now too. People
say truque instead of truck. They don&#039;t have a word in Spanish. Do you guys ever
remember meeting other Mexican folks at the shipyards.

DURÁN: Oh, yeah, sure. Used to be a lot of them there. From New Mexico. See,
New Mexico and Colorado, they&#039;re so close together they&#039;re about the same. Same,
what do you say--?

WASHBURN: Culture? Same kind of culture?

DURÁN: Yeah! That&#039;s it. Culture. You see the culture&#039;s the same.

WASHBURN: Sal, you told me once that you remember when Frank González came out
here for the first time.

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah.

WASHBURN: Where did you meet him for the first time?

CHÁVEZ: It was a large family. They came from--. I don&#039;t know where the hell
they came from.

WASHBURN: He said Arizona.

CHÁVEZ: He came down here. He had a brother was a minister.

WASHBURN: For the Mexican Baptist Church, right?

DURÁN: Yeah, that&#039;s right.

CHÁVEZ: I knew him, but he always was--. Matter of fact, I remember when he
first opened up his restaurant--

DURÁN: That&#039;s on Tenth Street.

CHÁVEZ: --he wanted me to go and work, washing dishes. I said, &quot;Bullshit. I&#039;ve
got a barber&#039;s chair. I don&#039;t want to be washing--. I&#039;m not a {_______?} guy.

DURÁN: He used to have a little, like one of those Pullman cars, in it. That&#039;s
what he opened his Mexican place right there on Tenth Street.

WASHBURN: Yeah, he told me about that. So where did you meet him for the first
time, Sal?

CHÁVEZ: I met him at--. Where the hell did I meet him? I don&#039;t remember. Like I
said, he had that store that he had. There used to be a hospital there a long
time ago, on Bird Avenue, where we have what it was at. He wanted me to go out
there and wash dishes. I said, &quot;No thank you.&quot; He said, &quot;We&#039;ll teach you how to
cook.&quot; And I said, &quot;Uh-uh. I&#039;m a barber.&quot; He got that place.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s one of the questions I had for you, Sal. You kind of have a
unique kind of past because you&#039;ve been living here this whole time. And all
these people moved here and the town grew from small town to a city. What was it
like for you to see all these people come into your town - like Frank González,
and like Mr. Durán.

CHÁVEZ: Well, I mean, you know, you didn&#039;t think nothing of it because they
moved into town and you got to be friends. But, I mean, there was never any
grudges because they were here. It was: &quot;Oh, we&#039;re the new neighbor.&quot; &quot;Oh, hi,
how are you.&quot; That was it.

WASHBURN: Mm-hmm. It was real friendly.

DURÁN: I followed him--. When I knew he was a barber, I&#039;ve been following him
all over hell just to get a haircut.

WASHBURN: Just to get yourself a haircut?

DURÁN: We&#039;re very good friends, him and I.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s nice.

CHÁVEZ: We&#039;ve known each other for years now.

DURÁN: Ever since hospital days.

WASHBURN: So for you--. You came here in--

DURÁN: &#039;45.

WASHBURN: You lived in &#039;45. I remember asking Polly Russell what it was like to
live out there on Hubert, and she says that--

DURÁN: It was a nice neighborhood.

WASHBURN: It was a nice neighborhood, but there weren&#039;t many Mexican folks who
lived out that way.

DURÁN: Oh yeah. No, there weren&#039;t. I agree with you. There weren&#039;t. We used to
have friends that I made there, neighbors, you know. Cash.

WASHBURN: Cashes, like Johnny Cash.

DURÁN: Like Johnny Cash, yeah. And I used to have Sisks.

WASHBURN: But when you guys were friends, did you ever go down to Barrett Avenue
and go visit him down there?

DURÁN: When he was in Barrett?

WASHBURN: Yeah.

DURÁN: At the barbershop? No.

CHÁVEZ: Definitely you&#039;d always see him at the barbershop.

DURÁN: I knew where he lived though.Your sister. I used to go down the barbershop.

WASHBURN: What I&#039;m trying to understand is how much people went back and forth
across town. And how much would you go over to Frank González&#039;s restaurant or
something like that.

DURÁN: I went there because I knew Frank González real good, and the minister.
I knew them all. Fact is, you used to go to González restaurant, George Miller,
the senator. The old man.

WASHBURN: George who?

DURÁN: Miller. He was a senator and he used to see my girls and he used to give
them money and give them candy, you know, buy them candy. George Miller, the old man.

WASHBURN: So he used to go over there to Frank González&#039;s restaurant?

DURÁN: Yeah, he used to go down there. This one here goes down there too, I
think. I don&#039;t know. I get a Christmas card from George Miller every year.

WASHBURN: Oh, you do?

DURÁN: Mm-hmm. I knew him pretty good. Another guy I knew too, that I&#039;ve got a
picture of him. Senator Nejedly. I&#039;ve got a picture of him, cause we were in the
{__} and we took a picture. {Nella Bianco} introduced me to him.

WASHBURN: Sounds like you know some neat people.

DURÁN: First time I went to the hospital, Nello came up and told him, and then
I got a card from Washington DC from Nejedly. &quot;Ned, hope you get better.&quot; Stuff
like that.

WASHBURN: So, do you remember--. Franklin&#039;s always said he was a leaderman, a
foreman at the shipyards before he opened the--.

DURÁN: I don&#039;t remember him. I was in the outfitting dock. I was in the boilermaking.

CHÁVEZ: It was a large family.

WASHBURN: What, the Gonzálezes?

DURÁN: Oh yeah. Fact is, one of his sons is a principal in the school right
there. Chávez? Yeah, his name is González.

CHÁVEZ: He had a sister that went in the airforce, huh.

WASHBURN: Oh really? Who? Rose?

CHÁVEZ: I dunno.

WASHBURN: I know Rose. I know Evelyn.

DURÁN: The one that worked at the--what&#039;s the name of that restaurant out
there? She used to work there. On San Pablo, by Lucky&#039;s. What was the name of
that restaurant? That Mexican restaurant at San Pablo. Right across from
Safeway. Remember the name of it? She used to work there. His sister.

WASHBURN: It wasn&#039;t González&#039;s restaurant?

DURÁN: No. What was the name of it.

CHÁVEZ: Oh, I know what you&#039;re talking about. It served both American and
Mexican food. It was right on the corner. What the hell was the name of it? You
can&#039;t miss it, it&#039;s by Safeway. What the hell. I got the name--The owner of the
place is Portoguese.

WASHBURN: Think of something else and it will come back to you. That&#039;s how
memory works.

DURÁN: I think her name was Rosa, used to work there.

WASHBURN: I know a Rose that&#039;s in that family. She worked in the shipyards too
for a while. But, you know, it&#039;s interesting. I&#039;ve talked to Frank a little bit,
but not as much as I like, and he said he used to work as a leaderman. He said
he worked in the shipyards from &#039;43 so he was there quite a while. But, do you
ever remember what it was like to work there and get promotions and stuff like
that? I guess him working there for a while helped him out.

DURÁN: I&#039;ll tell you one thing. There were a lot of people. Fact is, Kaiser
wasn&#039;t, what you call it? Used to promote people regardless of nationality.

WASHBURN: He didn&#039;t discriminate?

DURÁN: He wasn&#039;t discriminating. He had no bias against anything. They used to
have leadermen blacks. All mixed, right there. He didn&#039;t care. He had the people
working, and--let&#039;s face it--he done a good job. I think he&#039;s the one that had a
lot to do with Richmond being what it is now, very liberal. As far as
discrimination is concerned.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s interesting. You say that because he promoted a lot of people?

DURÁN: That&#039;s right. See, a lot of these companies, they didn&#039;t promote
minorities like that for a big job. You know. Just the big one, that&#039;s all, see.
Regardless if they knew what they were doing or not. That&#039;s true.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve read, though, that the black leadermen were only allowed to be
leadermen for a black crew.

DURÁN: Oh no, no, no.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s not true? So tell me, who was your leaderman?

DURÁN: My leaderman was a Portuguese guy. I had one that was the boss--. Gee,
it&#039;s such a long time ago. He was pretty good too. The foreman, you know. Cause
the leaderman was something like an NCO [non-commissioned officer] in the army.
The captain was commander, then you had the second in command was the NCO, let&#039;s
face it. That&#039;s what the leaderman was.

WASHBURN: The foreman was below the leaderman?

DURÁN: No, he was above the leaderman.

WASHBURN: Oh, the foreman was above the leaderman, yes. Well, it seems different
about Frank González is--. Like, when I go over to his house now, we still
speak Spanish together. He doesn&#039;t want to--

CHÁVEZ: He speaks in Spanish

DURÁN: Oh, yeah?

WASHBURN: Yeah, he doesn&#039;t want to speak English. He can, but he just feels more
comfortable speaking Spanish.

DURÁN: I imagine so, yeah.

WASHBURN: But that seems kind of strange. That they promoted him to a leaderman,
even though his English wasn&#039;t so good.

DURÁN: That&#039;s it, see. He was taking care of the Spanish-speaking people, I
guess. Sal? They appointed him as a leaderman because he talked to the people
who didn&#039;t know how to speak English? I remember, see. But I tell you, Richmond
has a very historical {__} after World War Second. To me.

WASHBURN: A historical what?

DURÁN: History.

CHÁVEZ: It was just a little town, a quiet little town--.

DURÁN: Then all of a sudden, it became a metropolis now. Let&#039;s face it. All
these people that came from--

CHÁVEZ: Oklahoma.

DURÁN: Oklahoma and all that.

CHÁVEZ: Arkansas.

DURÁN: All of them. That&#039;s what makes a good country, you know. Mixed. Come on,
let&#039;s face it.

WASHBURN: Why do you think that makes a good country?

DURÁN: Because they know each other, they learn their ways, you know. The ways
of living from different nationalities.

WASHBURN: Traditions.

DURÁN: Different traditions, see. That&#039;s what makes the United States the
strongest, to tell you the truth. That&#039;s what makes it strong. Different
traditions, different views, like that, you know. Different people, they come
from other cities or other states, and you learn their ways of living, and they
learn our ways--the way of living in the West, in the South, and all over.
North. That&#039;s what makes it such a boiling point in this country.

WASHBURN: Boiling pot, yeah. A unique spot.

DURÁN: Yes. I don&#039;t understand--. Oh, there&#039;s a lot of dissension or something,
but what the heck. You always find that.

WASHBURN: But some people say about Richmond&#039;s history--I&#039;ve read this in some
books--that they think Richmond kind of went downhill after the war.

DURÁN: A lot of people say that.

WASHBURN: They kind of sum it up that a bunch of black people moved into
Richmond and it kind of got ruined.

DURÁN: That&#039;s what they say, sure.

WASHBURN: What do you guys think about that?

DURÁN: I don&#039;t know. I wasn&#039;t here then. I&#039;ve been here since they were all
here. I worked with some black people There&#039;s a couple I worked for in the post
office. And I know of some people that they treated me damn good. Policemen,
black policemen, treated me good. It all depends how you treat yourself among
people, I guess. Like El Cerrito; I know a lot of people in El Cerrito that I
always meet them and they talk to me real nice. They thought that I was
postmaster up there one time. Take care of them, you know. But still, if you get
along with people, you&#039;re going to have friends. Which I do. I have friends,
blacks, Italians, you know, different. El Cerrito, I&#039;ve got a bunch of friends
there. I know the chief of police in El Cerrito when he was just a cop.

WASHBURN: You know a lot of people. What do you think about that, Sal? You heard
that too? That people talk that way, that Richmond kinda went downhill after the
war because all these people came in and they didn&#039;t contribute to the town, or
they kinda brought it downhill.

CHÁVEZ: To tell you the truth, I didn&#039;t pay any attention. I didn&#039;t pay any
attention. Just kept on living.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s good.

DURÁN: Just like I said, see. When I was here the city council was mostly
people that worked or retired from Standard Oil, see.

WASHBURN: So they were set in their ways, kinda, huh?

DURÁN: Sure they were set. They used to say Standard Oil was running Richmond.

CHÁVEZ: They wouldn&#039;t hire anybody. But soon as the war broke out, man! They
even took guys that worked in the Sante Fe camp. They worked in the section
houses. They couldn&#039;t work in the section, they went to work in the Standard
Oil, they started to make good money, so they didn&#039;t go back.

DURÁN: Yeah, but they treated them in Standard Oil to do the manual work. Laborers.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s the thing. As pipefitters, right? Doing pipefitting and stuff
like that.

DURÁN: No, regular laborers.

CHÁVEZ: They were putting tracks in the refinery to bring trains, boxcars and
everything. So they hired all them guys.

DURÁN: The Mexicans.

WASHBURN: So they didn&#039;t contract Santa Fe? They did it themselves?

CHÁVEZ: If you get the trains or something, pull them out of the refinery, or
whatever, you know.

WASHBURN: Standard Oil started hiring Mexicans during the war because they
needed them, not because they wanted to change their ways. But because they
needed them.

DURÁN: There you go. You&#039;re right.

CHÁVEZ: They had no choice. Either hire or whatever.

WASHBURN: So, why didn&#039;t they go back to their old hiring ways after the war?
When all the soldiers came back and there were more people to work the jobs?

DURÁN: Too many people. I think too many people. Too many voters all got
politics, I guess.

WASHBURN: Political?

 Durán

It was political, you know? I think that&#039;s the deal there. I don&#039;t know, it
might not--. Maybe I&#039;m wrong.

WASHBURN: What do you mean by &quot;it got political&quot;?

DURÁN: That&#039;s the time when the people started to vote, and they started to
vote for people that they wanted to get in. Get these people out of there that&#039;s
running the--. The way they were running Richmond.

WASHBURN: The old-style folks.

DURÁN: The old-style, sure.

WASHBURN: That makes sense.

DURÁN: There still is a lot of politics going on, anyway.

WASHBURN: Everywhere there&#039;s a lot of politics, sure.

DURÁN: I remember one time when Richmond didn&#039;t have a black councilor at all
during that time. All of a sudden, look at it. Even the mayor.

CHÁVEZ: [chuckles] That&#039;s it, see! I can&#039;t believe it.

DURÁN: This one they have in Richmond--Anderson--I used to know her husband. He
was a reverend. Reverend Anderson. Wonderful guy. He used to go to El Cerrito
post office and talk to me. Give me advice and all that. Real nice guy. You know
the councilman Bates? Well, Bates and I worked together in the post office in
Richmond. He worked in the post office with me. He was a clerk. But the trouble
is, see--. One time there was no Mexican descent in the city council.

WASHBURN: No Mexican descent?

DURÁN: Yeah. So we finally put in--. What was his name, on the city council?

CHÁVEZ: The Mexican guy?

DURÁN: I know him good. His wife--. John, John Marquez.

WASHBURN: When was that?

DURÁN: That was in the last ten years, five years.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s quite a long time for there not to be--.

DURÁN: Vera Montes is there. But the trouble is, it&#039;s up to the Mexican people.
About six of them were running at one time. That throws the Mexican vote all to
hell. One guy, a guy named Bustos, he was running, you know.

CHÁVEZ: He died, huh?

DURÁN: Yeah. And I told him, &quot;What&#039;s the matter with you guys? Why six guys
running? Put one guy at a time. And then everybody will vote. This way you&#039;ve
broken the Mexican vote all to hell, you know.&quot;

WASHBURN: Yeah. That makes sense.

DURÁN: It does, you know. Cause with six, you can&#039;t--. I don&#039;t know, the
voting--. Politics and religion don&#039;t mix.

CHÁVEZ: It&#039;s $1.41 for gas across the street.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s not bad.

CHÁVEZ: I want to fill it up. Look, that&#039;s why I put my glasses. So I could
see. A dollar forty-one.

DURÁN: I paid a dollar forty-seven. That&#039;s not bad. At that place over there by
San Pablo. Is that it?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah.

DURÁN: And don&#039;t send it back.

CHÁVEZ: Sit down and rest a while. Talk to the man about--.

WASHBURN: It&#039;s real nice to know--. I&#039;m doing some history on the Mexican
community in Richmond. Do you mind if I give you a call some time if I have any
other questions?

DURÁN: Why, sure. Any time.

WASHBURN: Yeah? That would be real swell. You know, Frank González is helping
me out cause he&#039;s been around a real long time.

DURÁN: Like I say, I don&#039;t know--. I&#039;ve been here since &#039;45 so the only thing I
know is--.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s all right. That&#039;s what Sal&#039;s here for - to tell me everything
before &#039;45, right?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

DURÁN: He was born and raised here.

WASHBURN: I mean, Sal, I&#039;m surprised that you weren&#039;t more uneasy about all the
new folks that came into town.

CHÁVEZ: Well, the new folks that came into town, they landed in--. They went
and got a job in the section. Right away they got a job there, and man right off
the bat you go to the commissary. You know, the Holmes Supply. They used to buy
groceries and, boy, they used to--. They&#039;d buy food. And before you knew it they
were up to here in the bill. So they had to pay.

WASHBURN: You sound like you were used to seeing people coming in and out of the
section houses.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, but then some of them lasted a long time. Some of them did last a
long time. I was born in the Santa Fe camp.

DURÁN: When I was 17 and 18, I worked in the section. I took the old track from--

WASHBURN: Where did you work in the section?

DURÁN: That was back home. I was 17 or 18. They were taking an old track in
Walsenberg, Colorado, and that&#039;s where I got my social security number.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s interesting. Let me write down your first name here. I got your
last name, but what&#039;s your first name?

DURÁN: Ernesto or Ned. I&#039;m known as Ned.

WASHBURN: Okay. I&#039;ll put down Ned. What&#039;s your phone number?

DURÁN: 2-3-4 8-4-9-9

WASHBURN: Yeah, it&#039;s a pleasure talking to you.

DURÁN: Same here. What&#039;s your name?

WASHBURN: David, David Washburn.

DURÁN: Same here, Mr. Washburn. Take care.

WASHBURN: Good-looking haircut.

DURÁN: He&#039;s a good barber.

WASHBURN: Yeah, he is.

DURÁN: One of the best.

CHÁVEZ: Oh, come on!

DURÁN: I&#039;ll see you, huh.

WASHBURN: All right. Have a good day, goodbye.

[Conversation in Spanish between Chávez and another client.]

WASHBURN: All right, Sal. I&#039;m going to get some lunch. Get a bite to eat.

CHÁVEZ: Go ahead. I&#039;ll be here till 5. No, I&#039;m going to go home at 4:30.
Today&#039;s Friday. I&#039;ll be here.

[tape interruption]

WASHBURN: Here we go. [tests and adjusts record level]

CHÁVEZ: Buy groceries or whatever.

WASHBURN: Let&#039;s talk for half an hour more, then I&#039;m outta here.

CHÁVEZ: Oh, it&#039;s all right. It&#039;s not going to make any difference.

WASHBURN: Again, I really appreciate how lenient you&#039;ve been, how nice you&#039;ve
been with letting me come in here.

CHÁVEZ: Durán, you see.

WASHBURN: Oh yeah. I&#039;m gonna meet him. Great guy.

CHÁVEZ: He knows a lot. He knows all about the army regiments and so and so.

WASHBURN: And politics and everything like that. Can I turn this down a tiny bit
here. I won&#039;t turn it down all the way, just turn it down like that. [turns down
radio in the background] So, I talked to you about pretty much everything,
except for everything after the war, so it&#039;ll be easy just to talk about that
stuff. One thing I never talked to you about was where you met your wife.

CHÁVEZ: In a cannery.

WASHBURN: You met her at the F&amp;P?

CHÁVEZ: At F&amp;P, uh-huh. I mean, I just saw her there, and I kind of took a
liking to her, you know? And then my brother-in-law, at that time he was going
around with her sister. He&#039;s a real good friend of mine--we went to school
together and all that--so I asked him, you know, &quot;How about me coming down with
you some time?&quot; And I did, and I met her. Then we started to go back and all
that. Five years.

WASHBURN: You met her before the war? You said you worked in F&amp;P before the war, right?

CHÁVEZ: I worked before and after.

WASHBURN: So did you met her before the war?

CHÁVEZ: No, I met her after the war.

WASHBURN: So after you got out of the coast guard, let&#039;s go from there. After
you got out of the coast guard, what was your first job?

CHÁVEZ: I went to work in the cannery.

WASHBURN: Okay. So you went to work in the cannery. Doing the same thing you did?

CHÁVEZ: The same thing as before I went in. I used to drive, you know, a
forklift, and then after I&#039;d finished the forklift, I used to go out in the
summertime, the season was over, and we&#039;d stay there and fix boxes. Fix the
boxes that were broken and everything. And that&#039;s it. And then I met my wife,
like I said, I saw her and on my break I used out there and talk to her, cause
she was working in the canning department. Then, like I said, my brother-in-law
at that time, he was going with her sister. So I asked him, I said, &quot;Take me
down sometime.&quot; The father knew me from way back, her mother knew me from way
back, knew my family and everything, and then after I got acquainted with her I
used to go and visit her. One time, my sisters, they both went up there to
listen to her mother and talk to her and all that kind of thing. That&#039;s when we
were getting, you know. So, we got married. We got married in &#039;48. June 20th.

WASHBURN: June 20th, 1948. So where did her family live, then, in Richmond?

CHÁVEZ: She lived on First Street. And then at the old Santa Fe camp. That was
right close by.

WASHBURN: That brings up something I wanted to ask. You said that there were
about fifty families that lived in the Santa Fe camp.

CHÁVEZ: I don&#039;t think there was that many. I think there was only 30-some odd
rooms, that&#039;s all.

WASHBURN: Thirty-some odd units?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: So maybe thirty families.

CHÁVEZ: Some guys lived by themselves. Some guys weren&#039;t married. They were
single, so they lived alone.

WASHBURN: Lived in the room by themselves. That&#039;s a good description. How many
families lived outside in the houses around the camp as best you can estimate?

CHÁVEZ: Well, maybe one or two. They saved their money and then they&#039;d buy a
house, but they wouldn&#039;t buy--. The furthest they would be was First Street,
because they had to be by the--. In case of an emergency.

WASHBURN: What I&#039;m asking is--. You said that there were about thirty units in
the Santa Fe.

CHÁVEZ: But they weren&#039;t full all the time. There were some times guys would
quit. Nobody got laid off, they just quit. They didn&#039;t want to work any more or
they got a better job that paid more money.

WASHBURN: You said you&#039;re wife&#039;s family lived there on First Street, and your
family knew each other from way back when. As best you can estimate, how many
Mexican families do you think lived in that part of town? As best you could estimate.

CHÁVEZ: I couldn&#039;t--. About twenty families or more. They lived around A, B, C
Street, First Street, Second Street. Close to the section house. But most of
them didn&#039;t work on the railroad. Some of them had jobs out there, different places.

WASHBURN: At the foundry and such.

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh, uh-huh.

WASHBURN: So you maybe say twenty families or so? You can&#039;t estimate?

CHÁVEZ: About fifteen. But they had thirty-seven--

WASHBURN: How about this: would you say few enough that you felt like you knew
all of them?

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah.

WASHBURN: Few of them, like you knew all of them.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah. Uh-huh. You got to know the husbands and all that, and the
families, you know. The kids.

WASHBURN: Well, that&#039;s a good way to ask it. So, before the war, did you feel
like you pretty much knew all the Mexican families that lived in Richmond.

CHÁVEZ: Oh, yeah. Some of them who lived over there on Second Street--. Yeah,
we knew them all. Either you knew them because you saw them in church and talked
to them, or in school, or you bumped into them.

WASHBURN: But after the war that&#039;s not necessarily the case, huh?

CHÁVEZ: No. After the war everything was different, you know what I mean. Even
a lot of the kids we went around with, you know, went in the service and when
they got out of the service their attitude changed sometimes. One, my
brother-in-law, his attitude changed. He used to be serious as all heck, old
Frank. Nice guy. He&#039;s got two. His kids are big.

WASHBURN: I guess I&#039;m trying to ask--families like Ned Durán and Frank
González came into town, and so how were you able to keep track of all the new
Mexican families that came into town?

CHÁVEZ: Oh you wouldn&#039;t know. Like there was a lot of Mexican families that
have moved over here or arrive. I don&#039;t know them any more. You don&#039;t known them
because, some of the kids, they&#039;ve already grown up. They have their families
and everything, see. And most of the people my age are gone.

WASHBURN: But it sounds like you knew everybody down there on A and B Street and
such, but people like Ned Durán, who moved over to Huber--

CHÁVEZ: Moved out here in a different--

WASHBURN: So how would you have known him?

CHÁVEZ: They were grown up. You met them when they were already grown men,
married and all that.

WASHBURN: I guess I&#039;m just trying to get at--. You know, people talk about how
many folks came to Richmond and how it increased in such a big way. The best
example of that is how many black people came to Richmond. I guess I&#039;m just
trying to understand because, you know, you&#039;ve lived so long in Richmond, how
big the Mexican-American community got because of all the people that came to
Richmond. Like Frank González, like Ned.

CHÁVEZ: They had a lot that came from different parts, Arizona. They came down
here to work, to get a job out here in the Bay Area, and most of them did. But,
like I say, Arizona, New Mexico, and all that they came over here and then they
settled over here.

WASHBURN: But would you say there were so many there was no way you could get to
know all of them?

CHÁVEZ: No. Most of the time you&#039;d meet them in church. The new people, you&#039;d
meet them in church. When they have some kind of a function, and then you&#039;d meet
them there and they&#039;d start talking. You know, you&#039;d get acquainted and then
you&#039;d know each other. And also, in church there&#039;d be a lot of people. You have
different masses that you go to, and sometimes you go to a different mass and
you run into somebody, &quot;How are you doing?&quot; and you get acquainted and all that.
That&#039;s it.

WASHBURN: Someone new. For instance, Frank González, he went over there to the
Mexican Baptist Church and you never went there.

CHÁVEZ: No. That&#039;s right. But I didn&#039;t know Frank that well. I knew when he
came over here, and I think his brother played ball. They were good ball players
and all that. He had a grocery store, on Second and Barrett right on the corner.
La {Maravilla}

WASHBURN: What side of Barrett? On the west side or the east side of Barrett?

CHÁVEZ: On the west side. He wanted me to go work in the restaurant washing
dishes. I said I&#039;m not going to wash dishes.

WASHBURN: Yeah, you told me that. So you worked the cannery for a while, you met
your wife there, and then would you say your first big job after the war was
working at the foundry.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, I did work at the foundry. But see, also I went to barber
college, and I had my apprenticeship license. You&#039;ve got to work eighteen months
apprentice, then you go for a journeyman. But I didn&#039;t have eighteen months; I
only had maybe six or seven months because I wasn&#039;t making any money. I&#039;m
learning how to cut hair. At the time I think haircuts were a buck and a
quarter, or something. I wasn&#039;t making any money, so I went to work. That&#039;s when
I got the job in the foundry. Then after that, I said, &quot;Heck, I&#039;m going to be a
barber so I&#039;m going to go to barber college.&quot; So I went and got my license. Then
I worked. Then I worked, and I said, &quot;What the hell am I doing here, busting my
back? I&#039;m gonna go cut hair.&quot; So I started to cut hair, and I worked at a store
on Second and Macdonald. I started there. That&#039;s it. I&#039;ve been barbering since 1948.

WASHBURN: You didn&#039;t have many jobs after you got out of the service, until you
started entering the barber business, huh?

CHÁVEZ: I had jobs I used to go and work on the ranches and all that sort of stuff.

WASHBURN: Right after the war?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, but not steady. Maybe one day.

WASHBURN: What would you do?

CHÁVEZ: Go out there and cut the lettuce and all that kind of stuff. And then,
like I said, &quot;What the heck,&quot; I said. I got my Public Law 16 that was {high up?}
and I went to school. Then after that I said, &quot;Lord knows, I&#039;m going to stick to
it,&quot; and then I got cutting hair. And I&#039;ve been cutting hair ever since. So I
guess I&#039;ve cut many heads, huh?

WASHBURN: Tons! So you said you worked at the foundry for how long?

CHÁVEZ: Not too long, because I got sick. For about six months.

WASHBURN: Tell me what it was like, working at the foundry.

CHÁVEZ: Too hot. You know, you work in a foundry, it&#039;s nothing but a furnace.
And I was forklift, and that means you stick the tub inside of the furnace, and
every time you open up the door to put the tub in there, boy, that heat would
hit your face. My God! You know, I used to wear a little medallion? That little
medallion would get red.

WASHBURN: Wow!

CHÁVEZ: You get out there--hot! You got to push. One guy would be on one side
and the other side, and when the guy pushes the buttons, and that opens the door
and you stick the tub in there. You have like railroad, you know, iron things to
here, and you put the tub on that. Sometimes it sticks and you have a hellish of
a time. Out there on there on that fork, is a long ways. You&#039;ve got to {__} the
other guy. And then after that then you find it breaking loose and you&#039;ve gotta
put it in the cradle--that&#039;s that little thing.

WASHBURN: It&#039;s tough work.

CHÁVEZ: Then the guy would enamel it fast. They were six hour shifts, but I
used to make good money.

WASHBURN: They paid pretty well?

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah. I was making good money. I didn&#039;t have no lunch. I had no
break time. I just hit and run. You know. You want to go and get a candy bar, a
sandwich. You never had a chance to eat a sandwich. But always, what I used to
do--. I used to take oranges. They&#039;d be cut, you know. And then we had a
drinking fountain. They had a lot of ice out there. That&#039;s where I used to put
my bag with the oranges in there. So every while I&#039;d go out there and get me an orange.

WASHBURN: Nice and cool.

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah, that&#039;s it.

WASHBURN: Did that pay as well as the shipyards?

CHÁVEZ: Better.

WASHBURN: It paid better?

CHÁVEZ: It paid better than the shipyards. See, they were six-hour shifts, like
I said. I don&#039;t remember, but I was making good wages.

WASHBURN: Over a dollar an hour?

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah. Way over a dollar. And then you&#039;d by the tubs. Six hours. I
don&#039;t know how many tubs we used to put out. When you got that run you don&#039;t
even--you go to the toilet and you hurry right back.

WASHBURN: Did you get paid by the hour or by the tub? Did you get piecework?

CHÁVEZ: We used to get piecework. Yeah, it was piecework. So naturally when you
got the piecework, you&#039;ve got the reamer and everybody you got to make the money
so you don&#039;t kill yourself, but you work in rhythm.

WASHBURN: So how long did you work there for?

CHÁVEZ: For about six months or more, then I got sick.

WASHBURN: What did you get sick with? Did you get something in your lungs?

CHÁVEZ: No. I just had a stomach trouble and all that kind of stuff. Every week
you&#039;d change the shift. They were six hour shifts; you go in like, say, six
hours around the clock.

WASHBURN: Were a lot of folks getting sick working there?

CHÁVEZ: A lot of guys can&#039;t stand the heat. That thing is hot in there. The
only thing I liked about that job was after, you&#039;d go and take your shower. I
used to stay in that shower. Take my clothes off and put them on hangers, you
know, cause they&#039;re all wet. Next thing you&#039;d go to them, they&#039;d be stiff as
heck. You could see right here on the creases of the shirt--salt. That&#039;s why
they have salt pills. When I got sick, I was taking too many salt pills. And
then drinking water.

WASHBURN: You told me you lived in the Santa Fe camp up until you got married.

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: But you said your pop died before you got married.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, he did. He died before I got married.

WASHBURN: So how did you guys stay in that house unless you guys were working
for the railroad?

CHÁVEZ: I still had my brother-in-law.

WASHBURN: He was working for the railroad?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, he was a foreman, there, working there. So I had a room there,
and any time they wanted the room they could take it, but in the meantime, you
know what I mean, I was there. And I met my wife and then got married. Then
after I got married, I rented a house. No I went in the housing there.

WASHBURN: Where did you guys move?

CHÁVEZ: To the housing authority.

WASHBURN: You moved in the housing authority? Tell me about that.

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh. I didn&#039;t last there too long because, my brother-in-law, he
owned three houses. He owned three homes, and so what happened was that I only
lived about a month there in one of the housings, and then he got a vacancy and
said okay, so I moved in there. And I stayed there until I had enough money and
we bought a house.

WASHBURN: Where was that house that he had?

CHÁVEZ: It was 106 Chancellor. First Street.

WASHBURN: One-oh-six First Street or 106 Chancellor?

CHÁVEZ: One-oh-six Chancellor. Right there.

WASHBURN: Where was that housing authority that you lived in?

CHÁVEZ: The housing. Right by there. See, he lived on Chancellor at the end of
town, and at the end of town was where the housing started. You know what I
mean? At Sixth and Chancellor--. It would be, I think it was First Street over
here and also over here, and then over here was--.

WASHBURN: Is that Atchison Village?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, that&#039;s the village.

WASHBURN: So you lived there for a while?

CHÁVEZ: No.

WASHBURN: You didn&#039;t live there?

CHÁVEZ: No, uh-uh.

WASHBURN: Do you remember Atchison Village being built, or were you in the
service when that happened?

CHÁVEZ: When they had that, it was hard to get in. They had a list a mile long.
Then you had to wait, wait, wait. So, I put my name in there, but I had a long
time to wait. In the meantime, my brother-in-law got a vacancy so I rented from
him and then from there I bought a house.

WASHBURN: I&#039;ve read about Atchison Village, that it was mostly white people who
lived Atchison Village. Is that true?

CHÁVEZ: I don&#039;t know.

WASHBURN: You don&#039;t know?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-uh. So then when I moved to 106 Chancellor--. I was still on
Chancellor, it was six-thirty, six-something, 636 or something. Then after that
I said as soon as I&#039;ve got enough money, we bought a house. So from there, I
went to my house, and I&#039;ve been there ever since. Twenty-eight years.

WASHBURN: Where did you buy a house?

CHÁVEZ: On Tara Hills.

WASHBURN: Is that out here in El Sobrante?

CHÁVEZ: No, no. That&#039;s over there on Tara Hills.

WASHBURN: In Richmond? Tara Hills in Richmond?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: If you were just starting out barbering, how did you get the money to
buy that house?

CHÁVEZ: I had money.

WASHBURN: You had some money?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, I had money.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s good. Did you get a loan?

CHÁVEZ: No, I didn&#039;t get no loan. I didn&#039;t buy it cash. I don&#039;t think I--. No,
no. We didn&#039;t get--. No, I don&#039;t remember. But I know that--. My wife took care
of all that. I said, &quot;I ain&#039;t gonna be paying rent.&quot;

WASHBURN: Tara Hills. Is that down there by A and B and all that, or that&#039;s
farther away?

CHÁVEZ: No that&#039;s over here in San Pablo.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s over in San Pablo?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: Is that where you still live now?

CHÁVEZ: I still live there, yeah. Over here, it&#039;s a nice area. I like Tara Hills.

WASHBURN: So what was that like, then, moving from where you had grown up your
whole life to out there in Tara Hills?

CHÁVEZ: I liked it. Better. Liked it better. More privacy, and more room, and
quiet, and everything. Course, you know, you&#039;re older then. By then you&#039;ve
settled down and then married, so--. We raised a family. They lived here. And
each one of them got their own house now.

WASHBURN: How many rooms is in that place?

CHÁVEZ: Right now?

WASHBURN: Then, when you bought it.

CHÁVEZ: Where I live?

WASHBURN: Yeah.

[mail carrier comes in]

WASHBURN: I&#039;m interested in how many rooms.

CHÁVEZ: In my house?

WASHBURN: Yeah.

CHÁVEZ: Well, let&#039;s see. Two bedroom. No, no, no. Three bedroom. Three bedroom
home. It was pretty big, and then I got a pretty big yard. Big yard. Then I have
eight big--. I got a helluva nice looking house.

WASHBURN: So what was that like compared to the place down there in the camp?
How many rooms were in your place in the section house?

CHÁVEZ: You had two rooms. It was like every room was a room, you know. You had
a double and you had over here one room and two rooms, that&#039;s it. When you
walked in there was a kitchen, and then over here was the bedrooms.

WASHBURN: To the right.

CHÁVEZ: That&#039;s it.

WASHBURN: So there was a main room for the kitchen and then off that there were
two bedrooms or one bedroom? Two bedrooms?

CHÁVEZ: Two bedrooms, yeah. But in the same room.

WASHBURN: It was all one?

CHÁVEZ: It was all one room, uh-huh.

WASHBURN: So, one room. So you had your kitchen table and everything, and your
beds all in that same room.

CHÁVEZ: And then you had--. The stove wasn&#039;t any bigger than that chair, there.
Small. Small burners. Wood.

WASHBURN: So that place was a lot smaller than where you moved into out here in
Tara Hills

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah. Like my house, plenty of room. Double garage.

WASHBURN: Do you ever think back, thinking about growing up in that room and
think &quot;How did we ever do it?&quot;

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, but everybody usually went through that. Like I was talking to my
friend this morning, saying, &quot;Remember back in Louisiana?&quot; Like I used to live
in Santa Fe camp, we had coal-oil lamps at nighttime and all. He started
laughing. &quot;Well,&quot; he said, &quot;same thing in Louisiana.&quot;

WASHBURN: Yeah, I know. Well, I don&#039;t know, but I can imagine what that was
like. It must&#039;ve been different. I asked that because, you know, Frank González
lived down there by the--I only have a few more questions and then we&#039;ll finish
up. [tape interruption and conversation about someone who came into the shop]
What I&#039;m asking though is, Frank González lived down there down off Tenth
Street, and you lived down there. And I was talking to Josephina Ramírez, some
other woman who went to the Mexican Baptist Church, also lived down there. Now
she lives out here in El Cerrito, Frank lives up here in El Sobrante, you live
out there in San Pablo. Seems like lots of people lived down there, moved out.

CHÁVEZ: But you&#039;d be surprised how many Mexican people have got a lot of money
now. You know what I mean? Oh, sheesh.

WASHBURN: Why do you think everybody moved out of down there? I don&#039;t want to
say &quot;everybody&quot;--.

CHÁVEZ: They wanted to improve themselves. When you got out of the planta baja
you want to get out. You want to get, you know--. That&#039;s why, when I--. Renting,
then when I found this--. My daughter called me because she got married,
&quot;There&#039;s a house out here, right by me.&quot; Bought it right away.

WASHBURN: House by who?

CHÁVEZ: By my daughter&#039;s. {_____?} Street. Tara Hills. Nice place. Got nice neighbors.

WASHBURN: That&#039;s interesting. But when you first moved there, you didn&#039;t miss
living down there?

CHÁVEZ: The other place?

WASHBURN: Yeah, where you had friends. Where you could speak Spanish more often.

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, it was too quiet.

WASHBURN: What was too quiet?

CHÁVEZ: Where we moved to. Way too quiet. Cause over there was a lot of
talking, a lot of baloney.

WASHBURN: Down there by the camp housing?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah. It was nice and quiet.

WASHBURN: But you say it was too quiet. What do you mean by &quot;too quiet&quot;?

CHÁVEZ: It was nice. Nice and quiet. Before you&#039;d be out there and there&#039;d be
screeching of cars going like a bat out of hell. Then there was a big old din
where we lived by, because they slowed--airborne. They used to hit that deck and
they&#039;d slide.

WASHBURN: So you didn&#039;t miss it too much though, not being down there.

CHÁVEZ: Not now. You go out there and, heck, you wonder how come I stayed out
there. You know, all the problems they&#039;re having out there, all the robberies
and things like that. Is it four o&#039;clock already? Geesh, it&#039;s late. I wish I
could do a couple more haircuts. Aah, tomorrow&#039;s Saturday.

WASHBURN: Thanks so much for letting me interview you. It&#039;s been fantastic.

CHÁVEZ: Okay. Stop by any time you wish.

WASHBURN: I will. I really appreciate it Sal. It&#039;s been a pleasure coming by
here and meeting people, and maybe I&#039;ll call you with a few more questions.

CHÁVEZ: Any time. Call these guys, there. They&#039;ll give you--. Fact, that kid
that was here that lives in North Richmond, he&#039;d give you a lot of information.

WASHBURN: I will.

CHÁVEZ: You know, Ojeida.

WASHBURN: I will. What was his first name? Joe?

CHÁVEZ: I don&#039;t know, but he&#039;s got a large family.

WASHBURN: Last question. You and Frank and all these other people moved out. Did
you know a lot of other people who moved out of la planta baja?

CHÁVEZ: No. See a lot of them, they--. What the hell happened? I tell you what
it was, everybody moved out because something happened. I don&#039;t know what the
hell it was. But everybody had to move out of there.

WASHBURN: Out of the section housing?

CHÁVEZ: Out of the section house.

WASHBURN: Did they rip it down?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, they did. And so, my sister moved to Second Street. Yeah, Second
and Barrett. The house is still there. That&#039;s it. Then I went in the service,
and after I went in the service, I got out of the service, and I still stayed in
one of the rooms there, like I said, in the section house. Then I used to work
in a cannery, like I said. Then I met my wife and then I got married and got the
hell out of there. No more section.

WASHBURN: I don&#039;t mean how people got out of the section housing. I mean how
people moved from maybe their house down on Second and Barrett to a house in,
you know, El Sobrante or something like that. Did you know a lot of people who
moved from a house that they were renting to a house--?

CHÁVEZ: Oh yeah, to different houses, yeah. Like, a lot of people moved over
here to El Sobrante. When they said they was going to build that house here,
where they put that Fry&#039;s, he was living out there.

WASHBURN: Why did they do that? When you say they wanted to improve what was
going on.

CHÁVEZ: They wanted to get out of there, because--. You should have seen the
section housing. It was cement. Like a motel.

WASHBURN: But I&#039;ve seen some of those houses nearby on Second Street, those
don&#039;t look so bad.

CHÁVEZ: They were houses, but those weren&#039;t the section house. The section
house was cement. Then they got out of there. What happened, like my sister at
427 C Street, right by there. But then they wanted to get out of there and buy a
better house. So they bought a better house.

WASHBURN: Where at?

CHÁVEZ: They bought a house on Sixth Street.

WASHBURN: Kind of nearby.

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: Did the crime rate go up over the years? Was that the reason?

CHÁVEZ: They didn&#039;t have no crime rate. You could go out at nighttime and come
late, nobody would bother you. Like a lot of times, you&#039;d have your bicycle or
something like that and leave it outside. Nobody would take it. Now you leave it
outside and it&#039;s gone.

WASHBURN: Sure. Are you talking about before the war or after the war too?

CHÁVEZ: That was before the war. They stole them any time. Before the war or
after the war. You know what I mean. I can&#039;t remember all that.

WASHBURN: But you don&#039;t remember it being too dangerous when you lived down there?

CHÁVEZ: No.

WASHBURN: Any shootings or anything like that. Any stabbings at bars or anything?

CHÁVEZ: Only after. Shootings and fights and a lot of stuff.

WASHBURN: Yeah, it doesn&#039;t sound so good now.

CHÁVEZ: Well, I hope I helped you.

WASHBURN: You definitely helped me. You helped me a lot. And now I can be more
informed than I was before.

CHÁVEZ: A lot of things I&#039;ve forgotten, it&#039;s been so long.

WASHBURN: I believe you. Can you show me one thing real quick though on this
map. Cause I tried to go down there the other day and figure out where
everything was and I couldn&#039;t really. It&#039;s kind of a confusing map, but you can
see, here&#039;s Barrett right here, and here&#039;s Macdonald, here&#039;s Garrard. Where was
the section housing?

CHÁVEZ: It gotta be on Macdonald Avenue, and the end of Macdonald Avenue. At
the end of Macdonald Avenue, that&#039;s where it was.

WASHBURN: Was it on the other side of Garrard?

CHÁVEZ: No, on this side. It went right by it.

WASHBURN: Was it below Garrard or right above it?

CHÁVEZ: Let&#039;s see. No, it was--.

WASHBURN: In between Macdonald and Nevin?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah, that&#039;s what it was. Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: So, right there. In between Macdonald and Nevin, and bordering on Garrard.

CHÁVEZ: My friend, old Frank, he lived on 420 Garrard Boulevard.

WASHBURN: Now they&#039;ve blocked it off. They have some kind of wall. How many
buildings were there, right on that site?

CHÁVEZ: Let&#039;s see. There was one, two, three, four, five.

WASHBURN: Five complexes?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh. No, houses.

WASHBURN: Two stories?

CHÁVEZ: No, {one of them?} was two-story, but then there was regular houses. Is
that what you asked me?

WASHBURN: Yeah, I&#039;m just trying to figure out if it was like long rectangular
apartment kind of style things.

CHÁVEZ: No. They were houses. They were homes. Small homes.

WASHBURN: With pitched roofs?

CHÁVEZ: Mm-mm.

WASHBURN: But they were connected, right?

CHÁVEZ: Yeah. No, no. They were close but spaced. They weren&#039;t connected.

WASHBURN: So your place that you lived in was totally separate from the next
person&#039;s place?

CHÁVEZ: At the section house?

WASHBURN: Yeah.

CHÁVEZ: No, no. Cement. It was all one unit. They had the room.

WASHBURN: So it was one long unit with thirty rooms in it?

CHÁVEZ: Uh-huh. Then another one was over here, and another one&#039;s over here.
That was one of the biggest ones.

WASHBURN: Okay. You said there were five houses.

CHÁVEZ: I thought you meant the houses that were by there.

WASHBURN: So there was just one long one there. That&#039;s what I want to know.

[End of Interview]

  

  

  

  

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>