<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042215" dt="2018-11-30"><version>5.2</version><date value="2003-01-17" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Tom Oishi | Interview 3 | January 17, 2003</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><subject>Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</subject><subject> Community and Identity</subject><keyword>Japanese internment</keyword><keyword> shipyards</keyword><keyword> Tanforan Race Track</keyword><keyword> race relations</keyword><keyword> florists</keyword><keyword> cut flower business</keyword><keyword> diversity in Richmond</keyword><keyword> work opportunities</keyword><keyword> Kaiser Shipyard</keyword><keyword> Japanese internment</keyword><keyword> Richmond</keyword><keyword> Pearl Harbor</keyword><interviewee>Tom Oishi</interviewee><interviewer>Donna Graves</interviewer><interviewer>David Washburn</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|40(2)|50(2)|65(2)|77(2)|86(9)|107(11)|119(14)|138(2)|155(4)|166(5)|184(11)|199(7)|211(12)|228(9)|261(3)|270(8)|288(14)|311(2)|325(10)|341(1)|357(5)|373(2)|390(15)|403(15)|417(9)|439(4)|460(2)|484(8)|500(7)|517(3)|530(2)|543(3)|552(2)|562(14)|575(5)|599(6)|614(1)|627(6)|641(13)|662(2)|683(2)|696(4)|711(2)|727(5)|739(2)|756(9)|769(12)|783(2)|811(6)|900(11)|913(2)|925(3)|938(5)|949(6)|962(2)|969(7)|983(8)|998(4)|1020(3)|1034(2)|1051(2)|1180(2)|1195(2)|1213(14)|1224(5)|1247(7)|1261(13)|1280(18)|1291(5)|1304(10)|1311(14)|1326(3)|1344(10)|1358(10)|1371(3)|1384(2)|1395(1)|1408(13)|1418(14)|1436(3)|1446(10)|1468(2)|1485(9)|1494(12)|1503(12)|1526(2)|1551(11)|1567(12)|1584(5)|1599(13)|1616(11)|1633(3)|1654(4)|1672(5)|1685(7)|1716(3)|1733(1)|1747(13)|1761(5)|1788(9)|1809(3)|1824(11)|1835(5)|1854(15)|1868(2)|1879(11)|1893(12)|1902(7)|1912(3)|1927(2)|1945(5)|1963(5)|1981(9)|1996(3)|2014(12)|2029(6)|2041(3)|2056(2)|2068(7)|2078(7)|2095(9)|2103(12)|2128(8)|2141(9)|2157(13)|2171(1)|2193(2)|2205(6)|2219(2)|2233(14)|2244(10)|2256(17)|2271(9)|2289(12)|2302(5)|2321(3)|2342(8)|2353(5)|2371(2)|2386(13)|2407(2)|2422(9)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>dGvEknRle5E</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Tom Oishi grew up a native of Richmond, California, where his family owned and operated a carnation nursery. After graduating from Richmond High School, Oishi trained to work as a welder at the Kaiser Shipyards in 1941. All of the Japanese families in Richmond were forced to move to the Tanforan Race Track in San Bruno, where they stayed until they were moved to various internment camps in the western United States. The Oishi family were interned in Topaz, Utah. Oishi left the camp to work in a nursery in Chicago during the war with one of his cousins, and returned to Richmond in 1944. He was drafted by the army in 1945 and served at P.O.W. camps in California and Virginia. Returning to Richmond again, Oishi continued to work in the nursery business until the 1990s. His interview highlights the Japanese community in Richmond, Japanese internment, the flower business, his perspective on race relations during this time, and life after the war. </description><rel /><transcript>OISHI: She flopped over, she was walking and everything. She was going to go to
a--with a girl with brown hair they&#039;re going to have their little luncheon
thing. She&#039;s all {heped}. She had her hair done and everything. Whoa, she fell
down, &quot;Tom,&quot; she says, &quot;Tom!&quot; I go over there, she said--

GRAVES: Did she have a stroke?

OISHI: She had a stroke.

GRAVES: And then how long did that last?

OISHI: Well, it last a long time.

GRAVES: That&#039;s hard. Well, I want to talk about your wife later but when we get
started, I think we&#039;ve done a good job going over your family and growing up and
high school, and then we wanted to start today at the end of high school.

OISHI: The end of high school.

GRAVES: Yeah, when you started working at the dredging company and stuff.

OISHI: Oh, you&#039;re--boy, you got a memory alright! [Laughs].

GRAVES: Well, I also wrote things down.

OISHI: Oh, oh, oh.

GRAVES: Can you say your name?

OISHI: Tom Oishi, O-I-S-H-I.

GRAVES: Okay. So we were going to start with graduating from high school and
what you did when you got out of high school. Can you talk a little bit about
the end of high school?

OISHI: Well, after graduating from high school, the first thing I did was--our
nursery, we were expanding a little bit. Our nursery was expanding--my two older
brothers running the nursery. And we bought a boiler. You know, we had a little
boiler, but we had to get a bigger boiler because we had more greenhouses. And
the first thing I did was--. I took shop in school--woodshop. And I thought I
was a pretty good, you know, cabinetmaker or something. And we had pretty good
teacher there, and he showed a lot of interest in me. And you know, I was his
number one student maybe. So I came back and we needed a boiler house and I took
mechanical drawing and stuff at the high school. So I had to submit a plan
first, the plot plan of where this building is going to be: plot number and lot
number and everything else, you know, and the location and everything. I had to
submit a plan--the foundation and what kind of building it is, and since I took
mechanical drawing in high school, I was able to do it. And I brought it up to
city hall, you know. We got a permit. And I put up the building myself. I was
awfully--it&#039;s still up there. I&#039;m awfully proud of that little building.

GRAVES: I bet.

OISHI: It&#039;s over sixty years old. No, I&#039;m twenty, eighty, that&#039;s over sixty
years old, maybe I was eighteen years old at that time.

GRAVES: And the boiler was used for?

OISHI: To heat the greenhouses. I don&#039;t think we spent a lot of money on the
boiler, but we put in a lot of modern equipment. Before, all boilers would run
this steam--we had steam pumps and everything. But this one here is electric and
it&#039;s much modern. The burner was new and a little fancy. We never did get the
boiler going, then the war broke out.

GRAVES: So you all bought the boiler and you constructed that building in &#039;39?

OISHI: &#039;39, about there. I remember my brother Joe and I went to San Francisco,
some dairy or something, they had a boiler. The boiler was sitting there and we
had broker in between and, &quot;Want to buy the boiler? That&#039;s a good boiler,&quot; he
says. So we bought it. See we bought it and they says, &quot;Well, we got to move
this boiler to Richmond.&quot; So Joe and I, we went over there to San Francisco, we
knocked the bricks off and got someone to put the boiler on a truck. We hired a
truck and we brought it home. And we set it up at home, see. And by the time we
set it up and by the time we had it going, but we didn&#039;t have it going real
good. And then the war broke out.

GRAVES: You also had some other jobs after high school, can you talk about them?

OISHI: Then after that, a buddy of mine says--this might have been in &#039;39 or
something, &#039;40. They were just thinking about shipyards in Richmond. Maybe
shipyards was started in very small way. This fellow in business--this was his
private business--he&#039;s going to open up a school. They need welders, he&#039;s going
to charge so much. I had to come up with, I don&#039;t know, a couple hundred dollars
or something. You give the man, and he taught us how to weld. And not only flat
welding, vertical, over head. And he bought us--no, we had to buy the welding
mask and gloves and leather jacket, leather suit. And we took a course, I don&#039;t
know how long the course was, couple months I guess.

GRAVES: Every day?

OISHI: Everyday for maybe one month or two months or something.

GRAVES: How many other students were in this school?

OISHI: Well, maybe he had about ten booths. Maybe every student don&#039;t go all day
long, maybe they just go four hours a day. He might of had three different
shifts going.

GRAVES: So, if the classes were just a few hours a day, were you working another job?

OISHI: Well, I used to help at home.

GRAVES: And you were taking the welding classes because you thought maybe you&#039;d
make more money than working in the nursery?

OISHI: No, I don&#039;t know, I think a buddy of mine recommended it to me, see. And
I was naïve, I didn&#039;t--I thought I was American citizen, I took civics and I
figured, you know, I was born here. But my brothers and them, they were older,
they knew, they knew they were Japanese, there would be discrimination--they
accepted it. But I did not accept it. So I got burned. That&#039;s how Korematsu was.
You know Korematsu? He was a welder too. He didn&#039;t accept it. He said, &quot;No, our
civics teacher said, &#039;We have our rights.&#039; Born here, you&#039;re an American citizen.&quot;

GRAVES: So, you were taking the welding class, thinking that you were going to
maybe contribute to the war effort and this was your naivete.

OISHI: Yes. And then I think my brother George, he might have twenty-six,
twenty-seven years old. They started a draft, just like now they&#039;re talking
about starting a draft. Now they came up, well we&#039;re going to start drafting, we
need men for the war, might be a war. So he was kind of early one to leave,
picked up. They choose numbers or something and he had to go into the service.

GRAVES: Around &#039;40, &#039;41? I can&#039;t remember when the draft started then. Before
Pearl Harbor.

OISHI: He was in the army before Pearl Harbor.

GRAVES: Okay. So when you got out of this welding class, what did you do then?

OISHI: Then the welding class, they weren&#039;t hiring too many in the shipyards
then. So there was big demand--I believe the name was San Francisco Bridge
Company. It was one of the bigger dredging companies in the West Coast. They
might have had yards in Los Angeles, in Seattle. They had a big yard in Richmond
here. And I started welding there.

GRAVES: What were you making?

OISHI: Well, they had these big pipe, might have been three or four foot
diameter, twenty feet long, steel pipe, maybe half-inch, one-forth-inch in
thickness. And as they use them, they wear out and you would have to mend
them--mend the pipe--with the hose inside there. Had to mend them more so on the
ends--both ends of the pipes would be damaged more than others.

GRAVES: Would you go where those pipes were and mend them or--?

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: So not in Richmond in the yard?

OISHI: No, in Richmond. Richmond had a big yard, they had thousands of these pipes.

GRAVES: What were they used for?

OISHI: A dredge is like a ferry boat. It has a boiler. And everything is done by
steam, I don&#039;t think {inaudible} steam there. So all the pumps are done by
steam. And when they dredge, they would stir up the ground in half water and
half dirt, and they would transfer this dirt many miles away. That&#039;s what they
were being used for. Just half water and half dirt, and they would pump this
liquid to wherever they wanted to fill up. Or if they wanted to dredge the
bottom of the bay, they would have to do that.

GRAVES: Did you know other people who were working there?

OISHI: No. And then the good thing is--build my ego up. Here, I&#039;m a kid,
nineteen years old, eighteen years old, there&#039;s a yard foreman, you know
{inaudible} all the time. There&#039;s a machinist, fifty, sixty years old, good
machinist. There&#039;s a blacksmith man, you know, blacksmith. And then there&#039;s a
bookkeeper, and me. Maybe I was getting more money than those guys because the
demand for welders was so high. Here&#039;s a young kid! [Laughs]

GRAVES: You must have been a good welder!

OISHI: No, I don&#039;t know, I thought I was good. You know, I have to think I&#039;m
good. Well, there&#039;s a shortage of welders. Do you need a welder? And I worked
for them, I don&#039;t know, I might have worked six months.

GRAVES: So there were only five people--?

OISHI: Five people and then there&#039;s a lot of--five is the main backbone of the
corporation, of this yard. Maybe they have other yards or parks.

GRAVES: And what were they dredging for?

OISHI: They would dredge the bay. You know Foster City? Foster City is all
dredged land. They dredged the bay around there, pumped all that water into
Foster City. And when the ships come in, you know, the ships come into Oakland.
If they didn&#039;t dredge maybe the depth of the water would only be twenty feet.
They need maybe eighty feet, maybe a hundred feet, so they would have to dredge.
Every once in a while they would have to dredge. But now, the environmental
people, it&#039;s a big headache, dredging. They won&#039;t let them dredge.

GRAVES: So they were dredging all around the bay when you were working there?

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: So you said you worked there about six months, then what happened?

OISHI: Then I figured, &quot;Geez, I&#039;m not doing nothing here.&quot; You know, welding
pipes day after day, mending pipes, that&#039;s no fun. [Laughs] You&#039;re working all
by yourself, see. So I figured, I went to the Richmond shipyards {inaudible}.

GRAVES: Was the shipyards becoming a big thing?

OISHI: No, I think they were just making the first ship, the first ship that was
there. That was the first ship--never been launched, never been a ship launched
in this Richmond shipyard and this was 1940 year, I don&#039;t know might have been
&#039;40--yeah, might have been &#039;41, I &#039;m not sure. And at first, they have to weld
the shell of the ship, half-inch thick or something, maybe three-quarters of an
inch thick. You need a lot of heat to penetrate through that. Amperage-wise, I
don&#039;t know, four or five hundred amps you have to use. And here a {inaudible}
weld it was all done by hand. Come home, boy my eyes are burning me out. They
didn&#039;t know it well. A lot of things in those days, they were harmful to the
body and they didn&#039;t know how harmful it was.

GRAVES: Did you ever have that flash people have talked about?

OISHI: Oh, we had masks on. And we had to use the--we have a helmet, covers over
your head and you have glasses, and there&#039;s a different thickness,
different--how dark, how much light that&#039;s coming through. If you&#039;re burning
heavy plates, you have to use a very powerful glass that won&#039;t burn your eyes out.

GRAVES: So how did you get the job in the shipyard? Do you remember what that
process was like?

OISHI: Maybe the school got it--told me to go there. Yes, the school told me to
go there.

GRAVES: And when you went, did they assign you to a particular kind--?

OISHI: Yes, yes. We were doing plate welding on the ground and we&#039;d have to
kneel down, which is hard, and we were out all day long, same old place, and we
were team welders.

GRAVES: That was Yard One?

OISHI: The first shipyard there, I don&#039;t know what it was.

GRAVES: So down Canal Boulevard?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: Yeah. How would you get to work?

OISHI: Oh, I had a car, I had a car and I used to pick up fellows around here.

GRAVES: So you had neighbors who were working in the shipyards too?

OISHI: No, no.

GRAVES: Who were you picking up?

OISHI: I don&#039;t know, the fellows I used to work with, in our same department.

GRAVES: You got to know them at the shipyard?

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: So did you have a crew you worked with most of the time?

OISHI: Yes, yes. What happened, like anything else, there&#039;s a foreman, there&#039;s a
leaderman. This leaderman might have fifteen people, see, and then out of
fifteen he has at least five of them are top man, these next five are middle,
the next five they&#039;re alright. But you know, he classified them. I was in the
five, top five, see. So, when the ship was launched the shell of the ship was
made. And the ship would launch, this leaderman, his assignment: go that ship
that was launched, so I went on there. I just stood by the same leaderman. And
we started from the bottom, bottom, rock bottom, way down in the bottom--the
refrigeration and everything. And then as the ship is being made, we come up
higher and higher and higher. Finally we were around--the ship was almost ready
to go out in the ocean, see. I was doing the railing of the ship and electrical
for the electrician. But down, first I had to do work in the galley, galley is
the kitchen. Towards the bottom of the ship. And a lot of stuff is galvanized
and your way down in the bottom of that hole and air circulation is very bad,
you have to go down with the blower. The galvanized would get you sick.

GRAVES: Who were the other people on your crew?

OISHI: I don&#039;t know.

GRAVES: Were there other Japanese Americans?

OISHI: No, no, no. Most of the people were older than me, older--maybe they were
thirty, forty years old. I was young kid then.

GRAVES: Do you remember if they were locals or people who came--?

OISHI: No, they came from Bay Area. I think eventually they got them from all
over the United States to come here because there was such a shortage. When I
was working there, you know, to launch a ship might take one month or something,
this is first ship. They might have been putting out a ship per day towards the
end. Our days, one ship per month we putting out. That&#039;s all we were putting out.

GRAVES: And it sounds like you got to work on all aspects of the ship.

OISHI: Yes, all aspects of the ship. So it was much more interesting than doing
plate welding.

GRAVES: So you did plate welding for a while and then switched.

OISHI: Yes, after ship after the shell was made, I started from the bottom and
work in the galley and all the way up.

WASHBURN: Well, Tom, explain too that first you worked on the ship where it was
docked and then once it was completed to a certain extent, what would happen?
You&#039;d float it and work at it--.

OISHI: Yes, it&#039;s floating on the water, and that&#039;s where we worked.

GRAVES: Right, it would go to the outfitting dock, right? Isn&#039;t that what it was called?

OISHI: First, I wasn&#039;t working on the ship itself, I was working on a flat
something, it had nothing to do with the ship. Someone else was welding onto the
ship, putting the shell on but I was doing flat welding or something, which was
hard on your eyes. Even when I was welding after ship was docked, you know the
noise, riveters, the noise is terrible. I had to wear earplugs, you know. You
come home with a headache and everything else.

GRAVES: I heard it was cold too.

OISHI: Yeah.

GRAVES: You were there in the early part of the shipyards. Were there many women
working alongside you?

OISHI: Not in my department. I don&#039;t think they were using women at that time.
This is the first ship that was built in Richmond. O&#039;Brien or something or--I&#039;m
not sure. Maybe you have the name?

GRAVES: I have it somewhere but it wasn&#039;t the O&#039;Brien, it was something else.

OISHI: O&#039;Brien might be the one that&#039;s in San Francisco.

GRAVES: Did you think about going to college?

OISHI: I didn&#039;t because what happened was my older cousins and friends, they go
to UC Berkeley and get a degree. They come out, if they were doctors, they were
alright they can open up practice If they were accountants, maybe they can open
accounting office. If they were dentist, they could open up their own practice.
If they were engineers, there&#039;s no future for them. If it was schoolteachers,
they would not accept Asians. You could not get a county job, you couldn&#039;t get
into the fire department, you couldn&#039;t get in a city, state, nothing.

GRAVES: So it didn&#039;t seem like college was going to benefit you?

OISHI: Yes, these people getting out of college, they would have to work in the
fruit stand or laundry or go gardening.

GRAVES: What about your siblings, what did they do?

OISHI: We had a business so my brothers went into, you know, help the business.

GRAVES: And your sisters?

OISHI: They helped too. No, my sisters, one was a beautician. She went to beauty
college and I think and that shortened her life. You know, you go to beauty
college and those days, you use all kinds of chemicals and they didn&#039;t know how
harmful it was. And maybe that&#039;s where she had got her cancer. She had passed on
before she was little over sixty, see. Could have been true the chemicals that
they were using, dying hair.

GRAVES: So, back to working at the shipyards. What was it like--what were your
social relations like with the other people you worked with?

OISHI: Good. Good. I asked the foreman, foreman--maybe didn&#039;t want to ruin
me--&quot;Listen, maybe I shouldn&#039;t be working.&quot; &quot;Oh no, were you born here?&quot; &quot;Yeah I
was born here.&quot; &quot;You got citizenship?&quot; &quot;Yes.&quot; &quot;Well, you can work here.&quot; I
worked there until the last week, until I evacuated. But there was all kinds of
restrictions. Anybody was Japanese--any portion of Japanese blood in them cannot
go over to the railroad tracks.

GRAVES: Cannot go?

OISHI: Over the Santa Fe Railroad or SP Railroad Track or something, there&#039;s all
kinds of ruling, it comes out in the papers, they come pertinent to me, you
know. You can&#039;t go over so many miles. Go over the bridge you have to get a
permit. Everything, all these restrictions was coming.

GRAVES: So those followed Pearl Harbor. Can you talk a little bit about--do you
remember when Pearl Harbor happened and how you heard about it and what you
thought at the time?

OISHI: Pearl Harbor, December 7th, we came out of Japanese School, you know that
Japanese School there? No, no, I don&#039;t think I was in Japanese School. I
couldn&#039;t&#039; have been going to Japanese School at the age of eighteen or
something. I think I quit when I was fifteen or fourteen or something. Anyway, I
still remember when Pearl Harbor happened.

GRAVES: What did you think?

OISHI: Well, I just thought nothing of it. I thought nothing of it. Yeah, I&#039;m a
son of a Japanese citizen. And my folks, financially they didn&#039;t--you know, we
had a big family. They weren&#039;t able to go to Japan. They came here and that was
it. Going to Japan was like going to the moon. You go on a boat--especially if
you had money, it&#039;s not so bad, you go on first or second class. But they&#039;re in
steerage. They&#039;re at the bottom of the ship where they put the cargo. They put
the boxes up there, maybe ten high. You don&#039;t know what they eat or something,
they&#039;re down there and maybe they don&#039;t see sunlight, I&#039;m not sure what
condition they&#039;re coming back and forth.

GRAVES: So, you didn&#039;t feel a connection to Japan?

OISHI: No, no. I had no interest in Japan, I had no interest. My mother and
father and stuff are--you know, my mother used to write a lot to Japan. My
father felt this was his country. A lot of Japanese--well, one reason for it
is--well, he had little high school education or something in Japan. They
weren&#039;t farmers. A lot of people had very little education, all they knew--how
to work. And he didn&#039;t know how to work. [Laughs]

GRAVES: Yeah, we&#039;ve talked about that.

OISHI: He didn&#039;t know how to work. So he thought this was a great country. He
felt this was the best part of the United States, which is true. The climate is
good. You&#039;re next to a port. Used to tell me, &quot;Tom,&quot; he says, &quot;This place is one
of the best places in the United States,&quot; he says. &quot;Other parts of the country
are too hot, too cold, snow, freezing.&quot; I didn&#039;t know I was a kid.

GRAVES: So, you were working at the shipyards when Pearl Harbor happened.

OISHI: No, I don&#039;t think I was working at the shipyards, I must have been
working at the other company. I&#039;m not sure, it was pretty close.

GRAVES: Yes. Do you remember anyone ever saying anything to you?

OISHI: No.

GRAVES: About your being Japanese American?

OISHI: No. It was like going to high school, you know. You have your German
friends, maybe my leaderman was Italian, I&#039;m not sure, he might have been an
Italian American, nice fellow. I would like to have meet him, I never saw him
after that.

GRAVES: There were a lot of Italian Americans here.

OISHI: Yeah, but these Italian Americans was mistreated too. If their father was
an immigrant and didn&#039;t have citizenship, you know, they were treated just like
Japanese Americans.

GRAVES: Yeah, so the other big employers in the city were Chevron and Pullman
and Ford, right?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: And you were able to get hired at the shipyards, did you know other
people who--other Japanese Americans who worked at the shipyards or worked at
these other companies?

OISHI: No, they would not hire. They would not hire. You couldn&#039;t get a job at
Chevron. You couldn&#039;t get a job at Ford. You couldn&#039;t get a job at Pullman,
Certainteed. You know, none of those people would hire you, it was known.

GRAVES: So the options were pretty limited?

OISHI: I think the only reason I got on was through the school. See, you give
this man, he had to guarantee you a job. You give this $150 or something and he
guaranteed you a job.

GRAVES: So he had an in for placing his students?

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: Okay.

OISHI: So he&#039;s making money all the way around.

GRAVES: When you started working there, since we know that--well, actually, we
don&#039;t know. You think you started working there before Pearl Harbor or after? I
think from your guys&#039; earlier talk, it was before Pearl Harbor.

WASHBURN: When we talked earlier, you said some time around November you started
working there.

OISHI: Yeah, maybe, I&#039;m not sure.

GRAVES: Well, at that point, what the shipyards were doing was supplying ships
to Great Britain, to help with the war in Europe.

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: Did you have any feelings about the war? I mean, you were pretty young,
but did you support it?

OISHI: No, I think the reason why I went to the shipyards was because I wanted
to do something for the war effort. That was the main reason. I was naïve. Just
like Mariucci, they claim he&#039;s naïve. He had a broker in between there, he had
a agent in between there and he was doing everything and Mariucci was naïve.

GRAVES: This is a sports thing?

OISHI: Yeah, I don&#039;t know if you follow sports or not. Anyway, this is what
{inaudible} said last night. He was very serious, he thought he had something to
do. The agent wanted $6 million or something, you know, in Miami or somewhere,
right? Mariucci was naïve and the agent was there, that&#039;s why the guy got
ratted out. &quot;The guy tried blackmail me.&quot; So they booted him out. That&#039;s what he did.

WASHBURN: Tom, before you--.

OISHI: Oh, okay. [laughs]

WASHBURN: Back to this. When you started working at the shipyards in the first
place, the war effort in the Pacific was not quite that strong. I think Donna&#039;s
asking, when you were working there, the ships were mostly being produced for
the war effort in Europe and did you any opinions about what was going on
there--against Germany and against Italy there?

OISHI: The war was not started. Japan&#039;s ships used to come into Richmond
refinery to get oil.

GRAVES: Right, right. The United States hadn&#039;t entered the war, but the Kaiser
shipyards were supplying ships to Great Britain to fight Germany and Italy.

OISHI: I don&#039;t know, oh were they? I didn&#039;t know that.

GRAVES: But then, after Pearl Harbor, you knew while you were working at the
shipyard that what you were contributing to was the American effort?

OISHI: Yes, yes. And it was very interesting in the shipyard. The plate welding
was bad. You know, I thought, &quot;Geez man, I have to quit here.&quot; You know, this is
no good for my health. You&#039;re on your hands and knees and welding all that time.
And then as I got in there, you go through different steps of the ship. Every
week or every month is a different challenge, doing something different.

GRAVES: How was the pay?

OISHI: Pay was good. Pay was very good. Pay was $1.10 and hour. And people
working in the nursery, maybe fifty cents, twenty-five cents an hour. We work
Saturdays, we got time and a half. We work Sunday and we got double time. So
maybe for two, three months, I worked every day of the week.

GRAVES: So you were making more than your family members?

OISHI: Oh, yes, yes. That&#039;s how I make big money. But that wasn&#039;t big money. You
add up just a dollar an hour, that&#039;s only $40 a week, so you get time and a half
and, you know, and double time, you might get $80, you might get $70 a week,
that&#039;s not big money.

GRAVES: What did your brothers think about you working at the shipyard?

OISHI: One of them was in the army and one was trying to keep the nursery
running. And then I used to help with the nursery after working anyway.

GRAVES: So after Pearl Harbor, a lot of leaders in the Japanese American
communities were picked up. Did that happen here and can you talk about it?

OISHI: Yes. Well, what happened was--from Japan, there&#039;s all different class,
all different state that came to this country. They all had different education,
different thinking. But my father, and his brother and few Oshima and stuff,
they had a little education or something. And they felt, in the market they were
collecting money with a {Hemushakai}, what they call a {Hemushakai}, I don&#039;t
know what that means. They collect the money, help Japan or help Japan out. It
was legal to do that, there&#039;s no war, see. And maybe a lot of them didn&#039;t have
property. We had property. So my folks felt, &quot;Geez, this is a great country.&quot;
Maybe they were making their money and they were sending it to Japan.

GRAVES: Before the war started?

OISHI: Yes. So when the war broke out, there was names. Treasury, the State
Treasury&#039;s {inaudible} all these things and more members. My folks felt, &quot;Wow, I
don&#039;t think this is right.&quot; You&#039;re in America, maybe we shouldn&#039;t do this. So
they were not picked up, even though they were kind of leaders in the flower
industry. But the other people, they&#039;re all different thinking, see. There were
a lot of them picked up in Richmond. They came to the house. They blasted over
the West Contra Costa Times. Adachi, big flower shop, one of the better-known
retail flower shops. &quot;Oh, Adachi big spy. We found cameras in his house. We
found a Japanese flag in their album. They&#039;re spies!&quot; They took him away like a
dog. Chained him up, took him away. All of those people. But they were not found
guilty, they were not guilty. They had a trial after a couple years or
something, they were not found guilty, they were not found guilty. But it
shortened their lives.

GRAVES: And they were picked up because they had contributed before the war to
this support for?

OISHI: No, they were on this board or something and maybe this--we don&#039;t even
know, maybe this guy would give them money, maybe he was sticking half in his
pocket. You know, maybe {inaudible}. We don&#039;t know. But friends of my father,
they didn&#039;t have faith in the man so they didn&#039;t go along with him.

GRAVES: And what was the name of the organization?

OISHI: Henmushakai.

GRAVES: Henmushakai?

OISHI: Yeah, I think that was it.

GRAVES: We can look it up. Did your family have any possessions confiscated?
Cameras, binoculars?

OISHI: No, they didn&#039;t come.

GRAVES: So it was only those other families that had people picked up and things
taken away?

OISHI: But you could have cameras, there&#039;s no harm in having cameras. Anybody
could have a camera. Just like this trial in Modesto. You know that poor guy, I
don&#039;t know if he&#039;s guilty or not. This guy who killed his wife, they claimed he
killed his wife or somebody. You know, there&#039;s all kinds of stories coming up
around it. They&#039;re just presuming, they don&#039;t know what&#039;s going on anyway.
Today, they had a different story. They says, &quot;He took out a big insurance.&quot;
$200,000 insurance. [Laughs] And he had a girlfriend! He didn&#039;t go fishing, he
went to girlfriend&#039;s place. [Laughs] Everyday, it&#039;s a different story.

GRAVES: Sorry, my mind&#039;s blanking, I knew where I wanted--.

WASHBURN: Tom, why do you think nobody came to talk to your family at this time?
Why do you think your family was left alone and others weren&#039;t?

OISHI: His name was not on the board. My dad&#039;s name was not on the board. They
had a--well, they don&#039;t know, these {inaudible} guys are probably thinks the
guys are crazy. This guy&#039;s a board member so many years or something.

GRAVES: What were some of the other restrictions that were put on people? You
mentioned some earlier, but can you talk about them?

OISHI: Here in Richmond, we were in a vital war zone or something. You know,
City of Richmond or something because we had Standard, we had the shipyards. But
in Berkeley, there was no industry for war effort or something. Maybe in San
Francisco, there was none. Different areas--maybe Alameda was a naval base or
something. So different areas was restricted to Japanese Americans. Any alien,
German aliens, Italian aliens, restrictions that came up. It&#039;s all in the paper,
I guess if you read, you go and look it up.

GRAVES: Do you remember being aware of places you couldn&#039;t go?

OISHI: The only thing I couldn&#039;t go is, maybe reading the fine print, maybe I
wasn&#039;t supposed to go over certain tracks. You know, the SP track or something.
And maybe I had to be in by a certain time, eight o&#039;clock in the evening or
something, by sunset I had to be in.

GRAVES: Did you follow this curfew?

OISHI: I was working daytime so it didn&#039;t affect me that much, but I used to go
over the tracks. But it came out in the paper, not a personal letter to me. I
didn&#039;t read the paper. [Laughs]

GRAVES: So you were innocent.

OISHI: And my mother, she was an alien. Asian aliens were not able to apply for
citizenship. Or a European alien--German alien or Italian alien--they come to
this country, for a couple of years they have a clean record, they can apply for
citizenship. Those are two difference.

GRAVES: So, you mentioned something about your parents moving to Berkeley during--?

OISHI: Yes, yes. When more restrictions came out, if you go buy the newspaper or
we get a newspaper, &quot;We&#039;ve got to do this.&quot; It says, &quot;If you&#039;re Asian {or
America},&quot; was out in the paper, &quot;Richmond zone is vital, you would have to go
someplace else.&quot; So my sister was in Berkeley, so my mother and father moved to
Berkeley. But we stayed in Richmond, my brothers and I.

GRAVES: Because the children were citizens?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: But your parents had to leave.

OISHI: Yes. The restriction was not on citizens. The restriction was on Japanese
American citizens cannot go over a certain tracks, you have to be in by a
certain time. There were all kinds of restrictions.

GRAVES: Was that hard on your parents?

OISHI: No. They just went to Berkeley.

GRAVES: They went to work in Berkeley?

OISHI: No, they didn&#039;t work.

GRAVES: Oh, okay. They just lived with your sister.

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: That might have been hard for her.

OISHI: I don&#039;t think if you&#039;re a citizen, if you don&#039;t have papers you can&#039;t get
welfare or something. So all these Asian aliens, since they can&#039;t get welfare,
they have to go on and do housework and make a {inaudible}. Domestic work.

WASHBURN: Tom, who was enforcing the restrictions?

OISHI: No one. It came out in the paper. The paper says, &quot;David, you can&#039;t do
this.&quot; Paper comes out, maybe the paper&#039;s wrong, maybe it&#039;s right.

WASHBURN: Right, did anybody say, &quot;Well, no one&#039;s enforcing this, why do we have
to do it?&quot;

OISHI: Just like the highway says forty-five miles, school zone is thirty miles
an hour. You might go forty miles an hour, but a police won&#039;t see you going
forty miles an hour, he can give you a ticket, throw you in jail. Same thing.

WASHBURN: Do you remember anybody that you knew in Richmond who challenged the restrictions?

OISHI: No. We&#039;re like a sheep. {Inaudible} newspaper, &quot;All Japanese Americans in
Richmond, go to this church--Methodist church in Berkeley. Have all your baggage
packed, you can only have so much. One suitcase, go over there.&quot; Paper comes out
and says. We&#039;re like a sheep, we do that. Nobody to enforce it.

GRAVES: So as the restrictions increased--.

OISHI: It was getting tighter and tighter, but it wasn&#039;t too long. You figure in
December 7th, we were out of here in, maybe end of March. December, January,
February--we didn&#039;t have a hundred days. New restriction coming everyday. Maybe
towards the end, these restrictions came back. &quot;You can&#039;t go over the railroad,
you&#039;ve got get permit to go over the bridge.&quot; It was getting to the point where
we wouldn&#039;t be able to function.

GRAVES: Do you remember when the evacuation notice was posted? Was it put in
public places in Richmond or did you see it in the paper?

OISHI: Paper I seen. It was mostly the paper.

GRAVES: And it said you had to report to this church in Berkeley.

OISHI: Yeah. So we&#039;re like a sheep. We packed all our stuff and went over there.

GRAVES: Your whole family went together?

OISHI: My mother and father was in Berkeley, so they packed their stuff from there.

GRAVES: Can you describe that day?

OISHI: I was not too involved because I was welding. My job was very
interesting. I was doing something for this country, building a ship for us to
win the war, see. You picture Pearl Harbor come in December, January maybe not
much doing, then February things getting a little tighter. In February, maybe in
the month of February, every week, new orders are coming out. So I wasn&#039;t too
concerned. I think my job was very interesting.

GRAVES: But you had to go to the church that day in Berkeley, the same as your
family. Do you remember that day, do you remember what it was like?

OISHI: The church was very nice. A lot of people in this country--there&#039;s all
different class of people. The educated people thought this was wrong. &quot;This is
unconstitutional, their American country, they have no right to do this. They
have no right to take the property away.&quot; Other people says, &quot;Geez, these Japs
are dangerous. They might bomb us. They&#039;re a bunch of spies, you don&#039;t know what
they&#039;re going to do, they&#039;re dangerous people.&quot; That&#039;s how the propaganda from
Sacramento came out. All the General DeWitt and all these guys says, &quot;Oh, you
can&#039;t trust these people.&quot; So a person reads it, he believes it in the
newspaper. Half the people believes it, but the educated people figure they
don&#039;t, &quot;This is wrong.&quot;

GRAVES: I read that the people in that church took it on themselves to--.

OISHI: Did they? I don&#039;t know.

GRAVES: Yeah, I actually have some newspaper articles I can show you. That the
people in the Congregational Church in Berkeley wanted to offer a large space
where the Japanese Americans could come register.

OISHI: Yeah, they treated us good. They gave us coffee and tea and donuts and everything.

GRAVES: Well, what this one articles specifically says is that they were worried
that if it was in another place, Japanese Americans would be lined up outside
and that people might be unkind to them and that they would provide this.

OISHI: Yeah, if you read everything in the paper, come from the government
office, General DeWitt. We were a bunch of spies, &quot;You can&#039;t trust a Jap.&quot;
Anybody that was a Jap, &quot;You can&#039;t trust them. They&#039;re loyal to their country.&quot;

GRAVES: Do you remember anyone specifically being unkind or hostile to you or
your family at that time, because you were Japanese American?

OISHI: Well, a German friend--our neighbor was a German. We had a quite a few
German friends. But they were Germans--second generation German or they&#039;re
German that was married to an American citizen. A German immigrant that came
here and they&#039;re citizens, but still they were Germans. They were awfully kind
to us, they knew the situation that we were in. So, a lot of our personal stuff,
icebox and stoves and anything. In those days, icebox is something new, gas
range was something new, radio was something new. It maybe came out five years
before that. Refrigeration maybe came out in &#039;35 or something--first one. Radio
maybe &#039;38 or something. You know, these are something new.

GRAVES: And you had all those and you had to figure out what--.

OISHI: Yes, yes. So our German neighbor looked after most of it for us, and they
used to come to--when we were in Tanforan, they would write to us and we would
write to them, and they would bring us cookies and stuff, you know.

GRAVES: Do you remember their names?

OISHI: Barch. I don&#039;t know. Barch, I don&#039;t know. I think they were both second
generation Germans.

GRAVES: Yes, where did they live?

OISHI: Next to us. Right next to our property.

GRAVES: On--?

OISHI: Right next to George. You know where George lives?

GRAVES: Yes.

OISHI: That building there.

WASHBURN: Tom, you were still working at the shipyards right before you were evacuated.

OISHI: Yes. Maybe I didn&#039;t even get my last paycheck. I didn&#039;t get it.

GRAVES: Because you were evacuated.

OISHI: Yes. No one&#039;s there to send it to me.

WASHBURN: Can you describe two things? You had told me once before that there
were restrictions from working at that time.

OISHI: No, there were no restrictions. At that time, the government didn&#039;t get
that far, they figured the Japanese wouldn&#039;t be working at shipyards. But later
on, when I went to Chicago and stuff, or when I was in camp, I&#039;m welder. Maybe I
could do something for the war effort. I applied for a job in Salt Lake City.
Ruling came out from Washington D.C. anybody of Japanese ancestry or Japanese
blood cannot work in defense work. I think that came out later. But when I was
here, there was nothing like that.

GRAVES: I see.

OISHI: They didn&#039;t get around to it yet.

WASHBURN: And can you describe your last day at the shipyards and what you said
to your leaderman about why you were not going to be returning?

OISHI: I don&#039;t think he believed me. It wasn&#039;t a sad something. You know, there
were so many things going on and it wasn&#039;t that--I was very interested in my
job. I wanted to get out of my shop. My goal was get on this ship. The ship is
in water--it doesn&#039;t run yet. My something was, I wanted to get on the ship,
when the ship hits the water--takes a trial run, maybe a couple hundred miles--I
wanted to be on board that. And I didn&#039;t get--the ship did not leave. It was
almost complete. Everything was complete, maybe another week, couple weeks or
something, maybe they wouldn&#039;t need no welders on there, I&#039;m not sure. But that
was my goal.

GRAVES: But you were evacuated before?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: So what David was asking, you had to go to work and say why you were leaving.

OISHI: I didn&#039;t tell them--I didn&#039;t tell the fellow workers I&#039;m a Japanese
American, I&#039;m not supposed to be working here. I told this leaderman one time. I
told him. &quot;No, Tom, go to school here? High school? Born here?&quot; [Laughs] &quot;Yeah!&quot;
&quot;They can&#039;t do this to you,&quot; he says. Okay, we go over there {inaudible}. If I
was afraid someone was going to drop a wedge on my head, someone was going to
drop a plate on my head or something. You know, it wasn&#039;t that way. I was well
accepted on the ship.

WASHBURN: You said it was out in the papers, all of this stuff.

OISHI: Yeah, but--.

WASHBURN: So your leader man knew what was going on?

OISHI: No, you don&#039;t read every article in the paper. Maybe a kidnapping or rape
or something, you read every line of it, see. What&#039;s this here? What&#039;s going on?
They don&#039;t even know what&#039;s going on, so complicated. The average citizen does not.

GRAVES: So you just left. You had your last day.

OISHI: Yeah, I left. I left and then what happened was--. Here in Richmond, you
know, it was few Japanese. Sports, I was interested in sports and San Francisco
got a big--lot of people there. They had basketball teams and baseball teams and
stuff, and the Japanese more or less stuck to themselves. They couldn&#039;t
integrate with the Caucasian people. They were smaller and everything else. So
we had our own team. The different churches liked the Buddhist Hall, they had
their own Buddhist gymnasium, see. You know, the YMCA in the City, that was
built by the Japanese or something. So they had their own courts and we had
Richmond High court. Ooh, that beautiful court. They all want to play there.
Even though we were bad, they want to play us. [Laughs] You get to play on that
beautiful court. They drummed the heck out of us, because we didn&#039;t have much of
a choice of players. When we went into camp, I think pay money to go see these
people play Japanese, you know. I used to pay money to go see them. Here I go to
camp, they sat there in my camp, in my mess hall, and they took me in. Here a
young kid, these guys are thirty, twenty-five. They were their high school
stars, maybe Cal graduate catchers. They even let me play. Ooh, that was a big
honor for me, see. They let me play every inning. I was one of them.

GRAVES: This was at Tanforan?

OISHI: Yes. So I enjoyed Tanforan. And then as kid, &quot;Geez man, I&#039;m going to be a
cook after this.&quot; I started off as a coal boy.

GRAVES: Coal boy?

OISHI: Coal--we had coal stoves. And you had to go in there and light the stove
before the cooks start. I started off in there. {Inaudible} They gave me a
stove. There&#039;s four stoves. Four stoves, I got one of the stoves, last couple
months or something, maybe six months at a stove. I&#039;m a cook.

WASHBURN: This is about to end, this would probably be a good time take a break.
We have to change the tape here, Tom.

GRAVES: Before we talk more about the assembly center, I just want to ask more
about how your family arranged to have the house, your car, all of that, either
taken care of or placed somewhere.

OISHI: Actually, we couldn&#039;t think it over too much because we didn&#039;t have time.
After the war broke out, we didn&#039;t know these notices were going to come, we
didn&#039;t know what was going to come. We felt we wouldn&#039;t have to move. So it came
so fast, we had to act fast, not much they could--.

WASHBURN: Hold on one second you guys. We missed that. In between that the mic
got pulled out just a little bit there. We&#039;re going to do that again, so Tape 2!

GRAVES: Okay, so back up and talk about how you guys tried to take care of
things before you left.

OISHI: Actually, we didn&#039;t have time. We only had a hundred days after war broke
out &#039;til the time we were in camp. All the notices did not come at one time,
gradually came. We thought that we wouldn&#039;t have to go to camp. So as it came,
we accepted what the situation was. First, we had to lease or rent, let someone
take over our nursery. Piazza Flower Shop, a wholesale flower shop in Downtown
Oakland. I don&#039;t know if you would know about it or not. Market Street and maybe
around Seventh Street, Market Street, the building is still there, Piazza. We
used to sell flowers to them--Italian family, young, very aggressive Italian
American. And we asked him, &quot;Okay, we&#039;ll look after the place for you guys.&quot; But
he has his own problems so he, &quot;Okay, we&#039;ll lease it to you, you look after our
place.&quot; Maybe there was nothing in writing or anything, just word of mouth. Leo,
I believe his name was. Then Leo had, you know, other interests. So he got this
guy {Thornstead}. Maybe in Oakland, the Thornstead Flower Shop is still there,
I&#039;m not sure.

GRAVES: Thornstead?

OISHI: Yeah. Anyway, he was, in those days, he was kind of aggressive. He had
maybe two, three flower shops. You know, he was businessman. So Leo told
Thornstead, &quot;You operate this {inaudible}.&quot; So he was running it, see. But he
was no grower, he was a flower shop man. He figured he was going to get somebody
to water plants, and you&#039;re going to get this carnation cheap. But they were not
that way. So he had to struggle. At least he kept the house in fairly good
condition, living quarters, and he didn&#039;t break the glasshouse or he didn&#039;t do
no damage. They didn&#039;t steal nothing out of the house even though they had their
lot of African American people in there. I think he got reliable men, reliable
people in there.

GRAVES: Who rented the house?

OISHI: Yes, and then he rented the house and stuff to the shipyard workers, but
he wasn&#039;t making much money on carnations. At least he didn&#039;t break the
glasshouse and he didn&#039;t do no damage or he made sure that no damage was done to
the nursery or the house.

GRAVES: And what about your car, your family car?

OISHI: Things was coming so fast, we had a Chevrolet 1940, I believe. Good car,
four door car. Oh, we were proud of it. I don&#039;t know, I was twenty, {inaudible}
thirty years old. He had a &#039;36 Chevrolet before that. You know, as first car he
was a pretty young guy. And then he bought this 1940, oh, he was proud of it.
And then war broke out, and you know, there&#039;s all kind of people, classmates and
stuff. Some friends of mine, I went to school with, he says, &quot;Oh, these people
have to move. I could buy this cheaper.&quot; So he come over here, he wants to buy
my car for maybe half the price. I threw him out of the house. &quot;Get the hell out
of here!&quot; And the stove and ice box and stuff too. You know, these guys, they&#039;re
young, they don&#039;t have the money. Maybe their family don&#039;t have no good car, no
icebox, they want to buy the stuff cheap. I threw them out, &quot;Get the hell out of here.&quot;

GRAVES: So what&#039;d you guys do with the car?

OISHI: So we had to come to a conclusion: we have to get rid of the car. Maybe
week&#039;s time so I told Joe, &quot;We&#039;ll jack the darn thing up, take the tires off,
put it inside the car.&quot; {Inaudible} we put inside the car, jack it up, put the
blocks underneath there. &quot;And we&#039;ll plant trees around this garage.&quot; We had a
single garage, garage maybe, I don&#039;t know, fifteen by twenty or something. It
was a new garage {inaudible}. Well kept garage, fairly new garage. You had a
{inaudible} before. And then we nailed the door up and everything and locked up
the windows and planted trees all around the garage. And when we came back, one,
no two--four years? Two, three, four--well, over three years. When we came back.
The thing was just the way we left it. And all these albums and stuff, pictures,
were in grandma&#039;s basement. No one touched it. All of our personal stuff was
back there. Lot of people lost all their--everything they had, they lost.
Pictures are very dear to a family, to even the niece and nephews and sons.
Pictures is very dear, more than money.

GRAVES: But all your stuff was still there. That&#039;s great.

OISHI: Oh yeah.

GRAVES: So you went to Tanforan and you worked as a cook, what was that like?

OISHI: Good. Well, maybe, the pay was maybe eight dollars a month. Eight dollars
a month! That&#039;s all we got. They didn&#039;t give us enough clothes or nothing. The
government gave me eight dollars a month. Sweat, my ego was to put out good
rice. I don&#039;t know. Nine hundred people we had to feed--four stoves.

GRAVES: Wow. Did people eat in shifts?

OISHI: I think there were two different shifts. We had, well, the kitchen was
here and the dining room here, then we were on this side, see. So from the
kitchen, both sides you could go to the dining room.

GRAVES: What kind of food were you cooking?

OISHI: Rice and whatever the government gave us. We had a lot of meat and stuff.
At first, it was very bad because, you know, any--the government--how it works
at first was very complicated. You don&#039;t know how to do the right amounts of
things. As the months go by, weeks go by, you get better food and everything
gets to be better. By the time we were going to leave Tanforan, everybody was
pretty good food and everything there--good supply of everything, whatever we
needed. But early part, it was pretty hard.

GRAVES: Well, I have some pictures in here of Tanforan.

OISHI: Oh, you do.

GRAVES: Yeah. The horse stalls.

OISHI: Yes. Oh, is this whole thing of Tanforan?

GRAVES: It&#039;s mostly about San Francisco&#039;s Japanese American community, but when
I saw that, I thought, &quot;Well, that must be what it looked like when Tom first
got there.&quot;

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: So can you talk a little bit about arriving? You want to look at that.

OISHI: April or March, I don&#039;t know what month it was. It was a rainy day. We
went over there and we were assigned to one of these horse stalls. Rainy, they
didn&#039;t clean up good. They cleaned up the best they could. Maybe the government
says, &quot;Well, we&#039;ll give you a couple of $100,000 or something--$100,000,
$50,000, you clean up this thing.&quot; You know, &quot;Okay.&quot; They guy grabbed our
$50,000 or whatever they gave him. He did the best he could do.

GRAVES: But it must have smelled.

OISHI: Yeah, if it wouldn&#039;t rain, it wouldn&#039;t have been so bad. But it was
raining and all this manure and stuff was all on the ground. There was no
blacktop. You could picture going to Golden Gate Fields, when it&#039;s raining. When
it&#039;s sunny, it&#039;s not so bad. So we were there and it was so bad, we complained.
And there&#039;s a new barracks--new barracks, not horse stalls--they put up
barracks. Maybe half of the Tanforan was barracks, but they didn&#039;t have time to
build the barracks.

GRAVES: So when you moved in, did you share a room with--?

OISHI: We had one room. We had one room. Our family, in the new barracks, we a
room--twenty by twenty, maybe. That&#039;s all we had.

GRAVES: And who was in the room?

OISHI: The whole family.

GRAVES: Your parents and--?

OISHI: Joe, Hannah, Lucy and me, and my father. Five. And then the building is
pitched, but they have sheet rock so high and in that pitched place, no sheet
rock, see. So you could hear the neighbor on this side, you could hear neighbor
on this side. [Laughs] When they turn the radio on too loud. So you have to be
awfully careful what you say. [Laughs]

GRAVES: So, if you worked in the kitchen, did other members of your family have jobs?

OISHI: Yes. Joe worked in the commissary. I don&#039;t Hannah and Lucy, they must
have been doing some secretary work or something.

GRAVES: Yes. There&#039;s a nice picture of the library at Tanforan in there too. Do
you want to see it?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: I think I can find it. I think it&#039;s right near here. Yeah, here.

OISHI: I enjoyed Tanforan, you know. Because I didn&#039;t see no guards. I didn&#039;t
see no guards with live ammunition. And the challenge becoming a cook, being on
a baseball team, trying to put out a good rice. Our rice for a meal is one of
the most important things for a Japanese dinner. You could cook all kinds of
rice, you can get it wet and something {inaudible} be not well done, see. To put
out good rice, it takes a lot of patience.

GRAVES: That&#039;s true. So you had some things you loved doing at Tanforan.

OISHI: Something new, I think. It was a challenge.

GRAVES: Were there young women you were interested in?

OISHI: Oh, my wife. My wife. [Laughs]

GRAVES: You met her at Tanforan?

OISHI: Yes, she was, I believe, on this side. The thing was open there. [Laughs]

GRAVES: So where did her family come from?

OISHI: Berkeley.

GRAVES: And you got to know her at Tanforan?

OISHI: Yes. We were both in the horse stables together. And her father was
little older than Joe, see. And my father was pretty old at that time. I was
twenty he was seventy, or maybe seventy-five. Oh, he was in his prime, maybe he
was in his fifties--my wife&#039;s family. So he had a pretty strong mind.

GRAVES: So did you start courting her there?

OISHI: Not courting her. We were friends, like. I wasn&#039;t serious. You know, at
age twenty marriage was not on my mind. Anyway, I had a lot of things on my mind.

GRAVES: And what was her name?

OISHI: Shizu.

GRAVES: Shizu?

OISHI: Yeah, Shizue, yeah.

GRAVES: And her last name?

OISHI: Akiyoshi.

GRAVES: Akiyoshi.

OISHI: Her something&#039;s in that Obata book.

GRAVES: She&#039;s in the Obata book?

OISHI: Yes, her name&#039;s on the Obata book. Did you read the Obata book? I showed
it to you, I think.

GRAVES: Yeah, but I&#039;m trying to remember why was her name in there?

OISHI: Oh, she&#039;s thought she was it. She&#039;s a secretary for Chiura Obata.

GRAVES: Oh, right.

OISHI: Chiura Obata started this art school, see. He&#039;s a University of
California professor. But we didn&#039;t know who Chiura Obata was. Maybe her family
knew Chiura Obata, see.

GRAVES: And this was at Tanforan?

OISHI: At Tanforan. And I was working the kitchen and she was secretary to
Obata. Obata had a new school or something, I think. He wasn&#039;t well-known in
camp yet, but when he went into Topaz and stuff, he started drawing and he drew
a lot of pictures for the camp something. He was well-known.

GRAVES: Did you take any classes from him?

OISHI: No, I&#039;m no artist. Her name was on the Obata book.

GRAVES: I&#039;ll need to look for it. Shizu Akiyoshi.

OISHI: Yeah, she was on the staff of Tanforan Obata School. It&#039;s hard to find
there. I had the book and it must have taken me, I don&#039;t know, couple hours
maybe couple days to find her name on there.

GRAVES: So she was interested in art?

OISHI: No, she wasn&#039;t interested in art, I don&#039;t think. Maybe her father got her
the job. I don&#039;t know.

GRAVES: There&#039;s another picture in here--there was a sign on the gate. It says,
&quot;Tanforan Assembly Center Notice,&quot; with Visiting Hours and it has all this
information about what visitors can and cannot do.

OISHI: Oh, I didn&#039;t read that.

GRAVES: Did you--why don&#039;t you look at it and we can take a picture? It&#039;s here.

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: Do you remember getting any visitors?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: Who visited?

OISHI: Our neighbor used to come and visit us. {Inaudible} was his name. I don&#039;t
know what his person was. Nice fellow.

GRAVES: Do you want to see this? [directed at Washburn] Or not really? Okay.

OISHI: He was a mechanic and he was a welder too, see. There weren&#039;t too many
welders in those days.

GRAVES: He welded at the shipyards?

OISHI: No, no, he was working for a {trucking} company and he was pretty good
welder too.

GRAVES: So, he came alone? Did he bring his family? Do you remember the visits?

OISHI: But, you can&#039;t go inside the camp. You have a visiting place, like a
prison. They can&#039;t come inside--where we live. There&#039;s a visitor&#039;s center or
something and you have to meet there. We&#039;re like prisoners, we&#039;re prisoners. And
you just meet there. They don&#039;t come inside your barrack and your mess hall and
have lunch with you.

GRAVES: How long were you at Tanforan?

OISHI: From maybe April to October, maybe.

GRAVES: And can you describe people leaving Tanforan and where people left?
Where people went and what the travel was like?

OISHI: Well, when we left, it wasn&#039;t so bad. I didn&#039;t see guards. I didn&#039;t see
many guards. And we went by bus to a train station, and then at the train
station we were told to keep the shades down.

GRAVES: Why?

OISHI: I don&#039;t know. Maybe in the city limits or something. No, maybe as far as
Sacramento or something. And then when we got into the High Sierras, we were
able to put the shades up.

GRAVES: Do you think that&#039;s because the government didn&#039;t want Japanese Americans--?

OISHI: [Laughs] I don&#039;t know! It&#039;s just like what&#039;s going on in the airport
today, you know.

GRAVES: Security.

OISHI: {Inaudible} Then we had our shades up and all the way through Utah we had
our shades up or something. And then when we went into Delta, Utah is the town,
which is roughly, probably seventy-five miles south of Salt Lake City. Maybe
fifty miles south of Ogden, Utah. Delta is a small town, maybe 10,000 people.
Alfalfa was the main industry. {Inaudible} alfalfa for hay. I guess we were able
to have our window up. The train stopped. I see a company of guards lined up,
&quot;Come down!&quot;. Their guns are drawn, MPs.

GRAVES: This is for your arrival?

OISHI: Yes, yes, they greeted us. Ooh, these people, the government really--this
is when I first found out these people mean business. When in Tanforan, I never
saw anything like this. Only thing was, when the visitors come, you know, we
have a visitor&#039;s center; that was a little bit odd for me.

GRAVES: So when you looked out of the train window and you saw all those men
with guns--.

OISHI: They were ordered by the government. They didn&#039;t do it on their own. That
was their orders from the government.

GRAVES: What did you feel?

OISHI: [Laughs] I was stunned. I was stunned. That&#039;s how the government felt. In
Washington, they thought that we were mean, dangerous people. That&#039;s the
impression California gave them.

GRAVES: So, the train stopped in Delta?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: And did you get off the train and, what happened?

OISHI: We got off the train and I don&#039;t think we walked too far. But we take a
few steps, the bus was already waiting for us. We got on the bus and it took us
off to Delta, maybe ten miles out in desert some place. It wasn&#039;t desert. It was
pretty high elevation. We had snow. In the winter months it freezes. So maybe
the elevation was pretty high, 5,000 feet or something.

GRAVES: And your whole family was there, together?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: What do you remember when you arrived at Topaz? What was it like?

OISHI: What the government does is, anything new--. When we went in to Tanforan,
first it was bad. You know, your food is bad. Living quarters is bad. First when
we went in to Tanforan, same thing over again. The government gives someone a
contract to build a barrack for 10,000 people. &quot;Here&#039;s a million dollars. I give
you so many months to finish it, so many days. This is where I want--.&quot; The
government says, &quot;I want it done in one month&#039;s time.&quot; &quot;Okay, Okay.&quot; You show
them another couple $100,000 I&#039;ll get it done in one month&#039;s time.&quot; {Inaudible}
And he&#039;ll get it done, not three months, or sixty days, it takes him maybe one
year, two years to get it completed.

GRAVES: So it was pretty crude when you got there?

OISHI: It was crude. When we got there, I think we had to put up our own sheet
rock. The grain was there maybe. They screwed sheet rock. They had nails there,
{inaudible} or something. That&#039;s how it is.

GRAVES: Was your family sharing a room again?

OISHI: Same thing. Same, maybe twenty-by-twenty room.

GRAVES: With open partitions?

OISHI: No, this time I think it was closed. Maybe we--they gave us the sheet
rock so we closed it. But we had no sheet rock to close it at the other place.

GRAVES: You talked about working outside of camp?

OISHI: And then another thing about camp was, it&#039;s a camp. You know how the
government works. All dusty, no something. And here comes a wind storm, it&#039;s a
dust storm. We have dust there. There&#039;s no trees or nothing. They got tractors
and everything. They took away all the vegetation, see. So we had dust storms.
In the fall, we went in for two months or something, dust storms came. And then
when the winter came, it wasn&#039;t so bad. And the only way you could get away from
this dust storm is--we have a lavatory. Lavatory, you know, all the beds, and
then there&#039;s 200 people in one block. And there&#039;s one mess hall and there&#039;s a
lavatory and laundry room.

GRAVES: For each block?

OISHI: Yes. Each unit did not have, and there&#039;s a public lavatory you go to.
There might be ten stalls, ten bowls or something. And you put water inside
there, let the water run, the moisture. Moisture in the restroom would ease the
dust storm. That&#039;s the only way we were able to get relief. And even before I
left camp that was it.

GRAVES: You talked about one of your sisters being pregnant when--.

OISHI: Oh, my sister Amy, in Berkeley, she was married before the war. She had
one child, maybe born in 1939 or &#039;40 or something. And then her second child was
due in &#039;42, latter part of &#039;42, November or something in there. So, the
government says, &quot;Well, Japanese you can&#039;t bring her to a local hospital. You
can&#039;t because of danger. You don&#039;t know what she going doing to do.&quot; [Laughs]
This is a ruling--government ruling. Well, you can&#039;t put a guard behind her. We
can&#039;t afford to have a guard, make sure they don&#039;t sabotage. So maybe in Topaz,
Utah, she left maybe before camp opened, maybe one month before camp opened, in
Utah--left Tanforan. She was in Tanforan, maybe she was eight months pregnant,
going to have a baby a month from now. So they--special trip or something, I
don&#039;t how she went. Her and her husband went to Utah, early ones, one of the
early ones. And her child was born in the laundry room.

GRAVES: At Tanforan? I mean, at Topaz?

OISHI: No, at Topaz. She was first child born in Topaz, Utah.

GRAVES: Were there any doctors?

OISHI: Yes. One thing about camp is maybe in Bay Area, there&#039;s quite a few
doctors. Other areas there&#039;s no doctors. So to each camp, they figure, well, we
have to have so many doctors, so many dentists. So they might have had more
doctors than we should have, so doctors from the Bay Area would have to go to
another camp. So there were sufficient doctors, and teachers too. You know, I
was worried about teachers in school, but there was a lot registered teachers
and college grads that they would teach.

GRAVES: But they didn&#039;t have a hospital, so she had the baby in the laundry room?

OISHI: Yes, yes, because the hospital was not complete.

GRAVES: And was the baby okay?

OISHI: Yes, baby&#039;s good. And she is sixty years old today. That baby that was
born, her name is Jeanie. And her doctor was a woman doctor. A woman, Japanese
American, second-generation. She might have been thirty years old. Maybe she
just got a doctor&#039;s diploma. Her name was Jeanie--Eugenia.

GRAVES: What&#039;s her last name?

OISHI: Fujita. Her father was a dentist in Berkeley. My father used to go to
him. And this Fujita, Eugenia Fujita delivered Jeanie. That&#039;s why they put
Jeanie on her name.

GRAVES: And what was your sister&#039;s married name?

OISHI: Takagi.

GRAVES: Amy Takagi, okay.

OISHI: And this daughter, Amy&#039;s daughter Jeanie, her son just got married. Her
son just got married, thirty-one, thirty-two years old. And Jeanie got married
in Los Angeles and we all gave him presents. And Jeanie got a lot of gifts from
Bay Area relatives. So she threw another party here for the newlyweds, roughly a
month after they got married. We just had it last Saturday night.

GRAVES: That&#039;s nice. So, how was it for your parents, in camp? I&#039;ve heard that
it was especially hard for older people.

OISHI: No. Different persons--I&#039;m going to tell you--different persons, they
took it different. Maybe my parents enjoyed it. My parents enjoyed it. They were
in Richmond, they had to work hard. They had to pay the bills. They had
{inaudible} debt and stuff, you know. Dentist problems and everything else.
{Inaudible} And illness in the family. They were in camp, they were very
relaxed. They had friends, neighbors, all kinds of friends. They meet friends in
the kitchen. They go to classes, art school if they have interest in art. They
have flower arrangement, if they have interest in flower arrangement. There are
teachers there. So they enjoyed it. I have a nephew. I have a sister in
Sacramento who has four boys or three boys. Gary was oldest. He&#039;s ten years
younger than I. If I talk bad about camp, he&#039;ll start coming to this and this
here. Gary says it was like camp to him, going to summer camp. Everyday go to
summer camp. All kinds of girls, he says. [laughs] He enjoyed camp! He loved
camp. I said, &quot;Gary, don&#039;t ever tell other people that you enjoyed camp! Tell
them how rough it is. How they mistreated us.&quot; But that&#039;s his version.

GRAVES: I&#039;ve heard a lot of teenagers--it gave them a lot of freedom.

OISHI: Yes. They enjoyed camp.

GRAVES: Now, you worked outside the camp when you were at Topaz, how did that
happen? Can you talk about that job?

OISHI: The group, they were kind of leaders in the Bay Area--San Francisco and
Oakland people you know. They had football players in UC, you know. And I used
to go see them play basketball and stuff. And I was in this group. So, since I
was in the group in the kitchen, somehow they got connections in Delta. Delta,
Utah, which is, I don&#039;t know, twenty miles or ten miles, out of our camp area.
There&#039;s a mill there. They grind alfalfa. Alfalfa is the main crop in the town,
around the town. They grow alfalfa and it&#039;s supposed to be high in protein, and
there&#039;s a big demand for that. And this mill grind up all the alfalfa. Buy the
alfalfa from the farmers and grind it and put it in the boxcars, ship it
wherever they wished. And we were employed there.

GRAVES: Were you paid the same as other employees?

OISHI: We were paid fifty cents an hour. An hour, that&#039;s quite a bit--four
dollars a day. Compared to in Topaz, Utah, they were giving them sixteen dollars
an hour. In Tanforan, they gave us eight dollars an hour--no, eight dollars a
month. In Topaz, I&#039;m sure, they gave us sixteen dollars a month. They doubled
the pay or something. But in this milling company, we were paid fifty cents an
hour. That&#039;s four dollars a day.

GRAVES: So you were making more in a week than your family was getting in a month?

OISHI: Yes. And then we would--we had no sleeping quarters over there, so they
would loan us a truck. And we would drive the truck into camp and then the next
shift would come and drive it back, and back, see.

GRAVES: So they employed a lot of people from the camp?

OISHI: Well, I think we ran three different shifts. Regular day shift, swing
shift and graveyard shift. Maybe to every shift there was ten people. And then,
that&#039;s alright, but they treated us like, you know the Mexican immigrants that
comes here, illegal people. Lot of people take advantage of them. We don&#039;t
though, no. We were treated like that. We would go to work. Cold, it could be
freezing weather. We go over there. Working conditions are bad. We go over there
and we see {Ridgetown?}, two hours. We don&#039;t get paid for that two hours {over
there}. We waited over there one day, the first hour, after one hour, we see a
{Ridgetown?}. Seven hours we don&#039;t work, we just came for one hour. We have to
stay there.

GRAVES: Were they treating other employees differently?

OISHI: Most of them was Japanese. Oh, we had a foreman and he was the one in
charge of them there. And no doubt they were making real big money off of us. We
were putting out a carload of alfalfa, ground up, hundred pound sack. That&#039;s
roughly 500 sacks a day.

GRAVES: Do you want some water?

OISHI: No, that&#039;s alright.

GRAVES: So, when you were in Topaz and working at the alfalfa mill, did the
whole issue of the Loyalty Questionnaire come up then?

OISHI: I don&#039;t think we were--we had to because we were living in camp. I know
another thing is, every time we come in, even though they know us, we
make--everyday, we&#039;re there, they search us, harassment. They search us like we
were a bunch of criminals. So we couldn&#039;t bring in whatever we wanted. Well, we
figured, this time {inaudible} we could bring in some beer or something. You
know! [Laughs] You&#039;ll bring something in. You know, you couldn&#039;t bring in beer
or something, see. I think he {inaudible}, you couldn&#039;t bring it in! They
usually, they search us like a bunch of criminals. They were ordered, the
company of guards--MPs.

GRAVES: They were there at the mill?

OISHI: No, no, at our camp. At our camp. Maybe two hundred MPs or something.
That&#039;s their duty, they got orders from Washington. {Inaudible} They have to go
by that.

GRAVES: How long did you work at the mill?

OISHI: I might have given David--I want your answer David. {Inaudible}.

GRAVES: What did he say before? He&#039;s wondering.

WASHBURN: I don&#039;t know.

OISHI: Maybe from fall--October, November, December, January, February,
March--six months or something. We made a lot of money for those people. They
got rich out of us. They were shipping that stuff to Los Angeles. High protein,
they would mix it in with feed, you know, for chickens and something.

GRAVES: So then you got to work at a nursery in the Midwest. Can you talk about
how you got that job?

OISHI: Oh, that. I had to get clearance from the government that I was a loyal
American citizen. They had to go through my records, give me a clearance.

GRAVES: How did you hear about it?

OISHI: Oh, one of my relatives, my cousin. Maybe I told you about him.

GRAVES: Yeah, but we need--we want to be able to have this whole story.

OISHI: Okay. Well, Jun Agari--my cousin, see. He went to Cal. He went to
Richmond High. Richmond High, you know, he--a pretty brainy guy, see, gutsy,
brainy. And he was in Richmond High, and the teacher felt, &quot;Geez, this guy
Jun--good speaker, he&#039;s got a good line. Maybe he would be a good commencement
speaker.&quot; So they recommended Jun, &quot;He&#039;ll be commencement speaker.&quot; Maybe she
helped him out to make his speech out. And when he graduated, he was
commencement speaker. We were very proud of him. Then he went to Cal and got
{inaudible}. He got a diploma. He come out. That was nothing for him, you know.
But he was kind of early one being drafted from Richmond. One of the early ones
being drafted. We were in the army, and he was Fort Ord. He had a good job at
Ford Ord or something. Maybe it was because of his education, but he wasn&#039;t no
commissioned officer or anything. He didn&#039;t even have a rating, maybe a PFC or
something. &quot;Alright, you&#039;re Cal graduate, you should go to OCS.&quot; With your IQ,
they classified you. But being a Japanese American, no. So when the war broke
out, &quot;What are we going to do with Jun,&quot; they figure. &quot;We have no place to put
Jun. He&#039;s a Japanese American, we can&#039;t trust the guy.&quot; So they released him
from the army. He was on reserves or they put him on the Army Reserves or
something. Well, my brother was in Fort Custer, Michigan when the war broke out.
But since he was away from the West Coast, he stood there. They didn&#039;t release
him. Since Jun was in the West Coast, they released Jun. So Jun had to go into
camp. And Jun might of made flower magazine--. We have a magazine--flower
growers have a magazine--help wanted. So he answered that. He put it down in
writing or something, I don&#039;t know. Maybe he had a typewriter or something,
maybe he just wrote it down. And the guy answered it. &quot;Jun, come on over,&quot; he
says. &quot;We got a place here. Fifteen guys we need. Come on over, I want you to
operate it.&quot;

GRAVES: And where was this?

OISHI: It was Melrose Park, Illinois, outside of Chicago. Maybe roughly ten,
fifteen miles west of Chicago.

GRAVES: So your cousin got his subscription to this flower grower magazine at camp?

OISHI: Yeah.

GRAVES: And answered this ad?

OISHI: Yeah. And he&#039;s good at writing, you know, he could put words in piece of
paper when the guy--the guy was a young gentleman {inaudible}. This Premier Rose
Garden was one of the biggest rose-growing corporations in the United States.

GRAVES: And so Jun helped you get a job?

OISHI: Yes. He asked me if I wanted to come.

GRAVES: Did you go out with him or did you follow?

OISHI: No, he was in a different camp. He was in a different camp than I was.

GRAVES: What camp was he at?

OISHI: I think he was in Arkansas.

GRAVES: Rohwer?

OISHI: Yeah. He moved to Stockton because they had a sister or something in
Stockton so they moved over there. They wanted to be all together. So they moved
to Stockton, I think, instead of going to Berkeley, they went to Stockton or
something. Maybe they were able to do it.

GRAVES: So he contacted you and said, &quot;Do you want to go work?&quot;

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: And then you had to apply for clearance?

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: Did any of your brothers or friends go with you?

OISHI: No, I think I went myself. He went first and he had half the crew there
by the time I got there.

GRAVES: How did you get there?

OISHI: Oh, train. It was a good ride, you know. Get on the train. In those days,
the train would burn coal, not oil. From Delta we went to Salt Lake City. From
Salt Lake City into Chicago. And if the wind is blowing a certain way, all that
coal dust come inside your car. No matter how tight it is. If the wind is
blowing the opposite the {inaudible} is not so bad. And by the time we get to
Chicago, we&#039;re all black. [Laughs]

GRAVES: So you must have been kind of odd, this one Japanese American on a
civilian train, in wartime. Do you remember, was that--?

OISHI: I didn&#039;t feel nothing. Maybe I was too excited. [Laughs] But I know when
I got off the train, and I was walking in Chicago, ooh, I felt every Tom, Dick,
and Harry looking--staring at me. I was paranoid. Being out of camp and being in
a public street, I thought everybody was looking at me. {Inaudible} Didn&#039;t&#039; take
long to get over it though.

GRAVES: Do you think they were?

OISHI: No, no, no. I just felt that way, you know.

GRAVES: So, did you live with your cousin?

OISHI: No, I lived out in the--the corporation had a big house and they put
addition on. They had a bunkhouse for us too. The corporation had big money,
they were making big money. And they spent money and they put additions, and
they have a big bunkhouse and everything for us. And there was about fourteen or
fifteen of us guys were living in that. We had good living quarters.

GRAVES: Was the whole crew Japanese American?

OISHI: Yes. No, well, there was one man, German man. He was elderly. He was more
or less supervisor. He used to come and look after us. And then everyday there
was a superintendent or general manager would come and consult with the
German--what to do and what not to do.

GRAVES: Were you treated the same way you had been at the mill, or was it different?

OISHI: No, it was much better, much better. But still, you know, maybe instead
of getting fifty cents an hour we got sixty cents an hour.

GRAVES: Wait, I didn&#039;t understand.

OISHI: Sixty cents an hour instead of fifty cents. But they started a union
since it&#039;s a big city. Union started sixty. As the first year, we got a little
bit more and more and more, see.

GRAVES: So you all were able to join the union?

OISHI: Yes, we were in the union.

GRAVES: Do you remember the name of the union?

OISHI: No. Melrose Park--the gangsters in Chicago used to live there. Is that
the name, Al Capone or somebody? In Melrose Park is real close to where our
nursery was. Italian something, big gangsters, Al Capone--.

GRAVES: So you lived in company housing, and when you weren&#039;t working--?

OISHI: Oh, we had a good time. We had a good time. We had a car. We had a couple
cars, you know. Couple of the boys had cars. We would go to Chicago, see
Chicago. Went to football games. Went to a baseball game. Went to see a college
play. We enjoyed ourselves. We had a good time in Chicago. Theatre, stage plays
and everything, theatres. Melrose Park and--do you know Oak Park?

GRAVES: I&#039;ve heard of it.

OISHI: Oak Park is like Evanston. It&#039;s a classic place in Chicago. And Oak Park
was very close to us.

GRAVES: Was it strange for you to have all this freedom, knowing your family was
back in camp?

OISHI: No, we enjoyed it! [Laughs] We enjoyed it! And then we were doing
something. More than that, we were putting out flowers. We were making big money
for those people. We were growing flowers the way we grow on the West Coast.
They were growing the way they grow in the Midwest. See, in the West Coast we
cut flowers all year round. But in the East Coast, it gets too hot. So maybe
there&#039;s no demand for the roses in the summer months. So they would have no rose
in the summer months and late spring. But we grew it our way, and the war is on,
there&#039;s a big demand of roses. So we grew flowers twelve months out of the year.

GRAVES: Did you Premier how to do that? Your crew?

OISHI: Yes, yes, our management. Jun and {inaudible}, they felt that way.

GRAVES: Really.

OISHI: They had an oldtimer. They had a set way of roses over there. You know,
the foreman and everything, and they just went by that way. They didn&#039;t realize
that the was a war going on and they&#039;re injuring themselves.

GRAVES: And so Jun and the other people introduced this new way of doing it?

OISHI: Yeah, but I think they went over that way.

GRAVES: Oh, they didn&#039;t keep it.

OISHI: We just did it at our place. There were three different nurseries. Our
nursery roughly had 100,000--150,000. That&#039;s roughly three acres. The other
nurseries maybe had twelve acres, and the other nursery maybe had twenty-four
acres. That&#039;s how big the corporation was. We were the other smallest nursery.

GRAVES: How did that compare to your nursery at home?

OISHI: Well, we had about three acres here. But the corporation biggest nursery
had twenty-four acres.

GRAVES: Were you able to go back and visit your family?

OISHI: Yeah. Once a year I used to make it.

GRAVES: What?

OISHI: I think I went two, two or three times to came back. But what happened
was every time I come back, the camp&#039;s getting better. They have a contract like
I told you. Maybe they didn&#039;t even have no water tower up there. Maybe the
hospital was not complete. Maybe the library was not complete, they didn&#039;t even
start. They didn&#039;t even have no gymnasium. One year I come back, the camp,
they&#039;re growing trees around there. The Japanese people, you know, they get one
of the desert something, get trees to plant. They fix their garden. They fix
their block. They make it much nicer. Baseball field getting better. By the
time, the last time I went the camp was beautiful. The contract is there, the
government intention is right. One of them got to teach these guy&#039;s right. You
have a hospital, everything else, is not complete. After three years, two and a
half years, finally it&#039;s complete.

GRAVES: Now, so there were opportunities for you and other men to work outside
the camp. Did your sisters or do you know of other women--?

OISHI: Yes, my sisters came out. They came out to Chicago too. Well, about a
year later or something.

GRAVES: And worked at the nursery?

OISHI: No, they had--they worked in downtown Chicago, at the Loop. They used to
get on the L-train and find whatever secretary work, or whatever they were
doing. They lived downtown.

GRAVES: Oh. So that would be--which sisters?

OISHI: Hannah and Lucy.

GRAVES: Did they enjoy it?

OISHI: Yes, I think they did.

GRAVES: And you saw them?

OISHI: Well, yes, I saw them.

GRAVES: And what about your wife? Were you still in touch with her?

OISHI: Not much but we used to write back and forth.

GRAVES: As friends?

OISHI: Yeah, as friends. Maybe she didn&#039;t see it that way but I {inaudible}.

GRAVES: It&#039;s Joe who was in the army right?

OISHI: No, George.

GRAVES: George.

OISHI: And then George, George I know, when I was in Chicago, maybe 1944 or
something--now, he used to come to see me. He was in Michigan--Fort Custer,
Michigan. Fort Custer, Michigan to Chicago, maybe couple hours drive or
something. So he figured, &quot;Well, the little brother.&quot; He&#039;s eight years older
than I am, see. He figured, &quot;I have to look after him. Maybe that guy&#039;s going
wild.&quot; He used to come every few months, see how I&#039;m doing. I didn&#039;t mooch no
money off of him, I just had to give him the money, see. He was stationed in the
hospital. He had a good easy job. He had a corporal rating, you know.

GRAVES: What was he doing in the hospital?

OISHI: I think he was supplies in the hospital. But he was in med corps or
something. Maybe he&#039;s something else. And then later on, they says, &quot;Geez, these
guys are laying around here. How can the other Caucasian people and other
African American and Mexican and stuff are going overseas and getting their legs
shot off, getting killed? All the Japanese are in the States and they got a good
easy job in the hospital, mess hall. It&#039;s not right.&quot; George was there a long
time, two years or something. Maybe he&#039;s thirty-three or something. They says,
&quot;Well, we&#039;re going to form a combat team.&quot; They formed this 442 combat team. So
they grabbed them all. All those guys like George, they grabbed them, send them
down to Mississippi, give them a rifle.

GRAVES: And then he went to Europe?

OISHI: He went to southern Italy, came all the way into France. I followed him
in his letters.

GRAVES: Before the 442nd, what did your family think about most of you being in
camp and one of the sons being in the army?

OISHI: That&#039;s why I give my father a lot of credit, see. My father&#039;s still stuck
by. He stuck by. &quot;This is our country. Now, son, this is a good country, the
war&#039;s on.&quot; The other people in camp, they pushed around, maybe their family lost
all their money, their sending it to Japan. Maybe they were in Japanese banks.
They were there buying property in Japan. It&#039;s all--every situation is
different. But my father figure, &quot;Oh, my son in the army. Tom has to go. For the
good of the country, he&#039;s going to go.&quot; I thought, &quot;No, no, don&#039;t send your son,
don&#039;t send your son.&quot; Some example--send your son. {Inaudible} There&#039;s all kinds
of thinking.

GRAVES: So there was this debate in the camps among people about loyalty and
there was this Loyalty Questionnaire that people had to sign, did you have to
fill that out?

OISHI: Maybe I was out of camp by then.

GRAVES: And there were also people who formed the Fair Play Committee. Do you
remember hearing--. Saying that there shouldn&#039;t be a draft unless there were
citizenship rights. Your family, it sounds like--.

OISHI: We were all citizens.

GRAVES: Not your parents.

OISHI: Drafted. Did you say drafted?

GRAVES: Well, there were people who thought that people should have citizenship
rights, meaning they shouldn&#039;t be in a camp.

OISHI: Yes, yes.

GRAVES: If there was going to be a draft of Japanese Americans. So there were
people having this debate in the camps.

OISHI: There was all different thinking. Just because you&#039;re Japanese, they all
don&#039;t think alike. They all have different financial status, different
education, different parts of Japan they come from.

GRAVES: But in that debate, where would you say your family--?

OISHI: I gave my father a lot of credit. I was afraid he was going to get beat
up. I was afraid that he was going to get beat up by some of the friends.

GRAVES: Why?

OISHI: You know, because he felt his boys are American citizens and {there was
no} right to fight for the country. And other people felt--they were bitter.
They were thrown into camp. They lost all their personal belongings. Their
house, maybe they lost the house, everything they lost. Just like the Hoshi
family and the other family, Fukushima, right. They lost it. They have debt. The
bank says, &quot;We feel sorry for them.&quot; {Inaudible}. They&#039;re in the banking
business. They&#039;re out to make money. You don&#039;t pay, they take it away.

GRAVES: But you&#039;ve described feeling bitterness.

OISHI: Pardon me?

GRAVES: You&#039;ve described feeling bitter.

OISHI: Yes, yes, yes.

GRAVES: Did you feel better then or was--?

OISHI: Yes, I did. No, I didn&#039;t feel bitter but my bitterness was against
throwing me into camp. I thought that was wrong.

GRAVES: What did your parents think?

OISHI: I don&#039;t know how they felt. Maybe by rights, they were aliens. They could
do it to aliens. I had Italian friends and German friends here. They were living
in Richmond. They had a good job here. They had a home here. I think German and
Italian immigrants, they didn&#039;t have to be citizens to buy a house. While
Japanese, Japanese could not buy house, even though they were aliens. But
Italian aliens, I believe, could buy a house without being a citizen. We would
have a house here, two boys are in the army, father and mother are aliens. They
have to move out of the house. Go someplace else. They were restricted. You
can&#039;t go no more than five miles. You have to be in by eight o&#039;clock. When the
sun sets, you have to be in. So we were restricted, try to go more than two
miles, you got to get a permit.

GRAVES: Yeah. So, is there anything else about living in Chicago that you remember?

OISHI: What was hard was we had money, we&#039;re go to the store, want to buy meat,
you can&#039;t buy meat. We have stamps. [Laughs] We got a lot of stamps. We can&#039;t
buy meat. We don&#039;t know nobody, see. But I did work with all Germans, mostly
Germans. But there&#039;s a shortage of meat. No matter how many stamps you got, you
can&#039;t get it. A lot of things, sugar, restrictions--everything you buy.
{Inaudible}, shoes--.

GRAVES: Gasoline.

OISHI: Tire, gasoline, everything you need stamps to buy.

GRAVES: And would you get the same amount of stamps as other people?

OISHI: Yes, we get the same amount of stamps, stamps don&#039;t mean nothing. You
don&#039;t have friend, you don&#039;t know nobody. And that&#039;s how it was. Maybe in the
early part of war, when we first went out, it was tough. But as it got on, whoa,
we could buy up all the ham and everything--little black market. You know the
right people, all the tires and the sugar, whatever you want you were able to
buy more than we could use.

GRAVES: So you found that in Chicago you were able to buy things?

OISHI: Yes, but maybe in the early part, maybe I&#039;m not sure, if we knew the
right people, we were able to do that from the beginning. It was tough. In camp
we didn&#039;t have that stuff. Oh, we had all kinds of restrictions in the war
years. You could picture here in Richmond, you know. Richmond must have been
awfully tough.

GRAVES: Oh, I remember you talking about some of the chemicals you&#039;d use at the
nursery being from Richmond.

OISHI: Yes, yes. Richmond, being a refinery town, we had Niagara Chemical here.
We had Stauffer Chemical here. We had Ortho here. Those were the three major
chemical plants in the United States, all over the world. We might supply the
whole world of these things. And we go to this place in Melrose Park, Illinois,
and we {inaudible} all these chemicals that we buy--manufactured in Richmond,
California. That&#039;s a brand name. We {inaudible}. We grow flowers here, beautiful
flowers here. We shipped them to Canada, New York, Chicago, Nashville,
Tennessee, Texas. We sold it as Oishi Carnations, grown and raised in Richmond,
California. And throughout the whole year, average throughout the whole year, we
thought our carnations was better than any carnations in the United States.
Better than Redwood City or Mountain View or East Oakland because we had the
ideal growing conditions. That wasn&#039;t because we were great growers, or we were
great agriculture management in carnations. We had the ideal conditions to grow.

GRAVES: As you were in Chicago--.

OISHI: The City of Richmond don&#039;t know. We buy greenhouses. We buy all the
supplies for nursery. Sales tax, everything you buy there&#039;s sales tax on it. We
buy greenhouse--one the eastern greenhouse. &quot;Where are you going to put it?&quot;
&quot;Richmond, California.&quot; They have to look up what the sales tax rating is in
Richmond, and give Richmond the money. All we did was give to the city of
Richmond. We took nothing out.

WASHBURN: You want to just take a break right now, there&#039;s only about three
minutes left. Let&#039;s take a break.

GRAVES: So, can you talk about the end of the war, and coming back--out of
Chicago, and the return home.

OISHI: Well, in 1945 seems like we were able to come back. Kind of surprise, we
didn&#039;t know how long we would have to be out of California. But it was a big
surprise to us, war wasn&#039;t even over. We&#039;re still fighting in Germany and Japan.
And we got notice saying, &quot;If you want to come back, you could come back. Apply
for it.&quot; Geez, it was a big surprise. Joe was working in defense plant in
Chicago, and I was in Melrose Park, Illinois. So, me and Joe, we met a couple
times you know. It was quite a distance to go, you have to go by L train, and he
was on the south side. So we had a couple meetings and we decided, well, we&#039;re
{inaudible}. We&#039;ll order some plants, carnation plants, good, clean carnation
plants, anything clean. And the roots is--even a human being, you know, the
roots is the most important thing. Good, clean carnation plant {inaudible}. So
we went to one of the better nurseries over there, small family operation-like.
We told him to send us plants in maybe April, May, June, and July. Maybe it was
5,000 each month or something. We just took a chance. We ain&#039;t had no money, but
we gave him the order. And we came back, and we prepared for that. We learned
that our nursery was not in good condition, we were told. But our greenhouse and
everything was in good condition. So we came back and we started running
{rebuilding} it, 5000 plants in April, so we had to prepare our soil. Sterilize
our soil. No, we had to change our soil in those days.

GRAVES: And this is just you and Joe?

OISHI: Me and Joe--we decided just Joe and I. My mother and father was in camp.
But Joe and I, we came back in February or something and we got started. And
when we came back, the nursery was in good--the glass house and buildings was in
good condition, but the plants was not, and you know, was all rundown, old and
dead. So we started a little bit at a time and our main goal was in April, we
had to get so many square foot of soil ready since the plants were going to come in.

GRAVES: Were there people living in your house?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: So where did you live?

OISHI: When we first came back they might have been living there three shifts a
day, I&#039;m not sure! There were many people there. It was much bigger. We had more
buildings then what it is today. And they&#039;re living in any place that has a roof
over it. As long as they could put a bed and they had running water or something.

GRAVES: So where were you and Joe living?

OISHI: I think we lived at our cousins&#039; and then we ate their too.

GRAVES: A cottage on your property?

OISHI: No. Cousins, cousins.

GRAVES: Oh, with cousins. Where?

OISHI: Sakai&#039;s. And Sakai&#039;s was in much better condition. Since roses are good
for four, five years. They can go up for eight year period without transplanting
one. Carnation, every year you have to transplant. So they were in much better
condition than we were. As soon as they came back, you know, they had a good income.

GRAVES: And there wasn&#039;t anyone living in their house?

OISHI: I think they were able to get them out.

GRAVES: So you and Joe got the greenhouses started again.

OISHI: Yeah. And then we ate for two, three months at Sakai&#039;s. Mrs. Sakai and
Tetsama, my cousin, says, &quot;Join us.&quot; They had workers there. They had maybe ten
or twelve people there. To cook for two more people doesn&#039;t&#039; mean nothing, you
know. So we had lunch and dinner over there for two, three months until we were
able to get our house back. We can&#039;t just boot them out as soon you come
back--you can&#039;t just get out and boot them out.

GRAVES: So there were other Japanese Americans who were coming back to Richmond
at the same time you did?

OISHI: No, we were kind of early ones.

GRAVES: And how did you feel people received you, the other people in Richmond?

OISHI: I didn&#039;t think nothing of it.

GRAVES: Were there neighbors who were happy to see you back?

OISHI: Yes, yes, yes, our neighbors were happy to see us back.

GRAVES: So you got a draft notice?

OISHI: Yes, yes. And then, I don&#039;t know, soon as I came back or something, I
changed my draft address, changed the address. When I was in the--. [phone rings]

GRAVES: Wait just one second.

OISHI: When I was in Chicago, they didn&#039;t bother me, but as soon as I came back
to Richmond, when I notified my change of address, they drafted me. They wanted
me to go to physical.

GRAVES: And you were trying to get the nursery, and here you got this call to
join the army, what did you think?

OISHI: No, and then, in between there, when we first came back to Richmond, in
February or something, maybe March or something, we got a notice from the War Department.

GRAVES: From the what?

OISHI: War Department, government, &quot;Your brother George--your son George was
shot in {action}.&quot; Whoo, that&#039;s thunder. We didn&#039;t know how bad he was, going to
be crippled for life, he&#039;s going to die or just a minor wound. And he got Purple
Heart and Silver Star and everything else. But when he went overseas, he was in
a medic. He had the Red Cross on something, he had to after the--. The law says
he had the Red Cross, you&#039;re not supposed to shoot at him. You know, that&#039;s a
point in international law. They don&#039;t go by laws.

GRAVES: How long before you found out he was okay?

OISHI: I think he wrote to us. Maybe--it takes maybe a month or something--took
two or something.

GRAVES: Boy.

OISHI: That was a big relief. That was just about war, just about over.

WASHBURN: Let me ask you, Tom, when you came back, who was staying in your home
and why were they staying there?

OISHI: Well, Richmond had a shortage of housing. And the shipyard--Richmond was
a town of 20,000 before the war, maybe by the time I came back, maybe it had
120,000. So, you picture 100,000 coming into the town of Richmond, they have to
stay some place. And they&#039;re working three shifts a day at the shipyard. Maybe
they&#039;re putting out a ship per day and they have to have some place to share.
They had that federal housing they built. I mean, vacant land, they put up
federal housing projects, but that wasn&#039;t enough.

GRAVES: So, who was in your house?

OISHI: Oh, African Americans. I think they came from the south, in New Orleans,
or Mississippi or Oklahoma, I&#039;m not sure. They weren&#039;t Caucasian. They were all black.

GRAVES: Did you get to know them at all?

OISHI: No, no. Some of them even used to work in the city. I think what happened
is, one family comes in and they get their friends so it&#039;s not so bad, you&#039;re
not getting all different people. Maybe the guy was smart enough, he got a good
family and he got his brothers, he got his auntie, he got his uncle, got his
brother in law. And then we&#039;re were lucky we got good people in there. I was
surprised. Just like we had the nursery there, we get people from this one
little village in Mexico. They grow corn. Maybe it&#039;s a good town. They&#039;re good
people, see. We get their friends, their uncle, their friends, that&#039;s all we
get. We know we get the friends, the family, they&#039;re good people. We have no problems.

WASHBURN: So Tom, who was watching your house and did he make money off of the
people staying in your home?

OISHI: Maybe he made money by rent--renting to the individual people rather than
growing flowers. I think that was it. So he was getting a pretty good income and
he was able to pay the taxes or whatever, because we didn&#039;t have to pay back
taxes or anything, we didn&#039;t have no bill when we came back.

GRAVES: So what was the process for getting people out of your house, do you remember?

OISHI: I think the guy, Mr. {Sorensted}, maybe had them move or something. Maybe
he gave them notice that he would like this thing vacant. Maybe he gave them
thirty or sixty days. And we had no problems getting them out. When that time
came, the thing was empty.

GRAVES: So, you said your neighbors were happy to see you. When you went out to
the store there was no problem?

OISHI: The only thing in between the time we came back, time I went in the army
was we had this good car. You know, they weren&#039;t making cars, they were making
guns and tanks and ships and stuff. They had no time to make cars. So for a long
period of time, they weren&#039;t making cars. So we had this good car, just about
new, and we wanted to get insurance on it. We couldn&#039;t get no insurance on it.
We were told these Japanese Americans, you know, the way it was, &quot;A Jap is a
Jap, they&#039;re bad people.&quot; You come back, you go to court. You get arrested, you
go to court and you have a trial, you&#039;d lose. So we weren&#039;t able to get
insurance on it.

GRAVES: When you returned.

OISHI: Yes. So I think some of the wiser Niseis, older Niseis, they got in with
a company, maybe with a higher premium, and we got insurance through them.

GRAVES: So, let&#039;s get back to the draft notice and talk about entering the army
and everything that happened.

OISHI: Well, in August I was inducted. What happened was, when we came
back--must have been about seven, eight people, you know, Japanese Americans
that came back from camp. We all had to go to a physical at the same time, and I
was the only one that was accepted. The others were--maybe before the war they
went to a physical and maybe they were in {inaudible} service or they maybe had
some eye problems or some problems and at that time they weren&#039;t too strict. And
then, during the war years, they took anybody. Then, when the war was just about
over, they got choosy again, so they just picked the good--the guy with no
defects at all. And to me, it was quite an honor. You seven guys go to army
physical, and just me passed! It was an honor to go, you know, I was kind of
proud even though I was bitter about the other thing.

GRAVES: And so where did you get assigned and what was your job?

OISHI: I was assigned to Marysville.

GRAVES: Marysville?

OISHI: Marysville, Camp Beale. Camp Beale, Marysville.

WASHBURN: Which is just north of Sacramento right?

OISHI: Yes. And this happened at that time, the peaches and fruits were coming.
That&#039;s a great peach orchard area. And they had no one to can them. The cannery
was there. So they asked for volunteers. I raised my hand. You know, I raised my
hand and I went to work. I ate at the army camp, they made me lunch, everything.
They pick us up at the camp, they bring us to different canneries. We went from
all around: Lincoln, Oroville, Newcastle, Loomis, Marysville, you know, there&#039;s
canneries all over. So everyday--we weren&#039;t assigned to set cannery so maybe for
two months. From camp I went working there. They gave me money. The army fed me.
I stuck the money in my pocket. I was a little older than most soldiers, see. I
was maybe twenty-two or twenty-three years old. But the other soldiers were only
eighteen, nineteen or something, so I was a little wiser to them.

GRAVES: Were there other Japanese Americans?

OISHI: No, no.

GRAVES: How did the other soldiers interact with you?

OISHI: Well, maybe some of the soldiers was just like me. We were in the same
shoes. We used to go to work at the canneries.

GRAVES: But you didn&#039;t feel any prejudice?

OISHI: No, no.

GRAVES: So you did that for a few months?

OISHI: Yeah.

GRAVES: And then what?

OISHI: And then I think they delayed my assignment and then they send it way to
Camp Lee, Virginia, across the country, just about fifteen, thirteen of us guys,
and one sergeant. Sergeant looked after us. And it must have taken us a week to
get to the West Coast. We had all kind of meal tickets--no, we used to eat in
the diner, see. We&#039;re army. We&#039;re government property now, see. We sit in the
good chair. We go to the diner and eat--eat whatever you want. [Laughs] Must
have taken us a long time, sometimes we were on--maybe we were on a tube train,
I&#039;m not sure. They put us on the side in Chicago, we might have stayed a half a
day. We go to Cincinnati or some place and stay there, maybe three-quarters of a
day. And we had a good time on the meal on. We ate in the dining car. I remember
that and we enjoyed that.

GRAVES: What did you do in Fort Lee?

OISHI: I was assigned to a baking outfit, baking bread. At Fort Lee is a service
company, you know, clerks and bakers and cooks. We&#039;re not infantrymen. We&#039;re not
the medics. We&#039;re not the field artillery. Service people--easy job. I was lucky
I got in there.

GRAVES: So you learned how to bake bread?

OISHI: Yeah, we had to bake bread in all conditions. Freezing weather, hot
weather. We went to work in a camp bakery, station bakery. But most of it was
field bakery, we had to learn out in the field.

GRAVES: How would that differ?

OISHI: Oh, the bakery is--they have a big building and all machinery, done by
machinery. But out in the field, you have to get your own flour and make it on
the field with a little stove.

GRAVES: It&#039;s funny that at the beginning of the war you were perfecting cooking
rice and at the end of the war, you&#039;re learning how to be a good bread maker. [Laughs]

OISHI: [Laughs] Yeah, yeah.

GRAVES: So how were you there learning in the bakery corps?

OISHI: I had to take my, I don&#039;t know, my regular army training and then they
send me two, three months baking outfit. And then I got my assignment to go
overseas. Ooh, Japan. I was lucky. I was happy about it. Then I broke out with
mumps. And my group went overseas, the group I was supposed to go over with.
Maybe a baker, certain amount of bakers, certain amount of cooks, certain amount
of medics and certain amount of infantrymen, you know, that&#039;s how the army work.
They had to get all assigned and when you first enter. So I missed out on that.
I missed out on--my outfit went overseas and I had to stay back.

GRAVES: Because you were sick?

OISHI: Yeah.

GRAVES: So you would have been a baker in the occupation of Japan?

OISHI: Yes.

GRAVES: And what did you think about that?

OISHI: Good. Maybe I can make some money on black market, I don&#039;t know. [laughs]
No, in August or something, when I first entered the army, I think Pearl Harbor,
Nagasaki and Hiroshima was bombed. And maybe in March or something, April or
something, Germany gave up, see, I&#039;m not sure.

GRAVES: What did you think about Hiroshima and Nagasaki?

OISHI: Nothing of it. I was American, because I had no knowledge of Japan. I had
no knowledge of Japan.

GRAVES: Was it communicated in the press how incredibly devastating those bombs were?

OISHI: Oh, yes. Oh, it was terrible. Truman&#039;s the one--maybe if Roosevelt was
living, maybe he wouldn&#039;t have done it. Truman was--he just, soon as he got in
there. I think Roosevelt died, didn&#039;t he? Truman was in there, {inaudible} he
dropped the bomb. I&#039;m not sure.

GRAVES: I can&#039;t remember. But so you saw it as a necessary evil?

OISHI: We didn&#039;t know what atomic bomb was. No one knew what the atomic bomb
was. And then another thing, when I missed my assignment to Japan, I was laying
around in Camp Lee, Virginia, doing nothing. Doing nothing in the army,
especially for me, was very boring, see. And we didn&#039;t have to pick up cigarette
butts. We had German prisoners--German prisoners from Europe. They brought them
over to the States. Italian prisoners, they had a camp for them in Camp Lee,
Virginia. They would do all the dirty work for us in Camp Lee. They would pick
up all the cigarette butts. I showed you we&#039;d smoke, we&#039;d throw the cigarette
butts away. [laughs] Here come Germans and Italians have to, they pick up all of
our cigarettes. They would do all our kitchen work. They&#039;d do all the dirty work
for us. I was in a white man&#039;s camp, see. There&#039;s a German prison camp, Italian
prison camp, black camp and a white camp. I had been in the white camp.

GRAVES: And the Germans and the Italians served you guys.

OISHI: Yeah, {inaudible}. Black did not come and do the dirty work for us.

GRAVES: Wow. Your life has so many ironies, it&#039;s amazing.

WASHBURN: Tom, will you tell us about riding the buses there and where you sat
in Virginia?

OISHI: Oh, yeah. Maybe you won&#039;t believe it, I didn&#039;t believe it. Virginia is
where they fought the Civil War. Civil War was what? Eighteen--, Seventeen--. I
don&#039;t know when it was.

GRAVES: 1860.

OISHI: 1860. See, that&#039;s not too old, that&#039;s not too far from my days. When we
went to Fort Lee, Virginia, we had these fellows from New England states. Our
company or our platoon or something, would amount to, I don&#039;t know thirty people
or fifty people or something. And we had people from the South. Half from there
and a few from California. They&#039;re fighting, they&#039;re fighting about the Civil
War. The Yankees and the Rebels. First time I heard this. Yankees and the
Rebels, we maybe just read a little bit in the history--civics--in history
books. And we didn&#039;t think it was that bitter, you know. I thought it was
ancient times. But their father and their grandfather was in the Civil War.
They&#039;re fighting. They dislike one another. And our camp was--throughout it was
going on maneuvers and stuff. Major so-and-so died here. So many rebels was
killed here. Certain artillery lost so many men. All over camp. Camp Lee,
Virginia is a beautiful place. It rains in the summer months and spring, and the
rolling hills. It&#039;s one of the other prettier places in the summer months. I
don&#039;t know how it is in the winter months. Nice and green. Here in California,
everything turns brown after spring during summer. But in Fort Lee, Virginia,
it&#039;s awfully beautiful.

WASHBURN: Tom, when you were off the camp, when you rode the buses, can you
describe what the buses were like and where you sat?

OISHI: Oh, the buses in Virginia. Were you ever down south? Virginia, in those
days, you had a black toilet, a white toilet. You go in the bus, in those days,
the bus is all full--standing room--half of the people are standing up. You
know, war years. And all the black has to go to the back. So, hey, one black guy
is going to get to on. The guys has to get off the bus, let this one black man
go to the back, then go back on the bus. You follow me? I was surprised. I
didn&#039;t see that in California. When I went to Camp Beale here, blacks and whites
were in the same camp. They weren&#039;t separated.

GRAVES: So where did you sit in the bus?

OISHI: I sat in the front. I&#039;m a white man, even though I&#039;m an ex-spy. [Laughs]
I was labeled a dangerous Japanese American, can&#039;t trust him. That&#039;s just like
these Arabs. Every one of those guys are suspects. What are they doing to them
now? A lot of stuff they&#039;re doing to them, they don&#039;t come out in the paper,
it&#039;s there.

GRAVES: Yeah, they&#039;re all being registered.

OISHI: Registered, if they {inaudible}, they&#039;re going to lock them up or
something. When the Japanese Americans, there&#039;s only 100,000 here. You could
shove 100,000 do anything you want to 100,000. But you have a million people,
it&#039;s pretty hard to do anything.

GRAVES: So is there anything else about Camp Lee you want to--?

WASHBURN: Was it in Camp Lee that you were assigned to--no, that wasn&#039;t there.

GRAVES: That&#039;s in Gilroy.

WASHBURN: Okay, we can cover that then.

GRAVES: So after Camp Lee, where did you get sent?

OISHI: Camp Lee, I was laying around, that&#039;s the hardest thing to do. I have no
assignment--couple of months. So, someone told me, why don&#039;t you go to certain
office and try to get an assignment. So I went over there. They were {inaudible}
in California--Camp {McQuaid}. It&#039;s in Watsonville--stockade. What the heck, I
want to go there anyway, you know. I went over there. First, they&#039;re going to
put me at a guard. I don&#039;t care, I was on guard duty, live ammunition and
everything, I&#039;d done that before. I was going to be a guard. &quot;Shoot to kill!&quot;
they said. &quot;Shoot to kill those people! That person gets away, you&#039;re going to
take his rap if he gets away, you shoot to kill.&quot; That was my order.

GRAVES: And who was in the stockade?

OISHI: The stockade was the court martial people, general court martial people.
Now, I&#039;m a guard in the stockade, before I was inside the stockade. That&#039;s where
I got the word stockade, they called it a stockade. I just {saw on them} they
call it, Relocation Center. I told Ruby, &quot;We were not in no Relocation Center,
we were in a stockade. We were in the brig.&quot; Ooh, they get very upset. They
didn&#039;t do nothing bad, why should they be in a stockade or brig? They didn&#039;t
like me.

GRAVES: It made your family mad when you said that?

OISHI: Yeah. But after we got the $20,000 they realized what the government
really did to them. But I was ahead of them because I went through all that.

WASHBURN: So did you sympathy when you were assigned to guard the people who
were court martialed in the stockade? Did you somehow feel sympathy for their situation?

OISHI: Well, I didn&#039;t know this guy could be inside there, maybe he&#039;s taking the
rap for a sergeant, maybe he&#039;s taking the rap for a captain. I didn&#039;t know. I&#039;m
not going to shoot that man. So I told you, I went up there, I told them the
situation I was in. I saw people being shot in the camp that I was in. So they
assigned me to the hospital.

GRAVES: At the stockade?

OISHI: Yeah. But I was in the range, shooting the carbine, shooting the pistol,
shooting the M-1. We used to go out in the range every week, you know,
shoot--shoot to kill.

GRAVES: But then, once you were actually out there, you realized you couldn&#039;t do that?

OISHI: Yes. I was there until they reassigned me.

GRAVES: To the hospital?

OISHI: No, from the guard duty. I was a guard at--.

GRAVES: Right.

OISHI: Then, I told the captain or company commander the situation and he says
they need someone in the hospital.

GRAVES: What did you do at the hospital?

OISHI: At first they wanted me to--. I had a California Drivers&#039; License, they
wanted me to drive the truck for them, and get supplies in Monterey. And then
they were awfully short of medical help because the venereal disease, syphilis
and gonorrhea was new--no, it was always there, but they had no cure for it. In
maybe in 1946, spring or something, penicillin came out to our camp. Maybe
penicillin was in other camps before that but we didn&#039;t get penicillin until the
spring of 1946. And we had a whole mess of soldiers that was infected with
gonorrhea and syphilis.

GRAVES: And so you were helping treat them?

OISHI: Yeah. Since it&#039;s the brig , the nurse is--you being a nurse, you know,
you have your own license, state license from army lieutenant. You just have to
make sure that the treatment is being done and they used a guy like me, a PFC,
and I had to do all the work.

GRAVES: So how long were you--is that what you did for the rest of your--?

OISHI: Yeah, and then I think I went there in Camp {McQuaid?} in February or
something and I was discharged in December.

GRAVES: And came back here. So maybe that&#039;s what we should cover next time, if
there&#039;s a next time.

OISHI: And then there was malaria. Malaria was in the hospital. Mostly syphilis,
gonorrhea and malaria was our patients. And then the patient was real sick, they
would bring him to Fort Leavenworth.

GRAVES: Wait, I have one more question. So all of these soldiers who you were
helping treat--.

OISHI: They were inmates.

GRAVES: Right, but they had been soldiers, American soldiers, and they&#039;d been
out fighting--.

OISHI: Yes, no doubt they were. I&#039;m not sure what they were doing. They were in
the Pacific.

GRAVES: How did they feel about being cared for by a Japanese American man?

OISHI: Well, there&#039;s a guard with a gun, so a guy don&#039;t like it, &quot;Yeah, this guy
maybe, something.&quot; Here, I&#039;m giving shots. I poke him, he yells. I know I got
him over a {inaudible} because I have a guard there with live ammunition. I do
in war zone, see. In war zone. Poke him and maybe the first time I poke him I
want to harass the guy. I poke him again. I poke him again. He gets upset. He
can&#039;t do nothing about it. He gets rough, I call the guards. So he gets to the
point where he accepts me. Then next time I go one shot, I poke him, give him
the dosage, go out.

GRAVES: This was everybody or just the people who were--?

OISHI: No, but there was patient like that.

GRAVES: What do you mean &quot;like that&quot;?

OISHI: No, everybody is different. If you were a patient and I&#039;m a medic and I
shoot you and you dislike it, you&#039;re afraid, you&#039;re timid, I would harass you
more, see. But if you accept it, good, one shot, you get the dosage.

GRAVES: So it didn&#039;t have to do with who you were as a Japanese American, it was
that you were poking them with needles?

OISHI: Yeah, yeah. So it&#039;s--you go to a local hospital, say I&#039;m a nurse in local
hospital, they&#039;re paying money. There&#039;s no guard there. Army is different.
There&#039;s a different a story altogether in the army.

WASHBURN: Nobody said anything to you about, you know, &quot;Who are you? Are you
Japanese? Are you Chinese?&quot; Did anybody say something like that?

OISHI: Actually, the West Coast, just San Francisco, Los Angeles, major cities
in the West Coast, the propaganda came out from the governor&#039;s office. So the
other part of the United States had no knowledge. They were naïve, they didn&#039;t
know we were Japanese, they didn&#039;t know that we were in camp. They didn&#039;t know
that we were labeled dangerous, bunch of spies. So when we went east, it was
nothing to it. When we go in the army, there was nothing to it. They didn&#039;t even
know I was in camp.

GRAVES: I see.

WASHBURN: So you think most people learned about it after the fact?

OISHI: Well, in the West Coast, it was blasted all over the papers.

GRAVES: But the people who would have been in that stockade were from
everywhere, they weren&#039;t just--?

OISHI: Oh yeah, yeah. When we went back east, they didn&#039;t even know that we were
in the stockade. Well, the other people call it Relocation Center. When you have
guards up there, a company of MPs, they have live ammunition, that&#039;s no
Relocation Center, that&#039;s a stockade. If I was a soldier up there and they give
orders shoot to kill, I have to shoot to kill. That&#039;s their duty, that&#039;s the army.

GRAVES: Yeah. Well, thank you. So do we have the energy to go look at the house
for a little bit or what do you think? Do you have the time? Can we get into
your house today?

OISHI: I don&#039;t know, I don&#039;t know. There&#039;s not too much to see in the house.

[End of Interview]</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>