<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00100076" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2011-11-03" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Ernestine Shepherd | Interview 1 | November 3, 2011</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewer>David Michael Dunham‎</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>dcLBgQXlGlo</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>DUNHAM: It&#039;s November 3, 2011, and this is David Dunham from the Regional Oral
History Office. I&#039;m with Ernestine Shepherd, in her home, in Richmond,
California. We&#039;re going to start at the beginning, if you could just tell me
your full name and your date of birth.

SHEPHERD: Ernestine Shepherd. Birth date-- ten--two--seventeen [October 2, 1917].

DUNHAM: Where were you born?

SHEPHERD: I was born in an Indian reservation in Oklahoma.

DUNHAM: Were either of your parents Indians?

SHEPHERD: Pardon?

DUNHAM: Were either of your parents Indians?

SHEPHERD: No.

DUNHAM: How did you come to be born on an Indian Reservation?

SHEPHERD: She was working for some Indians or something or another.

DUNHAM: Okay, and did you know either of your grandparents?

SHEPHERD: Oh yes.

DUNHAM: Can you tell me a little about their background--where they lived--worked?

SHEPHERD: They lived in Colorado Springs--Colorado. My grandfather and my
grandmother died--my grandfather died at eighty-nine and I&#039;m not sure what my
grandmother was--how old she was.

DUNHAM: What did they do in Colorado?

SHEPHERD: Well my grandfather had a horse and a wagon, which he hauled things
for people and drove them around--you know like you do a car, or like a person
would do that have a truck--he had a wagon. We also had a bugee, which we used
on Sundays when we were going--supposed to be dressed up.

DUNHAM: Going to church?

SHEPHERD: Going to church or where you wanted--you know going out somewhere.

DUNHAM: Was religion a big part of your life growing up?

SHEPHERD: Are they what?

DUNHAM: Was religion a big part of your life growing up?

SHEPHERD: Oh--Pentecostal.

DUNHAM: Were these--were your grandparents--were these on your mother&#039;s side, or
your father&#039;s side?

SHEPHERD: My grandparents were what?

DUNHAM: I&#039;m sorry, the grandmother and grandfather from Colorado--were they your
mom&#039;s parents?

SHEPHERD: Yes, they were my mother&#039;s parents.

DUNHAM: Okay, and did you know your dad&#039;s parents?

SHEPHERD: My dad was dead--he was dead when--after I was born I was about--

DUNHAM: Oh I&#039;m sorry, do you know how he passed?

SHEPHERD: No I don&#039;t.

DUNHAM: You didn&#039;t know your father?

SHEPHERD: No I didn&#039;t know him that well.

DUNHAM: Okay, so that must----

SHEPHERD: I had a step-father later on.

DUNHAM: But when you started it was just you and your mom, or did you have siblings?

SHEPHERD: I had a brother and----

S. SHEPHERD: I don&#039;t think your sister was born at that time was she?

 Shepherd:No.

S. SHEPHERD: Okay.

DUNHAM: Older brother and a younger sister?

SHEPHERD: Uh huh.

DUNHAM: What was life like for your mom when you were a young girl?

SHEPHERD: Well she worked very hard. She usually always had to take a job where
she lived in because of--you know having the children. My brother usually stayed
with my grandparents if he could, and I stayed with different people that would
keep me while he was working.

DUNHAM: Relatives or friends of the family--

SHEPHERD: Yes, friends of the family.

DUNHAM: Did you mostly grow up in Oklahoma?

SHEPHERD: No, I grew up in Colorado Springs, Colorado.

DUNHAM: So you lived near your mom&#039;s parents?

SHEPHERD: Yes--well yes--that&#039;s where they lived--in Colorado Springs, Colorado.

DUNHAM: What kind of work did you mom do?

SHEPHERD: Housework for people--working for people--cooking and cleaning.

DUNHAM: And then--

SHEPHERD: And whatever she had--sometimes when she had a job where she lived in
I could stay with her for a while--you know there--off and on like that.

DUNHAM: But otherwise she was doing live in housework?

SHEPHERD: Right, right.

DUNHAM: What was that like for you growing up and having to live with different folks?

SHEPHERD: Well I just got used to it as a way of life so--but it was okay.

DUNHAM: Were you going to school in Colorado Springs?

SHEPHERD: Yes.

DUNHAM: What was school like?

SHEPHERD: School was very well--very good.

DUNHAM: What was the population like ethnic wise? Was it very diverse?

SHEPHERD: In Colorado Springs?

DUNHAM: Uh huh, and at your school--schools?

SHEPHERD: Yeah it was--it was--I don&#039;t know how to say it.

DUNHAM: Were there many other African Americans?

SHEPHERD: There was a few, yeah. It was mixed.

DUNHAM: Did you experience much prejudice growing up? Were you aware--

SHEPHERD: Well not that much prejudice but it would be like--kids I didn&#039;t fight
very much so usually it was when school was out. It always ended up the kids was
running--chasing me home.--starting to run after me to fight.

DUNHAM: Oh yeah.

SHEPHERD: Until finally one day my mother had to a--my grandfather&#039;s horse whip,
and when I came--she was expecting me--when I saw that whip when she come--that
I was going to get a beating--I turned around and started fighting. And from
then on I didn&#039;t know I could fight.

DUNHAM: Oh yeah.

SHEPHERD: So then I made it a habit that I was going to get everyone that got
me, one by one. The one&#039;s that brought me home because I didn&#039;t know I could fight.

DUNHAM: So you learned to fight--you had to defend yourself.

SHEPHERD: I had to yeah.

DUNHAM: Did they stop giving you a hard time?

SHEPHERD: Oh yeah--yeah they stopped giving me a hard time.

DUNHAM: When you were a young girl, did you have any particular dreams or
aspirations of what you wanted to be when you grew up?

SHEPHERD: No, not really--after I grew up--well I don&#039;t know how old I was--very
young--I had a bad experience when I was in my--early--very early teens--barely
in them.----Just barely in my teens, and I had this very very bad experience
with a young man that took me out to a place called--you&#039;ve probably never heard
of it--Black Forest in Colorado. That is a big ole&#039; place where you can&#039;t even
see daylight in the day time--that&#039;s why they call it Black Forest, it&#039;s just
like night time. He abused me----as a result from that I had a child. So that
part was pretty rough.

DUNHAM: Sure.

SHEPHERD: I didn&#039;t know--too young to even know--so my mother took the child
from me and raised us. So things was pretty rough. I was afraid of men folks.

DUNHAM: Understandable, that must have been very hard.

SHEPHERD: Then it was a long time but then one came along who was very very kind
and nice to me--very nice to me, and was always trying to protect me. He didn&#039;t
know nothin&#039; about love, but he was just so nice to me. He wanted to marry me,
and so--that happened. We did get married.

DUNHAM: Now if you don&#039;t--oh sorry go ahead--the first child that you had you
were participating and raising? Was it she you said?

SHEPHERD: Huh?

DUNHAM: What was your first child&#039;s name?

SHEPHERD: Oh a girl.

DUNHAM: A girl okay, and you and your mom were raising her together?

SHEPHERD: Yes, yes.

DUNHAM: Did you have leave school then? Or were you able to continue--

SHEPHERD: Yes, just for a while, but I went back to school.

DUNHAM: Were you staying in Colorado at this time--Colorado Springs?

SHEPHERD: Yes, Colorado Springs yeah.

DUNHAM: And--

SHEPHERD: School went on pretty good, I did fairly well in school. Until I was
working--we called it Community Aides.

DUNHAM: What was that like?

SHEPHERD: Work in the community with the people in the community--social work
like--you work with--people that look out for the block and you get people to
come out to meetings for the a--

DUNHAM: Go ahead--

S. SHEPHERD: That&#039;s later on in life mama, he talkin&#039; about your earlier life--

SHEPHERD: That is the early part.

DUNHAM: You did some of that in Colorado?

SHEPHERD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Like neighborhood watch.

SHEPHERD: Yeah, they formed neighborhood councils, and that&#039;s what we were
working in--trying to get the people to come up and do something about what they
do--where to go--like they go to the city council and ask to be on the--program
so we could voice what was going on in the public--in our areas--and that they
could do something about them.

DUNHAM: And what kind of issues were you voicing and addressing?

SHEPHERD: Everything--whatever the people in the neighborhood got together and
decided was a problem--a big problem.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SHEPHERD: In the areas, and that&#039;s what we would go and let the them know at the
city council--what was going on.

DUNHAM: Do you remember any of those problems in particular?

SHEPHERD: Well we had so many of them that some people--you know that weren&#039;t
afraid to--you know to get out and speak up--go to the council and speak up for
it. The more that they understood what was going on you know--and how they could
do something about it by joining together.

DUNHAM: So were the--

SHEPHERD: So what happened to me was--I was one of the people you know that was
going out and doing it, and they didn&#039;t like it. They would do little nasty
things and would pile up a lot of broken glass in front of my door and things
like that.

DUNHAM: Oh really. So was this--

SHEPHERD: Protesting you know.

DUNHAM: Was this all racially charged? These are mostly--

SHEPHERD: No, well we lived in mostly segregated areas. A few Mexican people and
the black people.

DUNHAM: I&#039;m trying to understand what some of the significant issues are--this
is during the Depression in the thirties?

SHEPHERD: Oh yeah.

DUNHAM: What were the things you were voicing and why were some people upset
about you doing so?

SHEPHERD: Well they didn&#039;t quite understand--they didn&#039;t know what to do about
the problems in their areas and we was forming a neighborhood council so all the
peoples that were bothered would come to the meeting at the city council--where
they could be heard--or let them know they want to be heard and they could get
on the thing to speak.

DUNHAM: Right.

SHEPHERD: So that&#039;s the kind of work that I did.

DUNHAM: So you were an early activist in the community.

SHEPHERD: Yes.

DUNHAM: Again, sorry to repeat, but are there any specific issues that you
remember, you were focused on? Did it have to do with crime, or jobs or--

SHEPHERD: Yes, it was a lot of that--a lot of crime.

DUNHAM: But it wasn&#039;t so much around diversity, or white prejudice against
African Americans? It was more just within your community?

SHEPHERD: Yeah, just the problems among mostly ourselves.

DUNHAM: How did you feel about your experience participating in that way?

SHEPHERD: Well I thought it was pretty good. I learned a lot, you know, about
other people. You just can&#039;t be selfish and set to yourself. Whatever bothered
them bothers us all, and it keeps stretching and so--

DUNHAM: Were there specific signs of progress that came out of your efforts?

SHEPHERD: Yeah, it was a little slow but sure. We got more and more people
interested in coming out, you know, and showing up that they were concerned and
wanted to know how--how to do the--how to get them done. They&#039;re for somebody
else to look at so I think we did pretty good!

DUNHAM: It sounds like it--did you finish high school in Colorado Springs?

SHEPHERD: Yes I went to school --I had to go back and forth to school--so I kept
on until I got all the things that I need to do the things that I wanted to do.
So then I become a social worker. So I had to get all of these credits to get to
be the social worker. So I went to school for quite a while for that.

DUNHAM: This is in high school, or is this later?

SHEPHERD: Just later.

DUNHAM: When did you come out to California? Do you know what year--

SHEPHERD: I do not know because I was quite young.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

SHEPHERD: I don&#039;t know anything about where I was born, other than where I was born.

DUNHAM: Did you come from Colorado to California?

SHEPHERD: Oh yes.

DUNHAM: Was that with your mother and family? Or--who came out--did you come out
by yourself?

SHEPHERD: We came to a place--that was called--Allensworth.

S. SHEPHERD: You know Allensworth.

DUNHAM: Where&#039;s Allensworth?

S. SHEPHERD: It&#039;s down like by Fresno. It was a black town back then. The town
was named after Mr. Allensworth.

SHEPHERD: Yeah, Allensworth. He lived about a block from here. So he got a park
down there named after him--

S. SHEPHERD: It&#039;s a historic park. You never heard of it?

DUNHAM: I think I have but I don&#039;t want to say--well tell me about it--tell us
about it. How did you hear about it? How did you go there?

SHEPHERD: Because people needed a lot of--slave labor I call it.

DUNHAM: Oh really.

SHEPHERD: People would gather on account on corners--they would find people that
wanted to go to work--like if they planted cotton--then they had to harvest the
cotton. People needed work so bad they&#039;d come and gather them up--those who
wanted to go to work.

DUNHAM: Like day laborers?

SHEPHERD: Day labor, day labor.

DUNHAM: In Fresno, so people came to Allensworth--

SHEPHERD: From Allensworth--

DUNHAM: From Fresno for the farming--

SHEPHERD: --in Allensworth. But they came from Allensworth through Fresno.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SHEPHERD: But it was quite something learning how to do all those things we
didn&#039;t know how to do. If they planted cotton, when the cotton began to grow, it
come up and it was real thick. It was long, you know, how a farm is. I went out
there--they gave me a hoe--you know chopping--then some of them knew really what
they were doing so. I was chopping and you&#039;re only supposed to leave four of
five little things, and I was either chopping them all down too many at a time
[laughter]--and leaving them had to learn all of that. But then I--

DUNHAM: Your microphone fell off, let me just--oh it&#039;s okay if you could just
clip it a little bit higher than I had it. Thanks so much, that&#039;s great.

SHEPHERD: So I used to have terrible nose bleeds and I was a lot of problem too
because when it gets hot I&#039;d pass out with the nose bleed and they&#039;d have to
take me home-- back and forth, but I was always anxious and ready to go for the
next day.

DUNHAM: Oh you were anxious.

SHEPHERD: Yes.

DUNHAM: Because you wanted to make some money or--

SHEPHERD: --I wanted to make the money and we needed the money. So they kept
taking me, but I stopped them from doing a lot because they had to take care of
me and they didn&#039;t want me to go. But I insisted on going.

DUNHAM: Who is they? Are these other family members?

SHEPHERD: Yes, other family members or the crew that they, you know--that they
would gather up to gather.

DUNHAM: What family were you with in Allensworth? Was your mom--

SHEPHERD: Yes, well yes with my mom and her--I can&#039;t think of the people&#039;s name
I&#039;m sorry.

DUNHAM: That&#039;s okay. When you came out to Allensworth, did you already have
friends or family there?

SHEPHERD: No, the only--my a----I don&#039;t know who it was that told us about it
and we went--I can&#039;t even think right now.

DUNHAM: Okay, that&#039;s okay. Do you remember the trip out to Allensworth?

SHEPHERD: Oh yes.

DUNHAM: Did you come on the train or bus or--

SHEPHERD: No, they had an old car.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay. What was that like?

SHEPHERD: It was kind of funny because these people--we had met some older
people and that was in forty-nine I think it was--and they had--I don&#039;t know how
they got it but a old--they had bought a car--a Ford. They would come and pick
us up or let somebody in the family use the car. So I finally learned how to
drive the car, and of course naturally I go too fast [laughter] but they thought
I was great.

DUNHAM: Okay.

SHEPHERD: So they let me--let us drive us drive--it was about thirteen miles--we
lived in Earlimart.--to Earlimart from out there in the country where they
stayed. So I learned how to drive the car and I would drive them places, and
they liked it! But I didn&#039;t really know what I was doing [laughter].

DUNHAM: Well it sounds like you were doing it and doing it fast.

SHEPHERD: Yeah, they always wanted me--they come to get me and I would drive that.

DUNHAM: Well how long, oh sorry go ahead.

SHEPHERD: I didn&#039;t have any license so they said, &quot;Well you have to get some
license, you have to practice and go get some license.&quot; So I drove around and
around in the country, running over them walkin&#039; frogs-- I&#039;d never seen a
walkin&#039; frog before--and they would be walkin&#039; around. And I learned pretty
quickly you know--I would read the paper and what it says, you know, about the
driving and how to make the left turn and stop--you know, stop and go. So they
said, &quot;Oh we going.&quot;--I&#039;d go forward a long time--I had to learn to back up.
Finally, I learned how to back pretty good. So we was like, &quot;We&#039;re going to our
license! We&#039;re going to get our license today!&quot;--everybody went to get their
license. They had to go up the hill--a steep little hill going to the office
where they had it. Well, I ain&#039;t had no experience backing down a hill
[laughter]--hill or turnin&#039; around. But anyway, I managed to get my license, and
nobody else did [laughter]

DUNHAM: Oh you were the only one to pass--

SHEPHERD: --the only one.

DUNHAM: Do you remember how old you were then?

SHEPHERD: Oh I was very young, but I don&#039;t recall. But I know that I was the
only one that got em&#039;.

DUNHAM: So then you had to drive--

SHEPHERD: But I still couldn&#039;t drive--I&#039;d still would always just go where I had
to park and not back up [laughter].

DUNHAM: Wow. How long were you there in Allensworth and doing the day labor? Do
you know--

SHEPHERD: Allensworth--about how long--let me think how old Darlene was--she was
born there in the place in Allensworth.

S.Shepherd:That was 1940.

Shepherd:In 1940.

DUNHAM: And that was your second daughter?

SHEPHERD: That was my--no--yes uh huh.

S. SHEPHERD: No?

SHEPHERD: Roseena was the oldest one that I got, but she wasn&#039;t with me. She was
with my mother.

DUNHAM: So your mother and Roseena were back in Colorado--

SHEPHERD: --in Colorado, right uh huh.

DUNHAM: Did Roseena stay there and grow up there with her?

SHEPHERD: For the most part, yes she did.

DUNHAM: So how did you hear about the Richmond Shipyards, and when did you come
up here?

SHEPHERD: Well when they said there was a--a war--somebody had bombed Pearl
Harbor. I think it was Pearl Harbor.

DUNHAM: Yes.

SHEPHERD: And they said, &quot;Oh, everybody they want people to work! They want
people to work! They got jobs up there!&quot; So that&#039;s where I left Fresno and came
to --

S. SHEPHERD: North Richmond.

SHEPHERD: Huh?

S. SHEPHERD: North Richmond!

Shepherd:Yeah, come to Richmond.

DUNHAM: That was shortly after the start of the war?

SHEPHERD: No after it was--after the war was--

S. SHEPHERD: What year was the war?

DUNHAM: Well December 7, 1941 is when Pearl Harbor was bombed and so we entered
the war then.

SHEPHERD: Uh huh that&#039;s when--

DUNHAM: So then did you come up early forty-two?

SHEPHERD: I&#039;m trying to a--

S. SHEPHERD: Did you say it started in forty-one?

DUNHAM: Uh huh.

SHEPHERD: Huh?

S. SHEPHERD: No she was there--yeah, forty-two.

DUNHAM: Forty-two came to Richmond--did you come to Richmond on your own?

S. SHEPHERD: No she was with my Dad when she left--that&#039;s who she was with in Allensworth.

DUNHAM: They met in Allensworth?

S. SHEPHERD: No, they worked at Allensworth together.

DUNHAM: Okay, perfect, okay.

S. SHEPHERD: So she did--she had to come in the end of forty-one or the
beginning of forty-two because when she was working at the shipyard my brother
was born which was 1942--I wasn&#039;t born then.

DUNHAM: Okay.

S. SHEPHERD: So 1942, that&#039;s where we at.

DUNHAM: So tell me your earliest memories of Richmond. What was it like when you
got here? Did you find a place to live? Because there were already a lot of
people heading the same as you coming to find work in the shipyards and all
right? Was it had to find a place?

SHEPHERD: Yeah we found a place. What was that on seventh street--sixth?

S. SHEPHERD: There was a few--

SHEPHERD: North Richmond!

S. SHEPHERD: North Richmond on Market Street.

SHEPHERD: On Market Street in North Richmond.

DUNHAM: What kind of place?

S. SHEPHERD: Shacks.

DUNHAM: Yeah, temporary housing--

SHEPHERD: No it was a house.

DUNHAM: It was a house, okay.

SHEPHERD: It was a house, and I got a job--I had got a job as a waitress. What
was the name of that place Sharon? I can&#039;t remember.

S. SHEPHERD: No you was at the shipyard first you skipped it--

Shepherd:I mean after the shipyard closed?

S. SHEPHERD: No--you want to know before--during the shipyard time?

DUNHAM: Yeah, I would like to hear about your experiences at the shipyards and
initially in Richmond. So how did you come to get a job at the shipyards?

SHEPHERD: Oh that was--that&#039;s the day--you had to have some kind of--

S. SHEPHERD: Skill.

SHEPHERD: Skill! And most of the people didn&#039;t have any skills other than just
labor. But labor people could, you know, they&#039;d hire them to go into
shipyards--they wanted people with skills. So the Richmond High School down
there had a training thing, and I had heard about it and they trained people how
to do--to go to work in the shipyard that had some training. They needed
burners, welders and some other things they had--they used in the shipyard.
Anyway, I went to school-- at the school--at the training school that they had
at Richmond High.

S. SHEPHERD: Hold on can I say something?

DUNHAM: Sure, sure.

S. SHEPHERD: She&#039;s kind of skippin&#039; because in order for her to be a
welder--they wasn&#039;t hiring them as welders because they was black.

DUNHAM: Right.

SHEPHERD: Wait a minute, it wasn&#039;t that was--it was the unions were not taking--

S. SHEPHERD: That&#039;s what I&#039;m saying--unions well--who was in the union--the white--

Shepherd:And they was saying--what was the use of me getting that--you know
learning how to do that when the unions weren&#039;t taking in any black people. So
that went to the President--about it--people all got together and said they had
to hire em&#039;. That&#039;s how I was able to get in--you know as a welder. After I&#039;d
taking all the --

DUNHAM: So you had already done the training?

SHEPHERD: Yes.

DUNHAM: Then you went to try to get a job and the union denied you--

SHEPHERD: --right and I couldn&#039;t get a job and the unions did not take any black people.

DUNHAM: So were you involved with the Shipyard Workers Against Discrimination?
Do you remember that organization? Or Brown and the United Negro Labor Council?

SHEPHERD: Right, yes, yeah uh huh.

DUNHAM: You guys were working together?

SHEPHERD: Right we was all working together.

DUNHAM: So how long did that take after you had gotten all of your training? Do
you know?

SHEPHERD: After we got--it didn&#039;t take that long after--I think it was the
President or whoever that they had to go and see about--that they had to
hire--hire the people.

DUNHAM: Did you have demonstrations of any kind? Was there anything like--were
you aware of the Double Victory Campaign?

SHEPHERD: Well they had some--I don&#039;t think I was in--actively in them. But as
long--you know we got the job.

DUNHAM: And you had one young--you had a young child here with you already?
Or--when did you have your second child?

 Shepherd:Golly.

S. SHEPHERD: Phillip was born in 1942.

DUNHAM: Forty-two, okay.

SHEPHERD: Yeah, forty-two.

DUNHAM: So you were pregnant maybe while you were training and getting started?
Is that--

SHEPHERD: No.

DUNHAM: Or he was already born?

SHEPHERD: No I can&#039;t even get that together.

DUNHAM: Did you husband also study to work at the shipyard--train to work at the shipyards?

SHEPHERD: Yeah, he worked in the Shipyard Three--I worked at the pre-fab plant.
He worked--they had two or three--three of four yard--shipyards--different ones
you know. He worked--Mr. Barnes worked in a--as a burner--he was a burner in
shipyard number two.

DUNHAM: Did he--did you get hired around the same time, or did he get hired
before you? Was it easier as an African American man than as a woman?

Shepherd:Yeah, he was hired before me. Not that much before--he was in a
different shipyard--I was in the prefabrication yard and he was in yard three.
Then we worked at different times--he worked--excuse me--I worked the graveyard
and he worked the swing--swing shift.

DUNHAM: So you didn&#039;t see a whole lot of each other?

Shepherd:No--goin&#039; and comin&#039;.

DUNHAM: Yeah, so then you were taking care of your young son?

Shepherd:Yeah the lady--the lady that we lived--we was livin&#039;--we wasn&#039;t livin&#039;
on seventh street--we was livin&#039; in this lady&#039;s garage.

DUNHAM: Oh yeah.

Shepherd:And that&#039;s where--who was born there? Phillip?

S.Shepherd:I was born there.

Shepherd:You was born there.

DUNHAM: Okay.

Shepherd:And the lady that we rented it from took care of the kids for me.

DUNHAM: Oh yeah.

Shepherd:And it&#039;s long enough for me to go.

DUNHAM: Okay.

Shepherd:I&#039;d be home in the morning from working graveyard shift--I&#039;d get off late.

DUNHAM: So what was it like working at the shipyards in the fabrication--

Shepherd:It was nice--as far as I was concerned I liked it. And I liked to be--I
was a good welder. You had to be. I even remember--I remember even the things
that you had to weld with--532 rods for the welder. So you had to weld flat--you
had to weld vertical--and you had to do overhead. You had to do all of that real
good because you are like you are--you are making a steel room. Which is--when
it is completed is moved over to the other shipyard to go on the base. The base
is a--just like puttin&#039; rooms in a house.

DUNHAM: Well after the initial struggle and racism around getting into the
union--once you were in the shipyard did you encounter any of that kind of thing?

Shepherd:No, not at all. Not at all.

DUNHAM: What was your crew--what was the make-up of your crew and co-workers?

Shepherd:They were all mixed. They were all mixed.

DUNHAM: Men and women?

Shepherd:Then they had some--wait I think there was some Chinese people there too.

DUNHAM: Oh yeah.

Shepherd:But they are some--ooh they work you to death.

DUNHAM: You mean--

Shepherd:There were mixed people on the--

DUNHAM: So what was an average day like, or an average graveyard shift like for
you at the shipyards?

Shepherd:It was good. I liked it. There wasn&#039;t no problems.

DUNHAM: Now sometimes I&#039;ve heard that the graveyard shift in particular could
get a little--I don&#039;t know what the right word is but--I don&#039;t know rowdy, or
sometimes there might have been a little hanky-panky in the evenings?

SHEPHERD: I never experienced anything like that.

DUNHAM: What about--were you ever aware of any injuries, or what safety
precautions or issues were taken?

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: No, and you never had anything like that yourself?

Shepherd:No I didn&#039;t have any. Well in the first place--well a lot of people had
problems later on working in the shipyards--you know you get all different
{inaudible}--but I never had any.

DUNHAM: All different what?

Shepherd:Different kinds of things that happened to them.

DUNHAM: Do you remember any of those?

Shepherd:I don&#039;t remember any--I didn&#039;t have any that I know of.

DUNHAM: Well that&#039;s good. Well what was your impression of Richmond early on? So
you lived in a couple different places--it sounded like you were living in a garage.

Shepherd:Well mostly, mostly when I come to Richmond it was mostly a--I
guess--what do you call it--people just had the hot houses where they raised a--food.

S. SHEPHERD: Sun houses?

ShepherdYeah. And it just wasn&#039;t much of anything.

S. SHEPHERD: Flower houses, that&#039;s what they were.

DUNHAM: Flower houses.

Shepherd:Yes. I call them a hot house.

DUNHAM: Not a victory garden?

Shepherd:Victory, and lettuce--lettuce patches.

DUNHAM: Okay, and you remember rationing?

Shepherd:Oh yeah.

DUNHAM: Coupons and a--

 Shepherd:Hmm.

DUNHAM: Obviously you had undergone significant transitions coming out to
Allensworth and then up to Richmond--how would you say the war impacted you?

Shepherd:Well--Allensworth was very very far out--about thirteen miles to get to
a--to a town. I was there because my a sister in law lived up there and they she
a--lived in Allensworth. They bought a hog. [laughter]

DUNHAM: Bought a hog?

Shepherd:A hog yeah.

DUNHAM: Raised a hog.

Shepherd:Raised a--yeah they were raising a hog.

DUNHAM: So that&#039;s where you were living when you were living in Allensworth?

Shepherd:A huh.

DUNHAM: So after being in Colorado, and then being in Allensworth, how did
Richmond compare in terms of social life--did you have time--obviously you had a
young child and you were working graveyard and your husband was working a
different shift--did you have time for a social life?

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: No. What about just how crowded Richmond was? Were you aware of that?
You had lived in a more rural area, and you said it wasn&#039;t much. But it did
get--it grew an incredible amount during the war years. What was that like?

Shepherd:Well I don&#039;t know it didn&#039;t bother me too much.

DUNHAM: Okay.

Shepherd:I a--I was trying to think of the places--the places that I worked.

DUNHAM: After the shipyards?

Shepherd:A huh.

DUNHAM: How long did you work at the shipyards?

Shepherd:I worked till it was over.

DUNHAM: Okay, from forty-two all the way through the end of the war?

 Shepherd:Right.

DUNHAM: What was it like when the war ended?

Shepherd:You know I can&#039;t even describe it. Everybody was just glad that it was
over--in a way. Then in another way they were out of jobs.

DUNHAM: Did you lose your--

Shepherd:So you had to do--you know whatever you can--I got a job--I&#039;m trying to
think of the name of the places in the--

S. SHEPHERD: Tapper&#039;s Inn.

Shepherd:Tapper&#039;s Inn--you know as a waitress. And I was trying to think of that
other place they had--that was still in effect. I can&#039;t get my thoughts
together. [laughter]

DUNHAM: That&#039;s okay, no worries, we don&#039;t need all the exact names, but we are
just looking for some of the feelings and some of the thoughts about it too--

Shepherd:Buy anyway, I was a waitress.

DUNHAM: Did you lose your job right after the war ended?

Shepherd:Oh yes, but that was the only things that were left. Whatever the
people that had prospered--you know trying to find a place to work. That was the
only way that I did--I knew somebody wanted a--somebody to waitress. He had a
little--what do you call them--where you drink and dance?

S. SHEPHERD: A bar.

Shepherd:A bar.

DUNHAM: Tappers. Did other people have trouble finding work?

Shepherd:No, they was all doing about the same things. Whatever they could find
or do--here and there.

DUNHAM: Well you worked at the shipyards a long time--now you had a--did you
have other children during the war years? Were you born during that time Sharon?

S. SHEPHERD: A huh, in forty-three.

DUNHAM: Forty-three. So did you have to take some time off when you had your
children? When you had Sharon in forty-three?

Shepherd:Forty three--I don&#039;t know I can&#039;t remember.

DUNHAM: You don&#039;t remember okay. You don&#039;t know how long you were off for? Was
it any problem to come back to your job?

Shepherd:Oh no--as far as the shipyard--when it was over it was over. They had
other jobs.

DUNHAM: No but I mean when your daughter was born, do you remember how long you
were off work for?

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: Okay. Well a lot of people must have come and gone to some extent during
those years--were there many changes--did you do the same job all through the
war--at the shipyards?

Shepherd:Oh yeah, I was a welder. So there was always a need for the welder.

DUNHAM: And you were always working in the prefab--

Shepherd:--welders, chippers, burners--all of them--they had something for them
to do.

DUNHAM: People were coming from all over the country--a lot of folks from the
south in particular. How did you relate to the people from different places?

Shepherd:Well, most of the people that came from the south I couldn&#039;t understand
much of anything that they was saying. Because they just--you know I guess never
been to school or talked the talk--you know you had to figure out what they were
saying--trying to say. So it was kind of difficult for them getting&#039; jobs--you
know when you can&#039;t talk--or you&#039;re talking to somebody--trying to talk to
somebody and they don&#039;t understand anything you&#039;re saying. That part was hard so
you just--you know you just pass it up.

DUNHAM: You mentioned you kind of had a deal with the woman who you were--in the
garage where you lived--she helped take care of your kids when you were at work.

Shepherd:Yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: Was that just an informal relationship or did you--

Shepherd:--yeah well she had a house--a big house--and then she had the garage
out there.

DUNHAM: Okay.

Shepherd:And since it was hard for people to find any places--that was the only
place we could find to stay if we wanted to live in there. She let us live
in--but she had some other little shacks all around--you know in the back--her
and her husband. Their name was Turner, I&#039;d never forget that. They had
built--you know for them--but we were in the garage because that was the biggest piece.

DUNHAM: So were you there through most of the war years?

Shepherd:Oh yeah.

DUNHAM: When did you leave there?

Shepherd:We left there--we was--where did we go?

S. SHEPHERD: To another house. Miss Turner owned a--

Shepherd:Oh yeah, she had a house that was on a regular street--a regular
street. I call it a house. We moved in there until things--people begin to--come
back--you know and build their own places or move into their own places.

DUNHAM: Now you mentioned that you built this house, how much later was
that--quite a bit?

S. SHEPHERD: Oh yeah, we are still in North Richmond right now [laughter]

SHEPHERD: [laughter]

DUNHAM: Do you remember how much you made at the shipyards?

Shepherd:You know--I don&#039;t really know.

DUNHAM: Was it better money that you had been making in Allensworth? And previously--

Shepherd:--oh yeah, oh my god yes. Allensworth was nothing. Oh yeah. I&#039;d say--I
was trying to figure out--what did we make an hour--but it was big to us.

DUNHAM: Yeah, it was a lot better. Were you able to save some money with a young
family and all--were your expenses taking up all that?

Shepherd:No, we wasn&#039;t making nothing to save but we could live a lot better
than what we had been.

DUNHAM: Did you have also help support your mom or daughter back in Colorado, or
were they doing okay with your grandparents and them there?

Shepherd:I guess--I don&#039;t know--I don&#039;t know back there.

DUNHAM: Partly I ask about the wage too because similar to the problem you had
with getting in the union, and the prejudice you experienced there--sometimes
we&#039;ve heard there were also different wages, and African Americans and or women
didn&#039;t get paid as much. So I wonder if you were aware if that issue ever came up?

Shepherd:Oh I wasn&#039;t aware of that. Whatever trade you had you got the same pay
that anybody else got.

DUNHAM: Hopefully, yeah. It should have been, but sometimes I&#039;ve heard that
there were disparities and of course it&#039;s hard to know--

Shepherd:--there might have been by I didn&#039;t know about them.

DUNHAM: When you first got there how did the men workers treat the women
workers? Sometimes we have heard that there was a little--it was kind of a tough
transition--particularly you were there pretty early in the war and that
although the women were definitely needed--that men didn&#039;t always take to it
real easily.

Shepherd:I don&#039;t know anything about that.

DUNHAM: Okay. Now of course you mentioned growing up how you had become pretty
tough and had to learn to fight for yourself--did that sort of toughness and
strength you developed--was that ever an issue at the shipyard--something you
needed to rely on?

Shepherd:Well the only thing I was concerned about--you had to unionize to have
somebody to help fight for you when things come up that you don&#039;t like and you
report it to your union head and let them look into it. So they began to form
more unions for people that had complaints.

DUNHAM: And what kind of things came up like that?

Shepherd:Oh all kinds of things.

DUNHAM: Could you give me?

Shepherd:But when they know they had some help--and somebody is going to fight
them--I think it cooled it down.

DUNHAM: So that improved over the course of the war while you were working?

 Shepherd:Yeah.

DUNHAM: Were there any examples that you specifically faced that you needed to raise?

Shepherd:None at all.

DUNHAM: Okay, can you remember examples that others raised?

Shepherd:No not really because when I got through with work and got home that
was it. I wasn&#039;t worried about anything.

DUNHAM: So it wasn&#039;t, that you knew of, it wasn&#039;t with issues around wage--was
it issues maybe around safety--or unfair or different practices?

Shepherd:No, I didn&#039;t hear anything about any of those.

DUNHAM: Okay, but you were aware that as the union--as people became more
together in the union--similar to your earlier community activism--that there
was more strength and you had more--

Shepherd:--oh yeah, you had somewhere to go.

DUNHAM: Okay.

Shepherd:If something did come up, but I didn&#039;t have any of that problem.

DUNHAM: So you kind of had a healthcare situation built in with the person you
lived with, were you aware of others there who did get healthcare provided by
Kaiser or others during the war?

Shepherd:I don&#039;t recall any.

DUNHAM: Okay, I might have said healthcare--healthcare too, but I meant daycare.
I guess what I was talking about, sorry.

S. SHEPHERD: I was going to say healthcare--

DUNHAM: I know they started the childcare development centers here--again like
many things there is an issue of who got access to those things first--and at
first it was whites only who got access and I&#039;m just curious if who had heard
about that at all--and either yourself or friends who were able or not able to
utilize services like that.

 Shepherd:----

DUNHAM: Not that you&#039;re aware of? That&#039;s fine. I know you were very busy, but
did you go out some--to either the movies or clubs or restaurants?

Shepherd:No, not really. We mostly played cards or something at home.

DUNHAM: What kind of cards did you play?

Shepherd:Whist. Bid whist.

DUNHAM: Did you lis--go ahead.

Shepherd:That was all I was going to say, we&#039;d play whist or bid whist and that
would be for money. [laughter]

DUNHAM: With friends?

Shepherd:A huh.

DUNHAM: Did you listen to the radio?

Shepherd:Yeah, sometimes--I don&#039;t know if we even had one.

DUNHAM: Or do you remember listening to any kind of music in those days--either
the radio, or in person, or at the shipyards? Did they have lunch-time concerts?
So you were--were you graveyard all through--

 Shepherd:Huh?

DUNHAM: Were you graveyard shift all through your work years? Did you ever work
the day shift?

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: No, okay.

Shepherd:Only the graveyard.

DUNHAM: What about war bonds--do you remember advertisements for war bonds in
order to purchase war bonds?

Shepherd:Yeah I remember that--I don&#039;t think I ever purchased any.

DUNHAM: Do you recall how you were evaluated on the job?

Shepherd:No I don&#039;t.

DUNHAM: What would you say the culture was like at the shipyards? Was there a
strong sense of patriotism? Was it mainly a job and you needed it?

Shepherd:I think it was more like--patriot----you know togetherness.

DUNHAM: What about your sense as a welder--a female welder?

Shepherd:Oh there was others up beside me.

DUNHAM: Did you see images of the women war front workers--you know the iconic
Rosie the Riveter and that kind of thing in posters or newsreels?

Shepherd:Did I see any?

DUNHAM: A huh.

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: No, okay. Well what are other significant--you mentioned you were
dreaming about it last night. What was it like in your dream? What were you recalling?

Shepherd:Oh, I was just recalling working. With my leather suit on--I was just
welding away [laughter] that&#039;s all.

DUNHAM: Did you enjoy the work?

Shepherd:Yeah I did.

DUNHAM: Was it hard work?

SHEPHERD: It wasn&#039;t--it was hard but it was tiresome because welding you
know--depending on which way--flat or vertical--you had to be very careful to
get that metal metal--you know soft--up and down together to firm it up and it
all guzzle into the steel. I enjoyed it myself.

DUNHAM: Did you go to any of the ship launchings and celebrate those?

Shepherd:No, I never went to any of them.

DUNHAM: Were you aware of the Port Chicago disaster in July of 1944?

Shepherd:Only heard about it.

DUNHAM: You didn&#039;t feel it?

SHEPHERD: No.

DUNHAM: What did you hear about it at the time?

Shepherd:I can&#039;t even recall all the stuff [laugther]

DUNHAM: But you knew at some point that there had been a big explosion?

 Shepherd:Yes.

DUNHAM: Out at Port Chicago over 300 were killed, over 200 were African American
soldiers. Did you hear anything about the mutiny trial that occurred subsequent
to it?

Shepherd:No, I don&#039;t recall any of that.

DUNHAM: Because that--similar to the union issue--in that case fifty African
American soldiers were put on trial for mutiny which is a very questionable
charge to this day--which has not been overturned. Thurgood Marshall came out in
the appeal and got the sentences reduced but it was still was a tremendous kind
of--bad mark I would say. But--it also played a role in the desegregation
arguably of the military and the broader society ultimately. But it&#039;s a history
we&#039;re looking at closely--it&#039;s very few survivors at this point of course from
that time period. As I told you we did an interview with Mr. Herbert yesterday
and any others we have with direct or related experiences we are trying to
interview. The National Park now--the memorial for Port Chicago has become a
national park itself now.

Shepherd:Oh, that&#039;s good.

DUNHAM: So it&#039;s a little challenging because it is still run by the Army
now--it&#039;s not Navy it&#039;s now Army. So it&#039;s not always open to the public but you
can do tours. Anyway, the blast was felt throughout the Bay Area by some. Of
course at first people thought it might have been an attack since people had
been afraid of that.

Now do you remember that kind of thing? Of blackouts, or did you have any
concern being on the west coast around that? During the war?

Shepherd:No I didn&#039;t.

DUNHAM: Did you know of any Japanese, German or Italian Americans? Any who were
incarcerated during the war--Japanese particularly?

Shepherd:I think they sent them to a camp didn&#039;t they? That&#039;s all I know.

DUNHAM: But there weren&#039;t any that you had known personally?

Shepherd:No, no.

DUNHAM: Do you remember where you were on either V-E Day of V-J Day?

Shepherd:No, I sure don&#039;t.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay

S. SHEPHERD: What day is this?

DUNHAM: Victory in Europe and then Victory in Japan Day. I mean very shortly
after V-J Day is probably when you probably got a pink slip and most of the jobs
at the shipyards ended.

S. SHEPHERD: So they don&#039;t call that Veteran&#039;s Day do they?

DUNHAM: No, that&#039;s a--V-J Day--this would have been shortly after the droppings
of the atomic bombs in Japan in forty-five.

What were the years after the war like in Richmond? You got a job as a waitress?

 Shepherd:Yes.

DUNHAM: Was it hard to make a go of it?

 Shepherd:No.

DUNHAM: You were able to find steady work?

SHEPHERD: People always like to eat.

DUNHAM: So did you work many years as a waitress?

Shepherd:Yeah, and then I had a little restaurant of my own.

DUNHAM: Oh, when did you start that?

Shepherd:I can&#039;t--can you remember Sherry?

S. SHEPHERD: I don&#039;t remember--I remember it was on Third and Chesley.

Shepherd:Chesley, yeah.

DUNHAM: Ok, and what was it called?

S. SHEPHERD: We forgot.

DUNHAM: Okay, not sure what it&#039;s--

S. SHEPHERD: My sister had passed--she would have known. But I can&#039;t think of--

Shepherd:I can&#039;t think of what I called it anyway.

DUNHAM: So you ran that restaurant?

 Shepherd:Yes.

DUNHAM: What was that like? That a tough job.

Shepherd:Yeah, it is. It was good but it was kind of hard to keep--you had to
have somebody to help you and it was hard to keep good help--that are in there.

DUNHAM: Was your husband a partner in this?

Shepherd:No, he was dead. He was dead.

DUNHAM: Oh, I&#039;m sorry.

S. SHEPHERD: You ever heard of Minnie Lou&#039;s?

DUNHAM: Yes.

S. SHEPHERD: Okay it was directly across from where--Minnie Lou&#039;s wasn&#039;t there yet.

DUNHAM: Okay.

S. SHEPHERD: But Minnie Lou&#039;s was on this side of the street, and she was on
this side.

DUNHAM: Okay, and was it a particular kind of food?

Shepherd:Just ordinary food, but then you could--

S. SHEPHERD: Fried chicken was--

DUNHAM: And if you don&#039;t mind me asking, how did your husband pass?

Shepherd:He died--he had a hemorrhage.

S. SHEPHERD: Aneurism.

DUNHAM: Was this after the war ended?

S. SHEPHERD: Yeah, it was after.

DUNHAM: I&#039;m sorry. --Well what is your perspective having lived in Richmond all
these years? You&#039;ve been to the Rosie the Riveter Park and all, what is your
perspective on it?

S. SHEPHERD: Well she can&#039;t see it, she&#039;s blind.

DUNHAM: But you know about it, and you know that&#039;s been made into a national
park--I guess over ten years now. How do you feel about that?

S. SHEPHERD: Mom?

Shepherd:The what?

DUNHAM: I was just asking about the park--the National Park being here in
Richmond--the Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front Park.

 Shepherd:Oh.

DUNHAM: What&#039;s your take on that?

Shepherd:I think it will be nice.

S. SHEPHERD: It&#039;s already here Mom.

 Shepherd:Hmm?

Shepherd:I said I think--

S. SHEPHERD: But we&#039;ve been trying to get her picture out there--you know but we
go down to the home front down there--where there&#039;s that office you know
but--they said they lookin&#039; into it but--

DUNHAM: Trying to find?

S. SHEPHERD: Trying to get her picture up there.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay. You&#039;ve given them a copy of--

S. SHEPHERD: They already got all of that--they got her picture where she was
wearing her badge so--

DUNHAM: Yeah, that&#039;s great. Yeah. Let me get a close up of that. You know the
visitor center is I think going to open finally Memorial Day next year, and they
are going to have some different Rosie the Riveter events. So I&#039;ll try to make
sure to let you know, but you&#039;re nearby so I would check in with them.

S. SHEPHERD: We always go to--they didn&#039;t have one this year.

DUNHAM: No they did have the Home Front Festival, that&#039;s what your mom said.

Shepherd:Yeah, we were just talking about it.

DUNHAM: It was the first of second Saturday in October. Or maybe they didn&#039;t do
publicity well again.

Shepherd:They sure didn&#039;t.

DUNHAM: Because usually they would have sent your mom an invitation and everything.

SHEPHERD: A huh, we sure do. A lot of them said they didn&#039;t go.

S. ShepherdThe second is her birthday, and that&#039;s what she was--

DUNHAM: Right, well I&#039;m really sorry about that. I&#039;ll make sure that you guys
are on the list--I know they have you.

S. SHEPHERD: So you say that they did have it?

DUNHAM: They did--yeah I was there. I was talking to--

Shepherd:We didn&#039;t even hear anything about it.

DUNHAM: I don&#039;t know why that would have happened. But I&#039;ll make sure you&#039;re on
the list, and as I said they&#039;re going to have some events--

Shepherd:Because I was telling her--I was like, &quot;They didn&#039;t have Rosie the
Riveter like they used to have one every year--you know.&quot;

DUNHAM: Yeah no they had--

Shepherd:I was telling my daughter--

DUNHAM: Yeah, they did have it, and there will be some events--definitely
Memorial Day weekend is when it&#039;s targeted for and I guess they do maybe a big
baseball--maybe the Giants game--they&#039;re going to have a big thing honoring
Rosies. We&#039;ll definitely check in--let me go ahead and get at--well before I do
that is there anything else you&#039;d like to add today just about your life
experience during the war--that you&#039;d like to share with us for this interview.

Shepherd:No, it was quite an experience. I learned a lot from it. It was quite
an experience and some of the things I dream about sometimes unknowingly.

DUNHAM: What kind of things stand out that come back to you?

Shepherd:The things that come back to me is how I had to get into the yard--into
the shipyard for something other than the labor. Those are the things that stand
out the most to me, and I didn&#039;t want to go in there--they needed laborers and
then they needed people that had a trade that could do something. That stands
out a lot in my memories--how it worked and how it always worked. That poor
people or black people were the last ones on the list--you know you had to fight
for everything to get where you are. The thing is to keep fighting and not give
up. You think you&#039;re right and you can prove it--generally I think you should
have a space there to say--and for somebody to pay attention to what you say.

DUNHAM: Did those experiences in form--did that occur again later in life?
Certainly racism hasn&#039;t gone away.

Shepherd:No it hasn&#039;t. But most people just sort of accepted it, and don&#039;t think
about it until they run up on it.

S. SHEPHERD: I don&#039;t think that our family per se or--I say when we started in
North Richmond we didn&#039;t see much prejudice. We always read about it--you know
back south--but not here. I&#039;ll be sixty-eight years old--you know with the
school it was always black and white.

DUNHAM: Here at Kennedy?

S. SHEPHERD: No I went to Verdi School in North Richmond, they I went to
Richmond High. No I went to Verdi School, they I went to Hamm School--went to
Roosevelt and Richmond High was the last one.

[End of Interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>