<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042473" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2011-05-24" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Jack Rosston | Interview 1 | May 24, 2011</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><keyword>1930’s</keyword><keyword> Personal background </keyword><keyword>The Great Depression </keyword><keyword>Parental background </keyword><keyword> San Francisco, California</keyword><keyword> UC Berkeley</keyword><keyword> Racism</keyword><keyword>  Family’s migration</keyword><keyword> Family politics</keyword><keyword> 1906 Earthquake</keyword><keyword> National Youth Administration </keyword><keyword> Pre-atomic Research </keyword><keyword>WPA Bureau of Occupations</keyword><keyword> Bethlehem Shipyards</keyword><keyword> socialization</keyword><keyword> Pearl Harbor</keyword><keyword> War conditions</keyword><keyword>  accelerated education</keyword><keyword> working student</keyword><keyword> depression</keyword><keyword> family finances</keyword><keyword> diversity</keyword><keyword> Patriotism</keyword><keyword> dissents</keyword><keyword> evacuation and internment</keyword><keyword> conditions for Japanese</keyword><keyword> FDR</keyword><keyword> 1939 World’s Fair</keyword><interviewee>Jack Rosston</interviewee><interviewer>Sam Redman</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|16(2)|62(12)|75(3)|91(5)|104(10)|131(7)|193(13)|208(8)|220(5)|234(2)|259(2)|285(13)|320(11)|333(1)|369(9)|382(10)|412(4)|427(6)|456(3)|468(7)|476(11)|493(12)|502(5)|510(4)|540(2)|594(3)|629(6)|673(3)|690(1)|710(9)|741(9)|756(7)|786(6)|797(1)|812(10)|825(9)|841(8)|889(2)|912(6)|943(3)|987(7)|1010(10)|1029(6)|1042(9)|1054(4)|1075(3)|1088(9)|1096(7)|1128(6)|1150(12)|1161(1)|1172(11)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>QbfKfNz3bUs</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Jack Rosston was born in 1921 in San Francisco, where he spent his childhood. He later attended in the University of California, Berkeley where he would remain a dedicated member of the university’s Alumni Association, eventually serving as the alumni representative on the Board of Regents. In this interview, Rosston recalls memories of San Francisco during the Great Depression. A temporary job with a New Deal agency, the National Youth Administration (NYA) allowed him to start attending the University. In this interview, Rosston shares memories of life on campus as a student at the outset of the war, including memories of various student reactions to the bombing of Pearl Harbor. Rosston later joined the US Army, where he was stationed on the home front for the duration of the war before returning to California where he became active in Commerce, Industry, and Labor and in volunteering on behalf of the University. In the last section he recalls various aspects of fundraising for UC and for the libraries in particular.</description><rel /><transcript>REDMAN: Today is Tuesday, May 23, 2011. I&#039;m here today in San Francisco with
Jack Rosston. My name is Sam Redman, and this is the first tape of my interview
with Jack, focusing primarily on his life during the Second World War. In
addition to learning about the war, I&#039;d like to ask Jack about his recollections
of his time at UC Berkeley and his ongoing interests in the Bancroft Library
and his time with the Board of Regents and with the UC Alumni Association. Jack,
I&#039;d like to just begin by asking you to state and then spell your name, if you
wouldn&#039;t mind.

ROSSTON: Jack Rosston, R-O-S-S-T-O-N. Formally, John W.

REDMAN: Can you tell me
where and when you were born?

ROSSTON: I was born in San Francisco, October 18, 1921, at Mount Zion Hospital,
which is about ten blocks away from where we&#039;re sitting.

REDMAN: It&#039;s sort of come full circle for you. You&#039;re back in this area.

ROSSTON: Back in San Francisco.

REDMAN: Based on our conversations over the phone, it sounded like you were
quite young during the Great Depression. In fact, you wouldn&#039;t have really known
what life was like for people before the Great Depression. You sort of were
growing up, and some of your earliest memories would have been during the Great
Depression. Was there an awareness, maybe, when you were very young, that people
were very poor and this was sort of a tough economic time?

ROSSTON: I know that my family&#039;s income went way, way down. We used to turn out
the lights and all that to save money. I was sixteen when I started at Berkeley.

REDMAN: Let&#039;s jump back a little earlier. I&#039;d like to hear a little bit about
your parents and what they were like.

ROSSTON: My mother was born in Woodland, California, of six children. My
grandfather was a hale fellow. He enjoyed his life and his booze and his women,
but he raised his family very nicely. He had a store in Woodland. I didn&#039;t know
any of my grandparents, because my grandmothers both died in 1922. I was born in
&#039;21. My grandfathers predeceased me. I was the youngest of a family of a lot of
people, but the youngest of my generation. For several years, I&#039;ve been the only
survivor in either family.

REDMAN: You had siblings, then?

ROSSTON: I had a brother, who went to Berkeley.

REDMAN: He was an older brother? A couple of years older?

ROSSTON: Three years older.

REDMAN: So it was the two of you at home, and then your parents, growing up. Is
that correct?

ROSSTON: Yes. We lived in San Francisco.

REDMAN: Before you started at Berkeley, I&#039;d like to hear a little bit about what
San Francisco was like as a young child.

ROSSTON: I started at Sutro School, which was on Funston Avenue and is no longer
a school there. It&#039;s kind of a building that has replaced the building. Then I
went to Presidio Junior High School for three years, which was in the
neighborhood. Then I went to Lowell High School, which was the high school, but
George Washington High School had just opened. I was in the first group of
people that went to Washington, and I was in the first June graduating class. I
was the valedictorian. It was a successful place for me to go to school. Then I
went to Berkeley and I had a $125 scholarship, which paid my $26 fees and my lab
fees and my books. But I had to work.

REDMAN: Let me jump back to high school. I&#039;m curious, were there some topics
that you found particularly interesting, even as a high school student? Were
there some subjects in school that--

ROSSTON: Looking back, I was sort of herded into chemistry. I had a job of five
dollars a month, setting up the chemical experiments. I was fascinated with
chemistry. My father thought it would be a wonderful place to have an income.
Well, I got to Berkeley, and the first year I did fairly well. Then I started
falling apart. By the end of my sophomore year, my grades were going down. I
said, &quot;I don&#039;t want to be a chemist,&quot; so that&#039;s when I wanted to become an
economist. But I could not become an economist in two years, and I really wanted
to get out in two years, but I discovered that some of the courses I had taken
in chemistry would be a credit for me if I majored in agricultural economics. So
I changed into the college of agriculture and graduated in Agriculture/Economics.

REDMAN: Let me ask, because you had been a pretty accomplished young
student--even leading up to your time at Berkeley, you&#039;d been valedictorian.
You&#039;d graduated pretty early. You graduated from high school at, what, fifteen
years old? Is that correct?

ROSSTON: Sixteen years old.

REDMAN: Can you tell me a little bit about the acceleration of your academic program?

ROSSTON: I guess I accelerated one semester when I was in grammar school, and
then I was in high school--they were in for six-month semesters--and I was going
to get out in December. I thought, really I want to go to college, so I took an
extra course. Instead of four heavy courses a year, I took five, and so that got
me out six months early. I did six-month skips to get out of high school at age
sixteen in June 1938.

REDMAN: What were the other kids like growing up in San Francisco? Did you make
a lot of friends in San Francisco?

ROSSTON: I had a lot of friends. Of course, when I went to Berkeley, a different
atmosphere. I had grown up with this guy who lived a block away when we were
little kids, and we went all through public school together. But I got out six
months ahead of him and went to Berkeley and really never saw him again until
about a month ago. His sister moved in here. We put things together. We had
talked over the phone a couple of times. It was pretty exciting. Obviously, I
wouldn&#039;t have recognized him, and he wouldn&#039;t have recognized me.

REDMAN: Tell me a little bit in general about what the other kids were like
growing up. I&#039;m curious how diverse San Francisco would have been in that time
in terms of race and religion.

ROSSTON: It was not very diverse. I lived in the Richmond district. In my class,
there was one Japanese boy. His name was Seichi Matesueda, S-E-I-C-H-I,
M-A-T-E-S-U-D-A. I had two or three or four other friends, including this man
who I just met again. So I went through grammar school with Seichi. We were in
different classrooms in junior high school, but we kept in touch, but I had
other friends who were in my classroom in those days. Then I graduated from
there, and then I went to Lowell High School for six months, and then I went to
Washington High School. I ended up as the number one scholar, so I became
valedictorian. I was a very shy kid who worked, even going to high school, to
get spending money. My father&#039;s business--he was a brilliant man, but his
business just fell apart.

REDMAN: Can you tell me a little bit about that, when that happened, when his
business fell apart? It affected you by then because you had to go find work
here and there to--

ROSSTON: I started selling magazines when I was in grammar school. Then I got a
job in the chemistry lab, setting up experiments at five dollars a month to go
through high school. Then in my senior year I did some coaching and got paid
thirty-five cents a half hour.

REDMAN: What did you coach?

ROSSTON: Math, probably, or science. I only had a couple or three clients, but
it gave me a little bit of extra money, or a little bit of money.

REDMAN: So you&#039;d maybe spend that on clothes, or did you contribute to the
family&#039;s expenses?

ROSSTON: My clothes were all hand-me-downs. I had a cousin in New York who
shipped things out, and then my brother wore them, and then I wore them. I think
I did have a suit, a new suit, when I graduated from high school.

REDMAN: I&#039;m just curious if the idea to go to Cal was pretty clear in your mind.
It strikes me that in that time, even some of the very good students, or some
students that were maybe a little more average at the time, could go down to Cal
and you&#039;d register and you&#039;d pay your fee, and you were a Cal student. It wasn&#039;t
always assumed that even very smart people would go to college in that period.

ROSSTON: I think that there was some restriction. I don&#039;t know. I know a lot of
my friends from high school went to Berkeley, and some who could afford it went
to Stanford and other colleges.

REDMAN: For you, it was in part a financial decision to come to Cal, maybe?

ROSSTON: I just wanted to come to Cal. My brother was in Cal. He was three years
ahead of me at Cal.

REDMAN: What was he studying at Cal?

ROSSTON: Pre-law. He went on to law school. He then went to law school at
Berkeley, but he didn&#039;t finish until after the war. He went two years before he
went into the Navy.

REDMAN: I&#039;d like to get into that story again, too. I&#039;m curious. I&#039;ve read about
the waves of immigrants that really started to come, or migrants from other
places in the US, from, say, the Midwest and the South, that really started to
come here after the war started. But I know that there had been a lot of waves
of new migrants of different types of people coming even before the war, and I&#039;m
curious because we talked about growing up, maybe San Francisco wasn&#039;t as
diverse, but then prior to the war, you start to have a bunch of people moving
in. Did you notice any of that at the time?

ROSSTON: It started really early. My mother&#039;s parents came--she was born in
1885. She was the youngest of six, so they had gotten over here. They settled in
Lake County, and my grandfather had a store. Then they moved down to Woodland,
and he got involved a little bit in politics. He was the mayor of Woodland, and
he had a store. I think he had a wonderful time with life and booze and women.
My mother&#039;s family finally moved down to San Francisco in the early 1900s,
before the earthquake. My mother was here for the earthquake.

REDMAN: Did she tell stories about the earthquake and how that had affected her life?

ROSSTON: Oh, sure, yes.

REDMAN: What did she tell you about that?

ROSSTON: She, I think, went as far as the eighth grade in school, and then the
family moved to Sacramento, and she was terribly shy. She didn&#039;t want to go to
school, and so my grandfather said, &quot;You&#039;ve got to do something, or I&#039;m going to
send you to business school.&quot; At age sixteen, she graduated from business school
and became a secretary in Sacramento, at twenty-five dollars a month. She gave
her mother twenty dollars and had five dollars for spending money but also did
some work for taking shorthand from the assemblymen and worked for them. Then
the family moved to San Francisco in the early twentieth century. Then along
came the earthquake, and she worked for Southern Pacific for several years, and
then she was secretary to the--I guess he was one of the leading lawyers there.
He said, &quot;You&#039;re never going to get anywhere here,&quot; and he got her a job with an
importer/exporter, so then she went to work there. Then when she got
married--women, in 1916, who got married quit.

REDMAN: That was the end of your working career.

ROSSTON: That was the end of my mother&#039;s work.

REDMAN: Did she talk at all about the actual events of the day or the week that
followed the San Francisco earthquake?

ROSSTON: Oh, yes.

REDMAN: What did she say about that?

ROSSTON: The family lived west of Fillmore Street, so they were affected by the
quake, but not the fire. That night, her older sister was getting married and
had some wedding presents. They put her in a Morris chair, which is a chair on
wheels, and wheeled it out to Golden Gate Park, and they slept the night in
Golden Gate Park. They offered railroad passes to relatives outside the area, so
all my mother&#039;s family--a couple of her brothers had been married, but I think
about three or four of them went with her mother and father down to her older
brother&#039;s house, newly wed with one child. They all descended on him, including
her sister-in-law&#039;s family. Then they came back to San Francisco, and she got a
job at Southern Pacific. By the time she married my father, she had left
Southern Pacific; she was secretary to one of the vice presidents. He said,
&quot;You&#039;re not getting anywhere. I&#039;ll get you another job.&quot; So then she worked for
a year and got married, and that was it.

REDMAN: And that was the end of the working career. Let&#039;s go back to Cal. What
year, then, would you have arrived at Cal, do you recall?

ROSSTON: Nineteen thirty-eight.

REDMAN: Let&#039;s take some time, and I&#039;d like if you could explain to me what your
first impressions were of the UC campus and Berkeley, the city of Berkeley. In
1938, what were the University of California and Berkeley like?

ROSSTON: Oh, I was so excited. I was so pleased to be there. Actually, my first
semester, I got very good grades. Then I just fell apart during my second year.
My grades just went [makes sound effect].

REDMAN: The chemistry was challenging.

ROSSTON: It was challenging, but it was not my interest. My first job over there
was NYA and they were doing, I guess, pre-atomic bomb work.

REDMAN: NYA, the National Youth Administration?

ROSSTON: Yes. That was like WPA. At any rate, I got a job, would you believe it
or not. It was in the labs, where they were producing vacuums for research on
what eventually went into the bomb. The professor that was in the lab I was
working for had apparently been poisoned from inhaling mercury. There were
vacuum pumps. They had mercury in them, and the mercury pellets fell on the
floor, and the professor began to get poisoning. So this little kid, at forty
cents an hour, crawled around on the floor with a flask and a little vacuum tube
and swept up all these things. I guess I was exposed to mercury, too. But, at
any rate, obviously I&#039;ve survived it. I&#039;m going to be ninety.

REDMAN: It was dangerous, but thankfully--

ROSSTON: Then, afterwards, they found out I had some knowledge of French, so I
went in and library-searched for any articles about heavy water in French, and
to refer them to the scientists. That was a much easier job to do.

REDMAN: Yeah, certainly better than sweeping up mercury. I&#039;m particularly
interested in New Deal-era programs like the National Youth Administration and
the WPA and then the Civilian Conservation Corps. Can you tell me what your
recollections are about the NYA in particular? You got hooked up with them as a
student that maybe needed a little extra--

ROSSTON: For my freshman year, I got ten dollars a month. That paid for my
transportation to Berkeley from San Francisco, and that&#039;s about all I paid for,
so I had to have other jobs. Then my second year--

REDMAN: I&#039;m sorry to interrupt. Do you remember how you would sign up for a job
at the NYA?

ROSSTON: There was something called the Bureau of Occupations. Everybody was in
line, and there was this woman who was in charge of it, and she did a very good
job. She had a few jobs, but she had to be very tough. But she did a good job,
and I got that job. NYA, that was a standard, ten dollars a month. I had a
chance to move to Berkeley and to live in a co-op boarding house for twenty-two
dollars a month. Well, I couldn&#039;t afford it. Two of my mother&#039;s friends, whose
father died, said they&#039;d give me five dollars a month so I could move over
there, so I got five dollars a month when I was a sophomore. I worked, and NYA
went up to fifteen dollars a month, and then I did a lot of extra jobs. I would
work as a waiter at I-House for sixty cents. I lived in the co-op, which was
only twenty-three dollars a month.

REDMAN: I want to ask about both your experience at the co-op and at I-House in
the late 1930s. Can you tell me what your impressions of the other students were
at the co-op? Did you make friends there?

ROSSTON: Oh, I had very good friends. In fact, I still have one of my friends,
who is about ninety-three. We&#039;re trying to get together. He&#039;s the one whose
mother did an oral history on film.

REDMAN: One of ROHO&#039;s very early filmed--

ROSSTON: The first.

REDMAN: First filmed oral history. Anyway, your impressions of the other
students at the co-op, I&#039;m interested in.

ROSSTON: They were working pretty hard. There were certain degrees of
sophistication. I was at the bottom. I was the most unsophisticated kid. I was
one of the younger ones in there when I got there, but I was so damned
unsophisticated, it was unbelievable.

REDMAN: Tell me about in what sense you mean that. I&#039;m curious.

ROSSTON: I was very shy. I didn&#039;t have any money, practically, to date girls. I
could take her to a dance. It was fifteen cents a piece. Maybe we could go and
have a Coke.

REDMAN: Right, so your dating life was a little handicapped by your income at
that time. As far as the other students, were you impressed with their
intelligence and their interest in academics? I&#039;m curious if a lot of other
students at this time, because economic times were so tough, they were working a
lot of these jobs, it sounds like, and I&#039;m curious how that would affect--

ROSSTON: Some were and some weren&#039;t. I&#039;ve kept up with several of my friends
from the co-op. They&#039;re all in their nineties now. One of them, who has been my
best friend all these years, was raised on a farm. His father said, &quot;You don&#039;t
have to go to college to be a farmer.&quot; But somehow or other, he got to go to Cal
Poly for a couple of years, and then he transferred to Berkeley. That&#039;s when I
met him, when I started ag-econ with him. I could do the econ; he could do the ag.

REDMAN: So you helped each other out a little bit, maybe, studying periodically?

ROSSTON: Yes. He lived in Sheridan Hall. Then he got married when he was in his
twenties. He&#039;s older than I am. He must be about ninety-four now. That&#039;s been a
lifelong, very close friendship.

REDMAN: How about I-House? You said you waited tables there. Is that correct?

ROSSTON: Only when I could get sixty cents and an artichoke. I didn&#039;t really do
much at I-House.

REDMAN: I&#039;ll just ask this quickly. Prior to the war, did you attend football
games or sporting events or things like that?

ROSSTON: Yes. Ten dollars a year would get you into the ASUC, and you got a
football pass for the year.

REDMAN: Did you enjoy going to games periodically?

ROSSTON: I enjoyed it. I was not a great athlete or a great athlete follower,
but I did enjoy the spirit. I went to the basketball games and the football
games, but I was not athletic.

REDMAN: So it was less so for you about observing the actual sporting event and
more so the pageantry of having the band, the colors, the songs.

ROSSTON: I loved, and still love, Berkeley.

REDMAN: Yes, just spending time--

ROSSTON: Yes. I&#039;m still doing a lot of things at Berkeley. Not nearly what I was
doing, but I still get over for library meetings.

REDMAN: It sounds like, from the very beginning, you&#039;d fallen in love with the
idea of being a student at Cal and living in Berkeley. Was there a particular
moment for you where it sort of clicked, where you realized, this is going to be
a special relationship that you have with--?

ROSSTON: I just felt that way from the very beginning. I was so proud to go to
Berkeley. I had a lot of friends from George Washington High School who went to
Berkeley. During that period, Lowell had been the number one feeder to Berkeley.
A lot of students from Lowell went to the brand-new high school, and it became
the number one feeder to Berkeley for almost twenty-five years. Then Lowell
became more of a specialist area. It&#039;s been the number one feeder to Berkeley
for many years.

REDMAN: The next question I&#039;d like to ask is actually about Pearl Harbor. My
understanding is that Pearl Harbor was attacked in December of 1941, in the
midst of finals at Cal. I&#039;m curious if you could tell me about what your
recollections are of that day.

ROSSTON: During that period, I was not much of a scholar as I should have been.
I had to get a term paper in. I stayed up all night on December 6, finishing
that paper and submitting it. I got to bed and then I heard people screaming,
and that was how I learned about Pearl Harbor. I was isolated over there. I was
living in a co-op boarding house, which was fine. I think I called my parents
for ten cents, just to check on things. We had blackouts at Berkeley.

REDMAN: Did the blackouts come more or less immediately after--?

ROSSTON: Immediately after, just about. In San Francisco and Berkeley, I
remember we had black paper over our windows in my parents&#039; apartment. There was
a basement that they had for emergencies.

REDMAN: Now, I understand that, again, very quickly, people volunteered to be
blackout wardens, or would be paid--

ROSSTON: My father was in his fifties and not very healthy. He became a warden.

REDMAN: So he would go around in San Francisco--

ROSSTON: He would go around with certain equipment. I don&#039;t know where that came
from. It was pretty scary, because we thought we were going to be bombed. A
submarine did put shells in Santa Barbara.

REDMAN: Let me ask about that. I&#039;ve sort of been given some different
perspectives on the degree to which people thought there would actually be an
attack in the San Francisco Bay area. Some people tell me that, yeah, the fear
was very real and it was there, and other people say people wanted to be
prepared, but they realized that there was--

ROSSTON: Sort of halfway, each way. Some shells hit Santa Barbara from the submarines.

REDMAN: When there were submarines off the coast, and I know there were
newspaper reports about those. Were people also talking about that?

ROSSTON: Oh, sure.

REDMAN: So that was a very real thing?

ROSSTON: Yes. Women really hadn&#039;t started working in the factories. The movement
of people from other parts of the country hadn&#039;t started that much because the
jobs were not there, but they did get there. When I got out of college--I think
I told you--I got a job in a shipyard and made a pile of money, for those days.

REDMAN: It strikes me that in December of 1941, when Pearl Harbor is attacked,
students at Cal are presented in some sense with a series of choices. That they
could continue on with their education, and some, presumably, left Cal and
signed up for the armed forces or for other kinds of--

ROSSTON: Or in the reserves and were drafted. My brother was in law school, and
he was in the reserves. They clapped him in.

REDMAN: I&#039;m just curious how other students you may have known, or just what
your impressions were of students, how they would navigate this. It seems like,
for you, you were a little young at that time to join the armed forces, and then
you decided to go to work at the shipyards. How did you sort of come to that
decision, and how were other students navigating this?

ROSSTON: I really had applied for an ROTC program at Stanford. It was in
conjunction with Stanford Business School, which is just exactly what I wanted.
I went to Stanford, and I had to find money to go to Stanford, which I got in
the shipyards. Enough for two quarters.

REDMAN: Let&#039;s switch gears, then, and we&#039;ll talk about what life was like at the
shipyards. I&#039;m just curious. Let&#039;s just finish up on Pearl Harbor before we get
to the shipyards. Can you tell me just a bit more about what the reaction on
campus was like? Do you remember, maybe, the next day?

ROSSTON: Oh, yes. The student body of Berkeley always goes from left to right.
Maybe more on left, but I remember that boarding house, there were idiots who
were saying, &quot;We&#039;ve got to go kill all the Japanese and the Japanese students come.&quot;

REDMAN: There was a very powerful anti-Japanese sentiment?

ROSSTON: Not very powerful. There were just a few idiots. I just couldn&#039;t
believe it. I had been raised in a family that didn&#039;t have any racial problems
with anybody. That&#039;s what I grew up with. &quot;Let&#039;s get the Japs, all of them, and
kill them.&quot; That was the worst, but most people were not that way.

REDMAN: That was a surprising thing to you, having grown up in a place where
there was more tolerance, it sounds like, of different--

ROSSTON: Yes. There were just a couple of really rednecks in there, and I really
got upset with them.

REDMAN: Just briefly, I&#039;d like to ask about your impressions of political
activism on campus. Berkeley has this very exciting reputation as far as being a
place for activism and free speech and that. We associate that more in some
sense with the fifties, sixties, and seventies. I&#039;m curious--

ROSSTON: It was in the thirties. Before we were in the war, Germany and Russia
were together in Poland. There was the Young Communist League. Young people,
Socialists, over here at ASU, active at campus. The more extreme ones were
picketing the campus because they couldn&#039;t do anything on campus in those days.
I can remember posters at the gates to the campus: &quot;The Yanks are not coming.&quot;
When Germany and Russia got together, the signs were adjusted to say, &quot;The Yanks
are not coming too late.&quot; It really is absolutely true. I don&#039;t think there were
many Nazis, but there were Communists over there.

REDMAN: Were there people, too, that wanted to stay out of the war entirely for
a variety of different reasons?

ROSSTON: I didn&#039;t get that impression very much, no. It was a traumatic thing to
have your mainland bombed.

REDMAN: It seems like, then, as soon as Pearl Harbor happens, that sort of wipes
clean any sort of political fervent of trying to keep us out of the war.

ROSSTON: I think it did, but there were some people who were over-extreme. The
over-extreme, in my opinion, was what they did to the Japanese.

REDMAN: Tell me about that, because that happens soon after the start of the war.

ROSSTON: They took all of the Japanese on the West Coast. First of all, they put
them down in the peninsula, in Tanforan, which was a horse racing place, and
they accommodated them in the stables, and then they shipped them off to the
camps. I knew people who were shipped off to the camps. The University of
California was fantastic. The President and the Provost--there were some
students who were six months from graduation. They saw to it that they had all
their information so they could take the courses by mail. That was Sproul and--I
forget the name of the Provost. They were really incredible. On the fiftieth
anniversary of my class, the Japanese, who now had come back and been successes,
gave more money per capita than the other students to the University. They had
never graduated. They got diplomas by mail. So that year, they had a ceremony on
campus, handing out diplomas to the Japanese in caps and gowns. I was there and
I took part in it. It was exciting.

REDMAN: It&#039;s interesting. It seems like, for you, as someone who had grown up
with some Japanese friends, that that would have been a challenging moment for
you in terms of hearing about the Japanese being interned, but at the same time,
having this distant enemy. Were there any sort of conflicting emotions, or did
you sort of immediately--?

ROSSTON: I didn&#039;t have conflicting emotions. I didn&#039;t have many, because there
weren&#039;t many Japanese. I didn&#039;t have any conflicting problems about it at all. I
didn&#039;t like to see what happened to them. That was conflicting. But about them,
no, there were no conflicting feelings.

REDMAN: One of the things that I&#039;ve heard is that--and this would, I believe, be
true in your life--basically, your entire awareness, your life as a person,
Franklin Delano Roosevelt had been President. For a lot of people, they had seen
him as the end-all, be-all of the executive office. He was sort of the only
president they&#039;d ever known.

ROSSTON: Yes. I remember--I don&#039;t know how old I was when he came to San
Francisco. My aunt took me down to Geary and Van Ness, and I saw him go by in a
car. It was a parade. He was in an open car.

REDMAN: It must have been a truly exciting moment.

ROSSTON: Oh, it was. It was before we got into the war.

REDMAN: Speaking of which, I would like to jump back. There was a series of
questions--something that came up upstairs that hadn&#039;t come up over the phone
when we spoke earlier about the World&#039;s Fair in San Francisco. You had mentioned
that one of your odd jobs that you picked up was cleaning bottles up during the
1939 World&#039;s Fair.

ROSSTON: Picking bottles up on Treasure Island, yes. They had glass bottles, but
they couldn&#039;t take them off, so people just left them on the ground. Someone had
to go around and collect them.

REDMAN: Can you tell me what your recollections are of that fair? As someone who
obviously never had an opportunity to go to that fair, tell me about what it was like.

ROSSTON: It was a very exciting thing. I went both years. It was not a big
expense to go to that fair because the ferry boats were a nickel. It was still a
reflection of the Depression.

REDMAN: What was there to do when you arrived at the fair?

ROSSTON: Oh, there were all kinds of exhibits. All kinds of exhibits. Then there
were lots of things you paid for, and then there was a lot of entertainment,
outdoor entertainment. Orchestras and Hollywood stars and that sort of thing.

REDMAN: One of the things I&#039;m curious about is that it seems like art assumes a
place in your life. At least to this day, I saw your own art collection, and
then we talked a little bit about art on the way down to this room. At the &#039;39
fair, I know there were some art exhibits in addition to all kinds of
entertainment, related to music or everything else. Do you remember, just in
particular, if it was music or art or entertainment or dancing?

ROSSTON: There was music, and Hollywood people would be up there. [John Phillip]
Sousa&#039;s Band. No, I did not have much appreciation for art. I really got that
from my wife.

REDMAN: So that only came a little--

ROSSTON: I did get some, but then after I got married--she was an artist, or is
an artist. She&#039;s still doing things.

REDMAN: Can you tell me her name, because she&#039;s going to come into this story?

ROSSTON: Barbara Hearst-Rosston.

REDMAN: When did you first meet, so that I can ask you a question about that
later? It was following the war?

ROSSTON: Oh, yes. We didn&#039;t get married until I was thirty-six years old. I had
known her for over five years. The romance didn&#039;t start until after four and a
half years.

REDMAN: We&#039;ll get back to that. Let&#039;s talk about the shipyards. I&#039;ve seen
photographs and some old video footage of what it was like to sign up for work.
This was the Kaiser Shipyards, correct? In Richmond?

ROSSTON: No, I worked in San Francisco.

REDMAN: At the Bethlehem Shipyards?

ROSSTON: Yes.

REDMAN: At some places, you&#039;d go and sign up and you&#039;d get an identification
badge of some sort. You&#039;d have to fill out an application and maybe you&#039;d get a
health exam of some sort.

ROSSTON: I think maybe I did not. I&#039;m hazy on that, but I was young and I was healthy.

REDMAN: So that wouldn&#039;t have been much of a consideration?

ROSSTON: It wasn&#039;t important to me. All that was a concern was that I could get
in there. Of course, working twelve hours a day at double time was incredible
for someone who was in debt for sixty-two dollars. I really needed the money to
go to Stanford. It cost $162 a quarter, plus books, room and board. I was able
to finance it for a couple of quarters.

REDMAN: Now here&#039;s a big question. What was the difference in your impression of
the people that you&#039;d met at Cal, these young students that you&#039;d met at Cal,
versus the people you were meeting now at the shipyards?

ROSSTON: Oh, I was really shocked. I was out in the Richmond district. I was
pretty much protected. These were just unbelievable people. Yet I did make a
couple of friends.

REDMAN: What was so different about them from, say, your average young Cal
student at that time?

ROSSTON: I met one guy, who became a good friend, and he died quite young, who
was married and was not healthy. He was working in the shipyard and we became
good friends, but then he died shortly after the war.

REDMAN: You probably were interacting with men who may have been older or may
have had--

ROSSTON: Everybody was older.

REDMAN: Yeah, I suppose. You were such a young guy. Everybody was older. But
there may have been men with health problems or things like that, or maybe had a draft--

ROSSTON: I never noticed that. This was a rough-and-tumble bunch. I&#039;d never been
out in factories or that sort of thing. I&#039;d been in a rather protected environment.

REDMAN: How about things like the language or jokes or things like that? Was
there a different sort of--?

ROSSTON: Oh, yeah, and sexual performance.

REDMAN: Tell me about that in particular. Were there things like catcalling and
stuff like that?

ROSSTON: Oh, yeah. I was so innocent, I didn&#039;t know what was going on.

REDMAN: So these were all kind of new things.

ROSSTON: Yes, I was exposed to something--and I worked such long hours, and
transporting back and forth on the bus. Or streetcars, I guess I did part of it.

REDMAN: One of the things that you&#039;ve mentioned is performance of sexuality,
which is very interesting. San Francisco now is known as the city where there&#039;s
a more open and free sense of sexuality, and certainly it&#039;s known as a city
where there&#039;s a large homosexual population. Before that, in this period, from
my impression, it was something that was, in some sense, out there, but in
another sense, it wasn&#039;t talked about in nearly the same way.

ROSSTON: Homosexuals were made fun of. I think they would be gathering at Foster&#039;s.

REDMAN: What was Foster&#039;s?

ROSSTON: It was a cheap restaurant. Serve yourself. I don&#039;t know. It was like
something strange. A lot of people were observers. I didn&#039;t care to look at it.
Anyway, I couldn&#039;t afford to do any of these things, so it didn&#039;t make any
difference how I felt.

REDMAN: The impression that you had was that there was a distinct group that
maybe worked at shipyards or did different types of work and then would go meet
up at a restaurant.

ROSSTON: I didn&#039;t even notice. As far as I knew, everybody at the shipyard was
heterosexual. That was probably not true. I was pretty damn innocent.

REDMAN: My understanding is that at the very start of the war, the factories
were still heavily male. As more and more young men joined the service, there
were these campaigns to bring young women into the factory, the so-called Rosie
the Riveters. So &#039;41 is the start of the war, and then you end up at the
Bethlehem Shipyards for a six-month time period, starting when about?

ROSSTON: Forty-two.

REDMAN: Forty-two. It&#039;s just incredible that you can remember that.

ROSSTON: Well, I graduated from college in &#039;42. I don&#039;t think I spent six months
there. I got out in May and then I started in September. It was almost six months.

REDMAN: In that time, then, were there more and more women starting to enter
factory jobs?

ROSSTON: Not that I know of. The shipyards I was at were men--and white men.

REDMAN: That&#039;s the other interesting thing. My understanding at the Bethlehem
Shipyards is that they were slower to hire women, but also, in particular,
minorities. You had noticed that maybe a little bit.

ROSSTON: Yes. I don&#039;t know about Chinese, but obviously there were no Japanese.
I don&#039;t remember particularly any Chinese. I had one Chinese friend in high
school. There were a couple of Chinese. That was all there were in my high
school. In George Washington High School, maybe a couple of Asians. The Chinese
would be working out in Sea Cliff and have a basement room that was about the
size of a cubicle, and go someplace else to go to the toilet.

REDMAN: Different living conditions at that time. If there are any other
memories about what the other shipyard workers were like--there was a bit more
of a brash sense of humor than you&#039;re used to. Is that really one of the
striking things? How was the work ethic at that time do you think?

ROSSTON: I think it was pretty good. It&#039;s hard to say. But there obviously were
no women. Particularly, I did have one friend who I kept up with for a year or
two, and then he died. That&#039;s why he was 4-F.

REDMAN: One of the things that we talked about a little bit, we sort of talked
about the dissent with the Communist movement. There had been these sort of very
minor threads of dissent. It interests me because it seems like the vast
majority of people were very patriotic and unified at this time.

ROSSTON: Oh, no question. It was a very patriotic country.

REDMAN: It seems like the vast majority of people were volunteering, were
signing up for war bonds, for things like that.

ROSSTON: My father, in his ill health, in his sixties, was a warden. My mother
was out sewing for soldiers and sailors.

REDMAN: Let me just ask, then, was there any dissent that you had encountered in
terms of both from the Communist movement or an isolationist? It seems like that
sort of vanished.

ROSSTON: I think once we were bombed, this became quite a unified country.

REDMAN: How about Victory gardens? Was that something that existed at all in the
urban environment of San Francisco?

ROSSTON: A little bit, yes. A little bit. I lived in an apartment where we
didn&#039;t have a garden. People did do that.

REDMAN: The next thing, then, that I&#039;ll just jump to as we finish this tape is
rationing. Everybody seems to have a different story as far as what was their
priority. If you don&#039;t have a car, you maybe don&#039;t care as much about the rubber
tires being rationed, but if you eat meat or wear shoes, you obviously have a
ration for those things as well. How did rationing affect your life, if at all?

ROSSTON: Not that much. We didn&#039;t have a car. After I became an officer, I was
never assigned overseas. I bought a couple of second-hand cars, which were
absolute disasters, so I ended up with no car.

REDMAN: How would you get to work each day? What was your main mode of transportation?

ROSSTON: Getting to work, before I got into the Army, I took the streetcars.

REDMAN: Tell me a little bit about the streetcar system in that era.

ROSSTON: I was in the Richmond district. I would take a streetcar down to the
center of town, and then take a streetcar that would take me out to the
shipyard. It was maybe an hour each way. I don&#039;t remember that that clearly. It
may have been less.

REDMAN: How about the bridge systems? I&#039;m curious because the Golden Gate Bridge
and the Bay Bridge had been completed prior to the war, in the 1930s. Do you
recall those being completed or people talking about how that had changed?

ROSSTON: I went to George Washington High School, which had a gorgeous view of
the Golden Gate, and I watched that Golden Gate Bridge go up. I walked across it
the first day it was open.

REDMAN: Is that right? How did people talk about the Golden Gate Bridge as it
was going up?

ROSSTON: Everybody that I know was very proud of it. It cost sixty-five cents to
go across it when it was first opened, and then it went down to twenty-five
cents when it started to be used, and then it went up and up. The Golden Gate
and Bay Bridge both did about the same. Neither one of them were terribly crowded.

REDMAN: At that time, it was something that you could easily utilize as a way to
get across into Marin or back into San Francisco.

ROSSTON: Yes. I used to hike in Marin. I would take the ferry boat over or the
bus over. I guess before the bridges, I&#039;d take a ferry boat over and then take a
train to go to someplace to go hiking. That was rare. That was expensive. I
utilized the ferry boats when I first went to Berkeley, because the first six
months there was no service to Berkeley except by ferry boat.

REDMAN: Let me ask a follow-up question about that, but I&#039;m going to add a new tape.

REDMAN: Today is Tuesday, May 23, 2011. I&#039;m here in San Francisco with Jack
Rosston. My name is Sam Redman. This is the second tape of our interview today.
Jack, when we left off, we were talking about the Golden Gate Bridge and what
sort of an effect that had on the Bay Area. I&#039;d like to ask you a question about
the Golden Gate Bridge as a symbol of the San Francisco Bay area. Now, you grew
up here, and you were born in a San Francisco without a Golden Gate Bridge. I&#039;ve
heard it compared to--it&#039;s the Eiffel Tower of the West Coast, in some sense.
It&#039;s a symbol of, maybe along with the Hollywood sign and the Space Needle in
Seattle, the West Coast. Can you maybe tell me a little bit about what the
Golden Gate Bridge means to you and how you think it&#039;s an icon? Do you think
it&#039;s an icon in this sort of way, in some sense?

ROSSTON: I think it&#039;s more important than the other places you mentioned because
it&#039;s actually quite utilitarian and quite beautiful. It serves transportation,
getting back and forth on buses, and certainly transportation for the
communities from the North Bay. It built up that area, the suburbs of San Francisco.

REDMAN: That&#039;s really a terrific observation. Maybe you can just tell me a
little more about the first day the bridge was opened, walking across it. You
would have been a young man and--

ROSSTON: I was about fifteen.

REDMAN: What are your recollections of that? From the sounds of it, it just
sounds like it was a fun, big party.

ROSSTON: It was a fun, big party. I think I had a cardboard hat, a cowboy hat.
Everybody dressed up. All the young people were going across the bridge. I had
an elderly aunt who got on, and I remember seeing her on the bridge sitting down
on--there was a thing between the walking and the automobiles, and she was
sitting on that because she couldn&#039;t walk that much further. I was there on
opening day, but I was in Europe on the fiftieth anniversary. My son took that
walk. That was when the bridge cluttered up and almost fell down.

REDMAN: But he was able to do a similar sort of event, but it was maybe a little
too crowded.

ROSSTON: The bridge almost fell down, I think.

REDMAN: Let&#039;s get back to the shipyards. We&#039;ll maybe go from the shipyards up to
your time at Stanford Business School, and then we&#039;ll see where we&#039;re at there.
I&#039;d like to ask about union activity at the Bethlehem Shipyards. I have to
confess I&#039;m not sure, based on my readings, to what extent unions were there.

ROSSTON: I was a member of a union. I had to be a member of a union.

REDMAN: Do you recall what union you joined? So it was a closed shop?

ROSSTON: Something Electricians. An electrician&#039;s union. There was a fancier
name for it, but.

REDMAN: What were your responsibilities at the shipyards? Do you feel like the
union played any role other than--?

ROSSTON: One of the things we did--they had magnetic mines, and they had
something called degaussing. They put cables around inside of ships so that the
magnetic mine wouldn&#039;t go on one of them. I was involved in that. I got involved
in it because I went to the school to learn to become an electrician, which was
going to take six months, which was absolutely impossible. I had to do a diagram
the first week, and I could do it because I had taken physics. So I immediately
became an electrician.

REDMAN: After basically a few hours of--

ROSSTON: Yes. I think it was only a matter of a day or two before they took me
out of school and said, &quot;You don&#039;t need this school,&quot; and I got a job.

REDMAN: But in particular, it was the activity of drawing a diagram that
signaled to them that--

ROSSTON: I knew how to connect things in a diagram. I was mainly pulling cables
through holes in the things between parts of the ships. It was mainly manual
labor, but at least I could understand what they were doing, which I think gave
me a go-ahead that I could get in. I was the lowest-paid, which was pretty high
pay in those days.

REDMAN: Was the attitude of most of the workers towards someone like yourself,
&quot;Okay, here&#039;s this young guy,&quot; or &quot;Here&#039;s this college guy&quot;?

ROSSTON: I think they kind of put up with me pretty well, and I put up with them
pretty well, and I did make some friends.

REDMAN: So people were generally pretty friendly and--

ROSSTON: I wasn&#039;t used to people of this environment, actually, is the word to
use. I was only sixteen years old. They were having a hell of a good time. I
didn&#039;t know how to do it.

REDMAN: Did it seem to you like most people were enjoying? It seems like a lot
of people were suddenly making money.

ROSSTON: Yes, that&#039;s right. These people had all been workmen or out-of-work
men. This was pretty good pay.

REDMAN: Did you get an impression of what they did? You were obviously taking
your money and paying off debt from your undergraduate days.

ROSSTON: I did that in a weekend. That was the fastest I ever thought I could do it.

REDMAN: Then you&#039;re saving some money for future studies, but what do you think
most of the other people were doing with their money? Do you think they were--?

ROSSTON: I really didn&#039;t have any feeling. I&#039;m sure they spent it. There were
stories of women who worked in the shipyards going to [I.] Magnin&#039;s, and the
first black women to buy clothes at Magnin&#039;s. It was sort of a leveling,
leveling both in sex and in race. There were a lot of good things that came out
of necessity. I think it leveled the United States a lot. Women in the shipyards
and racial mixtures in the shipyards.

REDMAN: There were stories, then, that would have been circulating about black
women being able to go into these stores for the first time.

ROSSTON: Oh, yes. There were shocks when black women went into Magnin&#039;s.
Magnin&#039;s was the fancy ladies&#039; store.

REDMAN: But they had the money to--so it&#039;s interesting.

ROSSTON: Well, they had the money, but they also had the right.

REDMAN: That would have been something unique for a lot of people in San
Francisco versus places like--

ROSSTON: Well, there hadn&#039;t been any black people here. I don&#039;t know whether I
told you when I was a little kid in the streetcar that I saw the first black
person. I said to my mother, &quot;Why don&#039;t they wash?&quot; and my mother was going,
&quot;Shh! Shh!&quot;

REDMAN: These embarrassing things that kids say.

ROSSTON: I had no idea. I had never seen a black person before. I must have been
about seven years old.

REDMAN: Just a total mystery, right. I&#039;m curious about religion at the
shipyards. If you got any impression if there were people of maybe differing
faiths, or if that was even a consideration.

ROSSTON: I don&#039;t think I noticed anything like that. I really was not from a
formally religious family. I just went through it. I did not go to Sunday
school. We did not go to a place of worship.

REDMAN: It sounds like you were moving around the ship and doing this electrical
work. It strikes me that other people doing factory work, either building ships
or airplanes, would be working on one section of the ship.

ROSSTON: This was like wiring a ship, but it wasn&#039;t wiring. It was putting
cables in to reflect so that magnetic mines would not hit the ship.

REDMAN: Did you feel like you got an impression of what the entire ship was like
because you moved around the entire ship?

ROSSTON: Not that much. I just remember going into where I was going down to the
hole. It was manual labor, mostly, but I had some idea how electric things were
connected, and that&#039;s how I got through without going to school.

REDMAN: You would have been the youngest. Did you have a crew of men that you
would do this work with?

ROSSTON: It changed. Some of them were quite young, but I don&#039;t think any of
them were as young as I was.

REDMAN: They were, at this time, pretty much all white in that shipyard?

ROSSTON: Yes, they were.

REDMAN: But maybe from different class backgrounds?

ROSSTON: Yes.

REDMAN: Tell me about paying off your debt. It&#039;s an incredible thing to be able
to pay it off in a weekend.

ROSSTON: I owed sixty-two dollars, and I made $130 that weekend. That was just
absolutely outstanding. I hadn&#039;t made that much in a year.

REDMAN: You had it in your mind from pretty early on that you wanted to attend
Stanford Business School?

ROSSTON: Not really. It was a program that I thought was fascinating.

REDMAN: And you thought maybe you could do an ROTC program there while--

ROSSTON: That was part of it. I joined this program to become a quartermaster
officer. It was a contract, and it got all screwed up. I was moved in and out. I
went through basic training in Wyoming, Fort Warren. We had something called
pre-OCS [Officer Candidate School] that I went through. We had a lieutenant who
was in charge of it, and he had a book that he opened up. They didn&#039;t have
spiral books, so it always opened to one page, and I was on the page. So he
asked me all the questions. Then they gave me an examination of a course that I
didn&#039;t take, and I flunked it, so then they kicked me out of the program. Then I
got into what they called ASTP [Army Specialized Training Program]. Have you
heard of it?

REDMAN: No.

ROSSTON: That was the language--I applied to go to ASTP because I was kicked out
of the program I was in, and I was accepted. I ended up in Wyoming for training,
and then I ended up in Minnesota. They put me in French language, because I&#039;d
had French in high school. After about two or three weeks, they said they don&#039;t
need French anymore; they need German. I had taken one year of German at
Berkeley, and it was my first disaster with an academic thing. I got in. I was
sent to Minnesota at Carleton College. I had about four or five weeks of French,
and I was so excited. Then they said, &quot;We don&#039;t need French. You&#039;re going to be
changed to German.&quot; There was an aptitude test that I&#039;d take, and I could switch
language and I hated German. Well, I had fabulous set of teachers, and I really
enjoyed it. And I enjoyed German poetry. After about six weeks of this, the Army
caught on that they&#039;d had a contract with me about this ROTC. They said, under
the contract, could I get on a train and leave where I was and go to Stanford? I
got on and met all of my friends who were not kicked off the program. Six weeks
later, we were all called to active duty. I went back to OCS then, in Minnesota.

REDMAN: Tell me about what Carleton would have been like at this time. That&#039;s
actually not far from where I grew up. I&#039;m curious because it seems like a lot
of college campuses were asked to do various training programs and things like
that. You said your teachers were quite good.

ROSSTON: Oh, they were very, very good. I took a year of German at Berkeley. I
was getting As and Bs, mostly As, but Cs in German.

REDMAN: German is a tough language. It&#039;s not easy.

ROSSTON: I got in--for five or six weeks we were in a group where we didn&#039;t
speak English. We got along. Then I got other training, because I was
transferred out to Stanford again out of that program. I loved German poetry. I
loved it. I&#039;d hated it before. It&#039;s just how things are presented. My
father--who had spoken German in New York before he spoke English, I think--was
so excited he could speak German to me. I had gotten along without English. I
got back to San Francisco; I couldn&#039;t speak. I never could get back my German.
It&#039;s interesting when you get into a concentrated program. I brushed up on my
French a bit, but I&#039;ve lost that now.

REDMAN: Were your instructors at Carleton--you got the impression that they were
Carleton professors?

ROSSTON: No, they were sent from other places. There was {Herb Roker?}. I don&#039;t
know where he was from. And {inaudible name} something or other. They were both
just excellent teachers. I got into German poetry. I loved it. By the end of six weeks--

REDMAN: Pretty amazing for an Army training. Certainly, in order to learn
German, you want to--

ROSSTON: These were intellectuals doing their part. We would learn so that we
could be in the government when we got into Germany. That was what we were for.
My brother had learned Japanese, and he was in the Pacific.

REDMAN: So you both had some sort of an aptitude for languages.

ROSSTON: I guess we did. We passed tests well.

REDMAN: Let me ask about your active duty. You spent three years, until the end
of the war, in the US Army? Is that correct?

ROSSTON: Yes, I did. I had three or four months in Wyoming. I thought it was
just absolutely awful. In May, I was out in the rifle range, and the glue froze.
The whole bunch of us from Stanford went out. There were about thirty of us.

REDMAN: Wyoming was a bit different from Palo Alto.

ROSSTON: Yes. I was one of the few, maybe two or three, that didn&#039;t end up in
the hospital with pneumonia or other things, and I was not the most vigorous
kid. Then I was dropped out of the program, and then I got back in again. Then I
went to OCS, and I got to another guy where it opened to my page, but he changed
books and he never called on me again, so I got through OCS. Then
alphabetically, they put us in--I was in Camp Lee, Virginia for about five or
six weeks after I graduated. Hotter than hell in June. They really had nothing
for us to do. They broke a bit from the alphabetic roster, two rosters, both
starting from A and going to Z, and they sort of alternated. Then they gave
assignments. The Rs and Ss went to California, Camp Stoneman. I spent the rest
of the war there.

REDMAN: Then at the end of the war, you were discharged.

ROSSTON: My father had had some strokes, and he was the sole support of the
family. He really wasn&#039;t doing that well anyway. So I got early discharge and
really ended up as a nurse and running his business for him. Then he died, and
the business all fell apart.

REDMAN: I&#039;d like to do a follow-up interview with you about your continued life
at the University of California, but let&#039;s conclude at Stanford, if that&#039;s all
right. Let me ask about what the experience was like going to Stanford business school.

ROSSTON: It was a fantastic school. I had my two quarters there. I worked in the
library for forty cents an hour. I could study at the same time. I had the two
quarters there. Then after the war, of course I could have gone there on the GI
Bill, but I was also needed to support my mother and father.

REDMAN: So you used the GI benefits in that way, to support your family?

ROSSTON: No. I had adequate work fulltime, but then I went to work through the
Berkeley employment agency, which was called the Bureau of Occupation. I don&#039;t
know if it still is. I got a referral to Stanford. The Stanford Research
Institute was just starting, and I got a job down there. Then I worked there. It
was owned by Stanford, and it was later just associated. Then they said
employees could take one course a year, so I started taking courses there. Then
they ran out of money, and they fired two-thirds of the people because they
almost closed. I couldn&#039;t go to school anymore.

REDMAN: I want to ask a question that I completely forgot to ask. Port Chicago.
In 1944, there was a massive explosion.

ROSSTON: I was in Camp Stoneman, which was not far from it.

REDMAN: Tell me about what the reaction was like at Camp Stoneman at that time.

ROSSTON: We could have been on another planet. That&#039;s really what it was like.
It didn&#039;t affect us at all. The job that I had at Camp Stoneman--there were
truck companies, and the truck companies would take these GIs either to the
docks, or if there was a troop ship going out, they would take a skeleton group
to get things started. We would take them by truck. Then we would then take them
by truck down to the ferry boat, which would take masses of them down. Then
after the war, we were taking them back. It was a motor pool. I was assigned to
this. We never had a car. I didn&#039;t know how to drive. I was a real kid of the
Depression. At any rate, I had to teach myself to drive, because I was leading
convoys. They one day said second lieutenants will not have drivers. I took a
jeep and went around the motor pool, and then I was leading convoy. So much for
that. I was not happy there. I was so close to home.

REDMAN: When the explosion happens, presumably--I&#039;ve heard stories that people
in Berkeley and Oakland either had their windows shatter or they could feel it.

ROSSTON: I don&#039;t think that was true. I was at Camp Stoneman, which was quite
close. I didn&#039;t know it had even happened, except I read it in the papers.

REDMAN: The other thing is that it was quite secret.

ROSSTON: Yes, and it was all blacks.

REDMAN: Did you hear about that, then, later on? That there had been--

ROSSTON: I knew it happened, but that&#039;s about it. It did not affect what I was
doing, because we were not using that as part of our operation.

REDMAN: This is a challenging question. You&#039;d mentioned that you were a child of
the Great Depression. I think that&#039;s a really fascinating way to state it. You&#039;d
also come of age during the start of the Second World War. I&#039;d like to ask if
you could just reflect on both of these two things in the course of your entire
life. It seems like these were both pretty important influences.

ROSSTON: Oh, they certainly were.

REDMAN: Tell me if you could sort of summarize what the--

ROSSTON: Obviously, they gave me a discipline for just survival. I was very
close to my family. My father died very shortly after the war. My mother lived
for quite a few years after that. She lived to be eighty-five. He lived to be
about seventy, and he was eight years older than she. So she was a widow for a
long time. My life worked out. I worked at SRI, and then when that fell apart, I
was able to do some research on what I wanted to do. I had some reserve
practically done. I decided I wanted to get into marketing, and I thought the
two things in San Francisco would be either beer or bread. So I went to some of
the bakeries, and I also went just to a couple of the breweries, but I did some
research on them.

REDMAN: What made you decide beer or bread?

ROSSTON: Because I figured that marketing and advertising was important for
{brand checks?}. I prepared a study on the beer industry, and then I went to the
switchboard, and I said, &quot;I want to speak to the sales manager.&quot; It was a good
day. She sent me, and we clicked. Then he hired me.

REDMAN: What brewery was this?

ROSSTON: Lucky Lager. It was then becoming the largest brewery in the state, or
west, of the Pacific. I got the job there. I was living with my mother on 23rd
Avenue, in, I guess, a five-by-seven room, sharing the flat with my mother and
my aunt. My first assignment was during the Korean War, and I said, &quot;The Korean
War is here. I&#039;m in the reserve.&quot; So the guy who was hiring me said, &quot;So what if
it happens? I was here before the war and I came back after, so if you get
called back, we&#039;ll take you back again.&quot; So that made me feel good, but I was
never called up.

Then there was a steel shortage. They had a brand new brewery, and they couldn&#039;t
buy canned beer because they couldn&#039;t get steel. I don&#039;t know how I got involved
in it, but anyway, I did, about a request for an allocation. I knew how to write
reports. I had been an editor of reports. The President called me in. I was
making what a beer salesman was making. And I think the guy who hired me was
wonderful, and he&#039;s the one who was sort of pushing it. He said, &quot;He can do
something for us.&quot; At any rate, I wrote an analysis of what was happening to a
new brewery that had no allocation, and why should a brewery that had a huge
allocation--because they had to look at sales--should get an allocation. I did
some work on it, and then the President called me down and said, &quot;Don&#039;t tell
anyone, but I&#039;m sending you back to Washington,&quot; which was the beginning of my
career there.

So I was sent back to Washington, and I&#039;d never been there except for
{inaudible}. At any rate, I got back there, and the former Quartermaster General
was working for the can company in Washington. He took me to lunch every day. I
spent my time in my underwear in the hotel. It was summer, and the air
conditioner wasn&#039;t working. At any rate, I finally got in to be interviewed,
after about three weeks of just sitting and getting out at four o&#039;clock to go
see a museum. I got back, and I got an allocation, which was tremendous for the
brewery. So I was suddenly put on {inaudible}, and that was the beginning of my
career there.

REDMAN: Let&#039;s pause there. You and I are going to need to sit down, I think, for another follow-up interview, because this was very useful.

[end of session]</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>