<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042297" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2002-10-21" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Sal Chavez | Interview 1 | October 21, 2002</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Sal Chavez</interviewee><interviewer>David Washburn</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url></media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Born and raised in Santa Fe Railroad housing off lower Macdonald Avenue in Richmond. Chávez worked for local industries, such as the Santa Fe Railroad, American Radiator and Standard, Filice and Perreli Cannery, and Kaiser shipyards. During the war he served with the US Coast Guard, and later started a career as a barber. His interview offers a unique perspective into the history of Richmond's longtime Mexican community. Discusses: life of the employees of the Santa Fe Railroad, Mexican culture in Richmond, social relations (dating) in Richmond schools, race relations.</description><rel /><transcript>﻿ [Note: This is recorded in a barber’s shop, and towards the end of the
tape customers come in, some of them being included in the conversation. Some
words/phrases are in Spanish. It’s not always clear who is speaking once
several customers join.]

WASHBURN: We’re just going to start with some easy questions, and hopefully
you’ll think of it as just a discussion between me and you. Don’t feel
uncomfortable answering the questions. So we’re recording.

CHAVEZ: If I don’t want to answer I’ll just shut up.

WASHBURN: Yeah, just say: I don’t want to answer that. Forget that. Today is
the twenty-first, right. And we’re recording in Sal’s Barber Shop in El
Sobrante, California, with Sal Chávez and David Washburn is the interviewer.
So, Sal, you told me you were born in Richmond, right?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. The old Sante Fe camp. My father was a railroad man. He worked
in the section, so they had a section house where they kept all the workers, and
I was born there. Room number seven.

WASHBURN: What year?

CHAVEZ: 1921.

WASHBURN: 1921. Tell me about the house you grew up in. You kind of described it
a little bit to me.

CHAVEZ: It was a section house, made out of cement. The only thing that-- it had
a tin roof. Of course, the doors were wood, but the walls and everything were
made out of cement. The floors were cement. Then we had a wood stove, four
burner. Just wood, you know, but it had four --

WASHBURN: Four places for pots.

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. And small. We managed to survive. Seven of us.

WASHBURN: You said it was number seven, so how many units were there?

CHAVEZ: There must’ve been about fifty units.

WASHBURN: In just one structure or in a bunch of structures?

CHAVEZ: No, no, it was like a square. One row and another row and another row.
That’s what it was. About that many.

WASHBURN: Fifty units?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. That’s quite a bit, huh?

WASHBURN: Yeah, that’s quite a bit. And you say you had seven in yours.

CHAVEZ: Number seven. Apartment seven.

WASHBURN: How many people lived in your house?

CHAVEZ: There were seven of us. My dad, my mother, and my two--three brothers
and my four sisters.

WASHBURN: That’s quite a bit. When did your Pop move into that place?

CHAVEZ: I’ve no idea. I don’t know any dates.

WASHBURN: That’s okay. But you think --

CHAVEZ: I was born there.

WASHBURN: You were born in ’21, so when was the oldest of your siblings born?
Are you, like in the middle?

CHAVEZ: 1919.

WASHBURN: 1919’s the oldest, so you’re almost the oldest.

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. No, no, I take it back. 1919 was my brother. Then my sister was
the oldest, and she passed away here about five years ago. She was eighty-one.

WASHBURN: So even before 1919. Were they both born in the section housing too?

CHAVEZ: No, not they. Mexico.

WASHBURN: Oh, they were born in Mexico? So I guess it seems like your family
moved to Richmond some time before 1920. Right about then.

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: And do you know how your dad got a job working for the Sante Fe railroad?

CHAVEZ: He worked for the railroad. Anybody could get a job working for the
railroad. They hardly paid nothing. You got paid nothing at all. But before he
came over here, he used to work in--They had, like these boxcars. They lived in
the boxcars and they were pulling the rail, from New Mexico all the way down here.

WASHBURN: So they’d stay in the boxcars?

CHAVEZ: Well, they lived in them. It had a great big commissary, you know. A
boxcar like the Holmes Supply Company used to {call it?}.

WASHBURN: So he worked for the railroad before he moved to Richmond.

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah. He used to work in a gang, see.

WASHBURN: Would he tell you any stories about those gangs?

CHAVEZ: No. He’d just work, all the time. The wages weren’t all that good either.

WASHBURN: Yeah, I’m sure. How did he support such a big family if the wages
weren’t so good?

CHAVEZ: A hundred-pound sack of flour, a hundred-pound sack of beans, and a
hundred-pound sack of rice. And chickens. After we moved to this other--we had
chickens and rabbits. That’s it.

WASHBURN: In your yard? At the Sante Fe section housing?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, because we had a big yard. Now, you can’t raise nothing. But at
that time we had chickens, and goats, and cows.

WASHBURN: Do you know when he met your Mom?

CHAVEZ: No, I have no idea. We didn’t talk about that.

WASHBURN: But she lived there with you in the section housing?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, uh-huh.

WASHBURN: And did she work?

CHAVEZ: No. She never worked. None of my sisters worked either. My mother took
care of the kids and all that. One check only. That’s it. Then, I guess, we
had free rent. Free rent, we had, and that was it. Because we had lanterns,
coal-oil lanterns for light.

WASHBURN: No electricity?

CHAVEZ: No electricity.

WASHBURN: So, do you remember what the routine was for your Dad for his work?

CHAVEZ: He just had to go out there and fix the tracks. Sometimes a boxcar would
derail or something. They’d call him at three or four o’clock in the morning
and then they’d go to fix it or whatever they gotta do. They were on call 24 hours.

WASHBURN: So would he get up some times in the middle of the night and go out?

CHAVEZ: Oh, many times. Raining like the dickens.

WASHBURN: And would he sometimes stay away for more than 24 hours?

CHAVEZ: Oh, sometimes. He worked like the dickens, and that’s it. See, they
had section gangs all over the place. They had--where we lived, they used to
call them section houses--ours was Section 35, and then they had--right down the
line, they had them. They’d go so far, and then the other went so far, and the
other one so far. You know what I mean?

WASHBURN: Yeah. Why do you call it section housing? I’ve never heard that word before.

CHAVEZ: Section, sección. They called them {esparas sección?} so they were
sections. That’s it.

WASHBURN: Tell me what it was like there, growing up in the section housing.

CHAVEZ: It was a lot of fun. A lot of fun. I got a job delivering papers and
then played baseball, and we got our chores to do. We gotta take the goats out
in the morning and stake them on the field. Cause they had plenty of fields then
at that time. They had hardly no houses. Like, we lived across the street from
Macdonald Avenue, and that was--what they have now Atcheson Village. All that
was nothing but fields. We used to go out there. And the section houses on the
this side. So we used to go out and take the cow, goats, and put them out there
so they could eat grass. We’d just stake them out there with a chain.

WASHBURN: Nobody would mess with them?

CHAVEZ: Nobody.

WASHBURN: That’s great.

CHAVEZ: And then night-time you came, and you’d bring them home. Just take the
stake out and then run like a {____?}. [chuckles] They’d run like a
son-of-a-gun, you know! To the barn. Then they got milked.

WASHBURN: Did you go to school there?

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah. Grammar school.

WASHBURN: Where at?

CHAVEZ: Peres. That’s one over on Pennsylvania. A, K street, I don’t know
what it is. Pennsylvania. And, I can’t remember where it is, but it’s over
there by the railroad tracks. Then I went to Roosevelt. And then high school,
Richmond High.

WASHBURN: Did all the kids who grew up in the section housing go to school there
at Peres?

CHAVEZ: Oh, yeah. That’s it. That was a--you know how they have different
places, different schools according to where you live.

WASHBURN: So it seems like there was quite a bit of families there working for
the same company.

CHAVEZ: A lot of them. A lot of families.

WASHBURN: Were all of them Mexican families?

CHAVEZ: Just about. All of them were Mexicans. And then after a while, long
after they had the war, then they had a lot of Indians from Arizona. They came
to work.

WASHBURN: I learned about that.

CHAVEZ: That was back in--After the war, or before the war.

WASHBURN: So when you grew up there in the twenties, there weren’t any Indians
across the way there?

CHAVEZ: They’ve always lived across the tracks.

WASHBURN: Were they there in the twenties?

CHAVEZ: I don’t remember cause I was just a kid. No, by then there must have
been, because I remember when I was going to school, when I was going to high
school, there used to be some kids and they were going to high school too. We
had Laguna Indians.

WASHBURN: Laguna Indians, that’s right. So when you were there in the section
housing, do you remember there being any parties, birthday parties, or other festivities?

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah. It’s hard to explain. We had a big patio, not a patio. These
section houses were kind of low, but then they had a big long porch, and
they’d bring out a phonograph and records and say let’s play the heck out of
them. They’d dance in the--you know what I’m talking about. You know, when
you get out of the house, like a porch but it’s a long one.

WASHBURN: Was it wood, or was it cement? Or brick?

CHAVEZ: No, cement. Cement, cement, cement. Yeah, it was cement. And then after
that was the dirt. Uh-huh. It’s been a long time.

WASHBURN: That’s OK, your memory seems to be real good. When were those
parties? Were they pretty often?

CHAVEZ: When you had a baptism. It would be something big. Like when you had a
baptism, or somebody got married, you know. But mostly they’d have birthday
parties. But when they had a big thing, sometimes they’d do it there, or
sometimes they had a--There used to be a hall, used to call Winters Hall. They
used to rent it and have parties. They’d have bands. Like, maybe somebody
would play the guitar or clarinet, and they’d get together and play music.

WASHBURN: Do you remember where Winters Hall was exactly? Do you remember what
streets Winters Hall was on?

CHAVEZ: Macdonald Avenue. There was a florist, Winters Florist. And on top of
the florist was the dance hall. Old Mr Winters owned the whole thing. So they
had their dances there. And also when they had festivities like sixteenth of
September or the fifth of May, they used to have the celebrations there.

WASHBURN: Sounds like there was kind of a united--sounds like you knew everybody
there at the section housing.

CHAVEZ: Oh, yeah. Everybody knew everybody. And then sometimes they’d leave,
you know, they’d go some place else to make more money or for a reason or
another. And they’d leave, and they always had somebody to come in.

WASHBURN: Someone new.

CHAVEZ: They’d always be coming to look for a job. Right away they used to
give them a job, and then they’d buy their groceries. They’d go out there
and get their groceries from the company store supply. And then that’s it. So
they stayed there for a long time.

WASHBURN: What was the turnover like there, in the section housing? Did people
come in and out? How frequently did families come and go?

CHAVEZ: They stayed there for a long time. Yeah. Some were born there, like I
was, and raised there. Till you grew up. I was growing up when I went in the
service. After I got out of the service, then I got married. A lot of people
lived there. In other words, it was their home. But then what happened was,
later on, if you had people - some of them had money, saved their money, and
then they would either buy or go rent a house, just to get out of the section house.

WASHBURN: Where would they go buy or rent a house?

CHAVEZ: On First Street or Second Street. That area around there.

WASHBURN: Right nearby.

CHAVEZ: Mm-mmm. In case they called, you know, emergency. To go out there for an
emergency, like a train derailed or something like that.

WASHBURN: Did your folks ever do that?

CHAVEZ: What’s that? Washburn: How long did they stay in the section housing?

CHAVEZ: I stayed there--oh, man, I stayed there till I got married. I went in
the service. I went in the service and then when I got out of the service--Yeah,
I got out of the service, and I met my wife, and I got married.

WASHBURN: I guess a better question is, when did your mom and pop move out of
the section housing?

CHAVEZ: They died.

WASHBURN: They died there?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: In about what year?

CHAVEZ: My father died in ’46, and my mother died when I was just eleven years old.

WASHBURN: She died when you were really young.

CHAVEZ: Mm-mmm. Then I had my sisters, you know. Then he never married any more.
He stayed single.

WASHBURN: So it sounds like your sisters and you all had to pick up the slack
when your Mom passed away.

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah. Uh-huh, uh-huh. Well, you know, my sister was already grown up.
And helped around the house quite a bit.

WASHBURN: Did all your siblings work?

CHAVEZ: No, no. They never worked. They got married. But they never worked.

WASHBURN: What jobs do you remember you had before you went off to the war?

CHAVEZ: Selling papers.

WASHBURN: Newspapers?

CHAVEZ: After the war?

WASHBURN: No, before the war.

CHAVEZ: Before the war, yeah, I used to sell papers. Delivering, delivering
papers. And then when I was little then, I used to go to North Richmond. They
had a lot of fields that farmers raised lettuce, mostly lettuce. I’d go out
there and help cut the lettuce and sometimes I used to help when they were just
planting the lettuce. I’ve forgotten how to say it in English.

WASHBURN: How do you say it in Spanish? Semiar?

CHAVEZ: [__} Cambiar is work.

WASHBURN: Semiar. To plant seeds.

CHAVEZ: Semiar, no. When they planted, they plantar. O sembrar.

WASHBURN: What did you say in Spanish?

CHAVEZ: Plantale. Plant.

WASHBURN: I mean before that. You were saying something and you said you
didn’t know how to say it in English. And you said it in Spanish

CHAVEZ: I’ve forgotten.

WASHBURN: That’s OK.

CHAVEZ: But you see in Mexico they call it sembrar, [__], you know like a
sembrar and [__} means they pull all the weeds out with a plough. And then pick.

WASHBURN: Do you remember-- You said you delivered papers. In what neighborhood
did you deliver papers?

CHAVEZ: Maravista. At the end of town. I had to wheel my bike all the way up
there. Maravista, where all the rich people lived. I used to have my round - 60
papers. 64 papers. Chronicle.

WASHBURN: San Francisco Chronicle?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. But they was only paying me, I think it was $10 a month. And
every month I had to buy a tire for the bike. I’d wear out one tire. Then when
I put the new one, I’d put it on the front where it will wear out.

WASHBURN: Rotate ’em.

CHAVEZ: I had a lot of fun. I enjoyed it. I had to get up early in the morning
to fold the paper and then ride your bike. I got cold and everything but after a
while, boy, you got to sweat like {__} that paper. And {__} Maravista coming up
a lot of those hills.

WASHBURN: On an old-style bike.

CHAVEZ: On a Roadmaster. That was the name of the bike. And I won that bike.
Selling subscriptions for the Chronicle. I sold six 6-month subscriptions and I
won that bike. And then they give me the job. I didn’t have to ask them for
anything. Delivering papers on a Roadmaster.

WASHBURN: What can you tell me about the neighborhood down there by the section
housing? You said, when people could save up some money they moved out there to
the housing right there on First.

CHAVEZ: They wanted to get out of the sections.

WASHBURN: Tell me about that community.

CHAVEZ: Because they wanted to have--Well, they stayed the same people. They
moved out, and whether they had their old thing. They’d meet people as
neighbors, then they moved out. But they still met each other. They still knew
each other and run into each other and talked.

WASHBURN: But was there a--Was that neighborhood down there by the section
housing, did other Mexican folks live in housing down there?

CHAVEZ: Oh no. They had their own homes.

WASHBURN: No, that’s what I mean, did rather have some folks own their own homes?

CHAVEZ: A Street, and B Street. Yeah there was quite a bit of them. They bought
a house and that’s it. We lived over there because we couldn’t afford a
house. As soon as they had a little money they’d buy a house. They got out of
there. Cause you know, no electricity, so they got electricity and everything.

WASHBURN: So did everybody speak Spanish in the section housing?

CHAVEZ: All the time. Once in a while we’d speak English, but most of the time
Spanish. But a lot of them learned English. Like my father, he could speak it.
Not good, but he’d understand and all that. And of course we went to school so
we all knew how to speak English.

WASHBURN: Would people speak Spanish there on the street down by-- if you was
walking around the streets down by--

CHAVEZ: You’d hear them talking. Heck yeah. A and B Street, and C Street. All
the people--they were all there. Some of them were people who’d lived in the
section and then they bought a house. And then after a while, you know, after
the war they all started to buy better homes, and they started to have all these
different places, building homes, so they moved out.

WASHBURN: Were there businesses there? You said there was a company store.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, Holmes Supply.

WASHBURN: So did everybody who worked for the Sante Fe Railroad go and buy their
stuff there?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, everybody did. Just about. But the fault was that--higher and the
heck. A pair of shoes would cost you twice as much as if you went and bought
them downtown. They were pretty high.

WASHBURN: The company store. They charged a little bit more.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, the company store. They charged you double, or maybe--the store
that’s in the town would cost you more. No, I take it back. I’m talking
about the Holmes Supply used to charge more than downtown.

WASHBURN: It was called Sante Fe Holmes Supply or just Home Supply.

CHAVEZ: We used to call it the commissary.

WASHBURN: So why did people shop there if it was more expensive than--

CHAVEZ: Cause they didn’t have no money.

WASHBURN: Weren’t they working for the railroads?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, but everything was charged. They used to charge everything. My
father used to--like I said, put everything on--charge everything. They’d
charge everything, so they’d take so much out at the end of the--every payday,
and he’d bring home maybe ten or fifteen dollars, maybe, or a buck. I got that
check here. One dollar. The company store took the rest of it.

WASHBURN: So you mean they wouldn’t pay --

CHAVEZ: They wouldn’t pay like they paid out downtown.

WASHBURN: So you’d run a tab with the company.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, uh-huh. You ought to see, some of these people who had a tab, and
I don’t mean when they bought a grocery. It wasn’t no ten or fifteen, it was
always in the hundreds.

WASHBURN: So did people get in debt to the company also?

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah. Some of them poor people bringing home a dollar. But then
they’d go buy shoes from the store, groceries all the time. High. It really
was high. So that’s why a lot of people after they started saving their money,
used to go downtown and buy their groceries. Go buy meat downtown. They always
had neighborhood stores. But they never had the --

WASHBURN: Tell me about the neighborhood stores.

CHAVEZ: I think it was the--I forgot the name of that store. Italian store. He
could speak Spanish, and everybody went in there and bought groceries.

WASHBURN: That was down there by the section housing?

CHAVEZ: It used to be on--what street was it? I can’t remember. Between Third
and Fourth, I think, or Second and First. I don’t know, it’s been a long time.

WASHBURN: Can you tell me, how did you feel growing up in the section housing,
or down there in that neighborhood, and then you’d go up and deliver papers in Maravista.

CHAVEZ: Maravista. All the rich people.

WASHBURN: Tell me, did you ever feel out of place when you were up in Maravista?

CHAVEZ: No, it was just my job. I used to go there--as a matter of fact, at
Christmas time they’d leave me a $5 or a couple of bucks, tips and all that
kind of stuff. A lot of times they’d give you a cake or something. So that’s
it. I liked it. I mean, we survived. Most of us that were living in the section
housing had bikes so we were delivering papers most of the time, and some were
walking the streets selling it. Three cents a paper. The Tribune. Three cents:
you got one, and they got two.

WASHBURN: You wouldn’t deliver the Richmond Independent?

CHAVEZ: No, I never did. I just delivered the Chronicle. And then I sold the
Tribune on a corner.

WASHBURN: Where did some of the other Mexican folks who lived down there in that
neighborhood, where else did they work other than the Sante Fe Railroad?

CHAVEZ: The Foundry. American Radiator. That was hard work. Boy, that foundry.

WASHBURN: What did they do there at the foundry?

CHAVEZ: Tubs. Bathtubs. They had the foundry there. Then they had the enamel
room. And they had--As a matter of fact, I worked in the enamel room. It’s
where they put the enamel on the tub. They bring it in, you’d have to put it
in a rail, like, and you’d put it in a furnace.

WASHBURN: So people even then--so you’re saying before the war people worked
at the American Standard Foundry.

CHAVEZ: After I went out, they were still working.

WASHBURN: But before the war, they worked there?

CHAVEZ: After the war, too.

WASHBURN: Where was it?

CHAVEZ: That used to be on--North Richmond.

WASHBURN: Remember where?

CHAVEZ: Seventh and--I can’t remember the name of the street. Used to be on
Seventh Street, but it was in North Richmond. I forgot the name of the street.

WASHBURN: Chester?

CHAVEZ: I don’t remember. I bet if that guy would have been here, he would have--

WASHBURN: We can check on a map too and figure out where that was. So, as best
as you can remember, people worked at the Sante Fe Railroad. They worked at the
American Standard, and can you remember any other places?

CHAVEZ: Some of them worked in the fields and ranches. Lettuce or beets or
something else. But also we used to work at American Radiator, and that’s it.
American Radiator and the Sante Fe, and they had Southern Pacific. That was the
same as the Sante Fe. They had their section house, but not as big as the Sante Fe.

WASHBURN: Where was that at?

CHAVEZ: They had them in San Pablo. Right there by the first crossing. What the
hell’s the name of that store? The Food Bowl? Is that the Food Bowl.

WASHBURN: I read about one over by Cutting and San Pablo, used to be over there.
Right nearby there.

CHAVEZ: No, this one’s over there. The Food Bowl. That’s where the Food Bowl is.

WASHBURN: Food Max?

CHAVEZ: The Food Bowl.

WASHBURN: OK. So did people who worked for the Sante Fe know people who worked
for the Southern Pacific?

CHAVEZ: Well, yeah. They knew each other. But they even had small section houses
for the Southern Pacific. But they did the same work. The Sante Fe gang used to
be ten or fifteen guys going to a job.

WASHBURN: Things seemed to change a lot when the war happened.

CHAVEZ: Oh, yeah. A lot of them that were working on the railroad went to work
in the shipyard.

WASHBURN: What do you remember about that?

CHAVEZ: Well, they quite their jobs and they went and worked for the shipyard.
They got hired. A lot of guy who used to work for the American Radiator, same
thing. They quit there and went to work for the shipyard. Make more money.
Everybody worked for the shipyards.

WASHBURN: It sounds like a lot of people did that. Your dad didn’t do that though?

CHAVEZ: No, he was gone. He died. He died after Pearl Harbor. He died in ’41.

WASHBURN: Tell me how that community down there changed when the war came and
all these people came to work in Richmond.

CHAVEZ: Mostly the same, because they never bothered us. You stayed in your own
place. We never had any trouble at all, but we stayed in our--we stayed there.
We didn’t go around looking for trouble or--those days were altogether
different. You didn’t see it like you see now.

WASHBURN: When you say “we”, are you saying you and other Mexicans?

CHAVEZ: Yeah. At that time, you didn’t see--no offence--you didn’t see no
mixing with American. You didn’t see them. It was always Mexican-Mexican. Not
that the--It was because you felt that they didn’t like you. A lot of guys
didn’t give a damn.

WASHBURN: Did you say it wasn’t because you felt they didn’t like you, or
because you felt they didn’t like you.

CHAVEZ: Well, they thought that they didn’t like you, you see. But it was
different. I don’t know, you know, you felt kind of funny. But a lot of guys
didn’t give a damn.

WASHBURN: Don’t feel uncomfortable about it. I’d like to know how race
relations maybe were different then.

CHAVEZ: There was only one guy that was married to an American girl. One guy.
And that was it. But you never saw like now. Now you see everything mixing. At
that time, you know--I dunno, maybe that’s the way it was, but--heck, when I
was going to high school, I had a lot of girlfriends, you know what I mean, and
not all Mexican either. [laughs]

WASHBURN: So you went out with women who weren’t Mexican?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, I had two or three--you know. Portuguese or Italian.

WASHBURN: On that note, do you ever remember-- I know in Richmond before the
war, there were Greeks and Italians and Portuguese and Mexicans and some
Japanese. Do you remember though that those people maybe dated - like you say,
you dated a Portuguese and Italian - but you’d never date the white people in
town who maybe weren’t Portuguese or Italian? The more old-time folks.

CHAVEZ: Well, you dated them if they liked you. If you liked them, you dated
them, you know. But most of the time--I don’t know why you’d stick to your
nationality. But after a while everybody was going out with Italians, Portuguese
and all that kind of stuff. After a while. But before that, I don’t know why
it was. Because there was a lot of gals that used to like guys, you know,
Mexicans and all that. But after awhile, they’re all mixed.

WASHBURN: Are talking about at Richmond High?

CHAVEZ: Richmond High School.

WASHBURN: Do you remember if anybody used to tease you for being Mexican? Any of
the other guys tease you?

CHAVEZ: No. Not that I remember.

WASHBURN: Would they tease the black kids though?

CHAVEZ: Well, I don’t remember. I don’t remember that at all. You could
hear, when you go to Peres School or grammar school, you know you {__}.

WASHBURN: So you would hear it a little bit?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, but we didn’t really care. We paid attention like--You know,
“the dirty Mexican”, or something like that. Well. But, you know, we got
used to it.

WASHBURN: Sure. I’m just trying to understand what you can share, because
obviously things have changed since then. I’m just trying to understand what
it was like then.

CHAVEZ: Now you see all nationalities mixed. All nationalities. It’s not like
before. If you like saw somebody with an American girl, oh, right away, “Look
at that. So-and-so’s got a girlfriend.”

WASHBURN: An American girl.

CHAVEZ: I had a lot of girls. Well, no, not too many.

WASHBURN: Did you like dating the Portuguese and Italian girls more than the
Mexican girls.

CHAVEZ: I didn’t care what they were, really! [laughs] If you liked them, you
know what I mean. If they liked you.

WASHBURN: I’m just curious if there was a difference. What can you tell me
about speaking Spanish in the schools. Did you and your friends ever speak
Spanish in school?

CHAVEZ: All the time. All the time, we’d speak Spanish. In the room, in the
class, it wasn’t allowed for you to speak to somebody in Spanish and all that,
but on the yard, the schoolyard or outside, that’s all you’d do.

WASHBURN: What would you talk about in class in Spanish?

CHAVEZ: Anything. In class, no. You’d talk English. But once in a while
you’d have a conversation outside and you’d finish it in the room.

WASHBURN: Do you remember hearing other languages at the school too?

CHAVEZ: Oh, Italian. No, not like the Mexicans. The Mexicans spoke all the time,
but the Italian once in a while. Not too much. The Mexicans did all the talking,
because the Italians were bashful. They all knew how to talk Italian. They all
knew how to talk Portuguese. There was a family from Romania, they used to talk
their nationality all the time. [Phone rings]

WASHBURN: So tell me, why do you think if all those kids could speak another
language, why do you think all the Mexican kids spoke Spanish and the Italian
kids didn’t want to speak Italian.

CHAVEZ: I don’t know. Maybe they weren’t--They didn’t do it. There was
only one guy {________?} matter of fact he’s the one that owns the--he’s
dead now, but he used to own that, in Pinole--a bar there. [CUSTOMER comes in.]

WASHBURN: We can stop while this guy comes in. I’m just interviewing Sal here
about old times in Richmond. Did you grow up in Richmond too? Yeah? [tape
pauses.] Maybe you can tell me about all the parties you guys used to have there.

CHAVEZ: {________?} in the house. I said it was like a porch, but it was a
portal. Era portal, luego y [__}.

WASHBURN: What kind of music was it?

CHAVEZ: Hubo Ranchera. Yeah, we’d party. We’d really have fun.

WASHBURN: How long did it go on like that for? Did you guys--Did things change
after a while? What happened?

CHAVEZ: We were--Some died, and then the amount of people didn’t do that no
more. We didn’t go to any parties because sometimes there was no room. There
would be no empty rooms.

WASHBURN: You didn’t tell me this time, but you said last time that you used
to have parties in vacant rooms.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, in vacant rooms. Used to go out there and take the tables.
Because, the Sante Fe furnished you with benches and {_____?} tables. They were
big tables. They were not skinny little tables, they were big tables. Heavy
ones. And then you’d have a bench. And that was it. You’d {________?} on and
dance. {___?} was a phonograph. And sometimes people would have records, you know.

WASHBURN: Where did you guys buy your records of ranchera music?

CHAVEZ: The Holmes Supply Company used to have everything.

WASHBURN: So the Holmes Supply Company Ranchera--?

CHAVEZ: Yeah. {__} No a radio is what we got. {__} Santa Fe, and it was a heck
of a good one too.

WASHBURN: So they sold ranchero music in the store?

CHAVEZ: Well, yeah, at that time, you didn’t know anything about Pachanga.
{____} Then after a while, el mambo.

WASHBURN: But Cumbia wasn’t popular at that time.

CHAVEZ: No.

WASHBURN: So, when you had these parties, how would you get into the empty houses?

CHAVEZ: You had a campero. You had a man called campero, who took care of the
whole thing. [Sal answers phone.]

WASHBURN: He was like a manager of the place?

CHAVEZ: Yes, campero. He was the one who took care of the whole place. He used
to always give us the key. We’d open {_____?} invited to the party.

WASHBURN: He was a Mexican guy too?

CHAVEZ: Oh yeah.

WASHBURN: He didn’t mind you guys going into the empty house? He wouldn’t
say that’s against the rules, you can’t do that?

CHAVEZ: No. He worked for the railroad too, but he did that extra.

WASHBURN: Do you think you were not supposed to be doing that?

CHAVEZ: No, no, no. He placed no restrictions.

WASHBURN: Do you remember seeing in the section housing any of the officials for
the Santa Fe Railroad?

CHAVEZ: Wheels? No.

WASHBURN: No, officials. Who’d come in and say you can’t do this, you
can’t do that.

CHAVEZ: No.

WASHBURN: So you guys just kind of did as you pleased there?

CHAVEZ: We knew how far to go, you know. We never had no fights, nothing.

WASHBURN: So during these parties did people bring drink and food?

CHAVEZ: Yes. They always had liquor stores.

WASHBURN: So people would bring booze into the parties?

CHAVEZ: Yeah, but you never saw any--like now. Liquor all over. You had beer. [pauses.]

WASHBURN: Sounds like a fun time. Did girls and boys dance? Did people meet
their girlfriends and their boyfriends there?

CHAVEZ: No, it was just a family thing.

WASHBURN: Oh it was a family thing. So the kids didn’t --They had the parents watching?

CHAVEZ: Well, they had dancing. We had {_______?} like I said, Cinco de Mayo or
Sixteenth of September. They used to have societies, you know, they used to run
it, {La Munifica}  and all that kind of stuff. They used to run--They’d have acts.

WASHBURN: That was at Winters Hall?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: So all those kind of things were at Winters Hall?

CHAVEZ: Well, it used to have a big hall. But then after a while we started
having different things, like picnics and all that, after a while. We’d have
picnics {____?} in Alvarado Park.

WASHBURN: Where’s Alvarado Park? Is it still there?

CHAVEZ: Yeah.

WASHBURN: You said you remembered some stuff about the bullfighting.

CHAVEZ: One time they had--It wasn’t allowed. They had it over here in San
Pablo. As a matter of fact, we weren’t supposed to do it. They did have it. I
was just a kid. One time somebody started a fire and the people that were
selling the tickets, they took off and left with the money and somebody went and
cleaned them out.

WASHBURN: They looted their take for the day!

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh, uh-huh.

WASHBURN: Tell me, what about days like Dieciséis de Septiembre or Cinco de Mayo.

CHAVEZ: They’re celebrations.

WASHBURN: I know what they are, but what happened down there by the section
housing? Did people dress differently and go out on the street?

CHAVEZ: No, no, no. Like I said. We had dancing then, and they had some guy went
and danced {________?}or singing. You know, acts and that’s it. After that,
they’d have a dance.

WASHBURN: At Winters Hall?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh.

WASHBURN: Nowadays you can see people out in parks or something like that,
having a big picnic or something like that, or cooking carne asadas--

CHAVEZ: Well, you see them now, over there at the Point. They’ve got that
place out there like a park. They go out there every Sunday. They go out there
and they barbecue and all that.

WASHBURN: But do you remember doing that when you were younger?

CHAVEZ: Me, uh. No, at the time, when I was young they used to {_______?} barbacoa.

WASHBURN: Barbecue.

CHAVEZ: No. When they killed the cow and {__} Barbecue it, right?

WASHBURN: So you’d kill a cow right there, is that what you’re saying? What
are you trying to describe?

CHAVEZ: Well, they’d make a big hole, and then they cooked the meat in there.

WASHBURN: A hole in the ground. Stick some wood in there?

CHAVEZ: No. I don’t know how they do it. I know they used to do it at Pinole
all the time for the fiesta for the Portuguese.

WASHBURN: I’m trying to understand whether--you said you had lots of parties
at Winters Hall --

CHAVEZ: Most of the time the parties you had there were like Cinco de Mayo and
the Sixteenth of September. Then maybe a lot of societies, como La Munifica and
others {Guadalupana} and sometimes they’d have a party and they used the hall.
There’s where you had the bands.

WASHBURN: So what were those societies? Tell me about those.

CHAVEZ: Well, Guadalupana is like a religion, verdad?

CUSTOMER: Some church gathering.

WASHBURN: Uh-huh, a church gathering. So those societies were religious-based.
They weren’t like the Elks Club or something like that. Did the Mexican folks
down there ever had like a kind of an Elks Club or a fraternal society like that?

CHAVEZ: La Honorifica, verdad?

WASHBURN: La Honorifica?

CHAVEZ: [__]. Cual era la otra? That’s all I remember now. La Honorifica.
That’s all I remember. Honorifica, uh-huh.

WASHBURN: Como se traduce eso en ingles?

CHAVEZ: Yo no sé.

WASHBURN: You don’t know, that’s okay. Is is Horifica o Honorifica?

CHAVEZ: La Comision de Honorifica.

WASHBURN: Honorary commission?

CHAVEZ: Uh-huh. But I wasn’t up to all that.

WASHBURN: You weren’t involved in that?

CHAVEZ: No, no.

WASHBURN: So where did people go to church down there?

CHAVEZ: [__} que es Saint Marks, verdad? San Marco in San Pablo.

WASHBURN: It’s still there. [Customer offers a name.]

CHAVEZ: Saint Joseph at Pinole. San Pablo’s Saint Paul. [Another customer
comes in.]

WASHBURN: I was talking with Josephina Ramirez and there’s the Mexican Baptist
church down there on Barrett and B Street.

CHAVEZ: I don’t know. Now?

WASHBURN: She said she went down there in the forties down there, to the Mexican
Baptist church on B and Barrett. It’s still there.

CHAVEZ: I don’t know that. I haven’t been towards that part of town in years.

WASHBURN: Really? For reals? But your family used to go to Saint Marks, is that right?

CHAVEZ: Yeah. We lived in the Sante Fe camp so we used to go there to Saint
Marks. Then after that you moved out, so now I go to Saint Joseph’s, Pinole.

WASHBURN: Did they give people Sunday off to go to church?

CHAVEZ: From work? No, everybody worked. I mean everybody--That was a day of worship.

CUSTOMER:  I remember.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, he’s the old-timer.

WASHBURN: Oh really? Let’s talk to him. Sure.

CUSTOMER: It was a long time ago. [Another customer comes in.]

WASHBURN: So tell me, is that where you got your baptism?

CHAVEZ: I got baptized, married and confirmation. At Saint Mark’s.

WASHBURN: Is that where all the folks--

CHAVEZ: They were close by, verdad? Saint Paul’s. That’s in San Pablo.
That’s been there a long time too?

CUSTOMER: Oh yeah. He said, “If you put a dime in that basket, I’ll chop
your head off. {__}

WASHBURN: At Saint Mark’s would they have--

CHAVEZ: I haven’t been there in years.

WASHBURN: But when you went there, was the service in Spanish?

CHAVEZ: No. I didn’t hear any. Once in a while, they’d bring a missionary
from Mexico for a week. And I used to go and listen. They used to be {__?}
(sighs) I haven’t been to Saint Mark’s in years.

WASHBURN: But other than that, there weren’t services in Spanish. They were
all in English?

CHAVEZ: I don’t remember.

CUSTOMER: No.

WASHBURN: They were in Spanish too?

CUSTOMER: They were in only in English. Fifteen years they were doing it in Spanish.

WASHBURN: Only for fifteen years. For fifteen or fifty?

CUSTOMER: Fifteen.

WASHBURN: For fifteen, hmm. Wow. I’m doing a kind of a community project, a
community history of Richmond. [Discussion among customers.]

WASHBURN: I don’t understand the layout. The Sante Fe station’s right there.

CHAVEZ: Yeah, the station was right there, on the corner.

WASHBURN: So where was the ball park?

CHAVEZ: End of Macdonald Avenue. Garrard went this way, then they had the Sante
Fe Depot over here and everything. But before then, they had the section houses
on this side.

WASHBURN: This side of Garrard? Yeah.

CHAVEZ: No, they had it--Explain to him; I’ve got a customer.

WASHBURN: I can’t tape this guy.

CUSTOMER: They had a school there.

WASHBURN: Do you need your glasses to see this, or can you see that right. I see
Macdonald hits Garrard. Do you know where we’re talking about?

CUSTOMER: I used to. {__?} down by the railroad tracks. Down on the left-hand
side, going from here to Macdonald on the left, so the houses were there.
Because by now, everything has been changed.

WASHBURN: Everything’s ripped out.

CUSTOMER: Oh yeah. There used to be, during the war, all the houses built around
from Tenth Street, all the way down--Tenth and Ohio. Then Ohio to--They used to
be over there all this homes for the military for the war, for all the bombs. In
the fifties they was knocking down all that. Then they took down old Richmond.

WASHBURN: So what went on at the baseball yards there? There was games? They had
a team from Standard Oil, you said. Did different companies have different
teams, or what was it?

CHAVEZ: You had your {___?} House, you had your {______?} League, that’s it.
And then they used to have a lot of guys who’d come and they’d play a team.
What was the name of that team with all the black guys? They were bearded. House
of David. What a ball team. They used to have some nice baseball.

WASHBURN: There were black guys with beards?

CHAVEZ: Yeah. The House of David. They were good ball players.

WASHBURN: That was a baseball team, the House of David?

CHAVEZ: Yeah.

WASHBURN: And it was an all-black team, and they all had beards. That’s interesting.

CUSTOMER: During the war, those guys used to go to the show so they could get a
seat to go to sleep. They used to sleep in the show.

WASHBURN: In the shul?

CUSTOMER: Yeah, during the war. There was not enough room. Didn’t have enough
housing. All these people from back east and Oklahoma and different--they all
moved in here. Some of the guys, you didn’t know what the heck--

WASHBURN: Where was the shul in town?

CUSTOMER: There was quite a few. Peres was one. There was one in Point Richmond.
And Richmond High School was still in the same place. Another down on Fifth
Street. Not enough housing for all those people.

ANOTHER CUSTOMER: Wards. Macy’s. Penney’s.

CUSTOMER: Oh yeah. JC Penney’s used to be down on Eighth Street.

ANOTHER CUSTOMER: Montgomery Ward used to be on K Street. [Discussion among
customers about where different stores were.]

CUSTOMER: Saturdays and Sundays were like a fair.

ANOTHER CUSTOMER: In the fifties, ’55, ’58 since ’58 they started
pinching, closing stores business because there was so many--

CUSTOMER: Banks, restaurants. Everything was on Macdonald.

ANOTHER CUSTOMER: A lot of people started coming in.

WASHBURN: Do you guys remember how things changed once the top mall was built?

ANOTHER CUSTOMER: Yeah, before they opened Hilltop, they closed everything over
there on Macdonald {_____?}

WASHBURN: Everything closed on Macdonald.

CUSTOMER: A few business guys, and they were waiting for them. They jack all
those prices up, on southside, when they want to build the shopping center. They
said, “To heck with you, so they moved up to Hilltop.” They were going to
move downtown. We had three politicians in Richmond, and they tie all those
lots. So when they come in, the price went up. So they said to heck with it, and
went to Hilltop.

WASHBURN: So JC Penney moved from down on Macdonald up to Hilltop?

CUSTOMER: Yeah, it was down on Eighth Street. JC Penney, Macy’s

 

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>