<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042462" dt="2018-10-12"><version>5.2</version><date value="2002-04-05" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Mary Hall Prout | Interview 1 | April 5, 2002</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Mary Hall Prout</interviewee><interviewer>Ben Bicais </interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>H5A9R_DPrQU</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Mary Hall Prout was born in San Francisco in 1921. Prior to the start of World War II, she began studying to become a teacher, ultimately finishing her schooling at San Jose State University. An opportunity to be a head teacher brought her to Richmond, California and the Richmond Childcare Development Centers. Prout reflects on the pedagogy and theories involved in teaching of young children during this time, and how this affected her every day experiences in a continually changing community. During this time of change, Prout experienced and witnessed operational, social, and economic challenges in the community.</description><rel /><transcript>BICAIS: I&#039;d like to start off asking you about your early life. Where were you born?

PROUT: I was born in San Francisco. I lived with my parents and my sister. I was
seventeen months older than my sister. She is still alive. I went to Catholic
schools in high school and grammar school. My father was in the small-town
newspaper business and we moved around a lot. I was actually born in San
Francisco, and then my folks lived in Sacramento Valley. My mother came down to
have me because she used to be a nurse, and she knew a doctor in San Francisco
that she felt very secure with. So then she went back to the Sacramento Valley.
My dad had a newspaper, and he was a very creative man. So then finally he
started the Gilroy Dispatch, to Watsonville, Morning Sun News and then to Petaluma.

When we were in Petaluma I went to San Jose State University. I received my BA
in education and psychology. After that, I wasn&#039;t sure what I wanted to do. I
had a credential and could teach, but that didn&#039;t appeal to me very much. I went
over to Dominican College to see my sister, and there was a lady there that said
they were hiring in Richmond. This was in 1944. She said they needed teachers
because they were starting a large child-development program. They used to call
it &quot;child-care centers.&quot; We eventually got the &quot;care&quot; out and the State
Department of Education called it &quot;children&#039;s centers.&quot; We just didn&#039;t want to
be labeled as a welfare program. It was an educational program. I went over to
Richmond, and they needed teachers so badly that they just hired you. I became a
teacher, and the program was financed by the federal government because Richmond
had the shipyards and all the parents worked in the shipyards. The children
needed care; they needed a preschool program. The program started in 1943, and I
got into it in 1944. We had about twenty to twenty-two centers -- I&#039;m not
entirely sure about this. Richmond was lucky because it didn&#039;t have any old
school buildings to place the children. The Lanham Act was developed by
Congress, and there was money for regular nursery school buildings. They built
them in Richmond and we had a beautiful physical set up.

BICAIS: So all of the buildings in Richmond were brand new?

PROUT: All brand new, and people came by bus from all over California and all
over the United States to see these buildings. They were the first early
childhood centers that were really developed on a large scale. They had the
classrooms, and they had the little bathrooms attached to them and lots of
windows to look out. It was a beautiful setup. Going back, the federal
government financed the program, and the school district administered it. It was
really all over California. Los Angeles, Oakland and San Francisco all had them.
They also had them in Oregon and Washington, but in these states, they closed
them after the war was over. In our case, they kept them open. We had about
twenty-two centers, and we had one center that was open twenty-four hours.
Little children would come because their parents were on swing shift or
graveyard shift. The children whose parents were on graveyard shift would come
in their pajamas, and they would sleep. We provided the swing-shift children
with dinner, and the other little children would have breakfast to enhance their
nutritional needs. We had daytime students and swing shift and graveyard. That
was just in one center.

They had big staffs. They had a director and they had a nutritionist; the food
was excellent and well prepared. We had a kitchen in each site. These ladies
were very conscientious. They were all ladies that had had children, and the
food had to be perfect for the center&#039;s children. The parents appreciated this a
lot. At night, they could go home and maybe just give the children a glass of
milk and maybe some soup. They were all so busy; many of the men were overseas.
There was a lot of trauma connected with the times. The federal government had a
fee schedule. For one child it would be $3.60 for the next $2.75.

BICAIS: It was very affordable then?

PROUT: Yes, definitely. The teachers were not simply aides; they knew a lot
about child development. Our first director was a real educator. She didn&#039;t want
any part of welfare. She just didn&#039;t want the program to have that stigma. It
was really wonderful; she hired only credentialed teachers. They knew about
early childhood. When a child painted something, they knew what it meant. The
curriculum had science and art, all kinds of cognitive material and language
development. The children really learned how to read. Later on, when the program
was a little bit different, all the kindergarten teachers wanted our children
because they had had such an advanced background. The program was excellent.

The federal government pulled out after the war. I think it was in 1945 or 1946.
We had a hard time getting finances. The field was new, and people thought that
women should not be working. People had to work to be eligible for the program.
We had ways of verifying this. The state of California took over, the childhood
development office. Unfortunately, they never gave us enough money. At first, we
had ample funding. It was based on -- grants through the state -- on the number
of children you had, so much per child. We also had a full-cost fee, and
teachers and nurses children could participate in the program. The real cost was
picked up by the school district. The government wasn&#039;t paying anything for
them; they were paying themselves. We had an override tax that paid the rest of
it. It was all done on a means basis according to your income. When the men
began coming home, they took advantage of the GI Bill, which was probably the
most wonderful thing that ever came out of the war. Many of these men would not
have gotten an education without it. The state of California would give us money
for just a year at a time. It was really rough budgeting.

We were administered by the school district; we were all hired by them. Our
salaries were set by them. By that time, we had closed some of the centers
because we didn&#039;t need them. They were scattered all over Richmond which was wonderful.

We had an art supervisor, a music supervisor; the children received every form
of education. We did a lot of parent education. These were young parents who
needed help. Very cooperative. We had a PTA group and had good speakers come.
The centers stayed open from 6:00 in the morning to 6:15 in the evening.
Sometimes it was a little hard to schedule, but we maintained good ratios. We
had a fine medical program. We had a part-time doctor on our staff. When the
parent first brought the child in, Dr. Albert would give them a physical exam.
Six months later he would give them a recheck. We did a lot healthwise. We kept
track of all the immunizations, which some of the parents didn&#039;t. By the time
the children got to kindergarten, we had the whole record so we could just turn
it over to the schools. We didn&#039;t have to depend on the parents finding all
these pieces of paper. We had access to any special education in the district.
We had a psychiatrist that we could refer the parents to if we had a child that
had really deep problems. We had a dental hygienist and a full-time nurse at
each site. We had to cut this down gradually.

We opened two brand new centers. One was in the San Pablo area. There was a
wonderful minister that realized the need for one there. He talked to the school
district that talked to Sacramento. They put a beautiful portable set-up there.
It was made especially for this program. It had classrooms and isolation room
for ill children. They had a long hall going down the middle and bathrooms
attached to each one. We had school age children before and after school. You
should have seen the boys; they were so cute. They learned to knit, and they
didn&#039;t think anything of it. They learned all this art. Some of them were really
very good. It was all their work. We didn&#039;t use any cutouts or anything. They
could recognize their own painting. We had art appreciation. They learned so
much about the Impressionists.

BICAIS: Something everyone should know about.

PROUT: Absolutely. There was this one little girl who looked just like a girl in
a Van Gogh painting. I called her mother&#039;s attention to it. We had nice outdoor
equipment for physical development. The San Pablo center was full before we
opened it; we had such a waiting list. We had about 100 children there. It was
so intimate; everyone knew everybody else. It gave the children a great deal of
security. So many people say, &quot;Oh, child care; you&#039;re taking them away from
their parents,&quot; but you&#039;re giving them so much.&quot; When you have more adults. We
opened the Lake Center in San Pablo in the sixties. In the seventies HUD came
into the act. The city of Richmond received HUD money.

BICAIS: HUD was what exactly?

PROUT: HUD was the housing development of the federal government. The city
received the money, and then they knew that we were the only ones that knew
about childhood development. They came to us and asked us to develop a program
and to see that the right equipment was bought: &quot;We will pay for the equipment.&quot;
The HUD money paid for the equipment. It was the most beautiful center. We had a
young architect working on it. I was director of the program. My assistant and I
had to plan it under the direction of this architect. Every day when the child
would come in, we had an inspection, because we wouldn&#039;t take a sick child. The
architect planned the most beautiful center from the ground up. It was an ideal center.

BICAIS: It was federally funded, you said?

PROUT: The city had the HUD money to erect the building, and then the school
district bought all the equipment, the beds, instructional supplies, et cetera.
It was a wonderful cohesive interaction between these two big departments. More
of this should have gone on. I was a teacher for eight months.

Then I thought I should do something else. Instead of principals, we had head
teachers. I went to my boss who had valuable experience. She had worked in the
WPA and did a lot of things before she took over the job as the director of this
big program during the war. It became smaller, but at one time it was massive.
We had thousands of children, and she really knew what she was doing. I went to
her and told her I thought I was going to quit because this wasn&#039;t for me. She
said, &quot;Yes it is. I want to make you a head teacher.&quot; This instilled so much
confidence in me. I was twenty-three years old at the time. I said, &quot;I don&#039;t
know how to be a head teacher.&quot; She said, &quot;You can learn&quot;. And I learned! I went
to two of the big centers as assistant head teacher and then to a couple of
smaller centers as head teacher. When our director retired, I took her job as
director of the whole program. It was long lifetime career of about forty-two
years. It was so rewarding. For a long time we made it on our own with the state
money. However, it got to the point where costs were too high. We paid excellent
salary. We had to skimp a lot. The district began to give us money, but that
stopped after a while because they needed that money. The program was closed in
1990. I retired in 1985. They let the county take the grant over from the state.
I had been retired for three years, and they asked me to come back to help
settle the books. It really made me sick. The county had a poor program. They
were just using the grant money, and you just couldn&#039;t do that and have an
excellent program. It&#039;s still going that way. It really hurt us when we had to
close it.

BICAIS: So it still exists to this day, only the county runs it?

PROUT: It&#039;s not the same program at all. Many of our staff received jobs there.
Some of our custodial and classified staff. They tell me it&#039;s just terrible.
They don&#039;t have the standards that we had. They said if I were there it wouldn&#039;t
have happened, but it would have. It was dollars and cents. The district was
giving quite a bit of money, but they got to the point where they couldn&#039;t
afford it. It was just sad. I was there the last day. The new people didn&#039;t know
what they were doing, they criticized our program. The school administration
offered help, but they didn&#039;t accept it. It was the people involved. We had a
strange book-keeping system that was highly audited. Thank God we never made a
mistake. No gross errors. Our teachers kept attendance books. We started to call
them the Bible because they were audited so heavily. We received money on daily
attendance. It had to all be right. Each one of those hours were dollars. I got
paranoid over it. We had auditors, federal, state and local. We had certain
eligibility requirements for parents. The parent would give us verifications of
his employment. We would have a big file that we placed all this information.
Auditors would check. They would check the number of days they were there. We
knew the rules and we abided by them. Some places had a hard time. People
interpreted it incorrectly.

We had a great staff. Our nutrition program consisted of breakfast in the
morning. We had lovely nutrition program. We taught the children nice manners,
how to use a napkin. The three-year olds were in a classroom by themselves with
maybe two or three teachers and aides. Some would come at 6:00, 7:00 or 8:00.
Breakfast was served at 7:30, and it was brought from the kitchen on carts into
the classroom. They would set up a little cluster of tables, and the teacher
would sit down and eat with them. It was lovely. She would serve them and
correct their manners.

I know that a great deal of children benefited from the program. So many parents
were working so hard that I don&#039;t think that they ever sat down and had a nice
meal. I just don&#039;t think that they had the time. That worked out well. We also
had a well-balanced dinner that was served in the various classrooms from 11:00
to 12:30. That was set up the same way. Then the little ones had a nap for about
two hours. We would bring the beds in and put them down in the classroom. Each
child had his own bed. Nice clean sheets at all times. It was a Cadillac program.

BICAIS: It sounds like a very all-inclusive program.

PROUT: Oh, it was really. And then in the afternoon we would get up and have a
little snack. We would have milk, and there would be fruit wedges and sandwiches
so they would have a little bit more to eat before they went home.

Let&#039;s see. We had school-age children before and after school, and it was
wonderful. The little kindergarten children would go to the adjoining school
from the center. Each center had a different public school because they were
located all over Richmond. We got to know the teachers, they got to know us, and
they depended on us a lot to make sure that notes to the parents got home. And
then the children could do their homework. And then in the summer we had a
wonderful program. We would hire buses and take them all over, you know, to
Sausalito where they have the Model of the Bay that the US engineers put up. And
the children got so much out of it. And then we would take them to the zoo.
Thank God we never lost anybody. We could&#039;ve but we didn&#039;t.

But the school-age program was a big success so that children would come back to
us for the hot lunch. Because the school was very close. They would walk back
and then go to school in the afternoon. They would get nutrition and then come
back and do all kinds of activities. We even had a tea one time. We had an
elderly teacher; she was great. She really knew children. And she decided to
bring some of her nice little cups, her china cups. And the boys were even
involved in it. They loved it! And they would have tea in the pretty cups; it
was really a learning situation.

BICAIS: One of the things -- you said something about, just kind of when the
program went from not being federally funded anymore, after the war. I was
wondering, this could be a stretch, but do you think this was in anyway kind of
indicative -- you talked a little bit about how you did a lot to avoid the
stigma of the program being welfare. Do you think that was -- ?

PROUT: No, I don&#039;t think that had anything to do with it. I think that -- see,
they called them child care centers. And once the war was over we still had that
name, and we didn&#039;t want it. So we had to go to the legislature and ask them to
change it. Just as we changed them to children&#039;s centers the big boom in the
federal government in day care came out. We didn&#039;t like when it happened. We had
a big compliance bureau in Sacramento. They examined us from head to toe. We
always had some consultant coming up. Nutrition or education. They only had one
big department that could come and evaluate the physical setup. We had to have a
certain amount of square footage per child. We had more rules than the public
schools, I think. Because every department gave us rules. [laughs] But anyway,
then our name was changed to children&#039;s centers. So that denoted education.

That stayed all the time until I retired. Let&#039;s see, how&#039;d it go? This big
department in Sacramento was under social welfare, and it was the compliance if
they saw a teacher that was cross-eyed or something, they&#039;d report it. They were
just terrible.

Our whole division, which was a big division because it included all these other
towns, they fought so hard not to be put under this compliance. We wanted one of
our own. But they had one, and it was already established. Some of our head
teachers had terrible times with them. They would assume something had happened.
Like we had one big black aide, and he was a wonderful fellow, but he dressed a
little peculiarly, you know, and they found one child that had been abused. Once
we found a child that had been abused we had to report it to the police, you
know. And call the parents in. That was within the last fifteen years that that
law was passed. Well, they were going to accuse this man of doing it. I knew he
hadn&#039;t done it. He was a wonderful young man; he had a marvelous report. But
this woman was writing him up, so we had to go to the headquarters and say,
&quot;She&#039;s not doing it right.&quot; But they were very picky. And then of course we had
the child development office. We had to write a program each year, which was
wonderful, telling them what we did, what we did in science and why we did it.
The reasons for it and everything.

And one time we had something funny happen. This was a developing program, so a
lot of things happened, and they are still happening that way. I was directly
under an assistant superintendent in the Richmond schools. They had special
education, and our program was placed under special education. We were writing
this brochure. And language development beginning to develop. Dr. Ricklin said
to me, &quot;What do you do?&quot; I said, &quot;We assimilate the children&quot; -- I was just
guessing -- &quot;and these little children from Vietnam don&#039;t know the English
language, and they come in here, and they are so smart that they learn it like
that.&quot; And he looks at me and says, &quot;Well that sounds pretty good.&quot; And then
about two years later he came in, and some woman at Texas University had written
a paper on assimilation for language development! [laughs] And we laughed
together, we said, &quot;We were guessing about that.&quot; I&#039;m not taking credit or
anything, but it was just funny- the incident. And he laughed, and he was very supportive.

We had union problems. We had aides that had been kind of used as teachers a
little bit but weren&#039;t paid as teachers. Our former director was saving money to
hire them. Well once the aides realized that was happening, we went to
arbitration and won. We should have won. Because it was a little unjust. And we
had a good program for school-age children: if something was wrong with one
child, we could go through the schools and have counseling, and we had many
support systems. Then, as I was leaving, the program was declining because the
district didn&#039;t have the money for counselors. They had maybe one for four
thousand children. They are beginning to realize now that early diagnosis is so
important and to get the parent involved.

I feel we did a lot for the children, a lot for the parents. Some of the parents
were very young, and they needed to know how to treat their children. They loved
their children. Like one man who was a huge man -- and he was a nice man -- his
wife had died. But he had two little girls. When he spanked them his big hand
would almost destroy their muscle development. So I had to call him in one day,
and I said, &quot;You know, I&#039;m not being critical of you; I know you&#039;re a good
parent,&quot; because he used to hem up his little daughter&#039;s dresses -- he was just
nice -- but I said, &quot;You&#039;ve got to stop spanking the children because there&#039;s
going to be no muscle tissue left.&quot;

BICAIS: He didn&#039;t realize how strong he was.

PROUT: He really didn&#039;t, and he said, &quot;I don&#039;t realize how strong I am.&quot; One
blow from him would&#039;ve sent the child careening over. So we could intercede and
help the parent.

BICAIS: It seems like there were a lot of young families around at the time.

PROUT: Oh, yes.

BICAIS: Maybe kind of inexperienced with child raising and whatnot. I&#039;ve read a
little bit about just the Bay Area in general at the time, and it seems like it
was a mass exodus to the Richmond and Oakland area. Richmond went from like
25,000 to 100,000 in a few years.

PROUT: You know what? During the war the kindergarten teacher would have 100
students in one class. She could barely take them out to the bathroom and count
them. It was just a huge job. A lot of fine teachers. They were really
dedicated, and they did the best with the facilities that they had. But there
was something else -- but the school district really didn&#039;t like us, we were a
burden to them. Because they had the K-12, and they were having problems with
them. This was just an added program. But little by little they realized what we
were doing. By the time I was director there was much more understanding of the
goals and objectives of the program. Our first director would come back with
tears in her eyes sometimes.

BICAIS: The program was based solely on need, right?

PROUT: It wasn&#039;t for everybody. That&#039;s a good point.

BICAIS: So it was a relatively small percentage of the kids so they just saw you
guys as almost a nuisance.

PROUT: Yes, and we had different guidelines that they had to work on you know.
But then, when I took over, it was getting better. It was about twenty years
after the program had started. Dr. Griffin was wonderful; he was assistant
superintendent in charge of special education. He was very supportive of the
program. Anytime we had to go in front of the union -- the union became very
impractical -- he helped us. We had just so much money in our budget we couldn&#039;t
spend anymore.

BICAIS: This is the teachers union?

PROUT: No, this is the classified union and teachers both; all our teachers were
under this. And we had a bad time with them. Then finally they began liking us a
little bit. Realizing that we were doing something for the benefit of the
children. But we had one teacher who was always reporting me. Always reporting
me for some little dumb thing, you know? And, so the union leader and I got to
be good friends. And he says to me, &quot;Mary, get her off my back.&quot; So we all
realized that we had to work together. But when they wanted more money, one time
Dr. Griffin said, &quot;You&#039;re going to have to give it to them.&quot; And I said, &quot;If you
can find any extra money in the budget we will give it to the employees.&quot;

BICAIS: That was the school board?

PROUT: No, we had a teacher&#039;s union, and a classified union. The classified one
is for people who did everything but teach. They became very active in the
district. One of the superintendents -- he was very fair, he was a fine man and
he could see some of the injustices in education and tried to counteract them.
And so he didn&#039;t do it; he let the unions in. They were going to get in anyway;
they had a powerful man at the head. Part of it was good, and part of it wasn&#039;t
so good. There always benefits and tradeoffs.

What else can I tell you about the children? Oh I know! In 1962 remember when
Kennedy died, and they were enacting the civil rights legislation?

BICAIS: Sure.

PROUT: Welfare on the federal level was going to give us money for the children.
So we had to take for a while people that were on welfare but they were going to
school or ill. And they had to be doing something, and they had welfare grants.
And then many of them -- I admired some of the girls; they were marvelous. Some
of these black girls wanted babies, so they&#039;d have a baby out of wedlock,
wouldn&#039;t finish high school, and then go to community college and get their
degrees from community college and get good jobs. But they wouldn&#039;t give them
enough; it would be an entry-level job. So there wouldn&#039;t be enough money; the
grant was better than the money from the job.

So we encouraged them to give them a supplement, and welfare did. The supplement
lasted for about three years. And it was the only way to get them off welfare. I
don&#039;t know why the federal government hadn&#039;t figured that out. But one of the
girls -- one time a fee schedule went very high. See, the state had a fee
schedule that was based upon the income plus the welfare they got. And the fee
schedule was raised so high throughout the state of California. We knew these
girls would go back on welfare. So they had a welfare referee come to each
school district, and I had to represent the school district and just say that we
were doing what the law said. But we didn&#039;t believe in the law. And these girls
came and testified, and they showed us their budgets and everything. Oh, they
were wonderful. I couldn&#039;t have made a budget like they did. And they were
trying so hard to get off welfare. So the referee said to me, &quot;You&#039;re really for
these girls aren&#039;t you?&quot; And I said, &quot;Yes, I am because they are trying to
improve their status instead of going back 100 percent on welfare.&quot; All the
people in my position throughout the state said the same thing. So they changed
it. And it was so good because then it was realistic to say that they could have
a little welfare and have a job and do well.

BICAIS: And then the welfare didn&#039;t last that long.

PROUT: And social workers were telling them how to spend their money. These were
smart girls. They led their lives the way they could and budgeted. But we had
some parents that were really mad; one parent was cheating on it, I knew. She
didn&#039;t put down her welfare grant. So we had to go in front of a group, a
welfare group. And somebody said, &quot;You know, she&#039;s going to kill you.&quot; And I
said, &quot;No, she won&#039;t kill me.&quot; But she followed me down to the welfare office,
and I had all the papers in my hand to prove that she hadn&#039;t paid. I don&#039;t think
she would&#039;ve killed me, but who knows.

BICAIS: That&#039;s scary.

PROUT: They could get pretty volatile. But you know what has happened here in
California which is so wonderful? You know, when Dr. [Wilson] Riles was
Superintendent of Public Instruction for all education he started a pre-school
program. And that was for underprivileged mothers whose children needed that
type of education. Now that program is going 100 percent. In Richmond one of my
friends that was in our program became the director. Her name is Sharon
Fogelson. She is operating a beautiful program. She&#039;s gotten all kinds of grants
outside the government program. And she has twenty-eight classrooms. She&#039;s going
to be retiring in a year. I think she knows right now, more about early
childhood development than anybody. She&#039;s just marvelous. I&#039;m so proud of her
because she had been a head teacher in our program. And she&#039;s just very
dependable. Very, very good. But she received funding for I think four new
programs this year. And then there are a lot of grants coming through to the
Richmond schools, and she&#039;s getting a great deal of them. And then she can
improve her program and give orientation.

Oh, that something else we did. We had all kinds of orientation for our
teachers. You know, you can get a credential and know a lot about specific
programs their goals, and objectives have to be explained and how you relate to
those goals and objectives. That helped us a lot. Many of them were elementary
teachers who had not had too much preschool education.

BICAIS: In your previous interview, you talked something about how the school
district ate up the buildings after your program was finished, or something
along those lines?

PROUT: Yes, well a lot of the buildings were torn down. A few of them were
temporary. Now Lake [center], the one that I told you about that was the
portable setup? That&#039;s still going, and the county has that. And Crescent Park,
the one that was brand new -- but the county didn&#039;t keep up those buildings.
They look terrible. And we were so fussy about that. Of course they are examined
just the way we were. I don&#039;t know how they get by with it.

Then we had the two big programs, one was Pullman and one was Maritime, and
these buildings could hold 180 children. They had about eight classrooms and big
kitchens; all of them had kitchens, but some of the centers were a little bit
smaller. We ended up -- probably when I left, oh, we had to whittle it down a
little bit. We ended up with probably -- do you remember reading that?

BICAIS: No. I didn&#039;t see it.

PROUT: I&#039;m probably going to tell you too many, but there were probably about
450 children in the late eighties and nineties.

BICAIS: And there were thousands at one point?

PROUT: Oh yeah, it was just huge. You know, because we had all of those centers.
I threw away a lot of things when I left. We had a wonderful brochure. But I
thought I&#039;d never use that. I should have saved it. It was a happy program. Even
the housekeepers were concerned about the children. They did the custodial work.

BICAIS: It sounds like an ideal program.

PROUT: Very idealistic. That&#039;s put very well. Yes it was. Our first director set
the goals and objectives for the whole program, and she had such high standards.
Her name was Erla Boucher.

BICAIS: And she was the mastermind behind it?

PROUT: Oh, she was the mastermind behind it, and then I just continued it
because I realized what she had done was just right. And all of our teachers
would get mad at her because she was the last of the authoritative
administrators. She said, &quot;Do this, do that.&quot; And they did it. And then when I
took over, I really did both setups. I believed that the teacher should have
their say.

And we had an arts supervisor that was excellent. I&#039;d love to have that brochure
too. She had a brochure that showed how you would set up various art displays
and art activities. She did so many wonderful things and set it up so well for
the children. We had easels, and then she would take a long strip of paper, and
cans would have different colors of paint, and she would put a circle here and
the color. That was identifying the color. Everything was educational. It was
excellent programming. We had many of teachers on various committees that the
district had -- they learned. That last year that I was here I would haul great
big cartons of food to each center so we wouldn&#039;t have to call a truck driver.
We really just stretched everything and we couldn&#039;t stretch it forever. We just couldn&#039;t.

BICAIS: So it just slowly got smaller and smaller? You slowly lost funding?

PROUT: Well, it got the same amount of funding, but expenses rose. Salaries went
up, which they should have. And everything was more expensive, so that&#039;s what
happened. It&#039;s a shame when I see all this information that President Bush is
putting out about the Head Start Program. It&#039;s a federal program, and I know
it&#039;s a lot better than it used to be; I shouldn&#039;t be criticizing it, but it was
a poor program. And lately in the paper, he said that some of this money is
going to -- he did mention child development, which is good, but most of it is
going to go to that Head Start Program. And I&#039;m sure it&#039;s better than it was.

End Tape 1, Side 1

PROUT: When this federal money came into Richmond and they had all these home --
little programs, where maybe a lady would take care of twenty children. They
were little centers. And we had some wonderful people. A lot of people didn&#039;t
want advice. But a lot of people said, &quot;You&#039;ve been doing this for so long; what
kind of toys should I buy, what should I do?&quot; And we had this one lady, Roberta
Griffin. She was great. She really listened to us, and she had a great program,
but it was a federally funded program. It had nothing to do with the school
district. She did well. But some of them -- a lot of money was wasted, it made
you sick.

BICAIS: Just on --

PROUT: Well, on equipment. If they just listened to us and bought the minimum
amount, it would have been great. Equipment that pre-school children shouldn&#039;t
have. Developmentally they weren&#039;t ready for the task of heading a program of
this kind. And that was sad. I think we should have gotten some of that money.
We got some of it because we got to the point where we only took welfare
children, because the money was out there. We had to go over our books and find
out how many children were on welfare. I remember this assistant of mine, we
were pounding it out on the adding machine, and she says, &quot;I&#039;m tired&quot;, and I
say, &quot;Listen, this means money, and we&#039;ve got to do it!&quot; So anyway, we received
money for quite a while. Then the federal government pulled out, and it was just
the state funding.

BICAIS: It sounds complicated, dealing with the different agencies.

PROUT: Well, it was basically the state and the federal government. The federal
government started it first, then came into it again in the sixties, and then
the rest of it was the state.

BICAIS: Did Prop 13 have anything to do with this?

PROUT: Oh, it had a big impact because it had an override tax for some of the
special activities, and ours was one of them. And when that was done away with,
that really was the demise of our program. It really was. I&#039;m glad that you
mentioned that. Because we didn&#039;t have that extra money from the override. And
we could charge fifty cents an hour for children, and the school district would
pick up the rest of the cost per pupil. And adult education had it, and we had
it, and there were a couple of special programs that had it. It murdered us.

BICAIS: I think it was &#039;79.

PROUT: Seventy-nine. Well we existed for maybe about twenty years after that,
but barely. You see, we just made it every year. We could not carry money from
one budget year to the next; see, we had all these rules: state local, federal.

BICAIS: Sounds very complicated.

PROUT: Well, our teachers would get so mad because we had reports that we had to
send to the feds. Well little Mississippi had to do it too, and we were so big.
The teachers would get so mad. It was on how many welfare children we had, and
how many AFDC 1, 2, or 3. And it didn&#039;t apply to us, but we still had to make
numerous reports because we took that federal dollar.

BICAIS: Kind of just going through the motions?

PROUT: Yes, and they would get so angry because they didn&#039;t have time for much
paperwork. They did essentials and did them well. But that override killed us.
That&#039;s what did it. We got that extra money. We could make more children
eligible. It was a better assemblage of children. They weren&#039;t all poor little
children. Some of the mothers were teachers or nurses. So it was a good
socio-economic blending of children. And I think that helped.

BICAIS: It sounds like it was a good place for children to interact with their
peers and whatnot.

PROUT: And some of those school-age children were so cute. One little boy,
Johnny, was always getting into trouble, but never defending himself. He went to
public school, and the principal was always giving him a bad time. And I would
say to him, &quot;Johnny, speak up, don&#039;t just stay in the periphery of the group.&quot;
&quot;Oh no, Mrs. Prout, I&#039;m okay.&quot; So two days before I left, John called, and he
hadn&#039;t been in our program for years. He went into the Army. He said, &quot;I heard
you were retiring, and I wanted to thank you.&quot; I got tears in my eyes, because
he was always getting into trouble, and I was always getting him out of it. But
I loved that boy. He did well in the Army, got married; he married a nice girl.
So it was a thrill for him to remember. He was in his forties then, I&#039;m sure.

BICAIS: I&#039;m sure you made a huge impact on him. I&#039;m sure you made a huge impact
on all the kids.

PROUT: Well, I don&#039;t know, but we all tried. No one took all the credit. I
always felt that it was the teacher; we all just helped the teacher. She was the
important one. And we tried to instill that in her. We did in most cases. We
were there to support her.

BICAIS: That&#039;s a good philosophy.

PROUT: But if she was ineffective, the program was poor; we couldn&#039;t motivate her.

BICAIS: She is definitely the front line.

PROUT: She was the front line, and the aides were too. Some of the aides went on
to become teachers. They went back to school. One girl, she was a black girl and
a lovely girl. One day I was giving this speech and saying how important
education is and going on and on. And I looked at her face, and I didn&#039;t think
that she was maybe even listening. Well she went back and got her AA at
community college, and when she got it she came up to my office and she said, &quot;I
have a little gift for you, because you&#039;re the one who inspired me.&quot; That wasn&#039;t
completely the truth because she worked hard to develop her educational skills.
She was so honest and so sweet.

But another time I went to talk; it was terrible. It was to a bunch of
kindergarten mothers, and I was going on about the benefit of nursery school
education and how everybody had to have it. This cute little Asian mother came
up to me and said, &quot;Do you think I have abused my child because I didn&#039;t give
her a pre-school education.&quot; And I said, &quot;Oh no, no, no. I&#039;m sure you&#039;re a good
mother.&quot; You get too general sometimes so we all make mistakes. I&#039;m so glad you
mentioned the override, it was so critical. We gradually knew what it would mean.

BICAIS: When it first came out on the ballot, did you realize the dire
consequences that it would have for the program?

PROUT: No we didn&#039;t until later, because that wasn&#039;t publicized very much. But
then we began reading carefully and realizing and those other programs did too.

BICAIS: You have to read the fine print.

PROUT: Oh, you certainly do.

BICAIS: Someone who is advocating a political stance isn&#039;t going to come out and
tell you the down side of it.

PROUT: No, they are not going to tell you. But you know, we did a lot of
legislative work too because that kept us alive. You know senior George Miller
who was in Martinez -- his son is now a Congressman and he&#039;s one of the heavy
democrats, I think, in Washington -- old George was wonderful. My former boss
name was Erla; she would go to him, and he would say, &quot;Erla, what do you want
now?&quot; And she&#039;d say, &quot;We have to this and we have to do that.&quot; &quot;Okay, I&#039;ll see
that it&#039;s taken care of.&quot; He knew it was a good program.

And then a lot of these state legislators enacted legislation that helped us.
They would put us on the bottom of the bill where no one noticed we were there.
We would go up on Legislative Day, and they would have some of the organizations
would have it. And all of these legislators&#039; offices were open, and we would go
in and talk with them. We had powerful organizations too. We had a directors
group. When the program first started we all had Social Security, but we weren&#039;t
in the state pension system. San Francisco had a state pension system because it
was through the City of San Francisco, but they were the only ones. So, my boss,
and the gal from Oakland, and about five of them lobbied to get that. So now, we
all have pensions. We&#039;ve had them since the sixties, I think. So we have both,
which is wonderful because a lot of programs don&#039;t have both. The San Francisco
director said to my boss, &quot;You&#039;re going to ruin it for everybody.&quot; And my boss
said, &quot;What do you mean? You&#039;re the only one that had it. Your people have a
pension but our people don&#039;t.&quot; So by God they went to the right legislatures and
got it done. So now we all have good pensions.

BICAIS: Wow, that&#039;s great.

PROUT: The teachers were all under STRS, which is the State Teachers Retirement.
And a lot of us stayed under PERS, which is basically for classified people.
There was a fiscal man in Richmond that helped me a lot with our program. I had
a chance to go under STRS in the middle of my career. And he says, &quot;No Mary,
stay where you are, it&#039;s a better system.&quot; Well, it&#039;s debatable whether it is or
not. I think it&#039;s caught up with PERS. PERS is the largest public retirement
system in the world, I think. It has state and all the police, and community
officers are participants. When you get a job, make sure it has a pension.
Because it all happens very fast. And you suddenly think, &quot;Oh! I have to retire.&quot;

PROUT: And those dollars come in handy every month. Our district put in 13
percent for us, and we put in 6 percent a month. Which was pretty good; they put
in the bulk of it. Our district had wonderful medical coverage. I&#039;m still
getting it right now as a retiree. They put it in a contract, and they can&#039;t
renege on the contract. For a while we had medical, dental, and pharmaceutical,
and I paid one dollar for my prescriptions; that&#039;s all. I&#039;d walk into a doctor&#039;s
office and not give him anything because this was such a good plan. Now it&#039;s
changed, and we have to give a little bit more. We have $1000 dental coverage
which doesn&#039;t go too far, but it takes care of many problems lot of your needs.

BICAIS: Filling in cavities and whatnot. [laughter]

PROUT: And you get to be this age, and you really have to have construction work done.

BICAIS: Thank you so much for your time today. I really appreciate it.

Begin Tape 2

BICAIS: I was wondering if you could talk a little bit about how -- along I-580
and Cutting Blvd, how some of the temporary wartime housing was razed.

PROUT: It was mostly along Cutting Boulevard. And some of those streets that
went into Cutting. And then a lot of -- as you said, with I-580 [coming in]
there were a lot of housing areas there. Each housing area had a central -- it
was like and administrative building. There was a man in charge, and he would
collect the rents and do any maintenance that had to be done. We had Terrence
Center and Harbor Gate, and Canal Centers; they gave us room for child centers
in these areas. And they were awfully good to us. Of course they were under the
federal government too, and that&#039;s when we were under the federal government.
But they would give us rooms in their administration buildings to develop a
children&#039;s center. And we had, in one location, about 100 children. The manager
would come in and talk with us and help us on lots of things. So it was a good
correlation of these two agencies, of the housing and the school district, and
the federal government. And it worked very well together. And then, I can&#039;t
remember when they tore the housing down, but it was like in the fifties.

BICAIS: Early to mid-fifties I think.

PROUT: I think so too.

BICAIS: When they tore down the housing, they tore down the daycare centers as well?

PROUT: Let&#039;s see, we had two big daycare centers or children&#039;s centers that
survived it. And this was our Pullman Center on 23rd and Florida St; that&#039;s just
off of Cutting. And then our Maritime Center, which had been the first one to be
constructed, and that was on 10th Avenue off of Cutting. And those are still
remaining today.

BICAIS: But initially they were on the same land as the housing, and they got
spared basically.

PROUT: Yes. Right. And it was good because people could walk their children to
the children&#039;s centers. Especially the ones that were in the housing areas. They
had a lot of support from community of people. That was part of the housing
contingent; they were the ones that were torn down. We really didn&#039;t need them
after the war. Because a lot of people went home, and many people went to
school. Some of the GI fellows and their families lived in that housing. They
used to call it the GI housing. It had nice little apartments, and it was kept
up well.

BICAIS: After the war a lot of that temporary housing wasn&#039;t really needed at
that point?

PROUT: Well, it was needed while these men went to school. See they only had the
GI Bill and maybe their wives&#039; salaries. And so they needed low-cost housing.

BICAIS: Kind of an interim period?

PROUT: See, that gave them the incentive to go to school, and that was part of
the purpose of the GI Bill. That was really one of the best things to ever
happen to this country. It really was wonderful. And Roosevelt was responsible
for that. He signed it and everything. When they say he was the greatest
President, you wonder, but he did a lot. And there were so many isolationists
that didn&#039;t want us to go to war, and we had to. He just pushed the bill. To
think that the poor man was crippled and everything, but he was so smart.

BICAIS: He was President through a lot of critical times, that&#039;s for sure.

PROUT: And Churchill depended on him. I remember reading in a book about the
Lend-Lease and how Churchill didn&#039;t want any part of it. And Roosevelt knew that
it would save England. You&#039;ve got to have these ships and this power behind you.
If it weren&#039;t for Roosevelt, England could have gone under. They were bombed,
and they just had a rough time. And Churchill wasn&#039;t as realistic as Roosevelt,
but they were good friends.

BICAIS: Churchill was more from the old school, I remember reading someplace --
this is kind of off topic -- but that Churchill wanted to retain the English
Empire after World War II. And Roosevelt wanted none of that. He used to kid
Churchill about the old English Empire.

PROUT: It was a good relationship because they each helped each other quite a
bit. But I think Roosevelt helped Churchill more than Churchill helped
Roosevelt. But it was a different era. Mrs. Roosevelt played a big part. She
came out here and viewed our centers. They always said that Franklin would start
the programs, and he wasn&#039;t as mobile as she was, and then he would send her out
to evaluate them. It was a good team.

BICAIS: And she actually came out to your centers?

PROUT: She actually came out. I&#039;m sure she did. I could be wrong on that. I
never saw her. But I could be wrong on that. But her influence was felt on all
the legislation. It was an interesting time. A constructive time. All these men
going to school; it was wonderful. Some of them got their PhDs, some got
masters, some became teachers, engineers. Many of them are some of the famous
men today. They really worked hard.

BICAIS: It really got a whole generation going. And trickled down, so to speak,
to their children and grandchildren. A lot of people my age&#039;s grandparents are
really the solid force in our country today.

PROUT: Exactly, and everybody should go to school. You can never get enough
schooling. I remember my own father; it was so important to him to my sister and
me to college. It was marvelous.

BICAIS: That&#039;s the attitude that you have to take to be successful: put a
priority on education.

PROUT: Once in a while there will be someone like Bill Gates [laughs]. It&#039;s
funny; the children that came from this group of people were all staunch
Americans. They were all -- many of them were from the Midwest. They knew what a
dollar meant, and they knew how to get an education. It was really a
constructive time.

BICAIS: Do you think that coming out of the Depression, just the fact that money
was so scarce? That generation had the attitude that money was something to be
held on to; you saved it. And then coming out of the war, and having such an
unprecedented period of prosperity, do you think that in any way contributed to
the conservatism that followed. Because people had such a high value for the
dollar and maybe they didn&#039;t want to see it given away to social programs.

PROUT: Yes. Yes. And some of them gave too much to their children. Because they
had been deprived with the Depression and everything, they gave too much to
their children. And I don&#039;t think that was good. You needed the necessities and
you needed an education, but you didn&#039;t need a lot of other things.

BICAIS: It kind of spoiled the next generation, huh?

PROUT: Yeah, spoiled the next generation. But then some good things happened
too. You know. There were a lot of good kids out there. Like you! [laughs] I
mean you want an education and a future, and you don&#039;t just want to sit around.
And that comes from your family. I know it does. So it was a big era in the
history of the United States.

BICAIS: I&#039;m interested in looking a little deeper into how the country didn&#039;t
seem to have the same -- what&#039;s the right word -- I guess sympathies coming out
of the war. Maybe I&#039;m reaching here, but it seems like a lot of people in the
Depression maybe felt that, since they got through it and they were maybe
well-off after the war and felt the economic benefits of the wartime boom, that
maybe after that they were less inclined to be socially liberal, and to give
money to social safety net type programs. I&#039;m trying to work that in to your
experience with how the federal government after the war began to withhold funds
from your program. Do you think that -- I guess I&#039;m trying to make that connection.

PROUT: I think that they thought it just wasn&#039;t needed. And now more and more --
it&#039;s really early childhood education, and everyone should have early childhood
education. The child is ready to learn, and if he just stays at home all the
time he can learn from books and puzzles and all that. But they need the
camaraderie and the socialization with other children. And if the child doesn&#039;t
have that, they miss a lot, I think. And then the kindergarten teacher can&#039;t go
on to her next level. I remember the kindergarten teachers all wanted our
children because they had all of the aspects of child development along the way.
It wasn&#039;t just play it was learning.

BICAIS: And they were probably much better behaved than the other children.

PROUT: Well maybe not so well behaved [laughs] because they kind of got excited
a little bit. They were used to being in a group. But they did have the -- many
of them were bright, and they had been exposed to activities on their level. The
emotional part too. Children are so ready for kindergarten and first grade
because they&#039;ve have the emotional part tie of leaving their parents out of the
way. You know, being away from your parents. Also the health factors. I think I
told you that we had a pediatrician on our staff. They accumulated all the
records. So when it came time to go to kindergarten, all these things were
amassed in our files. It was the vaccinations and everything. So there were many
pluses and benefits, the child&#039;s whole health record.

BICAIS: Do you think that as the war came to a close and you received less and
less money -- I guess you stopped receiving money from the federal government
and it went to the state, but there was a diminishing in the funding overall, is
that right?

PROUT: I really don&#039;t know if it was a diminishing of the funds. The state did
pretty well at first, but we had a grant from the state. And it was good it took
care of a lot. And then of course with Proposition 13; we could add to the
program because that was local money. We were in pretty good shape. The only
thing that worried us was that the money from the state was enacted every year.
So on June 30 we didn&#039;t know on July 1 if we were going to be open. It was a lot
of emotional upheaval. Afterward, they put it on a permanent basis. But we
received money on an attendance basis, similar to the school district. It was
very involved as far as book work was concerned. But, we got along. And then, as
I said to you, after I left -- we didn&#039;t receive district money when I was there
-- but after I left they had to because we had good salaries, and they just
couldn&#039;t pay them with the grant. We were always going to Sacramento and asking
for more money. Sometimes we would get it and sometimes we wouldn&#039;t. It was a
little iffy there for a while. And then when the school district pulled out
because they needed the money, then they knew they couldn&#039;t make it. It was impossible.

BICAIS: Last time when I talked to you, you mentioned that World War II was
really the golden age of the program. You seem to have a lot of fond memories of
the program during the war. Was the same standard upheld after the war?

PROUT: Oh yes! And that&#039;s why we ran out of money. Because our salaries were so
good we insisted that we had credentialed teachers and had to pay them. The
money was getting less and less. We weren&#039;t getting any more money.

BICAIS: But the cost of living was still going up of course.

PROUT: Yes, the cost of living was going up. And so that&#039;s what broke the back
of the program. And then the county took over. But the county didn&#039;t have the
same goals and objectives that we had.

BICAIS: It just wasn&#039;t up to speed, huh?

PROUT: Oh, it wasn&#039;t and still isn&#039;t. All of us old timers feel very bad about
the demise of the program.

BICAIS: I guess what I&#039;m trying to get at was, after the war do you think that
the program was able to meet the same needs as it did during the war?

PROUT: The needs weren&#039;t as great as the years progressed after the war. We
developed these two new centers, and one was in the San Pablo area. There was a
minister there that knew there was a need. So he went to the school district and
went to bat for us. At that point, we had a lot of welfare children. And we
would receive money from the federal government as far as the welfare children
were concerned, and they didn&#039;t pay anything. That was on one other transition.
And then, a lot of that money dried up, and the eligibility rules changed a
little bit. You see, before, during World War II, we could take any child; we
didn&#039;t have eligibility rules. Once the state took over we had a means test, and
the parent could make just so much money. And then, when the federal government
came back in to the program with the AFDC children we had a little bit more
money, but not a lot. I hate to keep talking about money, but money really made
the program. We really became almost a welfare program, but we weren&#039;t; we had
the name &quot;child care center&quot; during the war. All of us hated &quot;care&quot; because it
denoted welfare. So then, we got the state legislature to change the name to
&quot;children&#039;s centers.&quot; Just as we did that, the big child care boom in the nation
came. Federal money was poured into some small programs. And so it identified
our program, but it didn&#039;t identify every program. We did not want to be called
welfare. It was education. This is what we stressed because we were under
education. We didn&#039;t want just a babysitter program. And we really fought over
the years. We didn&#039;t want it to be labeled that. When the school district tried
to call us welfare we said, &quot;We are administered by you, but we are not a
welfare program.&quot; When we got the name changed, it helped a little bit.

BICAIS: Do you think that people started calling you a welfare program because
during the war it wasn&#039;t need based, and then it became more for only the lower
income kids?

PROUT: It could be.

BICAIS: I&#039;m trying to tie in the trend towards more conservative politics at the time.

PROUT: That lessened the desire to have our program, the conservative politics.
Because a lot of those legislators thought the mother should stay home and the
child should be reared at home. And they didn&#039;t think that these programs were
very important. But we had a couple of key legislators that really helped us
out. When I think about it we would go and talk to them, and they would put us
in a bill, and we would get more for buildings or maybe supplies or teacher&#039;s salaries.

So it was very challenging. Very challenging. Our parents -- the parents that we
had were very convinced that their children were getting a good education, and
that was very rewarding. We had no problems with the parents at all. We had
parent groups, and the parents helped legislatively a lot on the state level.
They would write letters to the state legislators. They helped a lot with the
money programs. They were loyal and good, you know. Increased the money that
flowed. It made a better program.

BICAIS: I&#039;m assuming that the people who sent their children to the centers
during and right after the war, most of the women probably worked?

PROUT: And the men went to school. That was a whole period. That lasted for
maybe four or five years after the state took over. Then it became -- then we
took welfare children. Remember when Kennedy and Johnson had their big welfare
emphasis; they wanted to get people off welfare. And so we would get extra money
for children. And then our food program was developed around that as well. If
they had so much money, the child would be eligible or not. So we had a lot of
paperwork to do. And we had auditors all over the place. And thank goodness we
never had a bad report. But we had federal auditors, we had state auditors, and
we had local auditors. Each school district has to hire a team of auditors every
year to make sure the program was meeting its finance goals. We were very
fortunate. We had a many people that were conscientious, so we never had a bad mark.

BICAIS: So because for an initial time, you said it was GIs and their families
that used the center, and then after that it predominantly became welfare.

PROUT: Well there was a period between welfare and the GIs where we had means
testing. It was workers that made quite low salaries. So the government didn&#039;t
have to put a lot of money in, but they put some. So it was that period that
lasted about -- well, 1965 is when the welfare money came. And it lasted.

And see, the color of our program changed too. A lot of black people lived in
the public housing and paid rent and lived in the housing program, poor people,
after the GIs left. So that was a phase of the program. And many of those girls
went and got jobs, good jobs. They were eligible if they went to community
college or some kind of vocational program. So it helped the community a lot. As
it progressed, sometimes we would feel it was going down, but then it would go
up again. The federal government influenced the first days and those middle
days. And then finally they pulled out completely except for the lunch program.
And of course the lunch program is that way in the schools too. It was all based
on family&#039;s income. Then when I left we still had a lot of black children, but
we had a little bit of everyone. But the requirements were getting more, not
less. So but it was still under the state.

BICAIS: You talked a little bit about LBJ and Kennedy, their push to get people
off welfare. Do you think that this had a negative effect on the child care or
children&#039;s centers?

PROUT: No, I don&#039;t think so.

BICAIS: You don&#039;t think there was a conservative push to end programs like this
because it was welfare in the eyes of some?

PROUT: Well, in the eyes of some legislators. Some Republicans. They didn&#039;t want
anything to do with it. This was an anti-social deal; it was like Sweden in
particular: all the children out of the homes putting them in these other
buildings. It took them a long time to get that through. Some of them never did.
Some of them don&#039;t have it now.

BICAIS: They saw it as a negative thing?

PROUT: An anti-social thing. But more and more with early childhood education,
the theories are being developed that it&#039;s a wonderful thing for children. It&#039;s
now a plus rather than a negative. So the whole history of it has been very
interesting because we can see improvement during times, and we can also see
non-improvement at times. But most of it was constructive.

BICAIS: Overall it seems that without question it was a positive thing.

PROUT: And the school districts began to realize that these programs were very
important and they would build them up -- our former director was under
elementary ed as far as the school district was concerned. And then when I took
over we were under special ed. We had a wonderful superintendent that would meet
with me once a week and talk about our problems and everything. And he was very
supportive. So we finally got a little acclaim. Acclaim that we needed and
acclaim that we deserved. But it was a new program, and it was just one more
thing for the school district to worry about. They had so many special ed
programs. But finally we got the right people in some of those jobs. They were
younger people. They were people that had early childhood courses in college.
They knew the importance of it. But we always had that conservative element.

BICAIS: And you were always fighting them, Basically conservative Republicans of
the time were anti-New Deal, anti-welfare, and anti-FDR and his legacy. A lot of
conservative Republicans came into the House in the 1942 elections.

PROUT: Yes, they did.

BICAIS: They probably saw this as a borderline socialist program.

PROUT: Babysitting. They said it was babysitting. This just killed us. We
weren&#039;t babysitters, but that&#039;s what they thought we were. But then finally the
programs began being accepted. And this was very gratifying.

BICAIS: And this happened around what time do you think?

PROUT: Well, it was a gradual thing. As different legislators came in -- they
were younger some of them -- the whole country began conforming a little bit to
education at three years old or even two years old. It was better than having
the children at home with an inexperienced person who didn&#039;t know anything about
childhood development. A lot of legislators were young, and their wives were
working. It was just a different philosophy. Completely. It grew.

BICAIS: So in the sixties and seventies as women started working outside the
home, and it became more accepted, as opposed to the World War II generation and
before when women stayed home. It kind of became more accepted overall. That
makes sense.

PROUT: Yes, it was a whole philosophical change in the world. Some of it was for
the good; most of it was for the good.

BICAIS: A little more realistic in a sense, because it was inevitable that women
were going to begin to work outside of the home. It was just a matter of time.

PROUT: Yes, many of these women had a good education, and they wanted to develop
this. So anyway, it progressed pretty well. Anyway, San Francisco still has
children&#039;s center. Berkeley has them. I think Albany&#039;s are still open. And they
are funded just the way ours was. Los Angeles has them too. There aren&#039;t small
towns in LA anymore. We had a good situation, we had what we had a director&#039;s
association. And this director&#039;s association did a lot for the program. They
were all the directors of all the programs in the south and the north. And we
would meet once a year in either the north or the south. So we could get a lot
of legislation done that way. We were a bigger group, and we got a lot done.

BICAIS: It sounds like coming out of the conservatism of the forties and fifties
people eventually came around and saw that these programs were a good thing, and
we should support the teachers and whatnot.

PROUT: It took a while, and it would be great if we had a little bit more. You
know, like now the teacher&#039;s salaries are just terrible and the money for
teacher&#039;s salaries has to come from the local level. And if there is a bill that
comes from Sacramento that makes it look like there will be some money, they
spend it on something else. It&#039;s a great inequality.

BICAIS: And of course when you offer lower salaries, you are going to attract a
lower caliber of person.

PROUT: Lower people, right. And the teacher is the most important thing. I used
to say to our teachers, &quot;We&#039;re just here to help you. Because you are the ones
involved in the children.&quot; And the more I think about that, the more I realize
that it is so true.

BICAIS: And it&#039;s hard once you get the cycle started of underpaying teachers,
you do start attracting, I don&#039;t want to say lesser people, it sounds bad, but --

PROUT: Well you lower the standard.

BICAIS: Yeah, someone who is coming out of a really good college probably isn&#039;t
going to be inclined to take the $30,000 a year teaching position. And once you
get that cycle started, it&#039;s hard to throw more money at the teachers because
you already have a lower standard of teacher. You really need to keep the
standards high the whole time, because at this point, we have a lot of teachers
that are underpaid, but there is also a lot of bad teachers out there. In the
public schools.

PROUT: That&#039;s right, but there are a lot of good teachers too that stay because
they believe in what they are doing. I have a little niece who graduated from
John Hopkins, and she entered the Teach for America Program, and she&#039;s has been
there for three years. I don&#039;t know if she is going as a teacher to stay there
or not; she says she loves the children, and she feels like she is doing
something for them. I&#039;m so proud of her. Her degree was in international
relations. And she&#039;s a smart, lovely girl.

BICAIS: Probably could have gotten the high paying job out of school, but she
opted to teach?

PROUT: And she has about twenty little children, and they just do fine. She&#039;s
really motivated.

BICAIS: Those are the type of people that we need as teachers. You need people
that are highly qualified and don&#039;t mind taking a pay cut. Unfortunately,
they&#039;re hard to find.

PROUT: They&#039;re not worried about the paycheck. But it seems so unrealistic with
Silicon Valley. We did get teacher&#039;s salaries up a little bit, but now they&#039;re
just horrible. I have a couple of friends that have been in education for a long
time, and their salaries are decent. They&#039;re not bad. But they are in bigger
school districts. Dr. Riles, he was the public superintendent in Sacramento, and
he started a program for just poor little children. It was called 1331; that was
the legislation that started it. I think the eligibility -- I think the parent
still has to not work.

But I have a friend who is in charge of this massive program, and she&#039;s done a
beautiful job. She was one of the head teachers in our program years ago. She
has about twenty-eight classes, and she&#039;s doing beautifully. I think she knows
more about early childhood development and education than anybody maybe in the
United States. Her salary is pretty good. The districts are realizing that they
have to have programs of that nature, or they can&#039;t compete. That&#039;s a program
that evolved from this original program. There are a lot of benefits to it. We
belong to all the educational organizations, and we brought back all the
materials and everything. And we had a lot of information coming back from the
Eastern colleges that had early childhood programs. We had a lot of good
information so that we knew what was the latest.

BICAIS: That&#039;s great. Well, I&#039;d like to thank you for your time; I got a lot out
of this interview.

PROUT: You&#039;re welcome. If you ever need anything else, just let me know.

  

  

  

  

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>