<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042124" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2005-10-16" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Judy Hart | Interview 2 | October 16, 2005</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Judy Hart</interviewee><interviewer>Richard Cándida Smith</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url></media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Judy Hart, founding superintendent of the Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front National Historical Park, details the steps involved in creating the park from its legislative inception in 2000 to her retirement in 2005.  Hart also discusses her previous duties in the National Park Service, including her work as founding superintendent of the Women's Rights National Historical Park in Seneca Falls, New York.</description><rel /><transcript>CANDIDA SMITH: As we were starting to set up, you were talking about the issue
of having to start from scratch multiple times.

HART: There were many layers and many levels that I had to keep starting all
over again. Everything fell to me because the first couple of years I was the
only staff person. I had to start over again with the Regional Director. John
Reynolds had recruited me for the job. I had known John, worked with him for
twenty-five years. I admired him enormously. He was very easy for me to work
with. We understood each other; we had really helpful conversations. John had
the ability to--it was almost mystical; he could cut through so many issues and
just come right to the point. I&#039;d go away thinking about something that he&#039;d
said and kind of retool the way I was approaching something. Then he decided to
retire after I was there for two years. I was devastated when he left because he
knew how to build not-traditional parks, working with partners, collaborating
with community groups.

There were some in the region it seemed to me who somehow thought a partnership
meant the community would on their own do the tasks involved in developing the
Park. That was not the case, at all. Working with our partners, I had to do even
more work to collaborate and inspire somebody else to do something. I had to
create the dream, promote the dream, get agreement on plans, and then inspire
folks to spend their money and time to make their plans happen.

Jon Jarvis became Regional Director, and we started over. His position was that
I should wait until the General Management Plan got finished in a few years, and
then we&#039;d start doing something and get some funding a few years after that.

CANDIDA SMITH: Well, let&#039;s step back and discuss, or define at least, what a
general Management Plan is, what it was that the National Park Service expected,
and then what you were required to do.

HART: Well, it was core and spine to the challenge of Rosie, because in a
traditional park the General Management Plan is an outline of the development
that will happen in the park: the buildings that will be acquired, the roads
that might be put in, the parking lots that might be put in--the development to
be done by the Park Service. It is used in the National Park Service as the
vehicle for compliance with the National Environmental Protection Act, NEPA. So
it is a combined environmental impact statement and a development concept plan.
That works well in a conventional park where the Park Service is going to do the
development. Except in Rosie, almost all of the significant development, the
extensive, expensive development, was going to be done by the partners. It
didn&#039;t make any sense to write a plan about what they would do, if they weren&#039;t
willing to do it.

Particularly with Shipyard Number Three. Back when the team drafting the
legislation was sitting around in Washington trying to come up with a
legislative concept that would work, we fussed and fussed. I don&#039;t mean argued,
but tangled and created alternatives and did everything we could think of to
come up with how the National Park Service could write a plan for Shipyard
Number Three, which was fifty acres, five historic structures, a number of
modern structures, and the Port for Richmond. What was the National Park Service
going to say that would make any sense and comply with the environmental
requirements? Well, nothing. So the determination was that the City of Richmond
would write an Historic Preservation Plan that would be attached to the General
Management Plan. We knew that it could not be the Park Service sitting down and
writing that plan.

I confess when I first started working at Rosie, I was concerned about being so
dependent on the city. After I thought about it more and became familiar with
the folks in the city government, I decided having the city develop the core of
what would become the General Management Plan was absolutely brilliant, because
it gave the freedom to the city to say what they wanted. It gave them their own
power, their own determination, and it required the Park Service to work with
the city. The legislative team, including the Washington Chief of Planning
Warren Brown, was very clear about these legal and practical issues. But it was
a major struggle in the regional office. Talk about starting over. We had three
different team captains for our General Management Plan.

CANDIDA SMITH: How were the team captains selected?

HART: Well, the first one was a staff person in the regional office assigned by
the Chief of Planning there.

[Narrators addendum: We were in this first round successful in working with the
region&#039;s cultural resources staff to lay out and organize the research and
studies that would be needed to preserve the structures and develop the Park.
This became critical as the regional cultural resources Chief Stephanie Toothman
was excited about the Park, and she funded study after study so that we were
able to move ahead with the community as they found ways to fund preservation of
their properties.]

CANDIDA SMITH: The regional office is located where, in this case?

HART: In Oakland, California. I said after a while, &quot;We really need to rethink
how we&#039;re doing this. If the Park Service writes the standard Park Service plan
for this Park, it&#039;s going to be irrelevant.&quot; And that&#039;s the road we were going
down. I said, &quot;We have got to work with the community, the City of Richmond,
Contra Costa County, the owner of the hospital,&quot; which was the Northern
California Muslim Association--and this was right after 9/11. The wartime
housing was a co-op at this point, owned jointly by several hundred residents. I
said we had no traction at this point. We were not working with the community.
We needed to spend a lot more money than we&#039;d been talking about and revise the
way we were working. We needed to push this up several levels of money and
expectation. Folks became convinced that we needed to do a different kind of a
plan and that we could perhaps even cut some new territory here. And additional
funds were directed to the Rosie planning by Warren Brown back in headquarters
in Washington.

CANDIDA SMITH: What were the incentives for the various property owners in the
elements of the park?

HART: That is such a good question, because there really weren&#039;t any. That&#039;s the
problem; that was the challenge with Rosie. A relatively small group of
community movers and shakers had worked with the Park Service in the legislative
phase; they had lobbied like crazy to get the Park. It was maybe a total of
twenty or thirty people that had been involved. There&#039;s no way in the world you
could say it was a community effort. The Mayor knew about it--all the political
figures knew about it--but did the grassroots in Richmond know anything about it
or support it? No, I don&#039;t think so.

It became imperative to, frankly, inspire them that they wanted to have a Park.
It was okay, when they thought we were going to come in with a whole lot of
money and do it for them. That was okay, the few people that knew about it,
relatively few. But there was very little federal money. There was virtually
nothing coming in at the time; there was an operating budget of $114,000, much
of which paid my salary. We were not permitted by the legislation to fund the
big projects, being the Ford Assembly Building, Shipyard Number Three, and the
Red Oak Victory. What was their incentive? That was exactly my problem about a
year into it. It was like, oh, now what? When I realized that this notion of
dot-com money and incredibly wealthy people who retired at thirty and were
looking for something interesting to do, that wasn&#039;t going to happen in
Richmond. It became a challenge to work with the leaders of the community, and
also to get deeper into the community itself, to try and ignite some excitement
about the Park, so that they would want to do it. Richmond is a community that&#039;s
struggled with a lot of challenges, in terms of income, the success of their
education, in terms of the homicide rate, in terms of the deterioration of some
of the structures. The longer I worked there, the more convinced I became that a
lot of that was traceable directly back to World War II. They had created this
whole community in two years. Richmond had grown from a community of 20,000
people--very small, white, rural farming village--to a city of 100,000 people,
in two years. Many of the people who had created that explosion were African
Americans that had come up from the South who had been recruited by Henry
Kaiser. They had, by their account, not been treated well. In the words of one
woman we worked with, prejudice against African Americans was created during
World War II, along with this influx of Southerners.

[audio interruption]

CANDIDA SMITH: It sounds like within the City of Richmond, you were dealing with
their long history of racial difficulties, then. So the black majority in the
city. At least the city government, the majority was African American. You had a
set of more affluent white developers and white residents, particularly where
the Park is. Then you had Asians and Latinos moving in. How does that
demographic mix play out in the General Plan?

HART: Well, it made it very challenging doing the Plan because, as I was saying
before, the longer I worked in Richmond, the more I connected their current
issues with their history and their World War II, their Rosie history, because
about 125,000 people were employed in Henry Kaiser&#039;s shipyards and the shipyards
had been built for World War II. At the end of World War II, we declared victory
and shut down the shipyards. Almost overnight, over 100,000 people were
unemployed. Some thought that everybody who had been recruited to move to
Richmond would somehow move back to Georgia or Alabama or Texas or Oklahoma. But
they didn&#039;t; they stayed. I think there&#039;s a fairly direct line of disadvantaged
people, unemployed people in Richmond, going back to that occurrence, because of
course, there was no way that a community of 100,000 people could create 100,000
jobs overnight. So they stayed unemployed for some time. It became a personal
mission to me, to do my best to inspire some enthusiasm and community pride in
what they had done during the war years. It seemed to me in the beginning of my
time there that the spirit of Richmond had become the spirit of 100,000 people
put out of work overnight with very few sources of income, because their biggest
one was simply gone.

I wanted, to the extent that I could, to move through that and take a look at
what they had accomplished during the war, and inspire pride in that. I know
that that was successful, in part. That was what became the inspiration to make
the Park happen, was to celebrate the glory of what that community had been able
to do. Even though when I arrived in Richmond, the majority of the population
was African American, and they had personally experienced deep and profound
levels of prejudice against them when they came to Richmond. That wasn&#039;t an easy
thing to move through. But Richmond is also a community in transition, and while
I was there, the African Americans became less the majority, and it was a
combination of Hispanic and Asian--most of whom were young, and virtually all of
whom had recently arrived in the country. I had a pivotal conversation one day
with a woman who was a supervisor in the child care center. I was trying to
explain why it was important to keep things like the children&#039;s toys from the
forties, that were still up in the attic in that child care center. I quickly
ran through the usual vocabulary of preservation and history, culture, society.
I was not getting very far, and I tried just the basic, this is from the 1940s;
it&#039;s important to keep it. I realized halfway through the conversation, she
really hadn&#039;t a clue what I was talking about. She hadn&#039;t been born then. She
wasn&#039;t alive when World War II happened and she wasn&#039;t living in this country.
That remains a challenge. We talked a lot about it. We tried very hard to reach
the community with our public meetings. But in terms of what might inspire them
to get excited about the Park, beyond the fact that this is where they lived and
worked and had community connections, it was very challenging.

As the years went on, our efforts to reach the community evolved substantially.
We worked with the church leaders to figure out where to hold meetings, and have
them encourage people to come. Our last round of public meetings, I said, &quot;These
pages and pages and pages of words, they&#039;re just not going to cut it in
Richmond. We need more graphics.&quot; It&#039;s a complicated plan that showed
alternatives for all the different sites in the Park. So we need pictures and
drawings that explain what these concepts mean. We can&#039;t expect people to read
thirty pages of English after they arrive for a meeting. So it did make it a lot
more complicated. I was very pleased that I think the efforts to reach the
African American community were successful. Some of that was just plain word of
mouth, as some key individuals became committed to the Park and the leadership
of the community became more and more committed to the Park. It began to be a
critical mass of support.

CANDIDA SMITH: I think what we&#039;re doing is identifying the context, to use NPS
language. Is that correct?

HART: Yes.

CANDIDA SMITH: So that&#039;s the local community context. What about the context of
the developers, the investors who have to provide the money that the federal
government is not going to provide?

HART: Well, it was a lot of starting over, actually. The centerpiece, in the
eyes of the city, was the Ford Assembly Building. I only make that distinction
because I always felt Shipyard Number Three was at least as important as the
Ford building. But the city had already committed to having a private developer
develop that quarter-mile-long, 500,000-square-foot Ford building into a new
reuse and a new center for development in Richmond. It was interesting that the
Ford building, the historic Ford building, the land was given to Mr. Paar, that
whole area, Marina Bay, was given to him to develop on the condition that he
brought one big corporation into the area, and that&#039;s why the Ford plant ended
up there in the first place. So they were trying to repeat history with that development.

Forest City was the developer when I first started working on Rosie. They had
come up with a design for hundreds of live-work units that were really pretty
funky, I thought. You had a little window way up high in your studio, and your
normal windows and your front door opened onto a corridor inside the building.
There was going to be a picket fence around your piece of concrete in front of
your studio. The developer planned to open up the roof to provide air to these
internal sidewalks, but they discovered that because it was a national landmark,
they couldn&#039;t alter the roof. It seemed to me a pretty funky plan, and much
keyed to young dot-com people. When the dot-com bust came along, Forest City
pulled the plug on the project. The city again went through months and months
and months of arguing whether or not to demolish the building or to develop it.
Finally, those who wanted to develop it won out.

After a very, very intense period of competition, the city picked Ethan Silva
and Gerard Howland, who had fabulous ideas for an entertainment center in the
Craneway. They were going to do such wonderful things there. Their idea was to
collect all of the production sorts of folks who work in the movie industry and
the theater industry and have them work under the same roof. Kind of an upscale
professional commune, I always thought about it. I thought, &quot;Wow, if I was in
that field, I&#039;d love to be in that Ford building.&quot; You could just walk down the
hall and talk to the people who were making the foundation for the frame that
you&#039;re making, for this thing that&#039;s going to be 350 feet high. It was a
fabulous idea. But unfortunately, it just didn&#039;t come together.

That resulted in another round of discussion about demolishing the building, as
being incapable of coming to a new, productive use for Richmond. But the forces
to revive it and make it a centerpiece rose up again, spearheaded by City
Council member Tom Butt, who led the way on much of the preservation progress in
Richmond. Eventually the city hired a local person, with his headquarters in
Richmond, who had a whole long history of development in Richmond, Eddie Orton.
The Craneway was magnificent. It looks like a greenhouse with a sixty-foot-high
ceiling. A beautiful space that was literally built on stilts, piers, over the
water, looking over at San Francisco. Just a stunning, stunning space. And he
wanted to include the visitor center for the Park in the Craneway. Eddie Orton
loved the idea, was very excited about the Park Service being in the Craneway,
with a restaurant and a jazz club. Then he would fill the rest of the building
with whoever wanted to rent in there. He started working on that two years ago,
maybe three years ago, and is still trying to rent out the Ford building. The
good news is that the Park Service has put the visitor center on its
priority-funding list. So the Park Service may be part of what sparks the
renting and development in the rest of the building That was difficult and
challenging, to keep starting over with new developers for the Ford Building.

CANDIDA SMITH: What level of investment are we talking about for the developers,
just of the Ford Assembly Building?

HART: Well, it depended from developer to developer.

CANDIDA SMITH: So we&#039;re talking about a developer who&#039;s going to have to put in
tens of millions of dollars eventually?

HART: Oh, the Ford project was generally considered to be in the range of $80
million. $16 million had already been spent. That was money that FEMA, the
Federal Emergency Management Agency, had granted after the Loma Prieta
earthquake had damaged the building so badly. They had, I believe, spent $4
million of HUD money. I think about $8 million of city money did the first round
of work, which was to get the shell in waterproof condition--fix the windows,
replace broken glass, repair the roof, get the shell secure. So it was that
money on top of an additional $60 million to develop the building. And that did
not include finish work, and this is a huge building. That would just be to
create a shell, if you will, so that some individual business could come in and
finish their space to their own liking and needs. The Park Service estimate to
move into the shell of the Craneway and put in exhibits--I think the last
estimate was in the neighborhood of $5 million, for a relatively small piece of
space; we&#039;re talking about 8,000 to 10,000 square feet. It was a massive
building. Three different, very highly qualified, experienced developers have
tried to make a go of it and it&#039;s not open yet, or even very close to it.

CANDIDA SMITH: So that&#039;s the second piece of the context. You&#039;ve mentioned the
city. Were you primary dealing with the City Manager&#039;s office, the City Council,
the Redevelopment Agency, all of the above?

HART: All of the above and anybody who was willing to talk to me. In the first
year, really, it was a carryover of the group that had done the Rosie Memorial.
That was largely supported by the Redevelopment Authority. Tom Mitchell was the
head of redevelopment at that point, and Gary Hembree was the principal staff
person, as well as Richard Mitchell. Virginia Rigney, of the Arts Commission,
was heavily involved; the librarian, Joe Green; the head of Park and Rec, Jesse
Washington; Donna Graves, who was a consultant; certainly, Donna Powers, the
City Councilwoman who started it; the museum director and Red Oak Victory owner,
Lois Boyle. They were the ones--and city councilman Tom Butt--were the ones that
had promoted the memorial. The same group carried over into working with the
Park Service on the legislation, and the same group carried over into lobbying
for the legislation. That was the tight, inner group. Don Hardison, of the Red
Oak Victory, was also very much part of that. And John Gioia and Al Prince for
the child care centers owned by Contra Costa County.

When I started full-time, I&#039;d have a meeting every week with the coordinating
committee. They would all come and listen to what was not really happening yet,
really, was kind of what they told me after a while. There isn&#039;t any news going
on here because we didn&#039;t have any money. I remember saying, about three months
into it, &quot;We could create a sense of presence here by cutting a ribbon on
something. It really doesn&#039;t matter what. Pass a piece of paper; we&#039;ll make up a
ceremony. Are you all up for an event?&quot; This was the spring of 2001; they had
just come off the huge opening ceremony for the Rosie Memorial, in October of
2000, so it&#039;s about six months later. I said, &quot;I can&#039;t do it by myself. I can&#039;t
put together a ceremony that&#039;s going to be worthy of a National Park Service
event. Can you do it? Do you want to do it?&quot; They looked at me and said they
were tired, burned out. And they were fighting. They had turned against each
other, in their frustration and work and extension over the memorial, and there
were some nasty fights going on. Some weren&#039;t speaking.

CANDIDA SMITH: I guess we could think of this as a community group, but it&#039;s a
Rosie special interest group that consisted of people who lived in Richmond, but
probably also other communities?

HART: No, they were all Richmond, except for Donna Graves, who lived in
Berkeley. They were all Richmond, and all people who were deeply committed to
the community, really cared about it, really wanted to see change, that was
really what was motivating them. But it was a group that had no real structure
and really pretty much fell apart--it turned on itself--in my opinion because it
did not have a structure. Various people got upset about this or that or the
other thing, and once they got through this very successful commemoration, then
the fights really started, and the non-speaking and the insults. The first six
months I was there, everybody wanted to tell me just exactly how badly so-and-so
had behaved on something or another. I finally said, &quot;I wasn&#039;t here for that. I
can&#039;t solve that. You&#039;re going to have to untangle that.&quot;

CANDIDA SMITH: Was this group of people primarily from the West Side, from Point
Richmond and the harbor area?

HART: Mm-hm.

CANDIDA SMITH: So it represented the more affluent community?

HART: Definitely. Definitely.

CANDIDA SMITH: So did this, within local community politics, then mean that the
whole Rosie project was viewed as some Trojan horse to bring gentrification and
poor people removal? [Narrator addendum: It is important to answer that by
saying that Shipyard Number Three was already the Port of Richmond, and included
no housing or community facilities; it was closed to the public. The Ford
Assembly Building had been vacant since the Loma Prieta earthquake and been
under used since World War II but had never included housing. The smaller
structures were also under used, but no housing had ever been available in the
historic structures. Except the war worker housing of course, which continued on
as housing.]

HART: I don&#039;t think the community at large even knew it was happening, because
that was the first phase. The memorial group was fighting; some weren&#039;t speaking
to each other; others were fighting over who owned the names of the Rosies who
had come for the commemoration. The fight over who owned the names of the Rosies
went to mediation, actually, with the city attorney. I said, &quot;This is getting
nowhere. I need to change what I&#039;m doing here.&quot;

I started working more with the city structure, more with the political
structure; more with John Gioia, who was the County Supervisor; more with the
City Manager, Isiah Turner; more with the Mayor, Irma Anderson; and more with
the Redevelopment Authority, which still was Tom Mitchell and Gary Hembree.
Those individuals were becoming very excited about the project. Along with the
owners of the properties, they were the ones who participated in the first
General Management Plan meeting. We needed to build community participation and
the city government seemed a better way to begin.

CANDIDA SMITH: The Lowell model is not something of interest out here?

HART: Oh, absolutely not, not in the regional office of the Park Service here.
But the community stepped up to the challenge, and the Park is taking shape. A
group of people, headed up by City Councilman Tom Butt and Mark Howe, raised
about $100,000 to move the huge whirly crane up the Santa Fe shipping channel in
to Shipyard Number Three. It had been donated by Gary Levine to the Park.
There&#039;ll be the Red Oak Victory, back in the Shipyard where it was built during
the war, the graving basins where the ships were assembled, one of these huge
whirly cranes, and all these signs and interpretive elements. I started calling
it an &quot;instant Park.&quot; I would officially, in planning meetings, call it a
critical mass of visitor attraction; but to me, it was like instant Park. Again,
those first four years, just everybody thinking and telling me I was crazy and
there wasn&#039;t any money and, what in the world is that woman talking about? And
all of a sudden, there&#039;s going to be huge attractions going in Shipyard Number
Three. Port Director Jim Matzorkis is really proud of it. The Korean auto
importing company is really proud of it. They like talking about the fact that
they&#039;re part of a National Park. They funded some of the signs. Some of that was
the Red Oak Victory. The ease of working with the Red Oak Victory and Lois Boyle
helped to make a lot of that work successful.

CANDIDA SMITH: What about the big concrete bunker building? When is that going
to be open to the public? What would be required to make it open to the public?

HART: The good news is that the property that the Korean car importers--they
have a fence around all of their property, for security reasons, because they
have all those brand-new cars parked there. Their property includes the machine
shop, the other gorgeous building there, the Butler building, with the
corrugated metal sides, that looks like a cathedral on the inside. They actually
use that building in much the same way as they did in World War II. They fix the
cars that got dented or broken or need some work before they can ship them out.
But their property does not include the building you&#039;re talking about, which is
the General Warehouse. Nor does it include the very simple, one-story building
that is between the General Warehouse and the water, the Riggers Loft, the
famous building that has its roof on the ground. But it&#039;s wood-frame; it&#039;d be
easy to fix. Jim Matzorkis has said that that part of the Port could be
available to the public. The museum, the Richmond History Association, is
interested in either this simple building that&#039;s right on the water, or the
General Warehouse, or the Ford Assembly Building. A lot depends on the location
of the ferry. Whether it goes to the Ford building or Shipyard Number Three may
be the determining factor on a lot of development there. There&#039;s potential room
for far more parking in Shipyard Number Three. I don&#039;t actually know about water
access, but I should think that they would be able to take a ferry ride into one
of the graving basins and really play up on the history that way. I know the
developer of the Ford building wants them to dock right there at the Ford
building. So time will tell where that story goes.

CANDIDA SMITH: As part of the Park site, you have sort of miscellaneous
properties that are not on the waterfront, that are, nonetheless, important to
the story. The Kaiser Hospital is an important historic site.

HART: It&#039;s extremely important. Kaiser Permanente began there. Of all the
stories of discrimination, I never heard one about healthcare. Henry Kaiser
decreed that all of his workers would be eligible for pre-paid preventative
healthcare. For about a quarter a week, they could go in and have everything
taken care of. Not for their family, just for the worker.

I heard a very eloquent defense of the hospital structure, the saving of the
hospital, by an African-American woman, in a City Council meeting. I hadn&#039;t
worked with her; I didn&#039;t know who she was. Her family, she said, had lived in
Georgia and worked in the cotton fields. The first healthcare they ever saw,
having a doctor help them, was at this old historic building.

It was vacant for I think about five years. In &#039;98, perhaps, the Northern
California Muslim Association bought the building. After they bought the
building, they discovered it was in horrendous condition. The Park Service could
help with the repairs. I set up a meeting. They were very kind. My principal
contact was an engineer working for the state. He was who I worked with,
typically. But when we would have a meeting, there would be five or six that
would come. I quickly learned that they did not shake hands with women. And they
wouldn&#039;t look at me. As we kept talking, the relationship began to take a firmer
shape. Finally, they started saying that what they thought they would do is keep
the shell of the building, gut it, create the large worship space that they
wanted on the first floor, where the people would meet, and they would not put
the domes and the rest on top. They would allow the building to continue looking
as it had when it was a hospital. We could use a portion of the building to tell
the story of healthcare and the hospital. Certainly, we would not need to
interpret the whole hospital. When it seemed like perhaps they would be selling
it, they did allow us to appraise it, and we did offer a purchase price. By
then, it was after 9/11. They said That&#039;s not enough money to allow us to buy
anything else and they feared they would be unable to rent anyplace else. So
that fell apart. John Reynolds, God bless him, he was the one that said Try and
buy it; you just never know what you&#039;ll need the space for. There are fifty
different scenarios for what might happen with the old hospital, but I would be
very happy if just some part of it, some part of the front of the building could
be reconstructed. The original welcoming counter is gone, but it&#039;s clear from
the floor plan where it was, and we have pictures. We know what it looked like.
If that could be reconstructed and have some space for exhibits, it would be a
huge victory for the visiting public.

CANDIDA SMITH: What were your intentions for the child care centers?

HART: Whoa, what a saga! The Ruth Powers Child Care Center is still being used
for a Head Start program. There is a serious education program going on that the
county&#039;s quite proud of. The county applied for funds to build a new model Head
Start center, one of the biggest ones ever funded by Head Start, to be built in
Richmond, adjacent to the Ruth Powers Child Care Center. As part of that grant
application, the county requested and received funding to demolish the two
historic child care buildings that the legislation authorizing the Park gave us,
the Park Service, the authority to acquire. The county was not really aware of
that. That&#039;s where I sensed the notion of &quot;Who the hell do you think you are
telling us we can&#039;t tear these buildings down?&quot;

But John Gioia lived in Richmond and is very dedicated. He&#039;s County Supervisor.
His wife has been very involved in after-school child care, and he became very
enthusiastic about the importance of those two structures. John Gioia, bless
him, said that they were both historic, that we&#039;re going to keep them both and
take care of them. He said they were both going to go in the registry [National
Register of Historic Properties]. And they did. But that didn&#039;t really make it a
lot easier to actually implement that part of the plan. The buildings were very
flimsily built. One didn&#039;t have a foundation at all. We had to have a seismic
evaluation. Massive problems. They had dealt with the settlement problems by
just cutting off the doors a little more every year.

The other child care center, the Maritime Center was chockablock full of World
War II toys and furniture. There were rockers and sandboxes and kitchen sets and
tool chests and hundreds of big wooden blocks. It was almost spooky. It was like
somebody knew there was going to be a national park. There was a piece of fence
from the backyard, upstairs in the attic. We knew that because Henry Kaiser
loved to promote his fine work, and well he should have. He took photographs of
the child care center as it was finished, so we knew where the sandbox was, we
knew where the fence was. There was a picnic bench from the backyard, up in the
attic with all these toys. There was one of everything. Not two or three, but
one of everything. It&#039;s like somebody knew that someday, we would want to
restore that building and refurnish it. All you had to do was carry it
downstairs. Absolutely priceless things up there.

I followed what was called Prop 40 for four years. It was a large appropriation
of state funds for the preservation of California history. Those two child care
centers, every time they&#039;d come out with a new announcement about what they were
going to do with that money, I would think this was perfect for preserving the
child care centers for the Park. But there are matching grant requirements, and
the Park Service would not do it. I felt very strongly that if the Park Service
wasn&#039;t going to come up with much real money, at least in my lifetime, there was
no point in putting together a $5.2 million application for Park Service
funding, just for the Maritime Center. I was heartbroken. Are they ever going to
find a way to preserve that building?

[Narrator addendum: City Council member Tom Butt led the way for several years
putting together the funding for restoration of the Maritime Child Care Center.
The Park Service studies funded by Stephanie Toothman created the information
necessary to apply for Prop 40 funding, and for the collection of other funding
sources to match the Prop 40 funding. The restored Maritime Center opened in 2011.]

CANDIDA SMITH: Then there&#039;s the war-worker housing.

HART: It was hard to find anybody in the Atchison Village coop that we could
work with. Board members changed every year. We got a grant from the California
Coastal Conservancy the first year I was there. It was supposed to go towards
developing the visitor center and the Ford building. Some funds went toward
studying Atchison Village, and as we found out more about the history, it became
clear that Atchison Village had been more managers&#039; housing, that there were no
African Americans that were ever living there. It remains an important resource however.

CANDIDA SMITH: What about Parchester Village, it&#039;s post-war housing, but do you
view Parchester Village as part of the Park&#039;s larger story?

HART: It&#039;s certainly relevant, because it&#039;s so much a part of the story of what
happened after the war. Parchester Village was the one place where African
Americans could buy a house after the war. The man who was City Manager for much
of my time there, Isiah Turner, grew up in Parchester Village and talks about
the joys of being in a small community where you knew everybody, everybody loved
everybody. A lot of very highly accomplished people came out of Parchester
Village. It&#039;s a very important part of the story.

The Park Service has only in the last few months stepped up to the plate to fund
the visitor center. It has not stepped up to the plate with any substantial
money to operate the Park or to restore the Maritime Center or the hospital,
which are already deemed by Congress to be nationally significant. It would take
quite a leap of stretch for the Park Service to get to working on Parchester Village.

CANDIDA SMITH: What about the process of figuring out how to unify all these
elements? Is that what the four alternatives are about?

HART: We went through three General Management Plan team captains. The second
was from the Denver Service Center and had years of experience with Park Service
planning. But the standard Park Service process was demanding of more time and
patience than the partners were able to give.

The third team captain was the hero of Rosie Park planning. Stephan Nofield had
been a planner, very successful, working for the Town of Provincetown. He was
always teaching me. He understood collaboration, and he had the kind of
personality and the intellect to figure out how to work with large, diverse
groups of people. Support from the City of Richmond all came together in the
last round of public meetings, which culminated in a magical meeting when all
the property owners came together for the first time in four years. They all
laid out the commitments that they&#039;d made in the process of our preliminary
planning meetings, laid out the plans for their particular properties. Everybody
got to listen to everybody else and everybody got excited, and they agreed to
move ahead with making it happen. Stephan was crucial to this success; it
wouldn&#039;t have happened without his expertise and style.

I want to also give credit to Jay Corey, who was the Assistant City Manager for
a couple of years, and was really interested in making the Park work for the
City of Richmond, and he loved working on it. That was fun. It was part of his
job he enjoyed, and he was totally supportive. He moved it ahead enormously.

Another person in a very key position, who was also critical to it all coming
together, was Will Travis, Executive Director of BCDC [Bay Conservation and
Development Commission]. I had met him about halfway through our planning
process. There was a fascinating structure in Richmond that would put a train
car on a ferry to take it over to San Francisco. ABAG [Association of Bay Area
Governments] had restored that as part of the Bay Trail. I met Will at the event
unveiling that project. He later came over and looked at the Park plans and
listened to the ideas as we toured the Park facilities. I was very nervous about
that at first, because, of course, he&#039;s in charge of use and development permits
for shipping facilities for the entire Bay Area. As far as I knew, the position
of BCDC had always been to dedicate every inch of land that could be used for
shipping, to shipping, because it might be critical someday. Richmond had been
considered, in my perspective, a landmark for future shipping. No one thought it
was big enough for container shipping. But in that
you-never-know-what&#039;s-going-to-happen mode, let&#039;s make sure Richmond stays there
for future shipping use. Will Travis could have seen it as a conflict--public
use, public access, preservation of historic structures--but he fell in love
with the Park, and became one of our most enthusiastic advocates.

The fact that everybody knew that Will Travis loved the Park and was totally
supportive, was dead set against filling in the historic basins, dead set
against changing any of the historic resources-- particularly, frankly, in the
absence of that kind of power from the Park Service, Will Travis&#039; looming
presence in the San Francisco Bay, supporting and promoting Rosie at every turn,
was hugely important, in terms of it all coming together. If for no other reason
than the Port Director could have said, well, BCDC will never approve it.
Whether it was true or not, they could have been saying that for years. But they
couldn&#039;t and didn&#039;t, because Will Travis, in fact, did support it.

A private planning consultant, Larry Kennings, was also key in stopping things
that would have prevented Park development. He represented a firm wanting to
process and store asphalt in enormous tanks in Shipyard Number Three, which
would directly impact some of the historic properties. By quietly revealing the
true impacts, and dangers, of the proposal, the firm and the proposed huge tanks
of hot asphalt melted away.

CANDIDA SMITH: How does this then play out in the four alternatives that were
developed for how the Park might be structured?

HART: The full-scale one is the easiest one to describe. All of the historic
structures included in the authorizing legislation would be fully restored:
exterior and interior preservation, and actively interpreted by the Park
Service. The new ferry service from San Francisco would dock either at the Ford
Assembly Building on in Shipyard Number Three. The historic shipyard would be
the site for many community uses and events as well as visitors to the Park.

The second and third alternatives are variances and simplifications of the first
alternative: there would only be exterior preservation and interpretation of
some sites; or there would be exterior preservation and interior preservation of
only some of the sites.

The fourth alternative involved the community more actively. More like a
heritage area. It included the active interpretation of historic Macdonald
Avenue, and additional World War II sites around Richmond. It was very dependent
on the active support, and work, and involvement, of the community at large. We
knew that it was very important to have a community-based group to work to
support the Park. There was no such group. Never was, in the whole four years I
worked there. The fourth alternative might help create that group, or fail from
the lack of it.

CANDIDA SMITH: Other than the Rosie Trust.

HART: Yes, but they were not a widely-based community group. They were community
leaders, by any stretch of the imagination. They didn&#039;t have a membership behind
them. That made it very difficult for me. We&#039;ve already talked about the
difficulty of reaching the community at large. I never could find a way to fill
that hole with a group.

Isaiah Turner, the City Manager for most of my tenure there, was totally
enthusiastic about the Park. Really believed in it, wanted to make it happen,
was supportive. Everybody knew Isaiah supported it and his support was extremely
important. In the early phases, I worked with the Redevelopment Authority, which
was Tom Mitchell in charge and Gary Hembree. Totally excited about what we were
doing. But Tom got caught in a meat grinder over the Ford building and retired,
which was a huge loss to me because the replacement, Steve Duran, never seemed
to me to be as excited about the park. His focus was Macdonald Avenue. And I
didn&#039;t get to work with Gary Hembree anymore.

It became clear to me that the Planning Department focused on permits. You want
to build an addition on your house, you&#039;d have to get a permit from them, and
that was their focus. The Redevelopment Authority focused on redevelopment
projects, parcel by parcel. There wasn&#039;t anybody who was looking at the future
of the city as a whole, and how the Park Service might fit in. That was Isaiah
Turner, with limited time. That was why I was so grateful when Isaiah hired Jay
Corey, who was over the Port and redevelopment and planning. No one, to my
knowledge, ever previously tried to make those three departments work together.
Jay was committed to having them work together and develop a strong economic
base for the future of Richmond, and he felt that the Park was one of the
obvious ways of doing that. So Jay was really pivotal.

There were five City Managers, four of them Interim City Managers, during my
tenure that last year. It was very hard to get anybody&#039;s attention about
anything, frankly.

CANDIDA SMITH: One of the things, in our working together, that I&#039;ve found
interesting, and it seemed to me that it was a difficult push-pull factor for
you, was that this is a National Park about a national story, and yet you had to
be so closely attuned to the local story. Were you finding yourself torn between
the practical needs of connecting with the local community and your charge to
create a National Park about a national story?

HART: Oh, it was like being on the rack. I didn&#039;t retire because I was feeling
better or healthier. At the end of four years I retired because I was personally
a wreck from trying to hold it all together. Not that I did it all by myself,
but in phases and at times, and in those places where there really was no other
support, I was holding the dream together. I loved what Rosemary Corbin said,
the former Mayor who was also on the Rosie Trust Board, in commiserating with
some people about my leaving. She said, and I quote, &quot;Judy got us to believe in
the Park.&quot; That was my job. That&#039;s where it had to start. I went through phases
of being very frustrated with the legislation, because nothing was quite locked
into the future of the Park, via the legislation. But I kept coming back to
thinking that this was a good piece of legislation, given these realities that
survived the dot-com crash. And it&#039;s still a good piece of legislation.

We haven&#039;t talked yet about the other humongous part of the job, which was the
Ford project. Which really answers a lot of your question. Ford Motor Company
has had a contractual relationship with the National Park Foundation, which is a
national nonprofit that works with the National Park Service. I started working
on a proposal for Ford when I was still in Washington, working in planning. The
two women who were the principal liaisons in the project I had worked with in
other areas as well. We were good friends. So every year when they&#039;d go through
another funding cycle, I&#039;d come up with a proposal. Ford had had hard times, and
they were not really funding these efforts.

But two years ago, Ford decided to fund a call for Rosie stories. The original
plan was to use a quarter of their year&#039;s advertising budget to call for Rosie
stories--which, of course, had Ford&#039;s name on it, prominently. But it was a
beautiful idea. It helped Ford. As someone said to me, it was the first time in
years we hadn&#039;t been talking about Bridgestone tires and rollovers. We were
talking about Rosie stories, and everybody loves Rosies. They were promoting the
fact that Rose Monroe worked in the Ford plant in Ypsilanti and was the star in
the movie, Rosie the Riveter. So Ford said they created the first Rosie. It was
successful beyond anybody&#039;s wildest imagination. In part, Ford did a very cute,
fetching, catchy public service announcement that ran nonstop over Christmas. I
saw it on the Chinese television station. I didn&#039;t find anybody who hadn&#039;t seen
it on TV. I&#039;m told that advertisers don&#039;t like to advertise over the holidays,
so PSAs get big coverage. Also, there was a lot of word of mouth with families
getting together over the holidays. Well, we ended up with 11,000 Rosies
contacting the Park. Some of them entered entries in the Ford website; some used
our website. Most of them called the Park, because they wanted to talk to
somebody. We now have over 4,000 of their hand-written stories about their
experiences, and over 2,000 artifacts, which just bring me to tears every time I
look at them.

I was so moved that these women had kept these things so precious to them for
sixty years and then were giving them up to the Park Service. Of course, it
meant we would keep them in perpetuity and display them, but I was so touched
every time I would see something. We had three different tests from women who
had passed a welder&#039;s test. One was two pieces of metal, and there was an oblong
cutout in the middle of both of them, and they had to rivet them together so
that the cutouts still matched. No Rosie got hired just because it seemed like a
good thing to do, to hire a woman.

The Park received over 2,000 artifacts from Rosies because of that Ford
campaign. So what that did was give us, particularly the 4,000 stories, it gave
us that story of what was happening around the country. Of the 11,000 women,
about 500 were from the Northern California area. So that&#039;s a lot of stories
from all around the country. They all talked with such pride and excitement,
sixty years later, about what they&#039;d done. Most of all, their overwhelming
emotion that they were finally getting to talk about it, and that somebody cared
and somebody was listening, and they were being recognized. We mailed out 12,000
newsletters on the General Management Plan, and mailed one to every one of the
Rosies to make sure they knew that Congress had passed a Resolution honoring
their work and that, finally, after all these years, they were taking their
rightful place in American history.

So with great gratitude to Ford, although that project was overwhelming, we got
just enough money to hire two people part-time, and that was the help we got. We
had up to ten volunteers in there for months, answering all these phone calls
and opening the packages and processing them. We had two phone-a-thons, one with
community volunteers and one with National Park Service staff at Golden Gate
National Park, thanks to Superintendent Brian O&#039;Neill, answering over 2,500
phone messages that had been left on our office phones. But what came in was
priceless and irreplaceable. Most of these women are eighty-five and older, and
sometimes we would return a phone call, and the person on the line would say,
&quot;Well, we&#039;re really sorry, but that person&#039;s passed on.&quot; So the Ford project was
a really priceless addition to the Park.

In addition to that, the Park Service had funded, for a quarter-of-a-million
dollars, what&#039;s called a National Landmark Theme Study, which specifically
looked at all the other Home Front sites around the country. The first question
was, what&#039;s still standing? Because buildings that were built for World War II
were meant to be temporary. The study did confirm that in most communities, most
of the structures were gone, but it created an enormous base of information so
that if somebody came to Richmond and asked what else they could go see, we
could say, &quot;Well, there&#039;s the Charlestown Navy Yard, which has been in existence
since the beginning of this country. They did make ships during World War II,
and you can go there. You can go to this plant in Detroit.&quot; We now know what we
can tell people about the rest of the country.

[End of Session]

  

  

  

  

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>