<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00041941" dt="2018-11-01"><version>5.2</version><date value="2012-06-21" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Ortho Drew and Warren Gaines | Interview 1 | June 21, 2012</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><keyword>Kaiser Shipyards, Bay Area, Race relations, Civil Rights,  Japanese, Pearl Harbor, Port Chicago</keyword><interviewee>Othro Drew</interviewee><interviewer>Sam Redman</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|16(11)|28(12)|37(10)|52(15)|66(2)|80(5)|97(11)|110(8)|118(10)|133(17)|147(2)|161(1)|171(5)|187(3)|201(13)|211(1)|221(8)|232(3)|241(3)|252(4)|264(1)|274(6)|293(9)|305(9)|318(14)|329(12)|343(4)|356(1)|377(9)|386(3)|399(3)|421(11)|430(13)|442(3)|453(10)|473(1)|492(10)|512(2)|528(9)|545(14)|557(15)|565(13)|585(7)|599(2)|628(4)|646(13)|662(6)|679(9)|693(7)|705(9)|723(7)|734(2)|746(8)|759(11)|768(11)|784(14)|794(11)|811(12)|828(5)|838(3)|857(1)|868(7)|887(1)|902(7)|914(17)|930(9)|943(9)|958(5)|977(10)|993(2)|1004(8)|1015(15)|1027(1)|1041(9)|1058(5)|1068(13)|1082(8)|1093(3)|1109(7)|1126(6)|1137(1)|1148(8)|1162(13)|1175(6)|1185(8)|1198(1)|1208(3)|1220(10)|1233(3)|1250(9)|1268(10)|1283(6)|1294(1)|1309(3)|1332(3)|1345(2)|1360(15)|1378(2)|1397(3)|1409(1)|1421(5)|1445(6)|1460(2)|1477(3)|1491(8)|1524(10)|1540(2)|1551(11)|1568(4)|1581(4)|1591(3)|1604(13)|1615(10)|1629(9)|1641(1)|1654(6)|1665(4)|1674(3)|1685(9)|1700(7)|1716(8)|1736(14)|1751(4)|1767(15)|1780(8)|1793(4)|1808(8)|1820(12)|1829(6)|1842(7)|1862(15)|1874(7)|1886(8)|1897(7)|1916(12)|1925(6)|1940(12)|1959(10)|1976(11)|1993(11)|2004(3)|2025(2)|2038(10)|2051(1)|2084(12)|2094(10)|2110(12)|2123(10)|2134(13)|2155(7)|2179(1)|2193(6)|2209(6)|2237(7)|2251(15)|2265(1)|2277(12)|2295(15)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>vqLN8OojtrM</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Born in Coffeyville, Kansa, Othro Drew lived with his grandmother in Oklahoma until he was twelve years old, at which time he migrated to California to live with his mother who worked in the Kaiser Shipyards but ended up living with his uncles in Berkeley and Stockton. In this interview, Drew discusses his experiences of encountering racism, Japanese Americans, racism, and segretation. He also recalls the differences in curriculum in California and Oklahoma, Pearl Harbor, Nagasaki and Hiroshima, and Port Chicago. He goes on to comment on desegregation, Civil Rights, his involvement in the Congress on Racial Equity, police brutality against non-whites in the Bay Area, the Black Panthers, and the overall struggle to improve social conditions for blacks in America following World War Two.</description><rel /><transcript>REDMAN: My name is Sam Redman and today is July 17. I&#039;m back in Stockton,
California. Mr. Drew, would you mind stating your full name and when and where
you were born?

DREW: My name is Othro Drew. I was born in Coffeyville, Kansas on July 24, 1930.

REDMAN: And Mr. Gaines?

GAINES: Warren G. Gaines, born in Langston, Oklahoma, or Goodnight, Oklahoma,
whichever one you want to use. I was born on the farm. October 18, 1920.

REDMAN: All right, so gentlemen, one thing that came up last time during our
respective interviews that I wanted to talk about a little bit more, to see
whether or not some of these things resonated or if they didn&#039;t. I understand
that much of what was happening that was important for the African American
community in terms of art and in terms of music and things like that were
happening in Harlem, New York. The Harlem Renaissance. I wanted to ask about
Bessie Smith, Louie Armstrong and Duke Ellington, and see if those musicians
were things that you guys would have listened to growing up on the farm at all.
Would that music have been available?

DREW: Early on, those names are -- they&#039;re saints as far as the black community
is concerned. But early on -- I don&#039;t know about brother Gaines, but my great
grandfather and grandmother were slaves. My grandparents were the first free
generation. During those days, music, especially if you&#039;re in the South, the
only music that you had access to was white religious music, Western music, as
far as radio and this type of thing, because blacks weren&#039;t heard on the radio.
Or maybe at the street corner, there would be a group playing music, or the
church, or a club. That was the essence of the music. With me, for instance, I
was in the Army in 1947 and I heard about jazz. You were saying Louie Armstrong,
Bessie Smith, Duke Ellington, those people. I was saying, what&#039;s jazz? What&#039;s
jazz? Fortunately, there was a young man out there that I was in who lived in
New York. He understood jazz. There was the first jazz program that came on in
1947. It&#039;s called Jumping with Symphony Sid. For one hour, one day a week, they
played jazz music. Then I found out that there were innumerable jazz clubs in
New York. I&#039;d get a leave, I&#039;d go to these jazz clubs, and then I fell madly in
love with jazz. Then I started doing a little studying of jazz. Jazz was a total
different type of music. Probably the closest thing to jazz was blues and maybe
Western music. But jazz was created out of misery, just plain misery. You listen
to the old jazz songs compared to today&#039;s jazz, you can see the hurt and all the
angst that happened when they were alive. The pain that they suffered from being
denied the right. You go to college and you could study. You would get a Ph.D.,
and you couldn&#039;t get a job. You had a Ph.D., walking around Phi Beta Kappa with
a key hanging on your keychain, and you were lucky if you were a porter for a train.

REDMAN: Mr. Gaines, tell me a little bit about music. What do you think?

GAINES: What about music?

REDMAN: Yeah.

GAINES: There was something you said there before we got on the air. You said
you&#039;d go back to the past. I quote a lot of people that says, to know the
future, study the past. Without the past, there is no future. Let&#039;s go back to
the past. I mean the real past. Before jazz, before this music you&#039;re talking
about. This is one thing -- you&#039;re telling a story of humiliations you&#039;ve had
when you listen to what they call Negro spirituals. Now, let&#039;s take one song,
&quot;Carry Me Back to Old Virginia.&quot; Let&#039;s take that one. It was written by a black
guy, but who got the credit for it? A white guy. He took it and did -- same
thing with the cotton gin. Take the cotton gin. It was invented by Jim Ellis.
But they never tell you this.

REDMAN: Eli Whitney --

GAINES: Oh, shit. Oh, excuse me, excuse me. I hate to be vulgar. These are the
biggest lies. Why don&#039;t they tell the truth about who actually built this
America? You won&#039;t believe the rice production was produced out of South
Carolina. The biggest rice production in the world right out of South Carolina.
Who did the work? You listen to these newcomers come in, &quot;Who built America?&quot;
&quot;The immigrants built&quot; -- immigrants didn&#039;t build it. The thirteen original
colonies was built by black people.

DREW: Slavery.

GAINES: Slavery. And look, they were built by slavery, because here&#039;s what
happened. These people that come over here were too ignorant to do anything. But
the ones that they brought, the slave masters, the poor whites that they brought
over here, they had to do the same thing, make them the boss over the slaves.
But look, George Washington, for instance. I give anybody a thousand dollars
right now can find me one white man named Washington, George Washington, and
prove that he&#039;s not mixed, he&#039;s white. There were two people come over, George
Washington and his brother Henry. Henry went back to England. Martha was barren.
He had almost a thousand slaves. If you went on his plantation, it would be more
mulattos there. You understand?

REDMAN: Right. So --

GAINES: When you start talking about let&#039;s go back to the past, now you&#039;re
talking about radio. I was born in 1920. Radios wasn&#039;t even in our community
clear up until 1930, because you had electricity. Where I lived in the country,
they had a few battery radios. We had to go to the next neighbor&#039;s house, way
down, to listen to the radio. In so far as phonographs, Bessie Smith and all
this, yeah, they had all this.

DREW: Years later.

GAINES: But look, here&#039;s the problem about music. Music is fine, but we should
stop putting all our hopes in music. Let&#039;s see about getting some education. Now
this is where the real problem comes in, in education. I called Othro the other
night and told them to read the story about a guy named Jordan. This guy,
Jordan, was born a slave. He ran off --

DREW: In Virginia.

GAINES: He ran off and went into Ohio. Understand? He got a job over there and
was making money. Made $11,000 while he was working there. The slave master --
this was during slavery time -- he&#039;d run off, and Ohio was a free state -- told
him to come back and work on the plantation. Now, he&#039;s a slave already, but he&#039;s
in a free country, and he wrote him back and told him -- he was a man that
didn&#039;t know how to read or write, so he learned how to read and write, and he
wrote the slave master a letter. Excuse me a minute. Back. Here&#039;s what he said.
Here&#039;s what he said about coming back to be a slave and work for him. He said
this, and I quote, &quot;According to available records, Jordan Anderson was born in
Tennessee in about 1825, and by the age of seven or eight, he had been sold to a
plantation owned by General Paulding Anderson. In Big Spring, Tennessee, Patrick
Henry Anderson was one of the general&#039;s son in the eighteen and forties.&quot; So
when he said, &quot;Come back,&quot; he said, &quot;Would you want me to come back and take my
girls, my two daughters, to be humiliated by your sons to produce some more
children for you?&quot; This is showing you one thing, how smart this African
descendant person was. But you see, here&#039;s what happens to most whites. They do
not understand. You should read Frantz Fanon&#039;s We Wear the Mask. Have you read
it? You read it?

REDMAN: Yes.

GAINES: Well, you understand, we wear a mask. Most of us wear a mask. When you
look at me, you don&#039;t know what I have in my head. You understand? Here&#039;s what
happens. When you don&#039;t educate these people -- I see children every day in my
business. Some little kids like this are geniuses. They don&#039;t send them to the
better schools. You understand? What they do to them -- he&#039;s hyper. Let&#039;s give
him some -- what do you call it? Ritalin.

REDMAN: There are a lot of topics in there that I want to get back to. The
Frantz Fanon ideas, I feel like I also want to talk about writers like Ralph
Ellison and Richard Wright after the war. But before we get that far ahead in
time, I want to ask about something that happened when you were very young. You
were probably not aware of this, but in 1927, there was a great Mississippi
flood that affected a lot of people in the Deep South who were living in --

DREW: In the Delta.

REDMAN: In the Delta. A lot of people criticized this at the time. They
criticized Calvin Coolidge and the government as being incapable, and a lot of
people compared this to -- we think about that as being, oh, that was in the
1920s, but then of course what happened with Hurricane Katrina in New Orleans,
we&#039;re reminded that these sorts of things are alive today. Is that something
that people talked about at all? It seems like that&#039;s a forgotten moment in
history, these disasters that happened in the South.

DREW: Black people have been written out of history completely. We&#039;re taught by
the same history book, public schools, that you have access to. But I sit there
and I read this book, and I don&#039;t exist. When I was going to school in
California, there were three black people existed. That was all. You had Carver,
Booker T. Washington, and there was one other, and that was it. You had about
two lines for each one.

REDMAN: W.E.B. Du Bois, maybe?

DREW: No, no, no, no. Oh, no. He was too radical. Much too radical. What he was
talking about, wearing the mask, they didn&#039;t understand that Booker T.
Washington, George Washington Carver, they say, they&#039;re good niggers. They don&#039;t
cause no problems or anything. Very radical men. Blacks are always -- they&#039;ll
say, &quot;They don&#039;t know what they&#039;re talking about.&quot; There&#039;s always been this
double talk. I&#039;ll give you a for instance. The word &quot;peckerwood.&quot; White people
use it now. Initially, it was one of those words that blacks used among
themselves to describe white people. &quot;He&#039;s a peckerwood.&quot; Then white people
would say, &quot;Certain niggers so damn dumb, they don&#039;t even know what a woodpecker
is.&quot; They were saying &quot;peckerwood&quot; instead of &quot;woodpecker,&quot; and the blacks sit there.

GAINES: You mentioned this flood in 1927. That was when they had the flood down
there. They don&#039;t mention the Tulsa riot in 1921.

REDMAN: I know the Tulsa riots, we talked a little bit about last time, and how
your two uncles were --

GAINES: Passed away. But now, listen. Do you know anything about the
Rentiesville situation that happened in Rentiesville, Oklahoma?

REDMAN: No.

GAINES: You see, here&#039;s where I am a little bit different than most African
Americans, because I wasn&#039;t produced and raised up in a segregated community. I
was in a black town, all-black. Drugstores, everything in there, was black. I
didn&#039;t come in contact with whites. Black schools and everything. I was taught
who I am. The first thing, you&#039;ve got to find who you are. I know who I am. Most
people don&#039;t know who they are. I know who I am. So when you would find out who
you are, then that makes you a better person. I want to go back to slavery.
Sure, we&#039;ll go back to slavery. I know who my mother was. My mother was an
Ashanti. I did research and found out why. I met a gentleman in my shop the
other day. We were talking and I said, &quot;Where are you from in Africa?&quot; He said,
&quot;I&#039;m from West Africa.&quot; I said, &quot;What tribe you come from?&quot; He said, &quot;I&#039;m an
Ashanti.&quot; I said, &quot;What?&quot; I said, &quot;You may be my cousin.&quot; I said, &quot;Do you know
anything about the marks on Ashanti tribes?&quot; He said a lot of tribes had
different marks, just like we have the Indians in this country. Here&#039;s the
difference. People teach slavery and they teach history, but they only teach one
side of it.

DREW: That&#039;s all they know.

GAINES: So look. I was taught, on the right cheek of my aunty, one of them, it
was turned up like this. A half-moon. And the male&#039;s, on the other side, was
turned down. I know that. Now, look. He said, &quot;How do you know this?&quot; I tell
everybody one thing. I&#039;ve been in every country of the world. Why? Knowledge
don&#039;t fall out of the sky and hit your head. Knowledge is found in books. When
you read, you understand this. When the riot come in Tulsa, that was in 1921.
But before that, in eighteen and sixty-three, in Rentiesville, they had a riot
there. It wasn&#039;t a riot. The Texas Rangers come down from Texas, about 600 of
them, to Rentiesville. They heard there were some blacks. The blacks had moved
in from Tennessee, Mississippi, and every place, come in to Oklahoma because it
was a free country. When they came down to Rentiesville to try to take these
blacks back to Texas, the Texas Rangers come down there. Now, it&#039;s in the book.
If you study, you will found out, at Rentiesville, the blacks, in the First
Calvary out of Kansas -- not on the Confederate side, on the Union side -- they
met down there and they whipped these guys back, these Rangers back, and they
had 400 handcuffs in there to take the blacks back to slavery. You understand?
Now, this is not in your history books. If you go to your history, you&#039;ll find
this stuff out. Once you find out, it gives you a lot of dignity.

DREW: One of the main things that escaped, when it came to the Tulsa riots,
so-called Tulsa riots, there was a Greenwood District. The Greenwood District,
in those days, they were black communities. They were inclusive. You could live
in the black community. Everything that you needed was there, whether it was a
lawyer, doctor, dentist, department store, grocery store, whatever. The
Greenwood District was one of the richest districts in Oklahoma, white or black.
The average income there was unbelievable, because all these businesses were
located there, plus there was a university, Langston University. Blacks couldn&#039;t
go to white universities, but they&#039;d crowd -- the black universities were full
of them. They produced unbelievable people, teachers, black teachers. Almost all
my teachers came, when I was in grade school, came from Langston. Like I&#039;ve told
you before, when I came out here, I came out here thinking I was this poor, dumb
black who was incapable of absorbing the knowledge of white people. I came out
here, found out that I went to this little school and these teachers were so
successful that I was two years ahead of the children I was going to school
with. What he was talking about, about inventions, one of the things that has
escaped everybody, even blacks, primarily, have you heard the term that
necessity is the mother of invention? This was absolutely true. Most inventions
during that period of time was created by blacks, because it was a matter of, &quot;I
have to ride this wagon all day long. Carry loads and loads of cotton. This
thing is wearing my bottom out.&quot; So we developed the springs for the wagon, to
ease my butt. All of these inventions, but who gets credit for the inventions?
The master, because the black slave was what? Was property. Whatever he
produced, he didn&#039;t produce it. I produced it, because I&#039;m his master. And on
through history, like railroads. You start reading up on inventions, railroad
inventions. A hundred and twenty-something railroad inventions, black, out of necessity.

GAINES: When you mentioned railroad, the man that invented the wigwag that goes
up and down, his name is Richard Spikes I worked for him doing my apprenticeship
as a barber. I worked for him starting in 1945. He still had a shop in Stockton.
His hair was about that long. He&#039;d go back there and play his violin. He has a
bunch of inventions. Now, you take the Big Ben. The Big Ben clock that is in
England, you know who put that there, don&#039;t you? Benjamin Banneker. Benjamin
Banneker. Big Ben. He&#039;s the one that designed that clock. He also set up the
laying out of Washington, D.C. You&#039;ve read about Benjamin Banneker. If you don&#039;t
have the money today to produce these things, you&#039;re in the same shape. Just
like right now. I have a book that I got 800 pages of real book. I&#039;m going to
publish it soon, because it&#039;s telling the straight facts.

I have a grandson. Excuse me for skipping around. I have a grandson who&#039;s a
four-point student. Real smart. When he talks to me and I talk to him, just like
my dad talked to me -- I want you to read something, and I&#039;ll let you read it in
a few minutes -- I asked him one day, I said, &quot;Hey&quot; -- he&#039;s fourteen years old
-- I said, &quot;What about the Pyramids? Who build the Pyramids?&quot; He says, &quot;Pop,
slaves built the Pyramids.&quot; I say, &quot;Oh yeah?&quot; I say, &quot;If the slaves built the
Pyramids, how did they get these stones up there?&quot; He said, &quot;Slaves put them up
there.&quot; I said, &quot;Okay, but the stones that&#039;s in the Pyramids, the stones in some
of the Pyramids, are not from that area. They&#039;re from 300 miles up the Nile.
Tell me, how did they get them down there?&quot; He shook his head. He said, &quot;Pop, I
don&#039;t know.&quot; I said, &quot;Then tell me about the Stonehenge.&quot; He said, &quot;I really
don&#039;t know.&quot; I said, &quot;That&#039;s in your time.&quot; He said, &quot;Well, the book says that
they don&#039;t know how they put&quot; -- then I say, &quot;Just tell me about the Terracotta
soldiers in China.&quot; He says to me, he&#039;s been real red, he says, &quot;Well, I don&#039;t
know.&quot; I said, &quot;You see? Here&#039;s a fallacy in your Bible. The Bible tells you
that we&#039;re 7,000 years old. Explain to me about the Terracotta soldiers. Or
explain to me about the Stonehenge.&quot; You see, here&#039;s what happens. History has
been distorted.

DREW: Of course.

GAINES: When Hannibal crossed the Alps and went into Italy, come out of the
boot, he had seventy-five elephants and 25,000 soldiers. He saw all these people
living in caves with long blonde hair. They thought they were rats or something.
I&#039;m not kidding.

DREW: It&#039;s true.

GAINES: The truth. Because that&#039;s how they lived, because it was cold. Then when
the soldiers captured Rome, they were there for twenty-five years. The soldiers
were black. There&#039;s a lot of Italians that have kinky hair and everything.

DREW: Sicilians especially.

REDMAN: This is a big question now. How does the Great Depression affect the
black community? It seems like some of the advances that were made in the 1920s
in terms of the black community, that the possibility of even making a Tulsa
where there is a black Wall Street, some of that sort of gets rolled back by the
Great Depression in some sense, because blacks are the first people to lose jobs
and lose economic possibility. But that&#039;s sort of my assumption. Can you tell me
about how blacks were affected by the Great Depression?

DREW: I think blacks were affected differently than white folks. Number one, you
had black communities. A black community is totally different from a white
community in those days. A black community, everybody within a black community
knew everyone. It was like a family. If a person on the street got a
hundred-pound bag of potatoes, everybody around there had potatoes. Even the one
black policeman that was in that community, he was -- when you said your
policeman is your friend, he was your friend. He would see your two kids
standing on the street corner, and he would -- &quot;Boys, what are you doing
standing here? Does your daddy know you stand out here on this corner?&quot; &quot;No,
sir.&quot; &quot;You get home and tell your daddy I sent you home. I&#039;m going to stop by
and let him know that you&#039;ve been hanging out on these street corners.&quot; That was
the relationship within the black community. You read about all the poverty in
the white community. Well, we already had poverty in the black community. There
wasn&#039;t too much more you could do to us. In fact, there were some gains made in
some areas as far as blacks who had never been able to work at all. They got
shovel jobs, digging holes and this type of thing.

One of the big myths between blacks and whites -- like he was talking about,
wearing the mask. Blacks have always been able to do more with less. I guess we
always will. Even if we talk about education, school. When that black person
went to school, it wasn&#039;t to get an education for himself. He was obligated to
the entire community. Even today, in the South, there are kids that live in poor
neighborhoods, very intelligent black kids, no way he&#039;s going to go to college
with the fees and this type of thing. The people get together in that community.
The churches and the lodges and all these people get together. They get together
and raise money to keep this one boy in school -- or girl -- and when they&#039;re
graduated, they&#039;re obligated to come back to that community and share the
knowledge and try to improve that community. But then you&#039;ve got this large,
large volume, too large a volume, of just so-called black elite. They&#039;ve done
the same thing that a white person would do. If a white person lived in this
community, he got a million dollars, hey, I would expect him two weeks from now,
expect they&#039;d end up some other people. Black people do the same thing now. It&#039;s
constant --

GAINES: So-called bourgeois.

DREW: This constant knocking of, &quot;Those blacks don&#039;t want to get ahead. They
don&#039;t want to do anything.&quot; Who do we hear it from? From Bill Cosby, of all
people.GAINES: People forget one thing, and I tell them this every day. Look at
that. Here you have a president of the United States of America. Got a college
degree, cum laude and all this other jazz that goes with it, his wife, Michelle,
but he&#039;s still considered, as I, an uppity nigger. I&#039;m telling it like it is.
When you come back to the Depression, I&#039;m with the original Grapes of Wrath.
These are facts. When the Depression hit, we were very good livers. We had 160
acres of land and everything in Oklahoma, and around us was nothing but blacks
and a few German people, and whites that own land. You understand? When
Depression hit in 1928, I was eight years old. First time I&#039;ve seen my daddy
cry, when we started losing everything we had. But my daddy didn&#039;t lose his farm
because it was paid for and everything. The Depression lasted from 1928, clear
up until 1941.

REDMAN: That&#039;s a long time.

GAINES: Hitler eliminated the Depression when he marched into Germany. Now,
there&#039;s another thing that I&#039;ll mention here. I mentioned it before. We were
supposedly being freed, African Americans, slaves, in 1865. Eighteen and
sixty-five, we were just like the Mexicans here now. We were immigrants.

DREW: We were worse.

GAINES: We were immigrants and we were slaves. We didn&#039;t become citizens until
1869. Put these in your head. We were not citizens. We were here working.

DREW: We were property.

GAINES: We were property. After that comes the worst thing, as bad as slavery. Peonage.

REDMAN: Jim Crow.

GAINES: Peonage and Jim Crow. Peonage is worse than Jim Crow.

DREW: Slavery.

GAINES: It&#039;s slavery, taking you and putting you in jail, then send us a nigger
to Mr. Bubba&#039;s farm, and you work there for life. A life sentence. One of the
great senators right now in Alabama made his money off of slavery in the steel
mills in Alabama. He had peonage going. Read your books and find out who he is.
I&#039;m not going to tell you. Let you do the research and find it. He&#039;s up there
right now. Look, here&#039;s what happened to me. I was sixteen, seventeen years old.
I was going to school in Langston High School. I was born in the black town. The
high school was on a college campus. Now, here&#039;s the law in Oklahoma. Oklahoma
has one good law, its educational law. If you live in Oklahoma, you&#039;re going to
go to school until you finish eighth grade, or the truant officer is going to
come around in small towns and made you go. Got a hold of your parents and made
you go to a school. I went to school on a college campus. When I got ready to
graduate, four months to graduate, my brother came to California. We had a hard
time. People do not know what it is to be poor. I mean, really poor.

DREW: Not poor. Way back, they were called po&#039;. You were po&#039;.

GAINES: I know what it is to be poor. My brother had been in California,
working. He had come out here in the thirties. This is 1937. I got on a freight
train in Guthrie, Oklahoma and rode down to change trains near Parker City. When
we got on the train coming out here -- I&#039;ve seen this. People on freight train,
on boxcars, flatbeds. Stacked with people. Lawyers, doctors, and everybody else,
white and black, no discrimination, on this one flatcar. This white guy was on
there with his wife and three kids, with a goat to feed them milk. This is how
hard times work. My sister-in-law, my brother&#039;s wife, had graduated from
Langston. She was a schoolteacher. She got on the train with us. All of us on
the train coming to California. I tell people this. California, to the black man
and poor whites, is what God promised Moses. This is the promise land. You read
The Grapes of Wrath?

DREW: Up to a point.

REDMAN: Up to a point!

GAINES: At that time, this was the promise land, because --

DREW: Yeah, it was promise, but we find out the promise wasn&#039;t kept.

GAINES: But it was a haven from what we were going through, even for the whites.
Just look at The Grapes of Wrath, what happened. They tell it in the movie, but
they don&#039;t really tell you the whole story.

REDMAN: There&#039;s something that I was a little surprised that -- sorry. Do you
have one more thought on the Depression that you want to add?

DREW: No, the only point I was going to make is that there&#039;s been a continuation
of the Depression. Actually, before the Depression, right up through the day.
Right now, we talk about the recession and compare it to the Great Depression.
These things seem to go in cycles. We get the same thing over and over again.
The only difference is the people get dumber and dumber. Not smarter. They get
dumber. They roll with it. Well, what can I do? What can I do? I&#039;ve been
unemployed for two years. I&#039;ve joined unemployment. Now the Democrats want to
renew the unemployment bill. The Republicans say no. I&#039;m going along with the
Republicans. I don&#039;t get care if I&#039;ve got a couple kids and a wife. I agree.
They shouldn&#039;t renew that thing. They shouldn&#039;t give us food stamps. If they
didn&#039;t give us food stamps -- I&#039;m quoting a program -- television. These
interviews that was given on television. This is a gentleman with a wife, two
kids. He lost his home. He&#039;s renting. He&#039;s so poor and bad off that he&#039;s sitting
there trying to figure out how he&#039;s going to pay his rent. He&#039;s $250 short. His
rent is due the next day. He&#039;s going to go use his telephone, and he&#039;s not sure
his telephone is still on. His gas bill is due the next day. He&#039;s sitting there
and he&#039;s -- &quot;I&#039;ll call my mother.&quot; He called his mother and she said, &quot;I don&#039;t
have any money.&quot; He doesn&#039;t know anybody with any money. I&#039;m opposed to all
these giveaways and things. If they didn&#039;t exist, we would find a way to take
care of our own. I&#039;m saying, this man is stupid. I say stupid. I can feel that
way about me. If I want to sacrifice myself, fine. I have the right to do that.
But do I have a right to sacrifice my family? I don&#039;t give a damn what it takes
to feed my family or to house my family, to take care of my family. I&#039;m going to
do it. If you want me to bend down and kiss your boots to take it, so what, your
boots have just been kissed. But my family. Anything that&#039;s going to be
detrimental to my family, and I agree to it, there&#039;s something wrong with me,
and that&#039;s why we have a nation of people like that.

GAINES: But now, what Othro is talking about gets to be very deep here in this
political situation that&#039;s going on today, because why is it the rich people can
control the majority of poor and lower-middle-class whites? Why can&#039;t they see
through what&#039;s going on? Just like in the Depression. During the Depression,
Roosevelt saved this country from having a civil war, which would have
eliminated the rich people so far. It&#039;s as close as we have come to socialized
everything. Roosevelt stopped it. Then when Hitler come along, then they got
back on to defeat the rich people, and they started producing, and it was going
back into the same dilemma that we&#039;re in.

REDMAN: Did the war, in that way, mask a lot of what was happening and the
reality of it? The fact that a lot of people made a lot of money off of the
Second World --

DREW: Oh, worse.

GAINES: The war changed the dynamics of this whole country. The South moved out,
coming to Detroit and everything. Kaiser went up in Washington. Shipyards and
everything. They brought a lot of blacks with them. These blacks, they were very
well to learn and everything, but didn&#039;t have the proper education. Now that
they&#039;ve got the proper education now, there&#039;s more discrimination now than there
was, just as much as it is --

DREW: There&#039;s more.

GAINES: I was looking at some of the things that this gentleman and I did here
during the Civil Rights Movement. We stood on the corner. You couldn&#039;t work at
Safeways. You couldn&#039;t work at the banks.

DREW: You couldn&#039;t work anywhere.

GAINES: Couldn&#039;t work anywhere.

DREW: Anywhere. Just yard work, basically.GAINES: Here&#039;s one of the things that
I have here, where Othro and I have stood on the corner, right there.

REDMAN: That&#039;s great. Okay. When is this article from? Do you --

GAINES: This is in in the forties. Let me see what date is on here. This was in
the 1940s through the fifties and sixties. We were working in this capacity.

DREW: Actually, we started before the Civil Rights Movement officially.

GAINES: Riot here starts in California. In the same way it was in Berkeley or in
El Cerrito and so forth, and Richmond and all those places. But here&#039;s what I
cannot understand, getting through my small cranium. Why is it Europeans that
are in charge hate the people that built this country, and hate the people that
own this country? They treat the Indians just as bad or worse than we&#039;re
treated. Why? Why is it in their large cranium or whatever they have, why is it
this seed is planted down into the young kids now that blacks and Indians and
these people are not as good as we are? What is wrong with them?

REDMAN: There was something that came up that I asked about that didn&#039;t seem to
resonate with either of you gentlemen, and I want to ask about it now, related
to the Second World War, and see why maybe that didn&#039;t -- maybe it&#039;s a
nonstarter. We can talk about something else. The Pittsburgh Courier started
something called the Double Victory Campaign during World War Two. This concept
of, why would we go off and fight fascism abroad if we don&#039;t have civil rights
at home?

DREW: Don&#039;t have freedom at home. Just plain freedom.

REDMAN: Just plain freedom, right.

DREW: That&#039;s not civil rights, it&#039;s plain freedom.

REDMAN: Right. At the same time, there are a couple of other names that I just
want to throw out there to see if these resonate. Both A. Philip Randolph, of
course, became --

DREW: One of the greatest men of all time.

REDMAN: He becomes a major political leader in the black community. Then on the
arts side, I want to point out Marian Anderson and her big concert at the
Lincoln Memorial in 1939. Those are three sort of big, key things that I see.
Then also, too, the Tuskegee Airmen, as becoming a big symbol for the African --

DREW: He can tell you about the Tuskegee Airmen. He has friends that were --

GAINES: My classmate was one. But look, when you start talking about World War
Two -- I was drafted in Sacramento, California. I was twenty-two years old. I
had stayed on the Army before in 1941, early forty-two. When I was drafted, we
all went to the reception center and everything. When I got to the reception
center, of course I knew what segregation was. A lot of guys are -- we call them
black Portuguese. Some guys from --

DREW: Explain to him that, during that time, all military were segregated.

GAINES: Oh, yeah. All military. But some Portuguese, some of my friends, my same
color, they came up from Cape Verde Islands. I speak a little Portuguese. Some
of them, they didn&#039;t know what they were. But anyway, when we got to the
reception center, then we went to Monterey. They say, &quot;Okay, you fellows, you
Negros, you get on over here. We&#039;re sending some of you to Texas.&quot; I was going
to Texas. Now, we&#039;re on the train. We&#039;re riding along. When we got to Arizona,
here comes the conductor. Say, &quot;Okay, you Negros have to go back here in the
back, because we&#039;re getting ready to go through Texas.&quot;

DREW: Same thing in California.

GAINES: Here I am, American soldiers going to -- of course, I understood this.
When we got down there to Texas, we had all white officers. There was 15,000 of
us in the cavalry. Most of those guys were second lieutenants. They didn&#039;t know
anything about anything, you know what I mean? Most of them were racist, because
they didn&#039;t understand African Americans.

DREW: The other reason they were racist, too, there was such a stigma attached
to being black that if a white person was forced to affiliate with a black, if
you were an officer and they assign you to a black outfit, you hated blacks.
Plus, number one, they tell you, &quot;You&#039;re never going anywhere. You&#039;re never
going to progress. You&#039;re stuck with this group of people, inferior people. Why
do we send you there? Because we figure you&#039;re an inferior officer.&quot; You were
talking about World War Two. For a short time there during World War Two, whites
were so interested in this American thing about victory, winning the war, they
sort of pushed us to the side. It was okay for us working the shipyards and
things like that, because as soon as this is all over with, blacks will be sent
back to where they belong, back to their proper place. Along with that, the fact
that the military was segregated. You brought up Randolph. People give Truman
all this credit about integrating the military, but the reason that the military
was integrated was Randolph. Randolph had Truman&#039;s ear. He had the fear of God
in Truman. He&#039;d already arranged to bring over 300,000 blacks to Washington. He
explained to Truman, &quot;If you don&#039;t desegregate the military, we&#039;ll have a
million blacks out here permanently this summer.&quot; Truman got the message. I
disagree with him a little bit when it comes to Roosevelt. To me, Roosevelt was
one of the lousiest presidents we ever had.

GAINES: Racially, he was.

DREW: He was, because they gave him carte blanche because of the situation.
&quot;President Roosevelt, you can do anything you want.&quot; What did he do for the
blacks? Nothing. He could have, with just a stroke of his pen. He was in a
position, stroke of his pen, he could have --

REDMAN: Done much more.

DREW: He could have desegregated the military. He could have done everything. He
could have done enormous things. He did nothing. But that nothing that he didn&#039;t
do was better than the ones that had come before. [laughter]

GAINES: It&#039;s good to disagree. He&#039;s right. But I&#039;ll note one thing about
Roosevelt. He did this for the country when he established the NRA, the National
Recovery Act. Then he formed the WPA. That&#039;s the Works Progress Administration.
There was no segregation in the Works Progress Administration, because he put
black people on the WPA, because everybody was starving. Then he had the NYA,
National Youth Association. Then he did the CCC. He saved this country from
going communist or socialist. That&#039;s what he did. The same thing is going to
happen now. Why you say they&#039;re games? Here&#039;s why I&#039;m saying it. Right now,
right now, today, over 40 percent of young black men are being arrested and put
in jail. Fifty-two percent of them go to jail. Then, know what they do? They
take away --

DREW: Their citizenship.

GAINES: They take away their citizenship. They take away everything. Here&#039;s what
the drug program is producing. It&#039;s kept a secret now, but it&#039;s going to happen.
The penalty for crack cocaine is different than the penalty for --

DREW: For cocaine, regular white cocaine.

GAINES: They have a new drug out now that&#039;s affecting poor whites, and they
don&#039;t know what to do about it. It&#039;s a feeling of what&#039;s called --

REDMAN: Meth?

GAINES: Meth.

REDMAN: Methamphetamines? Yeah.

DREW: Also, that other -- oxycontin.

REDMAN: Oxy, sure.

GAINES: This is what&#039;s happening. Here&#039;s what&#039;s happening. The third largest
business in the United States, you know what it is today?

DREW: Prisons.

GAINES: The justice system.

DREW: Prisons.

GAINES: We&#039;re bringing back 35,000 people now, back from Louisiana, Mississippi,
Texas, that we were farming out to prisons. Who&#039;s building the prisons? The same
guy that built over in Iraq. [Dick Cheney] The same company is building --

REDMAN: Halliburton?

GAINES: Halliburton is building. You understand? Look, here&#039;s the problem.
Here&#039;s the whole problem. The people that are supposed to have the brains, they
don&#039;t talk about this, because he makes $400 million a year.

DREW: He&#039;s a college dropout anyway.

GAINES: They are not going to tell the poor whites what&#039;s happening to them.
When they wake up, if they ever wake up, it might be too late.

REDMAN: Let me ask two more questions on this tape. We talked a little bit last
time about Port Chicago. Go ahead.

DREW: One thing I think is extremely important to bring up, extremely important,
is that, during World War Two, [and] prior to World War Two, all we read about
in history books, about some black person at American Revolution here and there,
but [really] prior to that, if you were in the military, it was believed that if
you were black, you were incapable of fighting. They didn&#039;t want you to fight.
We don&#039;t want you to die for our country. You can drive trucks, you can do all
these things, but you can&#039;t go on the front line and fight. We don&#039;t want you on
the front line fighting. In Korea, they changed their mind, because these guys
were so proficient. But before that, they couldn&#039;t. Like I said, even after
World War Two -- we talk about the GI Bill and all the rights that came along
with this type of thing, like housing industry got started after World War Two,
primarily because part of the GI Bill was to provide these guys with houses.
They can buy houses. Before, they couldn&#039;t. But then only 3 percent of those
houses went to blacks. The soldiers fought, they came back, and they couldn&#039;t
[actually] buy houses.

REDMAN: Why was that?

DREW: Because of the system. Everything was white. The government was all white.
There were no blacks in the government or anything. Whatever the whites said, it
went. It was just like after the Civil War. The North won the war. What did the
Confederacy do? They walked back into Washington like nothing ever happened and
started demanding things. They had no contrition. No &quot;We apologize for what we
did, for the people that&#039;s killed.&quot;

GAINES: Is your [camera] still on?

REDMAN: Yes. Do you want me to pause it or --

GAINES: No, no. I wanted you to take a picture of this.

DREW: I&#039;ll just keep talking while you&#039;re doing that. This has been an ongoing
thing, but like you were talking about, today, the difference today than, say,
World War Two, World War Two it was always felt that once the war is over, we
can always return the coloreds back to where they came from. Today, the
situation has gotten a little bit different. The genie is out of the bottle. We
can hate them. We can do bad things. We can try to pass the laws to try to put
the genie back in the bottle, but it&#039;s not going back in the bottle again. Now
we have to try to deal with it. We deal with it in a totally different way.
We&#039;re back almost like the segregation beforehand. We&#039;ve got the South Side of
Chicago. We&#039;ve got parts of New York. Blacks are contained in certain areas.
Then you say, &quot;Well, if they would get an education.&quot; But how do you get an
education when you&#039;ve got -- not only discriminate by black, by race, we
discriminate by zip code.

GAINES: That&#039;s it.

DREW: You put all the blacks in one area, and then the board of education can
say, &quot;Well, we&#039;re going to send&quot; -- I&#039;ll give you a good example. Right here,
Edison High School. Edison High School, about seven, eight years ago, had the
lowest graduating rate of any high school in the country. Not California. In the
country. They only graduated 27 percent of their students. Twenty-seven percent.
The gentleman, Mr. Washington, Mr. Washington and I grew up together. He was a
good friend of mine. I went over to his office to find out what&#039;s going on. It
pissed me off when I read these figures. I went over and he was sitting there
with his hand like this, shaking his head. I said, &quot;What&#039;s the matter?&quot; He said,
&quot;I know what you come in here for.&quot; I said, &quot;What for?&quot; &quot;About the graduation
figure.&quot; I said, &quot;How could you let that be?&quot; He said, &quot;I have no control of
it.&quot; He says, &quot;You know what type of teachers that the board of education is
sending me?&quot; I said no. &quot;First-year teachers, substitute teachers, and teachers
that other schools don&#039;t want. That&#039;s the basis of the teachers that I have
here.&quot; He said, &quot;There&#039;s nothing for them to learn. They&#039;re talking about
dropping out of school.&quot; I can understand that. What amazes me is that a child
would get a high school education if he&#039;s not planning to go to college. High
schools are prep schools. They&#039;re preparatory schools. Prepare you to go to
college. That&#039;s all. You think of all the things that you learned in high school
if you didn&#039;t go to college. After seventh or eighth grade, what did you learn
that could help you in the world once you were out there? Nothing.

GAINES: I want to continue on education.

REDMAN: This is a T-shirt for a family reunion.

GAINES: Family reunion. What does it say?

REDMAN: 2005. &quot;Still growing.&quot;GAINES: This was in 2005, but this is 138 years.

REDMAN: &quot;Educational, business, and vocational.&quot;

GAINES: There you have it. I have twenty-something grandchildren, great
grandchildren. Five generations. This is what I teach. Academic, vocational, or
business. I&#039;ve never worked for anyone in my life. I work for myself. All of us
work by ourselves. There&#039;s thirty-something barbers in our family. Some of those
barbers are now lawyers, some are dentists, some are doctors, and so forth,
because [they work for themselves]. Here&#039;s something. When all my kids were
born, I took a California gift to minors. Most people never heard of it. I take
out a scholarship for them when they&#039;re born. They put it in the bank. They
can&#039;t take any of the money out until they go to college. During the time when
[Jimmy] Carter was president, I had some children born. When interest rates were
17 percent -- you understand? -- my kids go to college. None of them have got a
student loan. They paid for it and they worked. They worked every day. My
daughter worked for a clothing store. The other daughter worked for Old Navy. My
sons work in group home. They helped to put themselves through school. Now,
here&#039;s the point about education. If you get an education, you&#039;re ready to
compete, but you can&#039;t compete with the money. That&#039;s why I bring in the
business part. Let them go in business. I go in business for myself. Here&#039;s the
point. When people get millions and millions of dollars to invest, they want to
buy four, five different cars and all this other bullshit, when they should try
to help to pick somebody else up, to give scholarships to these unfortunate
blacks. There&#039;s a lot of unfortunate blacks that really can understand and have
a high IQ, but when they go to classes, they&#039;re not taught in the school.

My wife is a schoolteacher. She said this guy -- she got a student that comes
and had thirty-five kids in the class. This is why the guy sent his kid over
there and says, &quot;Look, I have too many kids. This is a real bright kid.&quot; Says,
&quot;He&#039;s real smart. You&#039;d be happy to have him.&quot; This is when they had the XYZ
system, which you may not know about. Do you know what XYZ is? A kid comes into
the first grade. He&#039;s put in the category of X group or Y group or Z group. Now,
the teacher has to teach three different groups in that class. She has
thirty-five students in there. You understand? How is she going to teach that
many kids when we wanted to reduce it? So anyway, when she got the kids, she
looked at his {queue?}. The kid was in the fourth grade. He couldn&#039;t read on a
first-grade level. Now we&#039;re passing students out today, that&#039;s finishing high
school, that can&#039;t read on a third-grade level.

DREW: Which has produced thirty million adult illiterates in this country.

REDMAN: Today is Tuesday, July 17, [2012] and this is my second tape today with
Mr. Drew and Mr. Gaines. When we left off, there was one topic that came up that
seems to be important for African American[s]. Especially, at the time,
servicemen, during World War Two, and something that was both known and unknown
at the same time, which is the explosion that takes place at Port Chicago The
legacy of that, of course, with the lawsuits that follow in terms of the mutiny
trial and Thurgood Marshall&#039;s position. But at the same time, we talked about
Port Chicago and it was [largely] covered up. It was more or less a military
[or] government secret. To what extent do you think that [incident] resonated or
didn&#039;t resonate with African American community? That here were these African
American sailors who were subjected to unsafe working conditions, and this
tragedy took place?

DREW: It was such a cover-up that whites didn&#039;t know what was going on. Like I
told you, I went to Port Chicago. It was off-limit. You could come up there, but
you couldn&#039;t go in, you couldn&#039;t see anything. The press couldn&#039;t go in. That&#039;s
why you saw almost no pictures of it. The few pictures you saw was usually shot
from long range or something else. It&#039;s like -- what&#039;s that place over in New Mexico?

REDMAN: Roswell? [Los Alamos?]

DREW: [1951]. Just like that. If the government decides to cover up something,
they can cover it up, absolutely, completely, and you&#039;ll never, ever know about
it. That&#039;s the way Port Chicago is. How did it affect the black community? The
black community heard rumors. Rumors, that&#039;s all. No proof, just word of rumors.
Maybe it happened, maybe it didn&#039;t. If you lived in New York or Pennsylvania or
Texas or some place, did it really happen? People now are questioning, did a man
really go to the moon? Of course, I lived in California, and they said that this
rocket took off in Florida. Did it really go there? Other people have
questioned, did 9/11 really happen? Did they really blow up those buildings? No,
the government probably did it. When you can&#039;t get the facts, you create
whatever you want. Port Chicago - the same thing. Almost all the information
that we received about Port Chicago was what people surmised to have happened.
They believe this happened. This could have happened. Well, maybe those blacks
were -- the blacks get uppity. Maybe they just didn&#039;t want to do their work.
Maybe they were lazy and shiftless and didn&#039;t want to go up there and unload
those ships. In fact, maybe they&#039;re responsible for blowing up the darned thing
in the first place. Here we are in the middle of a war, and they&#039;re going to
blow up the ship with all this ammunition and everything. It didn&#039;t happen, but --

REDMAN: That&#039;s the way the conversations --

DREW: If I tell you this, you tell your friend that, somebody else tells
somebody else, their friend, now they can do it more effective, using the internet.

REDMAN: Mr. Gaines, I wonder [if] can you speak to that? Port Chicago.

GAINES: Oh, yeah. I remember the story very well. It&#039;s all cover-up, the old
shell game. You caused it, but we&#039;re going to settle this thing right now, and
they never get to the bottom of it. They really don&#039;t know what really happened
in Port Chicago. In fact, they really didn&#039;t even -- they didn&#039;t care, because
most of the guys that got killed were black. It didn&#039;t make --

DREW: Almost all of them were black.

GAINES: Most all of them black. They didn&#039;t even care.

DREW: We got rid of part of our problem.

GAINES: The first thing you have to understand is, when you&#039;ve been in a
segregated army, which I was in the segregated army, it is terrible. When you
face segregation all your life, then you really look back and see how much bias
was against you, that you couldn&#039;t really get ahead. You begin to realize what&#039;s
going on now. Take Oakland, for instance. At one time, Oakland had more
businesses, black-owned businesses, than Atlanta, Georgia. Oakland today doesn&#039;t
have very many black businesses. What happened to the banks in Oakland? What
happened to all the loan companies in Oakland? Here&#039;s what happened. There&#039;s
discrimination in jobs today. I&#039;m driving down here today. On the highway, I&#039;m
looking. About fifteen people working there. Not a single black. I live right
down from this company, Enviroplex. They build schools to be sold to the
counties and other counties. Government work. Not a single black, and 200 people
working there. And they wonder why blacks are in the penitentiary. Just like
this kid said in Fresno the other day, white kid, he said, &quot;I will murder now,
and I&#039;m not going to sleep under the bridge. I&#039;m not going to go hungry.&quot; Now,
why did he say that? He was taken, when he was a child, and put in a foster home
that didn&#039;t teach him manners. They didn&#039;t teach him how to get an education.
They didn&#039;t teach him how to make a living. He stayed there until he was twenty
years old. Nineteen or twenty. What&#039;s he going to do? He can&#039;t get a job. He&#039;s
not qualified. He can&#039;t read. Naturally, he&#039;s not going to sleep under the
bridge. How many foster kids do you have in this country? A lot of them. You
know what the boys do? The boys go to selling dope or robbing or everything.

DREW: End up in jail.

GAINES: End up in jail. But that&#039;s where they want them, in jail, because they
make --

DREW: It&#039;s profitable.

GAINES: They make $41,000 a year off of him.

REDMAN: You brought up jobs and hiring, and then we&#039;ve also brought up the
lawsuits. Especially in Port Chicago, the mutiny trial, Thurgood Marshall. We&#039;re
talking about a couple of different things that would become really important
for the Civil Rights Movement as it took shape after World War Two. I&#039;m thinking
in particular about the NAACP and their strategy that they took, but then also
CORE, the Congress of Racial Equality, and organizations like SNCC, Student
Nonviolent Coordinating Committee. The people who were talking about civil,
nonviolent disobedience versus the legal strategy. Can you guys talk a little
bit about, after World War Two, starting to learn about some of these
organizations and movements?

GAINES: I can tell you about the NAACP. I joined the NAACP when I was nineteen
years old, in Sacramento. Reverend Muse was the president. I have been a member
of the NAACP. This is where I worked. I worked for thirty-five years with the
NAACP. I got guys together to picket Safeway, picket PG&amp;E, picket the motor
vehicle. They didn&#039;t hire any blacks. Here&#039;s one thing that happened when I was
chairman of the NAACP labor committee. They said, &quot;We&#039;re going to hire. Send me
someone down here in the motor vehicle. If they can pass the test, we&#039;ll put
them to work.&quot;

DREW: I think we should explain the NAACP in Stockton compared to NAACP in the
rest of the country.

REDMAN: That would be great, yes.

DREW: The first time I joined the NAACP was in Stockton. We were a very
aggressive organization. When I left Stockton, when I was forced to leave
Stockton, and I moved to the Bay Area --

GAINES: He was the first black librarian here.

DREW: I joined the NAACP over there. It was like a social club. After about two
months, I couldn&#039;t deal with it, and I couldn&#039;t make them understand -- I was
trying to explain to them what we were doing in Stockton. It was like, oh,
shoot, they&#039;re not really members of the NAACP. It was two totally different
worlds, the NAACP here and the NAACP across the country. I read about the other
parts of the country. They were more akin to what was happening in the Bay Area.
Mostly legal. Legal, legal, legal. Compared to other -- I&#039;m sorry, brother
Gaines, go ahead.

GAINES: No, no.

REDMAN: It would be a mistake, then, as a student of history, if I were looking
at this and you see the NAACP does this, or the NAACP does that, that doesn&#039;t
reflect all of the chapters, in your experience.

DREW: That&#039;s the crux of the entire matter. You can&#039;t pigeonhole blacks. Like
you say, you&#039;ve got all these different organizations that have different goals,
different aims. You&#039;ve got Malcolm X and all these different groups. Their
thinking is different. Initially, when Martin Luther King was busy, it was
almost you&#039;re either with Martin Luther King or you were with Malcolm X. Which,
for my past, I was almost with Malcolm X, although I appreciated what Martin
Luther King was doing.

GAINES: I appreciate it [the different approaches], too. See, I&#039;m different. I
was with the NAACP ever since I was a kid. Still belong to it. But there&#039;s
certain things that I would not take, you understand? I was telling you about
this gentleman here that wanted to send his daughters back -- Anderson was going
to send his daughter back into slavery. I was talking to my daughter, and I let
her read the article. It was in the paper. I said, &quot;This slave master was asking
-- this guy was freed -- to send him and his two daughters back there to
slavery.&quot; So I asked them, I said, &quot;Now, what would you think about me, as your
father, and I sent you back there?&quot; I said, &quot;If a bastard come to me and tell me
to bring my daughters out here, I want to have sex, I&#039;d blow his fucking brains
out.&quot; Excuse me. You understand?

DREW: He&#039;ll edit it.

GAINES: But look. She said to me, she said, &quot;Daddy, if you didn&#039;t do it, I
wouldn&#039;t respect you.&quot; You understand? This is the kind of [feeling]. I was in
the NAACP. I did all of this work. We&#039;re going to have a march that all of these
dignitaries and teachers and everything else, we were going to march from the
Stockton Hotel down to University of Pacific. I&#039;m one of the guys that -- Othro
and I don&#039;t buy where you can&#039;t work and all this. They asked me, said, &quot;Brother
Gaines, you going to march?&quot; I said, &quot;No. You know I don&#039;t march.&quot; They says,
&quot;Why can&#039;t you march with us?&quot; I said, &quot;I told you, I can&#039;t march. I just don&#039;t
march.&quot; Because my rearing didn&#039;t teach me to march. My father never taught me
to let somebody humiliate me and do everything to me and I don&#039;t fight back. I
was taught that. This is the way I am. So they kept on hounding me and said,
&quot;Gaines, you have to march.&quot; I said, &quot;You asked for this.&quot; I said, &quot;If a son of
a bitch spit in my face, I&#039;m going to stick my fucking knife in his belly.&quot; You
understand? This is what&#039;s happened. What happened to us is this. When you
brought him over here and took all the fight out of a black man, you could do
anything you wanted to with him. If he ever fought back, it would be a different
thing. You understand? Everything would fight back except for rabbit. You go and
run rabbit. You run off and leave his kids in the house. Son of a bitch come and
-- excuse me -- if a son of a gun come in my house, I&#039;m going to fight until I
die to protect my family.

DREW: On that line, white people do not understand blacks. Things that happened
-- you, even you, you&#039;re sitting there. I can see, the way you look sometime,
that your mind just can&#039;t digest these things. It didn&#039;t happen to white people.
It&#039;s going to be that way for probably another hundred years. They were saying
blacks should have more conversation. We should have more conversation. All
these things are right. But still, it&#039;s going to bring about some understanding.
It&#039;s not going to bring about complete understanding. My generation would have
to die out. Like I tell young people, the greatest thing that could happen to
them is all old people like me go somewhere and just lie down and die. That&#039;s
the greatest thing that could happen to young people, because young people have
a better chance of progressing. They won&#039;t have all of us old people
indoctrinating them with all kinds of ridiculous stuff. Some of the things that
I say, and I consider myself a person that&#039;s fair --

GAINES: This is the best Father&#039;s Day gift that I ever had from one of my sons.
I want you to read it.

REDMAN: You showed me this. Yes.

GAINES: I want you to read it. Read it loud so it will be on there.

REDMAN: This is -- all right.

GAINES: From my son.

DREW: There was an author, (John Howard) Griffin. His name was Griffin. He wrote
a book entitled Black Like Me (1961). Heard of it or read it? What Griffin did,
he was so interested in what was happening with black people. This book was
written about -- when was it? About the fifties?GAINES: Oh, yes, it was back
early sixties.

DREW: But anyway, he decided, as an experiment, that he was going to pass
himself off as a black person. He got these berries and dyed his skin dark, and
his head and everything, and he went out to pass himself off as a black person.
He tried this experiment for six months. Two weeks later -- the man almost ended
up in a mental institution. In his book, he concludes, he says, &quot;I can&#039;t
understand how colored people can even live in this country.&quot; People just
thinking that he was black, he had been humiliated so much over that period of
time and everything that he just couldn&#039;t -- his mind couldn&#039;t digest it.
Couldn&#039;t deal with it at all. But we do this, what we deal with every day.

REDMAN: I want to read this, and then I want to get back to a question about
civil rights activism in just a moment. This is from your son.

GAINES: My son.

REDMAN: &quot;From son to father, of all the wisdom you have bestowed upon me, I
carry it wherever I go. Now that I reflect on the journey I have taken and the
voices of conscious that guided me all the way, it has been yours. I see now the
importance of true fatherhood. The burden of worry, the constant nagging of
wanting more for your child. You have groomed me well. More importantly, you&#039;ve
made me a good person. With all the craziness in the world, you&#039;ve protected me.
I shall, for my son, only offer the same and encourage him the legacy that you
have created. Education is the key to success, and no matter it be through
vocation or traditional means. Thank you, from father to father. Love, Ali Gaines.&quot;

GAINES: The guys wanted to know who wrote this. I&#039;ve told them, I&#039;ve said, &quot;My
son wrote this.&quot; But this was written by my dad. In his mind, this is what he
wanted for all his kids. This is why I speak education, be it academic,
vocational, or business. You&#039;ve got to have that to get along. And respect. You
see, respect. My kids give me ties. They give me golf clubs. This is what is
passed down. The legacy is passed down 138 years from this, my father and my
mother. But see, we&#039;ve gotten away from that. We don&#039;t teach our kids this. You
don&#039;t have to beat them. I don&#039;t whip my kids. Teach them.

DREW: One of the worst things that happened to blacks was desegregation. When
desegregation came, [now[ can do all these type of things, [but] prior to that
time, Langston University, all-black university, you know what the graduation
rate was for that university over ten years? The highest in the history of this
country. Ninety-eight percent. Ninety-eight percent graduation. Your mind can&#039;t
even deal with it. Because the people that went there felt so obligated. If you
flunked out and you couldn&#039;t complete it, your best bet was to pack up and go
someplace else, go down to South America someplace. This went down the line.
There were a few things that we were allowed, and a few things that we did well.
It was the same thing with sports. They said, &quot;Why are black athletes so good?&quot;
They had to be. Like Joe Lewis. Joe Lewis had to be good. During those days, if
you were, say, a boxer, you were a black boxer, you lost a battle, a fight, to a
white person, you didn&#039;t come back home. You may as well have somebody ship your
bags to wherever you were going. Because say you went back home. It would be
such a humiliating thing. There wasn&#039;t many things that we had. Most of all, I
think, our black community, that was our lynchpin. That was our taproot. We drew
all our strength from -- the saying that it takes a community to raise a child,
we believed that. Every child in that community was subject to whatever any
grownup would tell. A grownup would never tell you wrong.

REDMAN: There&#039;s one question I want to get at. When you were involved with the
NAACP and with other civil rights organizations throughout California, one of
the things that a lot of historians have talked about recently is, this is a
different time, [but] women were treated differently within these organizations
than you might imagine today. Can you guys speak to that? How women would or
wouldn&#039;t fit within this --

DREW: When the Civil Rights Movement started, women were most valuable. The
other thing about black women in this country, black women, from slavery time,
there were things that black women were allowed to do, black men couldn&#039;t. A
black woman was like the maid of the house. She would -- &quot;Well, Ms. So-and-So, I
don&#039;t like the way you&#039;re treating that child&quot; and everything. &quot;Well, that&#039;s my
child.&quot; &quot;Well, I don&#039;t care. I have to take care of him&quot; and this type [of
thing]. It was tolerated. The black guy out in the field, if he says something,
or he just looks up -- you don&#039;t look the master in the eye. One day, he can&#039;t
take it no more, he stands up, he looks, he raises his head, [and] he&#039;s dead.
When the Civil Rights Movement came along, it was almost like slavery time
during the Underground Railroad. Black women could kind of ease out and do
things that men weren&#039;t allowed.

REDMAN: Rosa Parks is a symbol of that.

GAINES: Yes, but see, here&#039;s what happened. We go back to Mary McLeod Bethune.
You can go back to the lady [Harriet Tubman] that took all the slaves out and
took them up over to Canada and everything. But look, the black woman has borne
the burden ever since she got on the ship. It left the harbor in Africa. They
left, and sometimes it takes six months to get here to America.

DREW: If they got here.

GAINES: The girls, twelve years old, were raped and everything else on the ship.
Raped by saying, &quot;Come on, girl, go with me.&quot; This is why, when I hear a young
black man call a black woman a bitch, I look at him and I wear the mask. This
man doesn&#039;t understand what that woman went through all her life. She had to
have sex with the white man&#039;s son to break him in to sex. His daughters. Like
that bastard that helped to write the Constitution. He had black babies, five of
them, by Sally -- Jefferson. You understand? And yet wouldn&#039;t give her freedom.
You understand? When you mention a black woman, she has borne the burden. Any
time we mistreat her -- she was there scrubbing the floor. Oh, look at Sally.
She&#039;s scrubbing the floor for the white -- but sister Sally&#039;s daughter was going
to go to school, or sister Sally&#039;s son. That&#039;s what she was doing it for.

DREW: I was going to say something about the women, the black women. They kept
us alive during slavery time. We talk about all the soul food now. Chitlins and
all that kind of stuff [Chitterlings -- also known as &quot;Chitlins&quot;]. This was
throwaway food. This was stuff that whites couldn&#039;t [eat] -- they&#039;d bury it.
They couldn&#039;t feed it to animals or anything else. Nothing you could do with it.
It didn&#039;t make good fertilizer, nothing. They&#039;re getting rid of it. Oh, we&#039;ll
give it to the blacks, let them eat it. So they come up with all these different
-- these women. Not the men. Man&#039;s working the fields. She takes this stuff and
she does all these things with it and creates all these great dishes. Then
you&#039;ll hear some white person from Georgia, &quot;Yes, we had chitlins for dinner,
and we ate this here.&quot; God, this guy doesn&#039;t even know!

I was in CORE in San Francisco after I left over here and I couldn&#039;t reach an
agreement with the NAACP. About that time, CORE was starting. I read about this.
We formed a CORE group in San Francisco. Very militant group. Was loaded with
well-educated people. Before we did anything, we used to spend maybe a month or
two just on homework, just going out. San Francisco, people around the world --
and California has perpetuated this myth -- San Francisco has always been a
liberated city. San Francisco has never been a liberated city. If you think of
the people that came here, the sailors and all these people that came here and
the people in California, especially San Francisco, and that even when it comes
to education, it was determined, since there were blacks moving in to San
Francisco, how do we educate them? The first idea was separate schools. But
there was a woman, single woman -- they wrote a book about her.

GAINES: Madame Pleasure. She ran a whorehouse.

DREW: She ran a whorehouse. All the powers and divas visited the whorehouse. The
mayor, the chief of police, all these people. She kept very great documents on
what was going on.

GAINES: Kept the books.

DREW: When they were deciding on what do we do about education systems -- we got
all these blacks here, we feel obligated to educate them -- they finally decided
that they would have separate schools. She said no. &quot;Nothing you can do about
it.&quot; &quot;Oh, yes, I can.&quot; She waved her little book then. Had all these clipper
ships come in. This information -- we can take this stuff to New York and it can
be everywhere. They decided, okay, we&#039;re going to segregate the schools, but
we&#039;re not going to segregate them. How do you segregate and not segregate? The
classrooms, they put a sheet down the middle. Blacks sit on one side, whites sit
on the other side. Same teacher. The education system, education, there&#039;s a
constant among blacks. Get an education, get an education. The whites are not --
they&#039;re surreptitiously saying, &quot;Yes, you should get educated, you should get
educated, but we&#039;re not going to let you get educated.&quot;

GAINES: Now you&#039;re talking about --

DREW: We&#039;re not going to let you get educated. We&#039;ll make sure you don&#039;t get
educated, because we&#039;re going to give you the worst teachers.

REDMAN: One of the things I wanted to ask about that we talked about, between
1960 and 1964, this is a really active, active time. I&#039;m just going to mention a
few big things that happened during this period, and I&#039;d like to see if you
could speak to them. In 1960, of course there&#039;s the big sit-in at the Woolworth
in Greensboro, North Carolina. We talked about the sort of idea of why would a
black person even want to eat at Woolworth.

DREW: That&#039;s a great, great question. Prior to people being able to eat at
Woolworth, in the black community, black people said, &quot;I don&#039;t know how even
white people eat that food, it&#039;s so bad.&quot; But then when desegregation occurred
at Woolworth, blacks are lined up down there at Woolworth. The food that was
served in the black community, it was such that whites would come down to the
black community to eat. They&#039;d come in, and quite often, like the barbecue
places. Some of them would reach the point where it was a two-way street. Some
of the blacks had to come around the back to eat, and some of the whites didn&#039;t
want to be seen, so they would be able to come to this window and get this black
food, and sneak back and take it back and everything. When it came to the
desegregation thing, the black community missed a lot of it. Missed it in that
white people, they were money orientated. Let&#039;s go over to Fillmore District. I
can give you more exact point. The Fillmore District. Fillmore District was one
of the most complete affluent districts anywhere, and especially the state of
California. It was absolutely one solid block of black-owned businesses, black
houses and everything. Three hotels, two schools -- I mean, two --

GAINES: All the way from Sutter to Haight Street. Nothing but black business
down Fillmore.DREW: The interesting thing about it, the whites had abandoned
this area earlier, when blacks started moving in. This is right off the downtown
area. You can walk downtown. When the weather is bad everywhere else, you can be
in the Fillmore, you can look up to the sunshine. You leave the Fillmore
district, someplace else, and it&#039;s overcast and everythingelse. That area,
people, earlier on, before they came there to redevelop this area. Justin
Herman. Justin Herman determined that the Fillmore District was an eyesore.
Anywhere black people are is an eyesore, although we had the best jazz clubs and
everything. White people would come down there. You go to some jazz club,
there&#039;s more white people than there were black. Some of the restaurants, the
same way. But they decided to destroy Fillmore. They did. They came in. They
gave the people almost nothing for their homes and everything. So the question
was asked, why didn&#039;t they fight back? Who are they going to fight? The judges
are white. The system is white. The lawyers are white. Whatever they says, go.
That&#039;s it. We had one --

GAINES: You wanted to talk about the sixties. That&#039;s what you --

REDMAN: I&#039;ll just say because in sixty-one, CORE has the Freedom Rides, and then
a lot of Californians participate in that. Then in sixty-three and sixty-four, I
understand that there are the shop-ins at Lucky in Berkeley, which are pretty
famous, and then the Free Speech Movement.

GAINES: But you see, here&#039;s where CORE and all of them made a mistake. In this
article that was written by the Stockton Record to me, here&#039;s what it says,
&quot;Gaines first came to Stockton in 1945. After leaving Sacramento, he has since
then been constant voice of numerous committees and caucuses. One of the most
successful was being labor committee chairman for the Stockton chapter of the
NAACP, a committee which he headed for over thirty years at that time.
Throughout this time, Gaines was busy organizing various groups in effort to
attain better black representation in the job market. &#039;We have made a
considerable amount of progress where employment is concerned. You can now see
blacks working in many of the same places that they weren&#039;t allowed to go years
ago.&#039; He continued. &#039;It was our protest back in the 1950s and sixties that
created the new position that blacks hold today. The white-orientated system
didn&#039;t give anything to blacks. We had to take it.&#039; One of the methods devised
by Gaines through the NAACP was to have all blacks pay their telephone bills in
pennies, only to protest them not hiring blacks in the companies.&quot; You see, if
you hit a man in his pocketbook, that&#039;s what hurts. The CORE was doing the
sitting in the counters. All they had to do was boycott, like they did the bus
system down there in Alabama. What I preach and taught, don&#039;t buy where you
can&#039;t work. If you don&#039;t buy automobiles, you say, we won&#039;t buy any more
Chevrolets this year.

DREW: Like we did in San Francisco with the Cadillacs. They found out that the
people that bought more Cadillacs than anyone else were blacks. We asked the
Cadillac dealer down at Automobile Row to hire a black salesman. Across in
Oakland was Patterson&#039;s Cadillac. We went over to Patterson with these
statistics. We said, &quot;If we could direct most of these black people over here to
buy a Cadillac, would you consider hiring a black salesman?&quot; You know what his
reaction was? &quot;Can you have one here this afternoon?&quot; [laughter] Like he was
talking about with CORE, down South, CORE did sit-in, this type of thing. San
Francisco CORE was a complete different story, like I said earlier. We did our
research on how many people worked here, this type of thing. Like, for instance,
Safeway. Safeway, in the black community, was a total different entity than the
Safeway in the white community. We stood up. We watched what was going on. We
found out that the produce and meat that was sold in the white community, after
the expiration date, it was brought down and put in the Safeway store in the
black community, and the price was increased. They found out with the Bank of
America, which was formerly the Bank of Italy, the Bank of America,
three-tenths, or 1 percent, of all of its employees were minorities. Not black
minorities. They said, &quot;We have an officer working for the Bank of America.&quot; Who
was the officer? He was assistant branch manager in Watts, an all-black
community. We said, we&#039;ve got to devise a strategy to change this. We&#039;ve got to
devise a strategy to take care of the Safeway situation. All these things. There
were no such thing as, they call it, a driver salesman. The people who deliver
bread and stuff to the stores, and wine and beer. It didn&#039;t exist. We devised a
strategy, how do we get these people to hire? We did a lot of sit-ins and this
type of thing. I went to jail so many times. I would go in, come out, go down to
the place, and turn around and come back down there again. We had an enormous
amount of sharp people, lawyers and this type of thing. They&#039;re standing there
with bail bondsmen. We walk in, they book us, and demand to know what the bail
is. &quot;This man has never done anything. Release him on his own recognizance.&quot;
Back out on the street, back demonstrating.

REDMAN: Now, by this time, you&#039;re both a little older. I&#039;m wondering if you
could speak, just for a moment, your perception about the student movements,
say, at Berkeley, where either the Free Speech Movement, a lot of white kids
from California are going to the South, and for many of them, it&#039;s a really
eye-opening experience. They&#039;re bringing that back. But on the other hand,
you&#039;re in this multiracial organization, but are you ever looking at these
young, naïve white kids who want to help out with a degree of skepticism, or
are you just happy to have their enthusiasm and involvement?

GAINES: Let me tell you this. All white people aren&#039;t racist. We got some good
breaks from white kids. Without the whites that come in -- look at those guys
was killed in Mississippi. What&#039;s the name of the lady that was killed? Listen,
all white people don&#039;t think that way. Some white people are really down with
being what is the right thing for the United States. This is one thing that&#039;s
happening today. We are faced with a Mormon religion. Go to Salt Lake City, or
go anyplace. You don&#039;t see any blacks in there.

DREW: The first place I was ever called a nigger in my whole life --

REDMAN: Was Salt Lake City?

GAINES: What you talking about? It&#039;s the most --

DREW: I was going to Utah to ski.

GAINES: All black people -- you can&#039;t go unless a white man take you. You read
the Mormon religion. Okay. When I was listening to this, I was thinking about
how we were treated when we tried to get these good jobs. Now, today, you would
think we wouldn&#039;t have to sit in to get a job. But when I passed this place,
what I did, every day I passed it going to work or going downtown or going down
to my business, today they hired 200 people there, and not a single black worked
there. Now, look, that&#039;s what you&#039;re talking about years ago, but we&#039;re talking
about today. Why do you think a lot of black kids are in the penitentiary today?
They can&#039;t get a job. Back to this white boy who said he wasn&#039;t going to sleep
under the bridge. You&#039;re going to have trouble in this country if you don&#039;t
start to equalize and give people a job. Look at the Mormons this week. Billions
of dollars. They&#039;re opening up a new shopping center there. The Mormon Church is
the richest church. They&#039;re richer than the Catholic now. Now we&#039;re going to put
a head of the Mormon, or the head of the church, president?

DREW: Also, another thing. I don&#039;t believe in religion.

GAINES: Oh, no. Take religion away.

DREW: I&#039;m not religious. I can&#039;t understand it.

GAINES: I can&#039;t understand religion either.

DREW: When blacks came over here as slaves, the Christian religion didn&#039;t exist.
The people in West Africa, they had totally different religions. They came over
here, and to pacify the slave, maybe if we take him to church, let him stand in
the back -- you stood. You didn&#039;t sit in the back of the church, you stood in
the back of the church. Take a look at the Bible. Find me one thing where it
says something good about a black in there. Nothing. Everything that they say
about blacks is bad.

GAINES: Let me tell you something about religion. I used to be a Christian. What
do you mean, used to be a Christian? Here&#039;s what [I mean]. The Christian
religion is the best thing in the world, but hypocrisy has taken over the
Christian religion. I believe in the teachings of Jesus. The best teachings that
were ever given, love your neighbor as yourself.

DREW: But Jesus wasn&#039;t a Christian. He was a Jew.

GAINES: What did I say? Listen. Listen. I believe the teachings of Jesus. I was
talking to an African doctor, the biggest doctor in Stockton. He&#039;s a heart
doctor. I went to him because I thought I had a little palpitation heart,
whatever. I asked him about my heart. He said, &quot;Whoever or whatever put this
body together was a smart person.&quot; Now, you&#039;re laughing. But how did we get
here? How did we get here? You see what happened the other day, didn&#039;t you? You
see when they got this thing to try to figure the big explosion?

REDMAN: Smash atoms together. Yeah, sure.

GAINES: They smashed atoms together. How do you know what happened on a distant
planet? Huh? We&#039;ve gotten so now we can take the heart out and put in another
heart. How do you think a person could do with putting in a new brain? Huh? It&#039;s
going to be possible someday.

DREW: Oh, of course. We&#039;ll substitute the whole body. The question you asked the
last time, you asked again, and I know it must be important to you, about the
students at Berkeley. Were they naïve or this type of thing? We have the same
situation today, only it&#039;s dealt with on a much larger scale. The kids go to
college, they go to school, they learn. They learn a lot of the things that they
were taught are not true. It was just opinion. Like today, you&#039;re told by the
politicians, especially the Republican politicians, they say, &quot;Those leftwing
schools, they go to those&quot; --

GAINES: California.

DREW: Like Stanford and University of California, Harvard and Columbia. Since
Obama went to school there, we know it is, but I&#039;ve never been able to quite
figure this one out. He&#039;s a communist, socialist.

GAINES: He&#039;s a Muslim first.

DREW: What&#039;s the other one? Hitler was a --

GAINES: A fascist.

DREW: A fascist. He&#039;s a --

REDMAN: Communist and fascist.

DREW: Communist, socialist, fascist. I&#039;m listening to Fox News, and who says
this? O&#039;Reilly. This is a half-way educated man.

GAINES: O&#039;Reilly&#039;s getting paid to say that.

DREW: With the student thing, the main reason that [this] comes down to the
students, because students learn -- what do they teach you in college? How to
think. To think. You don&#039;t accept, you think. You question. You write a paper.
You write your college paper, you don&#039;t just take -- or even when you get to
college, you&#039;re writing a theme on a book. For this story, we want you to write
a paper on this. So what do you do? If you&#039;re a half-way decent student, you&#039;d
say, this is one person&#039;s opinion. Let me go out and check on some other
opinion. That&#039;s three or four different opinions. I read these opinions and I
say, well, now, automatically, can&#039;t see this side, but these two here, they
have possibilities. So now, all of a sudden, I&#039;ve learned something new. That
teacher back in high school, my parents told me, what they told me, may not be
necessarily true, because these people are much more intelligent and
better-educated than my father was.

You&#039;ve got youngsters going to college and they&#039;re learning these things.
They&#039;re not going to segregated colleges. There are blacks in these colleges,
there&#039;s Indians, there&#039;s Mexicans, there&#039;s Filipinos, everybody in that college.
They&#039;re learning from each other. They&#039;re talking about what happened in his
community. &quot;Did you go home for the weekend?&quot; &quot;Yes, I went home.&quot; &quot;What did you
guys do?&quot; This is a white guy talking to a black guy. &quot;Oh, we did this. What did
you do?&quot; &quot;We did this, then we did something else.&quot; &quot;Oh my. Really? Was that
fun?&quot; &quot;Yeah.&quot; &quot;Well, you&#039;re going to have to come home to my house.&quot; They were
going back and forth. You&#039;ve got these things going back and forth. That was the
reason I made the statement earlier on about the greatest thing that we old
people could do for young people is just lie down and die.

But Berkeley, there were those who saw this. There was a parallel between what
was happening at Berkeley. There was a lot of students that demonstrated in
Berkeley, and they were members of our CORE group. Our CORE group was an
integrated group. Mostly we had these young people, and they were down there,
they were going to jail, they were getting beat up by the police, all these
types of things, because they saw what was happening. But then where I felt
really bad, and to this day I&#039;ll go to my grave with this guilt, when the Civil
Rights Movement was over, they declared the civil rights -- we won our civil
rights -- and the first thing that came to my mind, we haven&#039;t won anything.
They&#039;re talking about we had won our right to a job. We don&#039;t own anything.

GAINES: Look, there&#039;s one thing I wanted to mention when you asked me about the
whites participating in our activities for the NAACP. Here&#039;s one thing you have
to look at. Who is white? This is a problem that most white people don&#039;t
understand. The people that helped me, a lot of them, are black, but they
thought they were white.

DREW: The bourgeoisie.

GAINES: Not bourgeoisie. These people had crossed over the color line. Over
50,000 black people crossed over the color line.

DREW: More than that. Three hundred thousand per year passed.

GAINES: Passed over the color line.

DREW: Passed as white.

GAINES: One of my best friends here, one of the guys, had a big {flooring?}
company. He thought he was white. He&#039;d come down to the shop. I&#039;d close the
windows down at night and straighten his hair. With the barber. I straightened
his hair. I knew him very well. He owned the San Francisco {Flooring Company?}.
A lot of people that you don&#039;t know that&#039;s passed over the color line, and this
is what I&#039;m talking about. You don&#039;t know who is black. When I told you Warren
G. Harding was black -- I told my son, I say, &quot;I&#039;m named after the first black
president,&quot; the other day, the same one. He&#039;s very smart. So he got on his
computer and he was reading Warren G. Harding&#039;s background. When he got done, he
says, &quot;It was rumored that Warren G.&quot; --

DREW: It&#039;s always rumored.

GAINES: But look, look. It was rumored that Warren G. Harding was black, but his
four sisters were teachers in Washington, D.C. But you see what I mean, what I&#039;m
talking about? All of these people that you think are white, they&#039;re not white.
Look at Dinah Shore. Dinah Shore&#039;s mother was half-white. Who was her son? This
is what I&#039;m talking about.

DREW: The anthropologists during that period of time did some studying -- I
think it&#039;s from Vanderbilt -- I believe it&#039;s Vanderbilt -- they did some
studying of the South. They had all this racial tension going on. Blacks are
bad, whites are good. Blacks are bad, whites are good. You&#039;ve got, like you
said, all these mulattos, half-black, half-whites, this type of thing, people
around there. So they went down there and they start researching. Looking at
family trees. Somewhere along the line, we find out that his eighth cousin, his
eighth cousin removed, was black, and on down the line. Their conclusion was
that very few people in the South could say that they were white or that they
were black.

REDMAN: That creates a big problem, culturally, for the South, because, for
years, it&#039;s been the precedent of the so-called one-drop rule.

GAINES: I can tell you about that. You know the girl in San Francisco, she was
suing this millionaire to get her inheritance out of Louisiana. They took her
back to Louisiana and went through the records and in the books there.
One-sixteenth drop of blood makes you black. The other fifteen drops won&#039;t make
you white. This is the laws. I&#039;m back to the cranium. What is in the white
people&#039;s head that&#039;s racist that way, that makes them think -- they&#039;re still
98.1 [water and] organic substances, just like everything else. Why does it make
them think that they are [better]? Because they push themselves. Now, back to
University of California. The white person has found out one thing. Most of the
students are Asian. You understand? They&#039;ve got so many of them that they&#039;re
trying to keep them out.

DREW: They tried to pass a law in San Francisco to keep kids out at law.

REDMAN: I&#039;m going to flip these around. I was going to ask about the Black
Panther Party, but before I do that, can I ask about KKK in Stockton? Tell me --

DREW: It exists today.

REDMAN: Tell me about the KKK.

GAINES: I can tell you a lot about the KKK.

DREW: Go ahead.

GAINES: Because I appeared before the city council all the time when I was
working with [NAACP].

REDMAN: But I understand that you&#039;ve had a personal incident at your home.

GAINES: Absolutely. A personal incident at my home.REDMAN: That&#039;s maybe a safe
way to say it, &quot;an incident.&quot;

GAINES: I went to the city council and I was talking about the vultures in
Stockton. I call them vultures. That&#039;s the absentee landlords. The absentee
landlords that owned all the buildings downtown Stockton, all dilapidated
buildings that they&#039;d moved out of and they started moving north. They rented to
blacks, because we were on the certain part of town, then we were allowed to
move up across Main Street. I rented one of those buildings from the Franzia
Brothers Winery. I&#039;m a person they called. They didn&#039;t do anything for the
building. The health department wouldn&#039;t do anything for a restaurant across the
floor like that. One day -- this was in the barber shop -- my barber, Lorenzo
was there -- a rat ran across the floor. A big wood rat ran across the floor
like that. The customer jumped. He said, &quot;Man, there&#039;s a rat!&quot; Lorenzo said,
&quot;Oh, that&#039;s a pet rat. We raised him around here.&quot; Look, if a rat died in the
hall in my building, I had to tear the wall out, put spray and stuff in there.
These guys are millionaires and they wouldn&#039;t fix it up. You understand? Now,
when I say the vultures, the absentee landlords that owned all the rent houses
and things, didn&#039;t fix them up or nothing, the health department didn&#039;t -- same
thing today. But anyway, when I went up there, the KKK called me up over the
phone and said, &quot;Hey, nigger, we&#039;re gonna [get you].&quot; They shot at my house.
When they shot at my house first, I come out. Being a World War Two veteran, I
come out and shot back with my thirty-ought-six. Wasn&#039;t in the paper. Nothing
said about it. They didn&#039;t come out messing around my house anymore. But see,
this is what I&#039;m talking about.

REDMAN: Was this incident, may I ask, was that during the day? Was it at night?
Was it --

GAINES: Nighttime.

DREW: KKK is not going to do anything during the daytime. That&#039;s why they have
white sheets. I guess it&#039;s on your bed, you&#039;ve got a white sheet on there, so at
night --

GAINES: I can tell you about the white man&#039;s -- biggest army he&#039;s got. He has
the best army in the world and the biggest army, because he talks to the
ignorant whites. You know what his name is, let&#039;s. You know what let&#039;s is?
&quot;Let&#039;s get him&quot;. He may not go do anything himself. &quot;Let&#039;s get him.&quot;

DREW: Back to the KKK here in Stockton. You couldn&#039;t separate the KKK from the
police department, because there were so many -- the KKK was peopled by -- I
mean, the police department was peopled by the KKK, so there was no difference.
The police department lends legitimacy to the KKK.

GAINES: Do you know who the biggest KKK organization in the United States today
is? Think. Think. What is the biggest organization in the United States today
that says the same thing that the KKK says?

DREW: You wouldn&#039;t be talking about the Tea Party, would you?

GAINES: No. It&#039;s bigger than the Tea Party. I&#039;ll let you guess. Think a minute.

DREW: The Republican congress?

GAINES: No.

DREW: It can&#039;t be bigger than that unless you&#039;re talking about the Koch Brothers
and that.

GAINES: I&#039;m talking about the [National] Rifle Association.

DREW: Oh, yeah. Well, they --

GAINES: They&#039;re the KKK. &quot;We believe in the Second Amendment.&quot;

DREW: But they only have 1,300 representatives in Washington.

GAINES: Only 1,300. [laughter]

DREW: Thirteen hundred lobbyists. There&#039;s 1,300 lobbyists, if you can imagine that.

GAINES: That&#039;s the KKK.

DREW: That&#039;s National Rifle Association.

GAINES: National Rifle Association.

REDMAN: We have time for one more question on this tape. Tell me about how the
Black Panther Party is misunderstood by members of the public and why.

DREW: I was over there when the Black Panther was formed, the whole thing. Huey
Newton and [Bobby] Seale and the whole group. Oakland was such a racist city
that it was almost like being down South. You couldn&#039;t do anything. They would
shoot a black person. He was just dead. That was all there was to it. Even
today, it&#039;s true today. A policeman in Oakland is never going to be convicted of
killing a black person. They have never been, never will be.

GAINES: Same here [in Stockton].

DREW: It&#039;s just not going to happen. This was so prevalent in the black
community. Policemen are talking about shooting, about these gangs shooting.
Cops do that. They can shoot a person [and] they know nothing was going to
happen. These young men could be someone where they weren&#039;t going to take it
anymore. Plus, all the food programs and things that were designed for the
Oakland community went to the white school. So you&#039;ve got all these black kids,
some of them didn&#039;t have a meal all day long. They were expected to get up, go
to school, and learn, without having a single meal. Part of their program was
providing meals for these kids. They provided food for people. They did all
kinds of things. Initially, they didn&#039;t carry guns. When they started doing
this, the police started coming out, harassing them, shooting, this type of
thing. They said, okay, we&#039;ll have our guns for our protection. We&#039;re not going
to carry concealed weapons. We&#039;re going to stand here with our guns and we&#039;re
going to announce to the world, we&#039;re not aggressive. They never, ever
aggressively went after anyone. They never shot a policeman. But their position
was, we&#039;re here to defend ourselves and defend our own. That&#039;s all it was. The
press across the nation [reported that] you got these radical blacks out there,
they&#039;re threatening to kill everybody else. They&#039;re parading around with guns
and doing these black hand salutes and stuff like this here. They&#039;re dangerous.
Like today, even with Congress now talking about the new Black Panther Party.
You know how many members there are in the new Black Panther Party? Eight
people. There&#039;s eight people. Eight people, and it&#039;s dangerous. New Black
Panther Party is threatening to take over the nation. They can&#039;t even take over
a block. Couldn&#039;t even carjack.

REDMAN: With that, I need to pause and change tapes here.

REDMAN: Today is July 17. I&#039;m back with Mr. Drew and Mr. Gaines, and this is our
third tape today. When we left off, we were talking about the Black Panther
Party and how that is remembered or not remembered in terms of its impact in the
Bay Area. Mr. Drew had a chance to speak to that. Mr. Gaines, I&#039;d like to ask if
you would speak to that.

GAINES: Okay. I&#039;m just talking about the Black Panther Party? When they went to
Sacramento and marched around with their guns -- the guns were empty. They were
unloaded, the guns. Here&#039;s what I have to say about the whole thing, is if you
can keep your head about your losing theirs and blame it on you, if you trust
yourself when all men -- that&#039;s &quot;If&quot; by Rudyard Kipling. But here&#039;s what I say.
If rabbits had guns, how many people would hunt rabbits? Huh? You&#039;re smiling.

REDMAN: That&#039;s a great point. You&#039;re right.

GAINES: All right. If black folks protect themselves and start shooting back,
you won&#039;t have no problems. But as long as you don&#039;t have no guns and they have
all the guns -- now, what he and I were talking about, what you were talking
about, when you asked us about the Black Panther Party. Here&#039;s what destroyed
the Civil Rights Movement, redevelopment. Redevelopment destroyed the black
community. It wasn&#039;t redevelopment. It was black removal. Now here&#039;s what
happened. Like they did in Oakland, like they did in San Francisco, like they
did in Stockton, California, Oklahoma City, and Memphis, Tennessee, they took
and run the freeway right through the black businesses. In Stockton, California,
we had fourteen service stations, we had grocery stores, we had drugstores, we
had hotels. This is the community I live in. We had one hotel, was seventeen
stories high. What did they do? They run the freeway right down, wiped out all
the black hotel owners. I moved four times, moved my barber shop. The last time
I moved, I moved and bought a corner lot on Airport Way and Main. They tore down
all those buildings. In Memphis, Tennessee, they run the freeway right down
Beale Street and wiped out half the black businesses. In Montgomery, Alabama,
Gaston had an eighteen-story building. They tore it down, wiped it out. They&#039;d
run the integration and the urban renewal, or black removal, destroyed all the
black businesses. The same thing that happened now happened in Tulsa, Oklahoma.
Black Wall Street had thirty-six square blocks of black businesses. They
destroyed them. They sent to Oklahoma City in Piper Cubs and flew over Tulsa and
dropped Molotov cocktails and set the whole thing on fire. But you don&#039;t find
this in your history books.

DREW: Those were government planes, by the way.

REDMAN: This brings up a good point in terms of we talked about sort of the
reflection at the end of the Civil Rights Movement, quote unquote, &quot;the end of
the Civil Rights Movement,&quot; in terms of what are we left with. What&#039;s
interesting to me is that you&#039;ve got the Civil Rights Act. LBJ passes the Civil
Rights Act. Someone might be inclined to read this as, oh, this is this major
advance, but then in 1965, a reminder of how life really is, there&#039;s a major
race riot in Watts, Los Angeles.

DREW: That brings back another point. The riots in Watts, these were just
symptoms of things that were going on. At one time, it was sort of an unwritten
thing that police could brutalize blacks and get away with this type of thing,
and so they would do it wink-wink. They go out and take this guy out of his car,
beat him up, wink, wink, wink, wink. Now we don&#039;t have to do that. With home
security and all this type of thing, now they say the policemen have a right to
do anything. White people don&#039;t realize that this affects them, too. One time,
if you were stopped in your car, there was only three ways they could search
your car. You gave them permission. Number two, they had to have reasonable
cause, or a court order. That&#039;s the only way they could search your car.
Otherwise, they could keep you there for three days if they had to go get a
court order to do it. You said no, they had to get a court order. Now they don&#039;t
[require a court order]. You can leave here right now, drive down the street,
policeman stop you and you haven&#039;t done anything, he can tell you to get out of
your car. &quot;Stand back there, we&#039;re going to search your car.&quot; &quot;But, but, but&quot; --
&quot;No buts. Are you questioning me? Because if you question me, I can take you to
jail.&quot; We have come to that.

When the Civil Rights Movement came to an end, and LBJ and the whole thing -- I
love LBJ. He&#039;s one of my favorite presidents. From his position, he did
something absolutely great. But see, blacks, we were bamboozled. As Malcolm X
said, we were bamboozled. We were led to believe, all the sudden, everything is
going to be great. Everything is going to be wonderful. We didn&#039;t realize
everything was great and everything was wonderful before this. When we had our
own little communities, we were thriving. We were getting bigger, because the
people over here on the edge of this community, they were unable to what they
call block-busting. If we wanted to move out further, all we had to do was
arrange for some white person to buy a house in that area. The black person move
into the house, then all of a sudden, &quot;The blacks are taking over this
community. Let&#039;s go.&quot; There was flight. Now we have another couple blocks to add
on to it, so we could always grow if we wanted to. But when the Civil Rights
Movement was over, I was lying there thinking, oh, this is great. We&#039;ve done all
this great work and everything. Then it dawned on me, we own nothing.

GAINES: We lost. We lost. We lost.

DREW: We lost what we had. We owned nothing. I worked for months putting
together a scheme. I [thought], what we could do, we don&#039;t have a lot of money
to start all these businesses and everything. What if every black person in the
country bought stock in whatever company we call it? We call it, say, Company X.
Every black person bought -- who could afford -- just put ten dollars. Even
welfare recipients could afford ten dollars. You buy ten dollars&#039; worth of
stock. Not donate ten dollars. Ten dollars&#039; worth of stock. We&#039;d put this money
in certain banks, like the bank of Harlem or Chicago bank, and we&#039;d give it a
deadline. We&#039;re going to raise a certain amount of money by this deadline. If we
don&#039;t, we&#039;re going to return your money to you with whatever interest is
accrued. But if we reach that point, we are going to start building black
businesses. We know we can&#039;t go out and build the biggest businesses. We&#039;re
going to start with garages, small. The thing about success, once you show that
there&#039;s success; people want to buy in to success. That piece of stock that you
bought is now worth so much more. My money helped me buy that service station
down there. By now, god knows where we would be. I talk to people about this. I
talk to Bill Russell and Jim --

GAINES: This is one thing that perturbs me, but I can understand it. The first
thing they did after the Civil Rights Movement was supposed to be over, which it
never will be over, they were supposed to treat you equally. When I started my
business, I wanted to borrow some money to build [it]. I had been moved four
times under urban renewal, black removal, and I bought me a lot. I bought a
corner lot. It cost me $25,000. I didn&#039;t pay for it, because I was being paid
cash for it. The way I got it, I told this lady -- she&#039;s a Jewish lady, and I
told her I wanted to open up a business, and she says, &quot;How much money you got?&quot;
I said, &quot;I don&#039;t have much money now, because,&quot; I say, &quot;I&#039;m working two jobs.
Running a business and I would like to open up a grocery store.&quot; She says, &quot;I&#039;ll
let you have a lot.&quot; She says, &quot;How much are you going to pay down on?&quot; I said,
&quot;How much you want down?&quot; She said, &quot;Oh, you give as little as you want.&quot; I
said, &quot;I don&#039;t have much money. I could give you a thousand dollars down.&quot; She
said, &quot;That would be all right.&quot; I said, &quot;How much would the interest be?&quot; She
said, &quot;It would be 10.5.&quot; I listened. &quot;Mm-hmm. Yeah. That would be fine.&quot; I
said, &quot;But here&#039;s one thing I would like to do. I would like to pay on the
principal without paying on the interest.&quot; She said, &quot;I&#039;ll give you twenty
years.&quot; I said, &quot;That would be fine.&quot; She thought it over. I have her fooled. I
had the mask on. My wife was working. She&#039;s a teacher. I worked in a barber
shop, had my barber shop. Guy working for me. Then I worked longshoreman, too. I
paid her off in two years. She flew up high, because she lost that eleven or
twelve thousand dollars interest.

DREW: See, that&#039;s where not only black people get bamboozled, white people, too.
Until recently --

GAINES: Wait, wait, let me finish. When I got the permit to build my building, I
go down to get a permit to build a business, the guy says to me, building
inspector -- I had built several houses, rent houses that I had built with my
own two hands -- I says, &quot;I want to get a permit to build this building.&quot; He
says, &quot;You can&#039;t get a permit. This is a public building. You can&#039;t get a
permit.&quot; I said, &quot;Why?&quot; He said, &quot;Because I say so.&quot; He was the building
inspector. White boy. A little short white boy, skinny nose, funny-looking
fellow. But anyway, I said, &quot;I&#039;m going to my attorney.&quot; I went to my attorney
and I said -- Jack Dozer was my attorney -- I said, &quot;Hey, Jack, I want you to
tell me what article in the city charter says that I can&#039;t be the general
contractor and hire subcontractors if I&#039;m going to own the building.&quot; He called
down there. He says, &quot;I have a client by the name of Warren Gaines that says he
wants to build a building. What article in the city charter says&quot; -- &quot;Oh, send
him right on back down.&quot; Found out later on, Burger King wanted that lot. So he
was working with them, and they offered me $87,000 for the lot. I told them to
-- you understand? But you see, here&#039;s what you have to understand. The
atrocities that&#039;s been conflicted upon the African Americans in this country is
beyond the human imagination. You couldn&#039;t imagine the things that we go through --

DREW: I see you [Redman] sitting there sometimes, the things we say, you sit
there like, I don&#039;t really believe that.

GAINES: He understands. This guy understands.

DREW: No, there&#039;s a lot of things he can&#039;t [understand]. You&#039;d have to be black.
You would have to be black to understand.

GAINES: He&#039;s beginning to understand.

DREW: Black people don&#039;t understand white people better than -- better than.
They don&#039;t totally understand white people.

GAINES: Do you know the reason I can talk to him freely? He&#039;s read Frantz
Fanon&#039;s We Wear the Mask.

DREW: I don&#039;t care how many volumes of black history he&#039;s read. I can tell by
the look in his eyes, he&#039;s sitting there and he&#039;s saying -- he&#039;s trying to
figure out, how could that happen? How could people do that? How can people
still live through that? You asked me the question the last time about if I had
to go back through this again. I told you, no, if I knew this was going to
happen to me, I had to go back through it again, I would kill myself early on.

GAINES: No, I wouldn&#039;t. I wouldn&#039;t.

DREW: You know why? If I had a vision, I think if I was twenty years old and I
was told, &quot;Now, when you get to be eighty-two years old, all these things will
have happened to you,&quot; I would sit there and I would say, &quot;Holy cow. I can&#039;t
deal with that.&quot;

GAINES: The reason why I couldn&#039;t agree with him -- you see this? A hundred and
forty-six years ago, my dad looked down and seen what his kids would do, and
this is what I&#039;m talking about what my son can [do]. I&#039;m living on the
{inaudible} putting this into my son, and then my son will put it in, and we
will continue to evaluate and get stronger. The generations that follow me will
have our teachings in them. All of our stuff didn&#039;t die with slavery. You can&#039;t
hold us down. They&#039;re going to try.

DREW: After all this time, the slavery mentality, slave mentality, still exists.
It sticks --

GAINES: There&#039;s hope. Like they say, where there&#039;s life, there&#039;s hope. They say,
where there&#039;s trees, there&#039;s ropes.

DREW: Basically, psychologically, that&#039;s exactly what it is today.
Psychologically --

GAINES: Where there&#039;s trees, there&#039;s ropes. [laughter]

DREW: As long as you are a minority, and you don&#039;t control the money and
everything -- it&#039;s all about the money. The thing about it, like I said earlier
on, poor white people are bigger victims than blacks, because they have been
bamboozled into believing, you can become rich. Like today, what they tell you.
You&#039;ve got these poor white people who are saying that they shouldn&#039;t raise the
tax on this [top] 1 percent.

REDMAN: I asked last time about one thing that surprised me, and I asked you
maybe at the wrong moment. I asked you, Mr. Drew, I asked you about anger, and
if some of the racism that you encountered, and some of the nasty things that
people would say, made you angry. I was surprised [at the time[, but your answer
makes sense. It was that you didn&#039;t have time to be angry, because you were
thinking about where you were going to sleep that night and where you were going
to get your next meal.

DREW: That&#039;s blacks. Blacks are docile. The worst thing that ever happened in
this country, the very worst thing, in my opinion, my humble opinion, that ever
happened to black people, was Christianity. Christianity. Now we are more
religious than any white group in the world. We can rationalize everything. This
thing was so ridiculous that during the Civil Rights Movement, before it
started, down South, they brought these black people into court because they had
demonstrated or something. They got this white judge. You probably read about
it. These black people were standing there, and this judge is reading all this
racial hatred, spewing out this racial hatred, to the point where he had a heart
attack. It&#039;s true. He had a heart attack. Know what happened? The black people
that he was putting in jail came over and got down around him and prayed for
him. He died, of course. Black people, the first thing that we --

GAINES: A lot of humility.

DREW: Yes. We rationalize everything, like Christianity. Like I said, they have
nothing good said in the Bible about black people. No version of it. I think
there&#039;s been like forty-something different versions of the Bible. Talk about
being racist or segregationist. They took out twenty-nine chapters, because
primarily it involved Jews or it was written by Greeks. True.

REDMAN: Tell me about your thoughts on black leadership after Martin Luther
King. One name that jumps out, of course, is Jesse Jackson. There are many more.
What are [your] thoughts on black leadership?

GAINES: Black leadership? That all depends on who you&#039;re talking about
leadership. See, my black leadership man would be different than all you guys. I
considered Malcolm X a black leader, because he was for the right thing. You&#039;re
talking about picking up arms, no? Defending yourself.

REDMAN: But that thinking is largely absent from the next generation that came
along in the seventies and eighties.

DREW: But it wasn&#039;t so much generation came along. Like I said, blacks had been
fully indoctrinated, even those who could understand the unfairness and all this
type of thing. But they had these so-called Christian values, which I don&#039;t know
what they are to this day. I have no idea what they are. We don&#039;t want to hurt
anybody. They&#039;ve been told that you do good, you do right, you&#039;re going to go to
heaven. You&#039;re going to get yours in heaven. But that is telling him, that is
stealing everything he can get. Well, I&#039;m not too sure about heaven. I&#039;ll
sacrifice going to heaven to make sure I have a good time down here. But then
they go and they read. It says, well, man was born in sin, and no matter what he
does, he&#039;s going to die in sin, and you can&#039;t get into heaven if you&#039;re a
sinner. I can&#039;t figure this stuff out. Like [Gaines] says [about] his pea brain.
My miniscule brain can&#039;t deal with all these complex things.

GAINES: What he&#039;s talking about, it makes a lot of sense. You heard me say I
believe in Malcolm X. He taught blacks wanted to get their own businesses and
everything. You can&#039;t get away from that. He taught one thing that I teach:
don&#039;t let nobody push you around. You understand that? He also taught that. But
I couldn&#039;t be a Muslim, because Muslims were the big slave traders in Africa. In
the Muslim religion, they took black girls out of Nubia, brought them down to
Saudi Arabia, young girls, and Ibn Saad had forty black sons. You understand? He
had maybe a hundred eunuchs that he had castrated, young blacks, to run his
compound. So how in hell I&#039;m going to be a Muslim? You understand? Although
Sonni Ali who went across Spain -- he was black, he was a Muslim -- went across
Spain, all the way to Portugal. The last city in Alhambra was built in Spain by
Sunni Ali. That&#039;s the reason the Portuguese language is the hardest language in
the world, because it&#039;s mixed with Africa, Latin, and so forth. But you have to
know who you are. That&#039;s why I say I know who I am. Just like I taught those
Africans, here&#039;s the key to the whole thing. Ignorance. Africa, by 2020, will
have a billion people in it. There are thirty-something states in it.

DREW: Forty-two.

GAINES: Forty-two. Do you know that literacy rate is only 14 percent? Eighty-six
percent illiterate people in Africa. Now, the Chinese have gone in there now and
they&#039;re building schools. They ask the Chinese, &quot;Why are you building schools
and roads?&quot; They say, &quot;We want people to be able to trade with us.&quot; But the
Europeans come in there and took the stuff out. You understand?

REDMAN: Two more questions. One, jumping forward again in time, in 1983, Harold
Washington is elected the mayor of Chicago. Does this do anything for black
politicians? Does this send a signal into the black community in any --

GAINES: It did, it did. It helped the black community.

DREW: In Chicago.

GAINES: In Chicago. In Chicago, because you couldn&#039;t go to Cicero. Blacks
couldn&#039;t go to Cicero. They&#039;d kill you if you go over to Cicero. The Italians
were --

DREW: Or any of the towns around Chicago.

GAINES: In Chicago, you had the polacks on one side. One thing about Harold
Washington, he appointed my niece as a judge there, and she just retired. Her
son is the state senator, and she&#039;s in the politics. I called her up on the
phone. I said, &quot;You&#039;re not going to jail, are you?&quot; I said, &quot;That other fellow,
the governor went to jail.&quot; Now Jesse Jackson, Jr. is in trouble. They say he&#039;s
having a nervous breakdown, but I think he&#039;s scared, because here&#039;s what
happened. Jesse Jackson, Jr. wanted to get that appointment. If he&#039;d had got the
appointment to the senator, my nephew would have been appointed to his position
as being congressman. But my nephew is still the state senator. Politics in this
country runs the whole country. It&#039;s politics.

DREW: Chicago politics is totally different from elsewhere. Like today, you hear
the Republicans talk about Chicago-style politicians. What does that mean? That
means that that period of time in America, Chicago is one of the few places in
the country where blacks were involved in politics. The black -- what do they
call it? Not ward, but the districts. Ward healers. They called them ward
healers. It was the leaders of these particular wards. You would move up. You&#039;d
sit there long enough, all these black areas, they would move up. They would
become a part of the city government. That&#039;s why the Chicago politicians have
been given more grief than any other city in this country.

GAINES: They&#039;ll put their gun to your head, too. Shit.

REDMAN: The last question I want to ask -- this is a big question, considering
the entire scope of your lives and the experiences that you&#039;ve been through.
With the election of Obama, I wonder -- some of the discussion that was taking
place. We&#039;ve talked a little bit about some of the problems that stem up when
people say, &quot;The Civil Rights Movement is over,&quot; or, when Obama was elected,
people talked about, &quot;Oh, now we&#039;re in a post-racial America.&quot; We see that
that&#039;s a naïve assumption. But can you tell me -- take a step back to 2008 --
how did you both think and feel when it finally came true? When it finally
happened, when Obama was finally elected, how did that affect you both personally?

DREW: Me, it affected me in that it was nice. It was nice to see him as
president. But I realized it was just a smoke screen. What was happening prior
to that, football. You had the Chicago Bears was down the tube. The Cincinnati
Bengals and these others teams weren&#039;t going anywhere. The white coaches didn&#039;t
want the job. Who did they hire? They went out and hired these black coaches.
They never coached before. They&#039;re assistant coaches. Please save our teams.
Like the guy that became coach of Indianapolis.

REDMAN: Oh, the Colts. Oh, what&#039;s his name? He won the Super Bowl.

DREW: Yes, won the Super Bowl.

REDMAN: Tony.

DREW: Tony Dungy.

REDMAN: Tony Dungy.

DREW: Dungy had the job down there with a team in Florida [Tampa Bay Buccaneers]
before that. The team had never won anything. They had never even broken even
one time. Nobody wanted the job. Dungy was an assistant coach and they gave him
the job. Dungy turned this team around, and they never had a losing team after
that. He kept forcing the owner to get the parts that he wanted. They would
draft them and this type of thing. Finally, he said, &quot;I&#039;ve got all the parts
that I want. Next year, we&#039;re going to win the Super Bowl.&quot; You know what
happened? They fired him. Then they hired the guy that was coach of Oakland, and
they won the Super Bowl. The players on the team were so enthralled by winning,
they wanted to vote Dungy a share of the winning money. But the rules prohibit,
because he was already coach of Indianapolis. The same thing with the President
[of the United States]. This country was going down the tubes. We&#039;re headed for
the biggest recession. Bush is taking us to the biggest recession ever. Who
wants the job, [John] McCain wants the job. Before 1999, I liked McCain. Back
[in 2000] when he ran against Bush to become the Republican nominee, I switched
over and literally voted for McCain. Most of the people on the Republican side,
they didn&#039;t like McCain, because McCain&#039;s position to that point was the
country. If it was a good idea, okay, me and [Joseph] Lieberman, we&#039;ll get
together and we will hammer out a good -- we&#039;re going to make this work.

REDMAN: But he moved away from that [after] 2000.

DREW: In 2008, he moved away from that. Two thousand, actually. He saw that if
Bush can get voted in with the things that he&#039;s saying, that&#039;s the only way you
can get elected. So he changed. You see what you have today.

REDMAN: Back to Obama, Mr. Gaines.

GAINES: Obama is a good man. Well-educated. Knows the law, knows everything. He
got in. I&#039;m glad to see him get in there, president, because we needed somebody
with some sense in there. Bush was a numskull. We know that. He&#039;s a drunk and
everything else. I don&#039;t know what else he did. But he had money, see. Obama
didn&#039;t have anything. He come along, he wanted to do the right thing for
America. The things that he&#039;s accomplished, they don&#039;t even talk about it.

DREW: He doesn&#039;t talk so that people understand it.

GAINES: They don&#039;t want to talk about him capturing and killing Bin Laden. They
don&#039;t want to talk about how he wiped out the people with the bombs over there
in --

REDMAN: Afghanistan.

GAINES: Not Afghanistan.

DREW: In Pakistan.

GAINES: Pakistan. What he&#039;s doing now, he ended the war over there. Now he wants
to end the war over in Afghanistan, but Afghanistan is the survival of America.
What are you talking about, Gaines? I&#039;m talking about arms, ammunition,
supplies. It&#039;s a good thing to keep the country going. That&#039;s the same thing
that happened in Iraq. You understand? It&#039;s a business. It&#039;s a business.

DREW: It&#039;s a business. Halliburton and --

GAINES: Now, what he wants to do, they&#039;re going to call it socialism. What he
wants to do, he wants to put Medicare in there. Right now, if you&#039;ve got to have
a certain kind of pill, it will cost you fourteen, sixteen dollars for one pill.

DREW: More than that, some of them.

GAINES: You understand? See, he&#039;s trying to get something for the people.
They&#039;re going to call him a socialist or whatever. But what I&#039;m talking about
now is you watch this country -- I may not live to see it -- this country is
going to go different than what it is, a capitalistic society, today, because
you can&#039;t have 350 million people and only about 10 or 12 percent of them are
living good. You understand? You&#039;re going to have a social revolution, and I
hope we don&#039;t have a violent revolution.

REDMAN: If you could tell a student of history, twenty-five years from now,
fifty years from now, a hundred years from now, anything about your story and
your life, what would be the things that you would point to?

DREW: Nothing. Because he wouldn&#039;t believe it.REDMAN: You think people will read
this and they won&#039;t believe the story?

DREW: No --

REDMAN: One of the other things, too, you said it&#039;s impossible to understand the
full extent of the pain, and I want to hear a little bit about that, too.

DREW: That&#039;s a great question. If something is done to you, no matter what it
is, from the day you&#039;re born until the day you die, it&#039;s repetitive. Over and
over and over and over again. After a while, you become [de]sensitized to it. It
becomes a way of life. The same thing that I would probably walk away from,
you&#039;d be ready to, &quot;I&#039;ll knock your block off.&quot; Believe it or not, eighty-two
years, I&#039;ve never had a fight. I&#039;ve never had a physical confrontation. Never
found it necessary. I embarrass people. I could hurt them with words worse than
I could ever do with hit -- they want to hit me? Go on, hit me. I don&#039;t care.
The only thing that&#039;s going to happen is I&#039;m going to get a broken jaw and
you&#039;re going to get a sore hand. I say, &quot;I know you can beat me.&quot; Or even if he
couldn&#039;t, I d {inaudible}. &quot;Oh, this nigger&#039;s crazy.&quot; And he walk away. But
twenty-five years from now, maybe they would believe me, because I don&#039;t see
things changing that much in the next twenty-five years. I really don&#039;t, because
things are going south now. The gains that they claim that we made in the
sixties, this type of thing, they&#039;re now being all tossed out. Women&#039;s rights
are now going. You hear even our Supreme Court justices, Scalia, Thomas, talk
about going back to -- in fact, Scalia and Thomas, they&#039;ve got to be -- I don&#039;t
know how these people can be judges.

GAINES: You&#039;re making my stomach hurt. [laughter]

DREW: These have to be two of the most ignorant judges that we&#039;ve ever had.

GAINES: You&#039;re making my stomach hurt.

DREW: Literally. They said we should go back to the Constitution days, back to
the days of the Constitution. Thomas doesn&#039;t realize that the days of the
Constitution, not only would he not be a judge, he&#039;d be out there working the
fields. Scalia, being an Italian, he couldn&#039;t even come to the country.

REDMAN: Mr. Gaines, what would you say to a student twenty-five or fifty years
from now?

GAINES: I&#039;d have them read my book. That&#039;s the first thing I would do, because
it tells the whole story of my life. There&#039;s hope. I teach my kids the same thing.

DREW: There&#039;s rope. [laughter]

GAINES: Where there&#039;s trees, there&#039;s rope. I believe this. Without progress, we
don&#039;t advance. [Just] two words, progress and advancing. Through education and
ownership, you can advance. But you can&#039;t stay in that same hole and expect to
get freedom. What I mean is total freedom. You&#039;ve got to have all of these
things, these three things that&#039;s all you need, and then advance. Listen, we
live in a society where you have to have money. You can&#039;t get money unless you
have means to get it besides robbery. We know the people at the top are robbing
you, because any time that you have gone and paid 31 percent on a credit card,
if you&#039;re stupid enough to have a credit card, then you&#039;re stupid enough to be
ignorant enough to stay in that same hole the rest of your life. You understand?
I try to teach my kids. The legacy that I try to leave is the same legacy as my
father left for me, and it&#039;s going on down through my grandkids and great
grandkids. Teach them this. You can&#039;t be this way and have a heart in you to
where you have separation in races. All people are the same, just like I said.
Ninety-eight point water and two points organic substances. That&#039;s it. So what
you do, have respect for everyone. You understand? Now, so far as religion is
concerned, choose a religion that you want that doesn&#039;t make me any different.
Because whatever you want to believe, that&#039;s your belief, but don&#039;t treat your
fellow man wrong. That&#039;s the wrong thing to do. Do unto others before they do it
to you.

DREW: We were discussing religion, and I said if I was going to form a religion,
I would call it &quot;Do unto others as you would have them do unto you&quot; religion.
That would be the name of the religion.

REDMAN: I missed something fundamental and so silly. Can you tell the story of
how you two met?

DREW: How did we meet?

GAINES: I don&#039;t know.

DREW: NAACP I guess it was.

GAINES: When I first met him, he was working for the city then. When did you
work for the city?

DREW: To give you an idea of how racist Stockton was, I went to college, got a
job as -- what?

GAINES: What were you doing?

DREW: Assistant --

GAINES: Janitor.

DREW: Assistant librarian. People don&#039;t even know who a librarian is. They put a
picture of me in the newspaper. This black guy is assistant librarian.

GAINES: He went to Cal, see.

DREW: You know what my job was at the library?

REDMAN: What&#039;s that?

DREW: You couldn&#039;t be out front if you were black. You couldn&#039;t be at the desk.
So I didn&#039;t wait on anybody. I would put books on the shelves and I&#039;d wipe dust.
This was my assistant library job. That was it. But just one more point, if I
may. You were talking about education. You kept emphasizing education,
education. But then we look at the country as a whole. We are declining
education-wise, continually. What was it? The last survey they took, national
survey -- I mean, a world survey they took -- we have now dropped to seventeenth
in math and science degrees. We have dropped down. We were the world&#039;s leader at
one time in education. We are no longer. We are seventh and dropping. Just a
year ago, we were fifth. Now we&#039;re down to seven, and dropping. Statistics, not
too long ago, eighth-grade math education in this country, math education among
the average eighth-grade public school student was so bad that it was declared
that eighth-grade math was to be considered math illiteracy. We are that bad. A
lot of areas, we&#039;re so bad that we don&#039;t have them anymore. English. When it
comes to learning sentence structure, parsing sentences and all this type of
thing, it doesn&#039;t exist anymore. Teachers don&#039;t even know how to do it. They
don&#039;t have to know how to do it.

GAINES: Diagram a sentence. They couldn&#039;t do it.

DREW: Can&#039;t do that. When it comes to learning how to write, printing is fine.
You don&#039;t have to learn how to write anymore. It&#039;s not going to be taught any
longer. We are getting dumber and dumber and dumber. We are still operating
schools the same way we did a hundred and fifty years ago on the agrarian
system, when summers was needed for kids to work in the field. Now it&#039;s no
longer needed. We&#039;re still doing the same thing. European schools, especially
Scandinavian schools, they&#039;re so far advanced, they have reached the point where
a child is interested in a particular area. If you&#039;re interested in computers,
we have schools designed for you to learn computers. You learn all these other
things. You&#039;re learning the Norwegian language and all this math and all this
kind of stuff, but you&#039;re also learning about the field you&#039;re interested in. In
Ohio, Illinois, some years back, the high school dropout rate was the lowest in
the country. It dropped down to 49.5 percent. They said, what can we do to
change this? So they went around and they were talking with kids. &quot;Why did you
drop out of school? Why did you drop out of school?&quot; This type of thing. &quot;I
don&#039;t see any reason why I should go to school. I&#039;m not going to college, so why
should I go to school?&quot; Like I said earlier, nothing I&#039;m learning in high school
is going to help me once I get out of school. So they decided, well, what we
will do, we will teach the regular curriculum during the first half of the day.
In the evening, we will steer this child into whatever it is he&#039;s interested in.
If he&#039;s interested in mechanics, we will find some elite garages, and we will,
the board of education will, give them money to teach this child how to become a
mechanic. Same thing in the medical field, whatever area. Within a few years,
the dropout rate had gone from 49.5 percent, and now the graduating student rate
was 60 percent, which was based on the European system. You tell them that --
talking to them about 60 percent dropout rate. &quot;Are you crazy?&quot; What is a 60
percent --

GAINES: What you&#039;re talking about is true, but he wanted to know about -- your
perspective, what you told him, was right. But now here&#039;s what I see about --
the whole thing is based upon education, and that&#039;s the reason that I teach my
kids this. I teach my children this. You have to have an education. It has to be
academic or vocational or business.

DREW: Let me stop you here. How many Gaines are there out there? How many
non-Gaines are there out there?

GAINES: But this is what I&#039;m talking about. This is what I&#039;m talking about.
Here&#039;s where you get sidetracked with education. You put entertainers in our
group of people. You put entertainers as our leaders. Like --

DREW: Jay-Z.

GAINES: Jay-Z. Not him. I&#039;m talking about entertainers. Football players.
Basketball. Baseball players. Entertainers.

DREW: The people in sports, role models.

GAINES: They don&#039;t have to invest any money. They don&#039;t do a damn thing. Ninety
percent of them can&#039;t read on a high school level. My kids don&#039;t have no
football, baseball, basketball, track. They don&#039;t do that. Because if you&#039;re not
the top, you don&#039;t get there. Look. The only ones that do, prosper, and you
don&#039;t hear of them. The mayor of Detroit now.

DREW: [Dave] Bing.

GAINES: Bing. But you know what he had? He has a steel mill. Work 800 people.

DREW: Five of them. His four daughters that head four of them, and he heads
one.GAINES: You see, this is what I&#039;m talking about. Now they talk about this
numskull up there now. He&#039;s a basketball player. A hundred and fifty million
dollars a year. He doesn&#039;t know how to tie his shoe so far as I&#039;m concerned.

DREW: He knows how to buy wheels.

GAINES: Because what could he do with $150 million? He could open up some
enterprises. Look at that other fool down there. He got thirty-something cars.

DREW: And shoes. A whole room designed for nothing but shoes.

REDMAN: It doesn&#039;t make any sense.

DREW: It makes no sense.

GAINES: It doesn&#039;t make any sense at all. Like I told this lady yesterday --
she&#039;s a professional woman. I was telling her about investing your money. She&#039;s
an insurance lady. She and I are good friends. I was going to change my
insurance to {inaudible}. I told her, I says, &quot;The average person don&#039;t
understand business. They don&#039;t understand interest and percentages.&quot; Here you
put your money in the bank, draw 0.5 percent on it. Maybe you draw 2 percent on
your money. I told her, I said, &quot;Look, people with brains invest their money
where it&#039;s going to make the best money.&quot; I said, &quot;Now you look at your
insurance company. You&#039;re with AAA.&quot; I said, &quot;Look at Omaha, Nebraska.&quot; We have
a place here, have 240 apartment houses in the ghetto. They&#039;re all rented.

DREW: Projects.

GAINES: Project houses. You know who owns it? Omaha, Nebraska [Mutual of Omaha].
Now, look. If you take your money that you have now saved up, and put it in the
banks, and you draw 1 percent, 1.5 percent, take that same money, buy you a
duplex, when you get it paid for, you get 80 percent profit. Twenty percent
upkeep. That is deductible from your income tax. You&#039;re making a 90 percent
profit. People don&#039;t understand this country is built on money. Now, the people
that run this country, like your future president --

DREW: Like you&#039;re saying, but all these people come from the same universities.
It&#039;s a repetitive thing, same --

GAINES: But they know how to manipulate that money.

DREW: Of course they do. That&#039;s what they learn in college.

GAINES: Look. Here&#039;s what&#039;s going to happen. Men running around with three
houses here and a house there like that, all that money, someday, somebody&#039;s
going to come up with a party -- not like the Tea Party -- they&#039;re going to
destroy all these millionaires is doing. Democracy won&#039;t be the same. Guys like
-- what&#039;s his name, with the [National] Rifle Association?

DREW: Oh, yeah.

GAINES: Down here at Carmel. He&#039;ll be dead.

DREW: He is dead. Didn&#039;t he die?

GAINES: Not yet. That movie actor [Charlton Heston 1923-2008].

DREW: I thought he [died].

REDMAN: Is he still alive? He might still be kicking around.

GAINES: He played Moses in --

DREW: Moses, yes.

REDMAN: With that, gentlemen, I&#039;d like to say thank you both for participating
and sitting down and sharing your memories. Thank you.

GAINES: I enjoyed listening to my buddy here talk. He and I went through a lot.
Hey, man, we know -- listen. When you talk to us, we&#039;re going to give you the
straight facts. About these bourgeois blacks, they don&#039;t mean shit to us. They don&#039;t.

DREW: See, the difference, the reason I keep emphasizing the thirty million
people that are illiterate, these are people that are lost. I don&#039;t care what
kind of business you&#039;ve got or what it is. You&#039;re lost. You&#039;re incapable of
really learning anything. Like politics today. These adults, most of them are
going to vote. Thirty million illiterate people going to the poll.GAINES: Tell
him about your buddy Bill Cosby.

DREW: Bill Cosby. He goes around, and he talks about the people should be
ashamed of themselves in the ghetto. They&#039;re not getting an education, they&#039;re
not doing this. But then I asked a question, &quot;When&#039;s the last time you&#039;ve been
down there to help out? When&#039;s the last time you went down there to educate
someone?&quot; &quot;Well, I gave twenty-three million dollars to my alma mater, Temple
University.&quot; Big deal. You&#039;re going to give to Temple University, you&#039;d have
paid it in tax, so what&#039;s the big deal? What have you done for the people down
in the ghetto? This community here, for instance. There is not a black policeman
here, schoolteacher. That low level. Doctor or anything else. Where are they?
They&#039;re all out in the suburbs someplace. Now, I expect this kid down the street
-- he&#039;s got the potential to be a doctor. I expect him to be a doctor. How does
he become a doctor? He&#039;s going to one of the worst school systems there is,
public school system. There&#039;s nobody. He doesn&#039;t have a person he can even talk
to. The only time he sees a doctor is when he takes his card and goes down to
Medicaid or whatever it is, and the doctor, he doesn&#039;t want to see him. All he
wants is his money.

GAINES: He&#039;s talking about Edison High School, their graduation [rates].
Franklin is the same way. Four of my kids graduated from Franklin. But if you go
to this ghetto school and you get the right thing -- and all five of them have
master&#039;s degrees now. But here&#039;s what happened. Excuse me. My kids went to
Franklin. Three of them went to Franklin, and the fourth one, my baby daughter,
they said, &quot;Daddy, don&#039;t send her to Franklin, because the curriculum isn&#039;t high
enough for her to get into a first-rate college.&quot; They were going to Fresno
State, which is a good school. Fresno State University. She said send her to
Catholic school. I sent her to St. Mary&#039;s. It cost me money to send her there,
but she got a better education at St. Mary&#039;s, and they told me why. When they
went to Fresno, they had to take bonehead English. You understand? One of them
graduated with honors. The other graduated without. I don&#039;t expect them to all
graduate -- but the point is this. They got their degree. They could have went
to barber school or whatever. Education is the key. You can&#039;t open that door
without it. That&#039;s what I preach. That&#039;s the main thing, is to get an education.
In this society, you have to have it.

DREW: The thing I can&#039;t even get brother Gaines to understand -- okay, I&#039;m going
to ask you. How many men have you met like him? White, black, or anything else.
How many men have you met like this?

REDMAN: None like you.

DREW: That&#039;s the point I&#039;m trying to get him to understand. He&#039;s got the
personality, he&#039;s got all the tools to do that with his kids. What about the
woman that&#039;s on welfare, that doesn&#039;t have the --

GAINES: Wait, wait, wait. Here&#039;s what I want to say about Franklin. Franklin
produced the only astronaut we have in Northern California, [Jose] Hernandez.
Now listen, that&#039;s Franklin school. That same Franklin produced the salutatorian
at Stanford, Tubbs, who&#039;s running for city council. Oprah Winfrey gave him
$10,000. Young black kid that went to Stanford, got his master&#039;s degree at
twenty-one years old. If a kid has it in him, it&#039;s putting him in the right
position where he can get the education, he will get it.

DREW: But you said he&#039;s put in the right position. He&#039;s put in the right
position. But when you grow up in this community, you grow up in this community,
what chances do you have? In the first place, there&#039;s no encouragement. There&#039;s
no encouragement to graduate from high school.

GAINES: Listen. If you can keep your head when all about you are losing theirs
and blaming it on you, if you can trust yourself when all men doubt you and make
it --

DREW: Mr. Kipling.

GAINES: But if you can dream and not make dreams your masters, and if you can
think and not make thoughts your aims, if you can meet with triumph and disaster
and treat these two imposters just the same --

[End of Interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>