<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00100719" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2016-01-01" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Bette Jane Gulliford | Interview 1 | January 1, 2016</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Bette Jane Gulliford</interviewee><interviewer>David Dunham</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>arylAgn5wRI</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>DUNHAM: And we usually start at the beginning, and so when and where were you born?

GULLIFORD: I was born in Pasadena, California, May 31, 1923.

DUNHAM: And what was your full name?

GULLIFORD: Bette Jane Smallwood. Smallwood is a family name.

DUNHAM: Oh, and how do you spell that?

GULLIFORD: S-M-A-L-L-W-O-O-D [spells].

DUNHAM: Okay, Smallwood, very well. And can you tell us a little bit about
growing up in Pasadena--well, actually before that, I&#039;m sorry, can you tell us a
little bit about your family history? Do you know when your family first came to
the United States and from where?

GULLIFORD: No, I can&#039;t. I don&#039;t have that in my memory. I just got some papers
this last week from my niece that looked up a lot of this.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay, well we can talk about that later then. Do you know your
family&#039;s ethnic background or what nationality they were originally?

GULLIFORD: Well, Mother&#039;s family was German, from what I understand, and Daddy&#039;s
I&#039;m not sure about. I think--it seems to me there is Dutch or something in that.
Mother&#039;s parents came from Germany prior to 1882. Mother&#039;s maiden name was
Ronge. Father was English. His parents came to US prior to 1826.

DUNHAM: What was it like growing up in Pasadena in the twenties and then in the
thirties, through the Depression?

GULLIFORD: Oh well, yeah, it was--it was good. It was a--you know, it wasn&#039;t
such a busy town. We walked everyplace, we did things we wanted to do. You
didn&#039;t have to worry about it.

DUNHAM: How many siblings did you have?

GULLIFORD: I had--my sister was ten years older than me, and then the two boys
in between and then me.

DUNHAM: Okay, so four of you.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, Norma and then Elmer and then Bob and then me. Elmer is Ann&#039;s father.

DUNHAM: And where did you live in Pasadena?

GULLIFORD: We lived on 448 North Wilson. [laughing]

DUNHAM: What kind of place did you live in? What was your home like?

GULLIFORD: Oh, it was a nice little three-bedroom place, just like all the other
homes around there.

DUNHAM: Okay, and what was life like for your mom while you were growing up?
What was an average day like for your mom?

GULLIFORD: Well, she was a homeperson. She kept the house and watched out for us
and took care of all of us. Sometimes she&#039;d go down to the print shop and do a
little something for my dad if he needed papers put together or something of
that sort.

DUNHAM: So your dad ran a print shop. What kind of print shop was that?

GULLIFORD: Well, it was--it was all his own and he did whatever people needed,
business cards. He printed programs for theaters even, in those days. And then
he&#039;d get free tickets to the movies, so every once in a while one of us kids
would get to go free to the movie. [laughing]

DUNHAM: What are your memories of going to the movies in those days?

GULLIFORD: Oh, well that was--it was good. There wasn&#039;t so many things to do in
those days, you know.

DUNHAM: Was there a big movie house in Pasadena or more than one?

GULLIFORD: We had about--I think it was two movie theaters there in Pasadena.
And we went to the closest one that you could walk to, you know.

DUNHAM: Okay, and would it have the newsreels and all of that, back in those
early years?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah, I&#039;m sure it did. Yeah.

DUNHAM: Did you work in the print shop at all, growing up?

GULLIFORD: No, I didn&#039;t. Daddy would bring things home sometimes that needed to
be put together and we&#039;d do it there, but I did not help in the print shop.

DUNHAM: What kind of work would that be, putting the things together?

GULLIFORD: Oh, papers that--a group, you know, that needed to be stapled
together. We would assemble them in the right order, and then so he could put
them into one thing.

DUNHAM: What was school like?

GULLIFORD: Oh, it was great. I still remember my kindergarten teacher&#039;s name,
Miss Crandall, and she lived in a little apartment upstairs, downtown in
Pasadena there. Once in a while we&#039;d go to see her and visit with her, even
years later after we were up in the other grades.

DUNHAM: What was the ethnic makeup of your school at the time? Was it diverse at
all? Or it was primarily a variety of white and European?

GULLIFORD: Ninety-nine percent white.

DUNHAM: Do you remember any exceptions, what nationalities they might have been?

GULLIFORD: Not other nationalities particularly. A few black, but not very many
in those days.

DUNHAM: Do you know what the black families in town might have done for work, or
what types of--

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t know. My daddy probably would know. Of course he got
acquainted with a lot of people through the business and knew what they were all about.

DUNHAM: You mentioned your kindergarten teacher. Did you have other favorite
teachers or subjects growing up?

GULLIFORD: Well, she was the main one, namewise, that we can remember. Oh--and
my classes were all normal and good, you know.

DUNHAM: When you were a little girl did you have an idea of what you wanted to
do when you grew up, if you will?

GULLIFORD: No, I don&#039;t--not really.

DUNHAM: Did you know any of your grandparents?

GULLIFORD: No, I never met them. When my folks, after I was born, the story I
kept hearing was that every time they moved they had a child, so when they came
to California and I was born they quit moving. Each of the four children were
born in different cities or states.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay--do you know where all your siblings were born?

GULLIFORD: Michigan mainly, I think. I&#039;d still have to look it all up. First was
born in Saginaw, Mich; second Dayton, OH, third Bay City Mich; fourth Pasadena, CA.

DUNHAM: And did the print shop business hold up okay throughout the Depression?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah, yeah. Yeah--we didn&#039;t, I didn&#039;t know we were poor or having
a depression, but that&#039;s the way that things were, you know. Print Shop
definitely had difficulties according to Ann&#039;s father.

DUNHAM: Did you grow up seeing the Rose Bowl Parade?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah, always, always saw it. Just that one year that we went down
and worked on the floats.

DUNHAM: How old were you when you did that and how did that come about--about?

GULLIFORD: I&#039;m thinking maybe around sixth grade or something like that, because
we were a little bit bigger to be able to be told what to do.

DUNHAM: And so what did you do? You worked with the flowers?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: And what was that like? Very intricate?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah, because we had to take flowers all apart and stick the
pieces on different parts of the floats where they were trying to make
complexions or you know, eyes and things on some of the characters on the floats.

DUNHAM: Right, right. Was it fun?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: Where would you watch the parade?

GULLIFORD: Right there on Colorado and--Mentor was the street where my dad&#039;s
shop was, and we would just go down a few doors down and stand there and watch
the parade.

DUNHAM: Okay, in those days would you have to get there extra early to get a place?

GULLIFORD: Well, we&#039;d get down there pretty early yeah, so we&#039;d keep a spot
where we could sit down, put a chair or a box or something to, a tricycle or
something to sit on so you could watch the parade.

DUNHAM: Yeah, before the US joined the war, were you following news of the war
in Europe and abroad?

GULLIFORD: No.

DUNHAM: Did you, aside from the movies and those types of things, what did you
do for fun? Did you have a radio, play games--or what kinds of things did you do
with your friends?

GULLIFORD: Well, my girlfriend and I would walk down to one of the main
libraries quite often, and we&#039;d get our books and read quite a bit. Where our
house was we had a--there was a vacant lot down on the corner and then behind
our houses. And we&#039;d get out there and play games or go dig around in the dirt
looking for things, and play baseball and stuff. We liked to--one girlfriend I
had and I, we made it a game of trying to climb every tree on our street, going
all the way down the street and then all the way back up. We managed to climb
them all and get up in them.

DUNHAM: Wow, wow, so you were an adventurous girl.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, pretty much.

DUNHAM: What kinds of trees, do you recall?

GULLIFORD: Oh, I don&#039;t remember what they were, but there weren&#039;t great big tall
ones, you know, they were regular ones that branched out.

DUNHAM: And so you graduated high school in June of &#039;41? Was it 1941, before
Pearl Harbor?

GULLIFORD: Yes, yeah.

DUNHAM: And so what were your plans after high school graduation?

GULLIFORD: Well, we knew we were going to go to work through the summer months
at least, and just go look for work. [laughing]

DUNHAM: Yeah, did you--so did you--do you remember what you did that summer?

GULLIFORD: Well, yeah, my girlfriend, her sister, and I got a job down in--I
think it was Alhambra at the airport down there, and that&#039;s where the little
two-wing airplanes were, you know, the family planes and that stuff. They taught
us how to take the wings and stretch the material over the wings and how--I
forget how we attached to--sewed them somehow.

DUNHAM: So to cover the wings when they were in storage kind of thing?

GULLIFORD: And then we would goop them so it would make them hard.

DUNHAM: These are planes that are being made? Or these are existing planes that you&#039;re--

GULLIFORD: Getting repairs, yeah, mainly, in a regular airport, airfield.

DUNHAM: And this is in the summer of &#039;41 before the US joined the war?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, before we went there. And that was just pretty much a temporary
thing too.

DUNHAM: Okay, so how long did you do that? Do you recall? Did you do that up until--

GULLIFORD: Several, a number of months, and then when the job opened up there
to--I&#039;ve got it all written down someplace here.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well I know it&#039;s in the article too. It says that on December 5,
two days before the Pearl Harbor attack, you guys went to work at Monitor Products?

GULLIFORD: Monitor, yeah.

DUNHAM: So how did you find out about the jobs at Monitor Products?

GULLIFORD: Well, they must have advertised, I think, is the only reason
we--because there were a couple of other girls that went in.

DUNHAM: And so what was the job at Monitor?

GULLIFORD: Well, it was very intricate. We would sit at a table and we&#039;d--they&#039;d
bring us these quartz crystals that were cut down to as small as they could get
them on the big machines, and then we would take them and we&#039;d have a dish there
with carborundum and a dish with water and we&#039;d put it on a little glass plate,
mix it up, and then we would take that little crystal and grind it down and then
we would wipe it off and stick it in a little plug-in and plug it in a machine,
and it would tell the numbers. We&#039;d have to get it down to a certain degree to
get them thin enough, small enough, to fit into the walkie-talkie radios that
they carried out in the fields in the war, you know.

DUNHAM: So that&#039;s what the crystals were for, they were for the--

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: So the numbers were regarding the size? Or something else?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, the size.

DUNHAM: What type of equipment did you use to grind them down?

GULLIFORD: Just our fingers and--

DUNHAM: Oh really?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, on the wet kind of carborundum.

DUNHAM: So they were soft in that--

GULLIFORD: Yeah, that was soft. The crystals were hard, of course, like glass,
you know.

DUNHAM: So was it hard work?

GULLIFORD: Well, it was--we had to be right. We couldn&#039;t just slop around at it.
We had to know what we were doing. And then eventually I got to where I was the
one testing the ones that were all put together in a machine, to be sure that
they registered what they were supposed to. And if they didn&#039;t I&#039;d have to send
them back and they&#039;d have to take them out of the little holder and redo them a
little bit and get it down to where it was supposed to go.

DUNHAM: Do you remember how many people&#039;s crystals you were testing, about?

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t remember how many. I know I would just--quite a few, because
we were--I think there were the five of us girls in--

DUNHAM: Who you&#039;d known coming in, had all--

GULLIFORD: Three of them I knew, the other two were just hired in at the same time.

DUNHAM: Okay, well backing up just a minute, do you remember applying for the
job and what that process was like?

GULLIFORD: No, I really don&#039;t. I just remember sitting there working at them.

DUNHAM: Okay, do you remember that first day on the job, if it was surprising or
challenging in any particular way?

GULLIFORD: No, not particularly one special day.

DUNHAM: It was just a small group of you, all women working together? There
weren&#039;t men doing it as well?

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t think they were, on the crystals. They were--the men were
back in the end of the room where the saws were, and they were cutting the
quartz rocks down and splitting them and getting them down into size.

DUNHAM: Yeah. Do you remember what you were paid?

GULLIFORD: No, I don&#039;t.

DUNHAM: Do you think it was much more than you were getting in your previous job?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I think--I don&#039;t remember what we got on that first one. It was
kind of a, for us, a kind of a play thing--

DUNHAM: Yeah, a summer young-person&#039;s job.

GULLIFORD: --that we didn&#039;t pay much attention to. We just, in those days, you know--

DUNHAM: So you started this job just before Pearl Harbor [was] attacked?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: What do you remember hearing about the December 7 attack on Pearl Harbor?

GULLIFORD: Well, everybody was up running around, talking to each other. I think
we even went outside and looked, you know. We were still there--when was it, &#039;45?

DUNHAM: At the end of the war?

GULLIFORD: The end.

DUNHAM: Oh, so you worked this job--

GULLIFORD: And then when we heard that the war was over, the whole--everybody in
the shop went outside and raised their arms and yelled and whooped it up. [laughing]

DUNHAM: Yeah, so you worked at this job all through the war?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, through that, yeah.

DUNHAM: From just before the US engaged till at the end. Wow. Well, do you
remember--on Pearl Harbor, when you first heard of the US being attacked, do you
remember that? That was at a Sunday. Would you have been working then?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: You worked--okay. What days did you work, or shifts, or days?

GULLIFORD: Well, we were working--we worked the day shift on that job and yeah,
the regular eight-to-four probably I think it was.

DUNHAM: Were you in a union?

GULLIFORD: No, no union, no.

DUNHAM: No, okay. And so did you--how long before, do you remember how long
before you became the inspector, about? Since you were doing that same type of
work all four years?

GULLIFORD: Well, making them pretty much the whole time, and then I guess the
last year or two I was doing the finishing up on them.

DUNHAM: Do you remember who was in the inspector position before? Or what--or
your boss. What was your boss like at that time?

GULLIFORD: We had men bosses, but I don&#039;t remember disliking anybody. [laughing]

DUNHAM: Did you get evaluations and/or raises during the war? How did that type
of thing work?

GULLIFORD: We must have gotten a nickel or a dime raise once in a while. I can&#039;t remember.

DUNHAM: And I&#039;m sorry, I didn&#039;t ask--where were you working exactly? What city
was it in? Was it in Pasadena?

GULLIFORD: South Pasadena, yeah.

DUNHAM: South Pasadena, okay. And then were you still living at home with your family?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay, all through the war years. And so how did you get to work?

GULLIFORD: Drove, had a car. Yeah, we had a car.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay, you had your own car or a family car?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I had a car.

DUNHAM: When did you buy your car and what car did you buy?

GULLIFORD: The first one was--what was it--it had a rumble seat.

DUNHAM: Okay, what&#039;s a rumble seat?

GULLIFORD: Where--it&#039;s instead of a trunk it&#039;s--the seat, the lid goes up and
there&#039;s a seat on the back of the car. It must have been a Ford or Chevy,
because in those days--

DUNHAM: Did you have it while you were still in high school or after you started working?

GULLIFORD: No, after I went to work.

DUNHAM: Okay. So how did things change in Pasadena during the war? How did they change?

GULLIFORD: Well, we were so busy working and just having fun on the side, that I
don&#039;t remember things really changing that much.

DUNHAM: Well, tell me about the fun on the side--what types of things, as a
young adult now, a young woman, were you doing for fun?

GULLIFORD: Well, we started--I&#039;m sure it was while we were--yeah, &#039;41 I was
eighteen. During those years we started going over--I drove, and my two
girlfriends, it was the one was the same grade and then her sister, but we&#039;d go
over to Hollywood on Saturday night, to the Palladium. That was the big deal for
us, go dancing to the big bands.

DUNHAM: Right, did you see--who did you see? Glenn Miller, Tommy Dorsey?

GULLIFORD: No, Glenn Miller was flying, he was in the service.

DUNHAM: Oh right, thank you.

GULLIFORD: He was about the only one that didn&#039;t come. But the Dorsey brothers,
Benny Goodman--what was his name Carle, possibly Frankie Carle--he was a piano
player. And during that time we heard about a place down in Santa Monica, by the
ocean there. Lick&#039;s Pier was the place, out on the pier. There was a guy hardly
anybody heard of in those days. Oh, I&#039;m going to say--

DUNHAM: Well, if it comes to you, just tell us later.

GULLIFORD: Very popular.

DUNHAM: Okay, a band leader or a singer?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, band--he was--Lester Kaiser, no. Oh, he was so popular!

DUNHAM: Lawrence Welk?

GULLIFORD: Lawrence Welk! Yeah, and that&#039;s--I don&#039;t know, why did it go--

DUNHAM: Oh, okay, yeah. Sure, he had the TV show many years later.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, that&#039;s before people even heard of him or knew who he was and
what was going on.

DUNHAM: What do you remember about seeing Lawrence Welk back in Santa Monica?

GULLIFORD: Well, good music! We always liked it, and when we went to Hollywood,
there at the Palladium, the Stage Door Canteen was just around the corner from
the Palladium ballroom, and the movie stars would be in there enticing the
servicemen to come up and talk to them and get their autograph. And then when
they&#039;d do that then they&#039;d come on into the Palladium there to dance. And so we
never sat out the dances--all those servicemen available and regular boys too.

DUNHAM: What was dating like at that time?

GULLIFORD: Well, unfortunately, when I was seventeen I got involved and got married.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay.

GULLIFORD: But we really didn&#039;t make that much of it and got a divorce before
too long.

DUNHAM: Oh, so--okay. Was that before you graduated high school?

GULLIFORD: I was still in school, that last year of school. We rented a little
apartment, but it just--I don&#039;t know.

DUNHAM: It wasn&#039;t meant to be.

GULLIFORD: It wasn&#039;t meant to be. Well, we were just kids, so I got out of that one.

DUNHAM: Okay, did you have any children with your first husband?

GULLIFORD: No, no.

DUNHAM: So you were married and divorced before this work started? Or was it
while you were--before the war work?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I think I was through with him before we went to work there, yeah.

DUNHAM: Anything else you want to say about that early, short marriage?

GULLIFORD: No. It just--my folks didn&#039;t approve, but they didn&#039;t kick me out or
anything. They accepted and tried to help me get through it.

DUNHAM: So then after you&#039;d had that experience, what was dating like after
that, while you had a little money and a car and able to go to the dances? Did
you do some dating?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah--I&#039;d find different ones to go out with for a while. But
it--and working too, at the same time, why, you know, you&#039;ve only got so much time.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure, but you were young and it sounded like you were out on the
town a bit. Where would you go to eat?

GULLIFORD: Oh, gosh--I don&#039;t even remember where we did dine around there. We
didn&#039;t--I don&#039;t think we even went out to eat all that much, and if you did it
probably would just be a hamburger.

DUNHAM: You mostly would just eat at home then.

GULLIFORD: Money--money was scarce, you know, for the boyfriends even. [laughing]

DUNHAM: What about rationing? Was there any problem having enough gas for your car?

GULLIFORD: Well, we had to have gas stamps, so any place we could borrow them,
or they would give them to us, why--the folks, my folks, or my girlfriend&#039;s
folks. Any way we could get the gas stamps in order to get over to Hollywood and back.

DUNHAM: Yeah, about how much did that take, to get to Hollywood and back?

GULLIFORD: Oh, I don&#039;t remember how many miles it was over there--forty miles
maybe, over into Hollywood there.

DUNHAM: And was that mostly on the weekends? Or it could be any night you might
go over there?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, but mainly Saturday night.

DUNHAM: Saturday night, okay, okay.

GULLIFORD: And the big bands would be there.

DUNHAM: Yeah, and so during the week would you listen to the radio, or what
types of things would you do in the evening?

GULLIFORD: Oh, my girlfriends would come over or I&#039;d go over to one of them and
we played games. I forget just what--

DUNHAM: Cards, or?

GULLIFORD: Cards and--we didn&#039;t play checkers. We played--well, Monopoly got to
be a big game in those days. That was one of them. And just sit around and
listen to the radio too, you know. No TV, of course.

DUNHAM: Right! What kinds of things would you listen to on the radio?

GULLIFORD: Oh, Saturday night we&#039;d always listen to the dance, the music. They&#039;d
play the popular songs of the week.

DUNHAM: Would you listen to the president&#039;s fireside chats when they were on?

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t think we did. I&#039;m sure my folks would.

DUNHAM: Were your girlfriend and her sister living with their folks? Or did they
have their own place?

GULLIFORD: Oh, they were still living at home with their folks, yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay, in Pasadena as well?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay, well, did you have a sense of patriotism while you were working
this job, working on the crystals? What was the feeling of the time?

GULLIFORD: Well, then yeah, for that yeah. We were very devoted to what we were
doing, and it was important and we didn&#039;t try to fool around and mess it up.

DUNHAM: So I know you were in a small group. Was the company itself a pretty big
company? Did they have events? Or was it a relatively small company?

GULLIFORD: It was a small company.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

GULLIFORD: It was the only one that was there in South Pasadena.

DUNHAM: And did you interact with the male workers at lunch time or on breaks?
What was that like?

GULLIFORD: No, we&#039;d--we&#039;d just, it was in a small town there, and I&#039;m sure we
just went out for lunch and back again.

DUNHAM: Did you get to see the crystals in the walkie-talkies, how it actually
worked? Did you have a sense of that? She told me she had a photo a soldier
friend sent her showing the radio with these crysals. If we ever find it, I&#039;ll
send it to you.

GULLIFORD: No, the last, they would be put once--for testing them we would have
the little plug-in container that they would put into the radios, but they would
leave the top open on it, so we can put the crystal in it and plug it in. And if
it didn&#039;t read right then we would pull it out and take the crystal out and do
it some more and then put it in and test it back and forth. But when they went
out of there, then they were sealed into the little plug-in mechanism that fit
into the walkie-talkies.

DUNHAM: Were there ever any--or what kinds of injuries might have happened at
the place you worked? Was there ever any problem with your fingers or
cutting--that type of thing?

GULLIFORD: No, we didn&#039;t seem to have any. I know I didn&#039;t.

DUNHAM: So it wasn&#039;t dangerous, the job you were doing?

GULLIFORD: No, no.

DUNHAM: Was it monotonous? Were you doing a very high number of them each day?

GULLIFORD: No, I don&#039;t think we ever got bored with it.

DUNHAM: Okay, it kept your attention.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, keeping you--being active the whole time, it kept you--

DUNHAM: Did your salary go up during the course of the war?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah. It went up some but not a great deal. The normal raises that
people would get then.

DUNHAM: Did you have friends that you knew were doing other types of jobs, like
working in the airplane factories or elsewhere, female friends?

GULLIFORD: No, mainly the ones I had were with me, working with me. I forget
what the others were doing, but--

DUNHAM: Did you see the Rosie the Riveter images while you were doing this work
or at the movie theaters? Were you aware of that symbolism at the time?

GULLIFORD: Not really. Like I say, so many things are so hard to remember.

DUNHAM: Yeah, then from now.

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t think it was an emblem in those days.

DUNHAM: What do you remember, once the war started about--like would you go to
the movies then and see the newsreels? What was that like?

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah. Yeah, we&#039;d go up to the movies, usually a Saturday afternoon.

DUNHAM: Okay, well what else--we mentioned a little bit about rationing with
gas. Did rationing--were there other things that were hard to come by during the
war because of rationing, in terms of meat--heard stories about nylons, other
types of things?

GULLIFORD: No, not really. We seemed to be pretty comfortable and hardly even
knowing it was--people were hungry and--

DUNHAM: What did you wear to work?

GULLIFORD: Well, that was just regular clothing in those days. We didn&#039;t all
wear pants like we do now.

DUNHAM: So you were still wearing dresses to work.

GULLIFORD: Dresses, yeah, and stockings.

DUNHAM: Did you see--again, back to--I know you didn&#039;t have friends who worked
at the airplane plants and all, but some women were wearing uniforms, pants and
other things, to different jobs. Did you see--

GULLIFORD: Well, you&#039;d see them around town wearing different things.

DUNHAM: So did you sense any fashion changes, per se, during the war?

GULLIFORD: Not enough that made any difference to us.

DUNHAM: Okay. And did you hear, see and/or hear of the zoot-suiters during the
war years?

GULLIFORD: Oh, that sounds familiar.

DUNHAM: But did you have any perspective on that, of Latinos and Latinas and
their fashion and/or anything else you heard about it in Southern California at
the time?

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t think we even associated with them for any reason.

DUNHAM: Okay. Did you participate in a victory garden?

GULLIFORD: Well, we had a--yeah, my daddy had a garden out in the back there,
yeah. But we also had a big fig tree and a walnut tree and avocado. So we had
all those fresh things.

DUNHAM: Nice!

GULLIFORD: Mother made great pickled figs and things like that.

DUNHAM: Oh! Pickled figs.

GULLIFORD: We&#039;d sit and crack walnuts so we&#039;d have--for cookies and stuff.

DUNHAM: How was your father&#039;s print shop business affected by the war? Did he
have more opportunities?

GULLIFORD: He had plenty of business, from all that I know. Of course like I
say, he printed for other businesses around town, the car dealers and the movie
theaters, restaurants--any place that needed programs or things to get by with.
She was the youngest in the family and her parents were not sharing with her
their difficulities. Like other families, her dad would barter printing services
for things they needed.

DUNHAM: What were your older siblings doing during the war?

GULLIFORD: They were in school. The three older siblings had graduated by 1937.
The two oldest were married. Her younger brother Bob went into the service in
1941. He was in the invasion of Utah Beach and served under General Patton. His
unit stormed Hitler&#039;s home and Bob kept a key that had been in the bedroom door
lock. He is pictured on the back cover of The Last Good War with the key between
his teeth. His story is in the book.

DUNHAM: Oh, in university? Her sister when to beauty school. The boys didn&#039;t
have higher education.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, well--my sister had a beauty shop of her own.

DUNHAM: Where was that?

GULLIFORD: It was in Pasadena too, on Hill Street. She would keep my hair cut
and take care of my mother and I, and the boys would go to the barber&#039;s.

DUNHAM: Cece. [a cat] [laughing]

GULLIFORD: She&#039;s getting brave now. [laughter]

DUNHAM: Did you date any servicemen?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, which one was that--yeah, I did date one, and I&#039;m trying to
think, put that together.

DUNHAM: Okay, well if that comes to you, let me know.

GULLIFORD: Where was he stationed? I&#039;ve put it out of my mind, but yeah, I know
I did date one serviceman for a while.

DUNHAM: Okay. And I didn&#039;t ask you, but did you go to church growing up? And if
so, what religion?

GULLIFORD: Just when I was little, and then I got away from it and didn&#039;t go
back again for a good many years.

DUNHAM: What church did you--

GULLIFORD: Methodist.

DUNHAM: And is that what you returned to then, later?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, when I did go back it was Methodist. That&#039;s when I married my
kids&#039; dad. He was--his family was pretty churchy.

DUNHAM: Okay, and about when did you get married the second time? Was that well
after the war?

GULLIFORD: Well, I was married more than once. [laughing]

DUNHAM: Well, when was your second marriage? Was that during the war?

GULLIFORD: [pause] I&#039;m trying to think now. Golly, I&#039;m going to have to dig out papers.

DUNHAM: Was it with your second husband that you first had children?

GULLIFORD: No.

DUNHAM: Okay.

GULLIFORD: I found, when I finally got pregnant, I found out that I had to have
them Caesarean, because I couldn&#039;t pass more than a pound or two baby. So
that&#039;s--after I had the two kids, why they tied the tubes and that was it. I
couldn&#039;t have any more.

DUNHAM: And that was your third marriage?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Yeah.

GULLIFORD: In between there I was married. He finally was cheating and doing
things that shouldn&#039;t be done, so I finally got rid of him.

DUNHAM: Oh, I&#039;m sorry.

GULLIFORD: But that&#039;s the way things go.

DUNHAM: Yeah, yeah. But it was--did you know many other folks who had divorced?
It must have been hard, maybe, in that time.

GULLIFORD: It wasn&#039;t a good thing to do. But by keeping working--

DUNHAM: Yeah, keeping independent.

GULLIFORD: Then the next job I had when the kids were born--well, Danny
was--Johnny was two and Danny was two months when I split up with the guy, and I
had to go back to work. So I went to work there in La Puente at the,
making--sewing. And we made--that&#039;s where we made panels, waterproof panels that
fit over wooden framed Quonset huts. And they were all shipped out to the war
zones for-- Bette was an excellent seamstress. She made most of her clothes and
also outfits for my mom.

DUNHAM: This is during the Korean War?

GULLIFORD: During the--yeah, so that the servicemen could sleep in them and live
in them. The panels were about so wide, {an armish?}. They had, on my sewing
machine it was about this big. They were--it was heavy sewing and they were
filled with fiberglass foam and stuff.

DUNHAM: Wow, so how did you get that job? How did you find it? Do you recall?

GULLIFORD: Oh, I&#039;m sure they advertised for it, and by that time I was living
down in La Puente. I&#039;d gone over and lived with my sister in her travel trailer.
She&#039;d take care of the boys in the daytime when I went to work, till I got
married and stuff.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay. So after the husband who fathered your children you--

GULLIFORD: Yeah, so--

DUNHAM: So did he have any contact with the kids after that?

GULLIFORD: No, no.

DUNHAM: Okay, so you were a single mother. And was this the sister who had the salon?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: So was she able to keep them at the salon? Or she--

GULLIFORD: No, she was--that was a little bit later then. She&#039;d married and they
settled down out in La Puente.

DUNHAM: And she had children of her own as well?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, but they were in school.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay. They were a little older?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: So what was--it must have been hard, even with that help, to be working
full-time and then coming home to a two-month-old and two-year-old.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, well, I don&#039;t know how I did it, but with the salary I made I
had a live-in housekeeper, so that I had to be to work at six in the morning,
and that&#039;s pretty early to have to get up and go to work.

DUNHAM: Sure, sure.

GULLIFORD: So I couldn&#039;t handle the kids at that hour in the morning, because
they&#039;d be sleeping. So I got the live-in housekeeper, so that she would be there
and take care of the kids in the daytime and get them up and keep them in the
yard there.

DUNHAM: And then how late did your shift go till?

GULLIFORD: I think it was two o&#039;clock.

DUNHAM: Okay. And then--and you were driving.

GULLIFORD: Yeah. I had an old Chevy in those days--an old one! [laughing]
Sometimes I couldn&#039;t get the dumb thing started, so there happened to be a guy
in the neighborhood that drove a taxi, so I&#039;d call him and he&#039;d bring his car,
his taxi over, and give me a push and get me started so I could get to work.

DUNHAM: Yeah, it sounds like it must have been challenging times to put it all together.

GULLIFORD: Oh, it was, it was.

DUNHAM: And be a young mother. Do you think having the work experience you got
during the war helped you be independent, strong enough to negotiate all that?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I think so. Yeah, I&#039;m sure, yeah.

DUNHAM: Do you think you might have stayed in either of the marriages without
those opportunities?

GULLIFORD: Oh--a possibility. Of course when you both work and you&#039;re busy, why
it&#039;s sometimes hard to relate like you should. [laughing]

DUNHAM: So then you married again--and how was that? Or how much later did you
marry again?

GULLIFORD: Oh boy--

DUNHAM: Or how old were the boys?

GULLIFORD: I&#039;m trying to think back now to their dad. Well, they were little
when--yeah, it was Wally that, when they were two and two months, and he was
overboard with religion. He&#039;d be out in the streets at night trying to convert
people or he&#039;d be in the bar trying to convert drinkers and that kind of stuff.
And it just got to where he wasn&#039;t--he wasn&#039;t there when he was supposed to be.
He was gone so much and wouldn&#039;t change. So anyway, but--

DUNHAM: So he just got kind of fanatical about religion?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, so I just--

DUNHAM: Had he been a drinker himself previously?

GULLIFORD: Not too much. Some, but not much.

DUNHAM: Did you yourself drink some?

GULLIFORD: In those days some beers, something, you know.

DUNHAM: So his religion was a source of conflict?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, a good part of it, yeah.

DUNHAM: Well, so then did you raise the boys on your own all through the years?

GULLIFORD: Quite a few years, yeah. I&#039;m trying to think when I did get remarried
again. We were together a long time.

DUNHAM: How did you meet that husband, who you stayed together with a long time?

GULLIFORD: It must have been at one of the dances. I&#039;m trying to think.

DUNHAM: So you were still able to go to those dance clubs on occasion?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, and on some weekends. But--

DUNHAM: Did you stay in touch after the war with your girlfriend and her sister?

GULLIFORD: Off and on, but never really that close anymore with the girls. I&#039;d
keep too busy working in family and stuff to--

DUNHAM: Yeah, you had a lot of responsibilities.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: During the war years did you know--I know it wasn&#039;t talked about as
openly as today, but did you know of any gays or lesbians at the time?

GULLIFORD: No.

DUNHAM: I had another--because with your German ancestry, was that ever known or
was that ever an issue because of the Germans in the war?

GULLIFORD: No.

DUNHAM: Yeah, no. Did you know any German Americans, Italian Americans, or
Japanese Americans who were incarcerated or that you knew had been prisoners of
war? Being on the West Coast especially, I guess, did you know of any Japanese Americans?

GULLIFORD: No, I&#039;m thinking--it seems to me there was something that happened
there, because there were a couple of Japanese families in the area, in Pasadena
there. I guess nothing that was serious enough that I remember.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well if you weren&#039;t close to them you might not have noticed, but
they probably were incarcerated during the war then, after Pearl Harbor.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I would think so, yeah.

DUNHAM: You don&#039;t recall what kind of work or businesses they had?

GULLIFORD: No.

DUNHAM: Okay, well anything else about the war years that we didn&#039;t cover that
you might like to share with us, about things that were going on or happening?

GULLIFORD: Well, the next job I had, when I was living in--well, let&#039;s see,
where were we?

DUNHAM: Well, yeah, you did talk about--so after World War II, during the Korean War--

GULLIFORD: I moved up to--

DUNHAM: Ridge--

GULLIFORD: Up to Ridgecrest.

DUNHAM: Ridgecrest, in the sixties.

GULLIFORD: My husband, at that time, worked for United Parcel. They needed a
driver to come up in the--locate in the desert area so they could go on up to
Lone Pine and Bishop, the northern towns on the main highway, 395 I think it was
then. So that moved us up to Ridgecrest, and for a while we had, on the side--a
little beer bar. And then we went into--got a gas station, a Chevron gas
station. And just--I was doing the books and he was doing the pumping.

DUNHAM: Okay, and what was running the beer bar like, if you don&#039;t mind me
asking about that?

GULLIFORD: Well, it was pretty good fun. We got acquainted with--it was local
people that would come in there daily.

DUNHAM: This is in Ridgecrest?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, and would sit at certain spots. Sometimes if I saw them get out
of the car, why I&#039;d--when they got into their seat I&#039;d have their beer waiting
for them there. [laughing]

DUNHAM: Ever any challenges there of folks who got in fights or any of that kind
of thing?

GULLIFORD: No, we didn&#039;t have that kind.

DUNHAM: It was a pretty calm group.

GULLIFORD: We had some pool tables in there, and the guys would keep busy. And
we had pinball machines in there too, and it was a beer--because it was a pool
hall, kids could come in. So sometimes I&#039;d be tending bar there and I&#039;d hear
that pinball machine making a strange noise, trying to react to something going
on, and I&#039;d have to go over and see, and they&#039;re trying to jiggle it and get
things to work that weren&#039;t supposed to. So we finally just drew the line and
quit letting them come in. [laughing]

DUNHAM: All right, well--but if that&#039;s as rowdy as it got in the bar, that&#039;s not
too bad I guess.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, that&#039;s about all.

DUNHAM: Did you already know how to tend bar, or did you learn on the job?

GULLIFORD: No, we learned on the--yeah.

DUNHAM: Was that fun?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, it wasn&#039;t bad at all, really. It was busy, and of course being
a small town up there you had the regular customers.

DUNHAM: But then you switched to a gas station, or did you do both?

GULLIFORD: We did the--we had the gas station first and then got the bar, yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay.

GULLIFORD: Well, then while we were there, then it didn&#039;t--sometimes I wasn&#039;t
busy enough, so I went to work at the Naval Weapons Center there in Ridgecrest.
[a cat meows]

DUNHAM: Yeah, that was in about &#039;63? Is that--

GULLIFORD: Ouch!

DUNHAM: Oops, you okay?

GULLIFORD: Ouch. My legs are all black and blue where she digs in when she--

DUNHAM: The cat, Cece, jumped up there, jumped off quickly. Well, you went to
work at the--what were you doing at the Naval Weapons Center?

GULLIFORD: We read film from the--that they would have, the cameras out on the
testing fields and testing areas, wherever they would test. A lot of it was
right there in Ridgecrest, because they had thousands of acres up there, where
they would drop their bombs or they would fly the planes low and all kinds of
things going on. They&#039;d have--sometimes six, seven, eight, ten--maybe a dozen
cameras out on the fields, filming all this action going on, because a lot of it
was testing new bombs and new ways of releasing them and all of that. So they&#039;d
had all these cameras, and then we would read that film. I&#039;ve got, somewhere
I&#039;ve got a picture of it.

DUNHAM: Oh, I&#039;d love to see that after we&#039;re done. What do you mean read the
film? What would you--

GULLIFORD: Well, we had crosshairs and we would put it on, like a bomb on an
aircraft. We&#039;d put the crosshairs on it underneath the aircraft, and when it
released then we would follow it down to impact. We had two dials and we&#039;d punch
in the both dials, the elevation and--

DUNHAM: So you&#039;re recording the data off of the photographs of the bomb tests?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: And do you know what kind of bombs these were?

GULLIFORD: Oh, I used to know, remember quite a few of them. It wasn&#039;t too many
years ago I recognized one that they had mentioned in the news that we had
worked on--

DUNHAM: That you had used--

GULLIFORD: --when they were new.

DUNHAM: So did you get special training to do this work? Or how did it--

GULLIFORD: Well, they trained us as we hired in. And then I got to be lead lady
of that group, to where I would have to be sure to keep the girls busy, have
film lined up for them to put in their machines to run through and read. We would--

DUNHAM: These are still photos? Or moving image--

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: No, still photos.

GULLIFORD: Still photos, yeah.

DUNHAM: And it was all women who were doing the reading of the photos?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, in the reading part. Men were in different parts of the
building doing different jobs around there.

DUNHAM: And you were civilian?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay.

GULLIFORD: But we did have a--

DUNHAM: Clearance.

GULLIFORD: --secret clearance.

DUNHAM: Yeah, so what--

GULLIFORD: Because of what we were working on.

DUNHAM: Right, so were there specific--there were specific rules about secrecy
around that, I assume.

GULLIFORD: Oh yeah.

DUNHAM: Were you--how close were you to where the bombs were being tested? Were
you nervous at all about--

GULLIFORD: On the same property, but of course they were farther out and around.

DUNHAM: Did they tell you anything about it, if there was any risk?

GULLIFORD: No. And some things were out at sea too, or different places that
they would bring in.

DUNHAM: Oh, bring the footage in from--

GULLIFORD: Sometimes they&#039;d bring it in for some other--an army group or some
place, you know, that we would do film for. And it would be--it would print out
on cards and then that would be printed into books.

DUNHAM: The data?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Okay, the data you were entering.

GULLIFORD: So that--then the people that were engineering all of this, then they
could read what happened.

DUNHAM: Okay, you didn&#039;t have to do any analysis of the data. You just entered
it, and it went on.

GULLIFORD: We just did the dirty-work part. [laughter]

DUNHAM: So was that work--was it engaging or did it get monotonous doing that?

GULLIFORD: No, it was interesting and it was serious work, so we all paid
attention. We didn&#039;t goof around with the job, not like you could do on other
types of work.

DUNHAM: Were you still working the bar at night?

GULLIFORD: No, no, then I went full-time.

DUNHAM: And was it a relatively good income?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, a pretty decent income and got a raise a few times.

DUNHAM: And your husband of the time, was he working as well?

GULLIFORD: Well, he was running the service--well, what was he doing? Running
the service station too, at the time, and that part of it. Well, what
happened--then eventually I split up with him.

DUNHAM: Before the boys were grown?

GULLIFORD: And the boys were still--no, they were going to school then, so they
were in school mainly while I was working.

DUNHAM: Okay. Did you marry again after that?

GULLIFORD: Finally--[laughing]--

DUNHAM: Oh, that&#039;s okay. I&#039;m just--I&#039;m just curious, because I see you&#039;re an
independent woman.

GULLIFORD: --Really going--

DUNHAM: I&#039;m curious also because you have these at least three different
wartime-type jobs. Was that a coincidence? Or was there any particular--

GULLIFORD: They just happened to turn up in that order, and that&#039;s the jobs I
took. But actually, I worked through all the wars. So that&#039;s kind of an
accomplishment, you know.

DUNHAM: So this job went through &#039;69, is that right? Or did it end? How did this
job end at the Naval Weapons Center?

GULLIFORD: Well, I quit. I retired off of that. And what am I doing now, down
here? [laughing]

DUNHAM: So do you remember--yeah, so in &#039;69 you retired, you were able to retire
from there?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, I think--what did I do then, stay home or not?

DUNHAM: Were you still in--what is it, the Ridgecrest area or China Lake?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, at that time, yeah. We moved up here in &#039;85--&#039;87, &#039;85?

DUNHAM: You with the boys? Or they&#039;re grown then?

GULLIFORD: They&#039;re grown and married, and with my husband again, the same--which one--

DUNHAM: The same one you ran the bar with and all?

GULLIFORD: Yeah.

DUNHAM: Oh, so you got back--

GULLIFORD: So anyway, that&#039;s--

DUNHAM: Okay, that&#039;s fine. On again/off again a little bit.

GULLIFORD: Just too much.

DUNHAM: Okay, okay.

GULLIFORD: That&#039;s some of what I forget on purpose.

DUNHAM: All right, well I understand. I don&#039;t mean to harp on it. Sometimes it&#039;s
just interesting to look at gender relations and even marriage and divorce,
because prior to World War II it was probably much less common, although you had
an early marriage and divorce. But to have divorce--so just curious in some ways
about your experiences, and if women don&#039;t have work, like you did, then it&#039;s
very hard to have the option really, to divorce, without relying on family, and
so--and it sounds like you were better off, for at least those early ones, to be
able to move on.

GULLIFORD: I was always busy working. My husband--we moved up here, he passed
away in 20ll. I had my stroke in &#039;10 and then &#039;11 then he passed way. And &#039;12
then I came in here.

DUNHAM: Okay, yeah. So you&#039;ve been here--

GULLIFORD: But that--well, that&#039;s part of it. It was such a massive stroke that
it&#039;s made me forget a lot of things too.

DUNHAM: Yeah, well I&#039;m sorry we didn&#039;t meet you before then, but I think you&#039;ve
done very well today, and so I really appreciate your sharing all that you have.
Is there anything else you&#039;d like to share with us about those early years, the
World War II years, or anything else before we close?

GULLIFORD: Well, I don&#039;t know. I just always liked my jobs and tried to do the
best I could. Like I say that last one, and I was lead lady over about--we&#039;d
have eight, ten, twelve machines going, so I had to keep things moving all the
time. Of course I had supervisors too, you know, to--

DUNHAM: Right, but it sounds like at two of the jobs you had you ultimately
became the lead.

GULLIFORD: Yeah, the lead, yeah.

DUNHAM: What does it mean to you now, to be recognized at this late date for
your role as a Rosie the Riveter, if you will?

GULLIFORD: Well, I like it. I&#039;m proud of it. [laughing]

DUNHAM: What are some things that you hope this generation or future generations
take from your experiences during World War II and beyond?

GULLIFORD: Well, keeping a good job I think is important. Try to behave yourself
while you&#039;re doing it. [laughing]

DUNHAM: What do you think of in terms of the work you did and paving the way, in
some way, for women in the workforce?

GULLIFORD: Well, I think so many things they&#039;re capable of doing, that if they
would try it. They don&#039;t always have to sit behind a register or be in a bank or
something like that. There are other things available that are interesting.
Well, the last, we were--in 1987--in &#039;95 we moved to Sutherlin, we&#039;re in Pine
View Senior Mobile Park, and every Monday morning we would get together in the
clubhouse, the girls, and sew. And we made quilts for places like this, for the
senior homes, and for the preschoolers. We managed to keep the fire department,
our fire department and police station supplied, so when they&#039;d go out on a
wreck they&#039;d have a throw quilt, about that size, to throw around patients that
are in the wrecks. And then we would take scrappy pieces and put them together
and we kept the shelter, the animal shelter supplied, because they&#039;d put them in
with the cats and dogs so they&#039;d have something special to cuddle up in and dig
at, you know--chew on! [laughing]

DUNHAM: Very nice. I forgot to ask you on camera, but going back, you changed
your name, the spelling of your name--can you tell us when you did that and the
story of that?

GULLIFORD: I don&#039;t remember just which year, but I was still in grade school,
I&#039;m sure, yeah.

DUNHAM: Oh, okay, okay. Was it your idea to change it?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, yeah.

DUNHAM: And so tell us why you changed--

GULLIFORD: Well, I just thought it looked--her name was Bette and it looked
better than having the y on there.

DUNHAM: How was yours originally spelled?

GULLIFORD: It was spelled with a y.

DUNHAM: B-E-T-T-Y [spells]?

GULLIFORD: T-T-Y. But she was the only one at the time that, Bette Davis, the
movie star, and so I just started changing it and that&#039;s the way it was.

DUNHAM: And your parents were fine with you changing it?

GULLIFORD: Yeah, yeah. No, they never fussed about it. [laughing]. I found out
after my parents passed that my dad&#039;s middle name on his birth cert was Lewis,
but at some time he changed it to Louis. Funny how they changed their names as
they pleased back then.

DUNHAM: Excellent. Well, thank you so much, Bette. We really appreciate you
taking the time to share your stories with us today. It has been an honor and a
privilege to meet you here.

GULLIFORD: Well, thank you. I&#039;m still just a normal little, old lady! [laughter]

DUNHAM: Yeah, absolutely--but we really appreciate it. You&#039;ve had a very
interesting life.

[End of Interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>