<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042712" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2010-08-13" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>George Miller | Interview 1 | August 13, 2010</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>George Miller</interviewee><interviewer>Javier Arbona</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|9(15)|23(15)|32(16)|46(8)|57(4)|66(5)|85(11)|96(6)|107(9)|119(5)|129(6)|142(10)|152(13)|164(5)|175(6)|188(8)|201(10)|216(12)|229(2)|239(1)|253(13)|265(9)|275(10)|284(4)|292(6)|301(4)|313(1)|322(9)|334(1)|356(6)|371(13)|384(3)|399(4)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>-v_switfdsQ</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index><point><time>16</time><title>His recollection on learning about the Port Chicago explosion</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>1944</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Community and Identity;Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>370</time><title>Trying to get the Navy to recognize the explosion</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Legislation;Mutiny Trial</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>port chicago mutiny trial</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>705</time><title>Giving people access to history </title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Community and Identity;Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects></subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1110</time><title>The course through Congress of Port Chicago memorial and Freddie Meek’s pardon </title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>1944;Bill Clinton;explosion;White House;World War II</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Community and Identity;Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1405</time><title>What Port Chicago has meant and how have things changed in the U.S.</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Black sailors;Racial history;Segregated war;WWII</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Community and Identity;Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1809</time><title>Labor relations, race relations, and military relations </title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript></partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>1944;Port Chicago explosion</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Labor relations, race relations, and military relations</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point></index><type></type><description>Congressman George Miller is the U.S. Representative for California's 11th congressional district, serving in Congress since 1975. In this interview, Congressman Miller discusses the process of getting a pardon for the Port Chicago 50 and efforts towards getting Congress to grant Port Chicago National Park status. He also reflects on what Port Chicago has meant for him.</description><rel /><transcript>ARBONA: Congressman Miller, I believe you were born a year after the Port
Chicago explosion. And so my first question was how did you come to learn about
Port Chicago and the explosion and if you have a recollection of that.

MILLER: The first time I ever heard about it was I think when I was in junior
high school, in Martinez, my shop teacher, was talking about an explosion that
took place--he probably said Port Chicago. I don&#039;t remember--that had, he said,
blew out some of the windows in town and houses and I think he said in our
school, at the junior high school, which was sort of up on a hill. There had
been an explosion many miles away that had done that. I don&#039;t know in what
context that was being raised. But anyway, that&#039;s the first time I ever heard
about it. And I thought, &quot;Hmm.&quot; But no, never any discussion about anything that
happened prior to that. I think the publicity around Robert Allen&#039;s book and his
interviews and discussions. We started looking into it in more detail.

ARBONA: So it sounds like for several almost decades you didn&#039;t really--

MILLER: Yes. From eighth grade until Congress there was no further discussion of it.

ARBONA: Of it. And so did you then start to meet with any of the survivors at
all or did you contact Professor Allen?

MILLER: No, no. We just started looking at it. John Lawrence, who was my staff
director at that time, was a historian and he became very interested in it. As
we talked to Professor Allen and others, it became pretty clear that there was
much more here and there was certainly a history that had little or no
visibility at all in American history, in the traditional American history or
the history of World War II. It was an asterisk. The explosion was sort of
commented on quite a bit, because it was obviously the largest explosion in
World War II inside the United States, but there was no other discussion about
the sailors or the policies that I was aware of. Now, obviously, with the trial
and with the orders to integrate the Navy, some of that went back, but pretty minimal.

ARBONA: How did then the impetus or the idea from a memorial come about or was
the interest first in sort of addressing the concerns of the survivors in the so
called Port Chicago 50?

MILLER: Well, you did both because you tried to figure out what could you get
the Congress to do. We tried to get the Navy to look at the policy and to see
whether or not, in fact, it was a policy based upon race. They concluded that
the trial wasn&#039;t. It was hard for me to believe that if these sailors weren&#039;t
segregated in this fashion, the workforce, the trial for mutiny would have never
taken place. So I couldn&#039;t see how you could have a trial for mutiny whose roots
were based in a racist policy of segregating African American sailors and then
say, &quot;Well, the trial was on the level.&quot; It didn&#039;t make sense. So we tried to
get the Navy to make it a mission and recognize what had taken place there. We
started to look for survivors and we also thought that this ought to be marked.
There ought to be some marker, historically what had taken place here. What we
wanted to talk about, what had taken place, was larger than what most people
wanted to talk about. But people did recognize the explosion so we figured we
could leverage the awareness of the explosion, the historical nature of it. You
could leverage that into the marker of the historical site and then you could
fill out the history and so far that&#039;s turned out to be pretty accurate of what
has happened. It&#039;s become very expansive now with a great deal of public
awareness. I don&#039;t pretend that it&#039;s of great national awareness but for
families and relatives and people who served there, passed through Port Chicago,
we see it with the marking of the anniversaries. More and more people attend,
more discussion, greater media coverage and even popular film coverage of it. So
we just had to fill it out but we knew there&#039;d be a lot of resistance in the
Navy and elsewhere. Of course, we got a great deal of help from President
Clinton&#039;s White House Attorney Charlie Ruff, who really helped us secure the
pardon and walked us through the very detailed difficult process to justify a
pardon. When you see how pardons are handed out, you wonder why we had to do so
much detail for Freddie Meeks. But anyway, we did the diligence and the pardon
was secured. That was big news, obviously, also. So we&#039;ve just tried to
continuously fill out the history of Port Chicago in the context of American
race relations and American wartime history.

ARBONA: So then there&#039;s a couple of different chapters there that are really
important. One is first appeal to the Navy to try to go back and look at it.
Then they say no.

MILLER: They didn&#039;t think that was a good idea.

ARBONA: It goes back to legislation to then make the Navy go do that and then
sort of appeals to the Clinton White House.

MILLER: Right.

ARBONA: Can you walk me through what did the Navy sort of come back with? What
reasons did they use when they didn&#039;t review it the first time?

MILLER: Well, I don&#039;t really remember. But it was, &quot;We reviewed it. We don&#039;t
think it&#039;s worth reviewing.&quot; That&#039;s just a barrier that&#039;s thrown up and that&#039;s
why we decided we had to go to legislation. It became pretty compelling when you
had a public discussion of the segregation of the sailors. That people were
aware of in a general sense, the Congress people were aware of that. The
engagement of the Black Caucus in that discussion. And then the fact that these
were the only people that were held for mutiny in the history of the Navy. It
changed the dynamics. But we could not let the Navy just stand with a self
review that said, &quot;No, it was the way we said it was.&quot; No, it wasn&#039;t.

ARBONA: So was it difficult to then get the legislation passed?

MILLER: It was difficult to get people&#039;s attention, to think that this was
important. Obviously there were those who were concerned that we were
besmirching the reputation of the Navy or what have you. But it was really a
question of whether or not you were going to disclose historical facts. I think
people understood that there was not a denial of the episode. The record was
clear from what you saw on Professor Allen&#039;s book and the court records were
there and Thurgood Marshall&#039;s involvement was there in all of these things. So
the question was whether the Congress would take action. People agreed to it. It
took a lot of work but I don&#039;t know. There was an uneasiness. There wasn&#039;t
necessarily opposition. But certainly within the military community there was
some general uneasiness about this.

ARBONA: I have seen a letter to President Clinton first to try to get Bill
Clinton to somehow take steps to address the conviction. That&#039;s before the
pardon process. How does that work, then, to go from the first letter to then
working with the White House?

MILLER: I don&#039;t remember. You&#039;d have to talk to John or somebody. I really don&#039;t
quite remember. I think that the first letter was our attempt and the second
effort was really at the suggestion of Charles Ruff, the attorney for the White
House out of San Francisco. I think he looked at it and said, &quot;You guys are
going about this the wrong way. What you really ought to be doing is putting in
for a pardon.&quot; He got Morrison &amp; Foerster to do it as a pro bono, to do all of
the legal work that had to be done. We knew what we were dealing with. We had to
dot all the Is and cross the Ts and get it up to snuff. But with his guidance
and the legal help, we were able to do that and I think that&#039;s really what
transitioned us. We were sort of going at it the wrong way. We weren&#039;t going to
be successful but he obviously thought we had a case of merit here and there was
another way to get that kind of recognition for Freddie Meeks. But obviously
whatever we did for Freddie Meeks would speak to the rest of the African
American sailors who were charged with mutiny. I think at that time we had three
survivors. But that was sort of understood, that he was on point for the whole episode.

ARBONA: So almost parallel to that, you&#039;re also working on getting the memorial
passed at the same time. Did one thing sort of counterbalance the other? Was
there any sense that if one of these doesn&#039;t work then the other one is still
sort of a consolation of sorts or addresses the concerns?

MILLER: No, I don&#039;t think so. As I said earlier, obviously getting the memorial
gave an opportunity for people to fill out the history. Whether we were going to
be able to fill out the history or whether others, as the memorial became
public, would fill out the history and sort of both things have happened. But in
Congress you just don&#039;t know what doors are going to open or when they&#039;re going
to open or how long they&#039;re going to stay open. So you want to try different
approaches, hope for success.

ARBONA: Now, it&#039;s always very interesting to me that a lot of these bills have
ended up as part of sorter larger omnibus spending bills, sort of defense bills.
So when the memorial became a unit of the park service, it went through the
defense bill. Is that usually a bigger challenge or is there any opposition to
putting it on there?

MILLER: The answer is yes and no. Sometimes it&#039;s a bigger challenge, sometimes
it isn&#039;t. We had a lot of cooperation. All these metaphors. But there are only
so many trains that are going to leave the station. Some bills you know that no
matter what they&#039;re going to be signed into law. If you can get into that bill,
you&#039;re going to become law. Other bills, you can get them passed in the Senate,
you can get them passed in the House, back and forth, but they may never quite
make it to get to the President&#039;s desk. The defense bills are going to get
there. So we hitched a ride.

ARBONA: Who have been some of your allies outside of Congress to work on these
various initiatives?

MILLER: We&#039;ve had the support of a lot of people. Not a lot of people, but Rod
Wright in the state legislature was very helpful. A young woman, her name&#039;s
escaping me, from the state legislature, a staff person there, very helpful.
Obviously Professor Allen was helpful. Some of the Bay Area media people took
that effort. There was a hardy band of people and certainly Freddie Meeks
willingness to come forward. This was a subject which was not really discussed.
As we&#039;ve learned from families since then, this was not discussed in families.
This was part of their father&#039;s, or their grandfather&#039;s, or their husband&#039;s
history that was not openly discussed, as he told us. I had an opportunity to go
down and meet with him in Los Angeles. He was afraid that he would get fired
from his job, he was working for L.A. County, if they knew that he was
dishonorably discharged, or had a notation, however it went down for the various
sailors. So to step forward, even at this advanced age. In fact, the reaction of
his grandchildren and others was just the opposite. They were quite proud. He
stood up for his rights at that time. So there wasn&#039;t a lot of places to go in
terms of people familiar with or an in-depth understanding, but there was sort
of a hardy band of people that thought this deserves more attention.

ARBONA: Now, I remember that there was a memorial, sort of a Naval armed guard
memorial that was placed at the site of the explosion. Is that correct?

MILLER: I think that&#039;s right. Yes, yes.

ARBONA: Late eighties. Did you ever visit that one? Was there a ceremony there?

MILLER: I don&#039;t remember. I don&#039;t think so. I don&#039;t think so. But I don&#039;t
remember whether that--it&#039;s very difficult to have access to the facility. It&#039;s
obviously better today with the cooperation with the Army and the Parks Service.
That&#039;s been very helpful. So you think if they put something out there who the
hell would ever see it in that time.

ARBONA: So what needs to be done? What do you think needs to be done in order to
kind of guarantee access?

MILLER: I think we have essentially guaranteed access. We don&#039;t have unlimited
access, we don&#039;t have all the time access, but there will be the redevelopment
of the remainder of the base. About half of it&#039;s being turned over to the City
of Concord now. We&#039;re working with East Bay Parks, with the National Park
Service, with the city to develop that. We&#039;d like to develop a visitor&#039;s center.
We&#039;d like to maintain the chapel. So that northern part of the Naval Weapons
Station property will be developed. A lot of it will have public access and
certainly we want this included in that part of it. There&#039;s some other
historical sites that I think you&#039;d probably want to keep, although they
obviously razed the town of Port Chicago in trying to get rid of the war
protesters during the Vietnam War, which was a tragedy. Another part of a stupid policy.

ARBONA: Okay. So that raises a couple of interesting questions to me, because
that&#039;s also something I&#039;ve been looking at as part of my research for a long
time. Like what happened to the town. And I actually had never heard the reason
being given that it was because of protestors. It had always sort of--

MILLER: Oh, they had--

ARBONA: --been in my head. I was suspicious of it but--

MILLER: Well, I&#039;m sure there&#039;s a dozen official reasons in terms of security of
moving munitions, if there was another explosion. But they didn&#039;t think about
that until Vietnam. No. They clearly wanted to secure the perimeters of the
base. They didn&#039;t want people driving through the base at that time. You can
make an argument about driving down on the waterfront, as the old road used to
be. The justification for leveling the town was pretty weak but powerful in the
Congressional sense. In the Pentagon&#039;s mind, they thought they were going to
take care of a problem. It didn&#039;t do that, but the town was gone.

ARBONA: There&#039;s a long legacy of politicians that have--for a long time I think
it was John Baldwin and Jerome Waldie that fought for the town pretty actively
and vociferously in Congress and trying all avenues. Is there anything else
you&#039;d like to see in the future when the base closes that can address that
history somehow.

MILLER: Well, I think it will be addressed eventually. If and when there&#039;s
greater access, there will be more interest. When you go down and meet with
visitors, they&#039;re quite surprised that there was a town there. You have to look
pretty hard to find it today. So I think it&#039;ll all happen. But because of the
lack of access, it&#039;s hard to get continuity. I think the Park Service has been
great but they recognize they have to set their priorities, too, and they deal
with sites where millions of people come, and thousands and thousands of people
come, and here&#039;s a site that&#039;s sort of fenced off for the most part and you can
only put so many resources into it. But I think as they continue to develop the
stories of the home front and Rosie the Riveter, Port Chicago or Great Lakes or
Dearborn, these various sites, that that&#039;ll all about. It&#039;ll come about. The
marker&#039;s there. The memorial&#039;s there. The status is there. So I think it
continues to grow and we see that growing. Hopefully somebody will get around to
it before all of the previous residents of the town are no longer alive.

ARBONA: Yes, they&#039;re getting up there.

MILLER: Yes, many of them are. Sure.

ARBONA: Do you anticipate that the end of this war right now would be sort of
the turning point when that base would--

MILLER: I don&#039;t think there&#039;s any connection. This is a project. It&#039;s a project
that has a limited number of people who are familiar with and interested enough
to continue to pursue it. But we were just down at the dedication and I was
really quite pleasantly surprised at the number of people who came and the
distances from which people came. And really, as I am almost every time that I
participate in one of the ceremonies. Families, great-grandchildren,
grandchildren who hear about it. &quot;Gee, we heard about that at the dinner table,&quot;
or some part of their life who come and sort of make the pilgrimage to see where
their grandfather, great-grandfather, uncle, whatever the relationship is, worked.

ARBONA: This site is also a place that has been sort of contentious also because
of the return of spent nuclear material that gets offloaded there now. Can you
talk about that at all? Is that something that--

MILLER: Oh, it was contentious in anticipation. In fact, it&#039;s a nonevent. The
few people who were concerned about the spent fuel rods, I don&#039;t even know to
what extent the shipments have taken place. Several have. It&#039;s still the
property of the government. I think they drew the short straws in the office to
go see the first load go through and it was essentially a nonevent. Whatever
shipments have taken place have no matter to most people. They&#039;re just big heavy
casks of spent rods.

ARBONA: Well, let me just take a look here how we&#039;re doing on time. We probably
have time maybe for about one or two more questions. And, actually, I think
we&#039;ve covered a lot of what was on the outline. Yes, I think we&#039;re kind of
getting close to what you have allotted for time. I think I&#039;ll sort of ask you
to talk more broadly about what Port Chicago has meant. You can even reflect
upon how things have changed in the United States.

MILLER: Well, I think what you see developing is you started out with an event,
with the explosion, that became about a place and the place became about racial
history in this country. And it&#039;s much more an historical marker of the courage
of these black sailors, of the President of the United States in wartime to
understand the racial segregation that was there, and of President Clinton to
issue a pardon to a person who had been formally charged with mutiny. And I
think that this effort that I&#039;ve gone through, and joined in by members of
Congress and others, is sort of, to me, always sort of a remarkable part of
America and that is the effort that goes in to exploring and making public the
things that we did that were wrong. Clearly these black sailors, like African
Americans in the Army and the Air Force and everywhere else, joined up to defend
their country. When they went to go participate, they found a segregated country
even in wartime, in the defense of that country, in most instances. So Port
Chicago, to me, is sort of the opening of the doors, another door, really,
because there&#039;s a story of the famous groups. It&#039;s the 442s. Japanese Americans,
the Tuskegee airmen. Those were stories of great courage in kind of ironic
positions that minorities were put in during the war. They were off fighting,
the 442s, and their relatives are in internment camps. Very strange. People go
to fight for the United States of America and it&#039;s not united with respect to
their participation because of their race. So it&#039;s a remarkable story and Port
Chicago was a way to sort of pull back the curtains on some of this. But it was
done before that by Thurgood Marshall. It was done before that by President
Truman and others. So it&#039;s exciting to participate in it and to have a chance to
sit and talk with--I think they were sort of an alumni of the Great Lakes
Training Center. African American sailors came to my office and we spent a
couple of hours and they were just telling me stories. But the excitement and
the pride that they had and that this was going to become public, because they
view what happened in Port Chicago part of what happened to them elsewhere in
the Navy at the same time. They were banned from serving on certain ships and
certain jobs and responsibilities and all of those things that happened to them
simply because they were African American, not because it was a question of
competency, skill, courage or talent or anything else. It was just race.

At the dedication I tried to make the point that I was involved in securing a
medal of honor for an African American soldier in World War II who, it turned
out, was in fact recommended for a medal of honor but when the paperwork was all
completed--he was recommended by his white commander--he was killed in covering
the retreat of the rest of the soldiers and the tank. I believe he was in a tank
group. He held the enemy at bay while they were able to retreat and he was
killed. That paperwork was put away because he was African American. When we did
that investigation, we came across several other African Americans who were
recommended for the Medal of Honor, our highest honor in this country, but were
denied because they were African American. To his credit, President Clinton
reengaged that process and ended up awarding the Medal of Honor--all of those
recipients had died by then--to their families. It was really something to be in
the White House and to see those families, the grandchildren--he told them they
could bring all the relatives and they did. To see them being able to talk to
the President of the United States and to participate in a very formal
ceremony--it was really quite emotional and very formal and rigid--on behalf of,
in a couple of cases, their husbands or their brothers, and then in other cases
clearly their fathers and grandfathers and great-grandfathers.

So, to me, that&#039;s all a continuum. That was the racial policy with respect to
the military and Port Chicago is one part of that. But so is the early temporary
segregation and working out the labor policies down at Kaiser Shipyards and on
the shipyards on the Bay Area. Rosie the Riveter. She was in the integration of
women. So I represent an area where a lot of this history took place and where
the family members were involved in that or neighbors or relatives. So I think
that&#039;s probably the attractiveness of Port Chicago to me, is that it helped make
public that episode.

ARBONA: Can I ask a wrap-up question?

MILLER: No, we&#039;re fine. Quickly.

ARBONA: Great.

MILLER: Your question will be shorter than my answer.

ARBONA: Well, you&#039;ve also been known as being a labor advocate. I&#039;ve even seen
hearings in Berkeley about sort of the post-docs contract and everything.

MILLER: Yes, the post-docs. Kicked the university&#039;s ass on that one.

ARBONA: I think they came around to signing a contract, right?

MILLER: That&#039;s what I hear. I haven&#039;t seen anything but that&#039;s very exciting.

ARBONA: My post-doc colleagues--

MILLER: They were great.

ARBONA: Is Port Chicago a labor story, as well? Have you sort of thought about
it as a labor issue?

MILLER: It&#039;s so heavily overlaid with the military aspect of it that it&#039;s hard
to think of it as a labor story except that we know the kind of jobs that
African Americans were getting at that point in American history. My father was
involved in labor relations at the shipyards in Richmond. Clearly there was real
problems in the shipyards and that&#039;s what his job was, to sort out the problems
with labor relations and gender relations and racial relations and it all sort
of got mixed up there. This was a community that was instantaneously integrated
and a workforce, and they both happened at the same time and they essentially
happened overnight because of the war. It was a struggle but in a different
setting there would be more of the labor story to Port Chicago. But how they
were treated and the insistence of what they do and not do, I think you could
find examples of that in the industrial side of the home front war effort. But
they were enlisted sailors so they didn&#039;t have quite the negotiating room or the
chance to have those discussions. So I think it&#039;s a little different than that.

ARBONA: So your labor consciousness has been shaped in other ways, by other events?

MILLER: Yes. You see the same actions, the ordering of people to go back to
work, the refusal to tell them whether it&#039;s safe or not, the refusal to provide
them safety equipment or better gloves that they wanted or another way of
loading the explosives onto the ship. You see those in workplaces today, very
modern workplaces. We saw that in the British Petroleum Texas City fire, the
same kinds of attitudes about management or the officers versus the enlisted,
however you want to play that out. But, again, there&#039;s such a heavy military
overplay on that. There&#039;s already a diminishment of your rights, the fact that
you&#039;re in the military. So it&#039;s not a perfect equation to what was going on in
the rest of the Bay Area at that time with the workforce on the home front.

ARBONA: Okay. Why don&#039;t we leave it there because it looks like you&#039;re getting
called off to another appointment.

MILLER: We&#039;re going to see a child nutrition site.

ARBONA: I appreciate it. I think we&#039;re hoping that you can do this again for the
Bancroft and maybe someday do a more extensive one about more of like your
entire legislative history.

MILLER: Ah, hell, you&#039;ve heard it all.

ARBONA: No, I don&#039;t think so. Great.

MILLER: Thank you very much. Thank you--

ARBONA: Thank you.

MILLER: --for your interest and your time.

ARBONA: This was a pleasure.

[End of Interview]

  

  

  

  

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>