<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.avpreserve.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042281" dt="2018-06-14"><version>5</version><date value="2012-07-24" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Robert Gray Interview 2: Rosie the Riveter World War II American Homefront Oral History Project</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Robert Gray</interviewee><interviewer>Sam Redman</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url></media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format></clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>﻿REDMAN: All right. This is Sam Redman. Today is July 24, and I’m back with
Robert Gray, better known as Uncle Bob. When we left off, we were talking about
your work in the shipyards up in Washington, near Portland, in Vancouver
Washington. And we were talking about building aircraft carriers and riding on
them --  Could you tell me a little bit more about testing the aircraft carriers
before their official launch, what that process was like? How many men would
have been on the ship when you’d test it? Gray: I would say we had about 400
civilians on the ships. These were people to operate the ship, to clean up
little odds and ends. And we had a lot of feather merchants that just went along
for the ride. [Note – “feather merchants” a common slang term for Merchant Marines.]

REDMAN: These ships had been built really quickly, and we talked about all the
ways that there could be problems. Would you ever discover that there were
problems that needed to be fixed? Gray: Well, yes. One ship --  I don’t
remember which one it was, maybe CVE-15 or 16, I don’t know which. We took off
from Vancouver and we got down as far as the Interstate Bridge, and something
was wrong and the engine stopped and we anchored. Then they fooled around most
of the day; and eventually, some tugboats came out and towed us back. But they
didn’t tow the whole crew back. And my job on the ship was as transportation
man, was to make sure that the crews got back, because we delivered the ships to
the Navy at Astoria. Then we had a civilian crew of about 400 people that had to
get back to Vancouver. My job was to go along and make sure that there were
trains and buses and somebody to get everybody back.

REDMAN: Now, I can imagine in my mind, that that could’ve been --  Well, not
only would that be a trick today, to coordinate, but in that time, that
would’ve been difficult to set up -- especially with rationing. There
must’ve been some sort of exemption for those crews. Gray: Well, it was
difficult because we had --  First of all, if you had a troop movement or a
train or a bus movement, that that was a postulate of national significance. So
it was difficult to get a priority [permission] to use the phone. If I used [a
priority to use] the phone, right away there’d be somebody someplace else,
hey, they got a troop movement here in Vancouver. Nobody knew what it was about,
but it was a movement of Navy personnel from Bremerton, Washington down to
Astoria, Oregon; and then it was a movement on the same train, of people,
civilians, back.

REDMAN: So they’d have to coordinate. Gray: Yes. Also because some of the
crew, about a hundred of the civilian crew, stayed overnight until the Navy took
over. I had four busloads of Kaiser people that had to get back. They left at
different times, when they were done. Right up till the time the flag went up on
the carrier, we had some civilians on it. My job -- and I just stumbled into
this job by luck -- was transportation man, and I went along all these rides.
Now, I had an exempt badge, which meant I could go anywhere I wanted. And I ate
in the officer’s mess, and we ate fine filet steaks and had beautiful bowls of
fruit. This is at a time, remember, when everything was rationed. I was going to
talk to you -- I thought about that last night -- about if you know anything
about rationing.

REDMAN: I’m curious then, in light of the fact that I understand that meat was
rationed and milk was rationed -- Gray: Oh, yes.

REDMAN: So a nice meal at the officer’s mess must have seemed like quite a
treat. Gray: Oh, boy! We had filet steaks wrapped in bacon, and we had Idaho
baked potatoes with butter -- and butter was something that nobody even knew
about, or you couldn’t get it. And we had these big bowls of fruit. I had
never seen a nectarine or some of these other fruits that were just routinely in
the officer’s mess. As I say, I just lucked into it, because I had to stay
overnight on the ship and make sure everybody got off the ship. I had a couple
of adventures, when everybody did not get off the ship; we left some of them in Astoria.

REDMAN: There must have been some sort of process to check the ships before
leaving and do some sort of headcount, but I can imagine that would be --  There
are lots of small nooks and crannies where -- Gray: Exactly. That’s what it was.

REDMAN: Okay. So maybe an engineer or an electrician could get locked in on a
task and you’d have to go find them before -- Gray: Well, this was the case,
where a bunch of the trial engineers wanted to play poker.

REDMAN: [laughs] Tell me that story. Gray: Did I tell you that story?

REDMAN: Would you? Gray: Well, this was a case where we were delayed for some
reason. Probably time. Sometimes we could come in in broad daylight, at four
o’clock in the afternoon; other times, we’d we waiting out in the little
swells until quite late at night. So this one time, there was nothing for the
guys to do. The trial engineers had done everything, got their papers put away,
got their briefcases full and ready to go, and we were still bouncing around in
the ocean. So they said they’d set up a little game of cards and they’d be
in the ready room. Well, I knew where the ready room was, but they were not in
the ready room. This is three or four hours later, when we finally got ashore.
There were communications all through the ship and these guys knew where they
were, so they turned them all off. I looked over that entire ship and I called
on their phones. Well, anyway, after an hour and a half of this, I sent the
trains off because we’re paying time and a half for 400 people, waiting for
these guys to show up. They were a little unhappy with me the next morning, when
they finally discovered they’d been left. So I had to get another extra bus to
get them home. It was their own damned fault. Fortunately, the uniformed guards
that were aboard the ship confirmed that I had tried and they had tried. But
these guys had just found this little nook and cranny, a beautiful place, turned
off the public address system, closed the doors.

REDMAN: And just played poker. Gray: Yes.

REDMAN: That is funny. So then we were talking a little in the interim about
what prompts you, eventually --  Well, let me first ask about shifts. Can you
tell me how shifts would’ve worked at that shipyard? There was a day shift, a
swing shift, and a night shift? Gray: Yes. Yes.

REDMAN: What would a swing shift have -- Gray: The day shift worked eight and a
half hours; they ate on their own time. The swing shift worked eight hours and
ate when they wanted to. And the graveyard shift worked seven and a half hours.

REDMAN: Did they have a higher salary rate or pay rate? Gray: No, they all got
paid the same amount; it’s just that you were on the job an hour a day less if
you worked the swing shift than if you worked the graveyard shift.

REDMAN: Okay, okay. Now, in the interim, I asked a little bit about what
prompted you to move then down to California. Could you tell that story? Gray:
The war was over. I knew that things were changing. I thought, well, San
Francisco was the center of the world, as far as the West Coast is concerned. I
didn’t know what I wanted to get into. I knew I did not want to be a historian.

REDMAN: That’s fine. Gray: No, no. I had thought at one point, of going and
getting a PhD. I may have told you this before, but I felt that I did not want
to be a historian, the world’s leading authority on something that I was the
world’s leading authority on because nobody else cared about it. After you
write your PhD treatise, it goes into the library and nobody ever looks at it again.

REDMAN: Right. Gray: And I just felt that the academic career was not for me.

REDMAN: So you came down here in 1945, I understand, when the war ended. Gray: Yes.

REDMAN: Okay. Let’s go back to the shipyard then for a moment, and talk about
the end of the war. We hinted at all of these different people coming to the
shipyard and there being potential for some problems, in terms of people being
able to work together. How about racially? With people from all over, were there
any -- Gray: I knew you were going to ask that.

REDMAN: Were there any racial problems? Gray: Yes, I would say so. I don’t
know how much of it was all through the country, but there was very definite
racial tensions in Vancouver. I think even more so in the Bay Area, because
places like Richmond, 20,000 before the war, 100,000 during the war --  And
three-quarters of those were black, as I say, semi-educated or uneducated. They
had been held down forever and they were up North and --  They had what they
called push day. I don’t know if you’ve ever heard that term. The blacks
would just get together and deliberately push white people on the sidewalk or
push white people in a line. It was troublesome. There were some racial riots
during the war.

REDMAN: So that would’ve been violence that would’ve broken out on occasion
in some cities? Gray: Yes, there were some cities that had violence.

REDMAN: Okay. Gray: I cannot tell you, because I’m giving an oral history
right now.

REDMAN: No, that’s fine. Just in terms of what you experience. That’s fine,
that’s fine. Gray: I know I went to jail one night, because I was waiting for
a bus to go back to my apartment, which was in one of the so-called integrated
communities. Had about 5,000 apartments. These two guys came up and they had
never heard of standing in line and just pushed, pushed, pushed to get on first,
when the bus doors opened. I did not take very kindly to that, so I just leaned
against the side of the bus and they couldn’t get by. So then finally, the two
of them together pushed me out of the way and climbed up. Somebody on the bus, a
white boy, said, “Who do those guys think they are?” And without even
thinking about it, I said, “They’re just a couple of ignorant Southern
niggers.” Whop! This is out of nowhere. So I went aboard. By this time, the
one guy was on the bus, and I went after him. Oddly enough, there were police
right there at the corner -- which there usually were -- so there weren’t any
blows struck, but we both went off to jail, and then we both had to pay a ten-
or fifteen-dollar fine. But this was a little minor thing, but the police were
around looking for that sort of thing all the time, because there was always
some little --

REDMAN: So the police there were cognizant of there being outbreaks of violence
or fights and things like that. Gray: Oh, yes. Yeah.

REDMAN: Okay. I see. Gray: Well, the blacks in the South, before the war, were
really subjugated. They knew better than to whistle at a white woman or to push
a white man. In some parts of the South, they even got off the sidewalk when a
white man came by. When they got up to the North, where they didn’t have that
--  Some of them just didn’t know any better, and some of them were what, at
that time, we would call uppity. I don’t know whether you know that term or not.

REDMAN: Can you tell me a little about that? Gray: That means that they’d come
up from the South and they thought they were better than, or at least as good as
the white people, and the white people at that time did not accept the blacks as
that. Now, I’ve known blacks all my life, but --  When I was a boy, they were
the servants. We had black maids. My mother always had black maids. And we had
black handymen. They were our friends. But I knew -- I don’t know how I knew
-- I knew there was a gulf between Bessie and me and Snowball and me. Now,
Snowball was a black man who worked for my dad, and was married to one of our
maids; I don’t remember which one. In the depths of the Depression, Snowball
came down the alley in his old junky truck, and he said, “You boys need a
rabbit.” He brought us this big fluffy rabbit, which we named Fluff. He gave
it to us and then came over and built a shed for the rabbit to live in. This is
something he just did because he was a nice guy. The negroes that I knew as a
boy were awfully nice; but on the other hand, they were probably nice because
they knew they had to be subservient. This is going back halfway back to the
Civil War. But racial relations are much better now than they were then.

REDMAN: Let me ask about another development that occurred during the war, is
that a few months after December 7, the executive order is issued to take
Japanese away from areas on the coast, to internment camps. Do you recall that
happening at the time? Can you speak about that? Gray: It was kept very quiet.
Now, if you want to know about that, there are three people living right here
[in this building] who were among those who --

REDMAN: Wow. Gray: George and Lily; I don’t know what their last name is.

REDMAN: I’d like to ask if that’s something that then you’ve learned
about. Gray: It was kept very quiet. On West Coast, it was known about. The
first that I knew about it was in my senior year at college, which would’ve
been ’42-43, we suddenly got a number of Japanese students, and there’d only
been half a dozen on the entire Boulder campus before that time. Well, some of
them were with the Japanese language school, which was a Navy school to teach
Japanese language to Americans. But quite a few of them, it turned out as we
talked to them, had been at Cal or Stanford. Because they were students, they
could go inland to 1500 miles in; they weren’t going to be signaling out at
Point Reyes some night. So that’s the first that I’d heard about it, and
this was at least a year after it actually happened.

REDMAN: I’d like to hear about those students just for a minute, because they
relate to Cal and the Stanford story, because a number of students, like you
said, from out here transferred inland. Did that surprise you? So it seemed like
that was the first you’d heard of it. Gray: Well, what surprised me was the
fact that I hadn’t even heard about the detainment camps. A lot of people
never did hear about the detainment camps. There’s still people that are
surprised that we had detainment camps. And there are people who would probably
be surprised to learn that we had detainment camps for the Germans and the
Italians, too. Did you know a lot of the old Italian families along the
Carquinez Straits were interned?

REDMAN: I did not know that. Gray: They’d been there for three generations and
never bothered to get citizenships. Here’s the old Italian grandma, speaking
only Italian. I don’t think that they were actually taken off to Manzanar or
anyplace like that, but they were required to stay in their homes and couldn’t
go out on the streets.

REDMAN: Another thing that changes during the war that a number of women who
were previously not -- Gray: That’s right.

REDMAN:  -- in jobs at places like shipyards, en masse, start arriving at those
types of industrial labor jobs. What was your experience in seeing more women,
presumably, arrive at the Kaiser shipyard over time? Gray: Well, my experience
would not be apropos, because I had not really been working; I’d been going to
college. So I was not aware of the fact that most factory jobs were men’s
jobs. Women wore high heels and dresses and sat in the office, and men wore the
coveralls and went out and got dirty hands. I cannot say that any of this
surprised me, because living in a small town --  The ladies, or the women who
worked at the New Mode Hosiery mills --  And there were quite a few who worked
in the hosiery mills. There were three or four hosiery mills in Kankakee. This
was a job that a lot of girls right out of high school, which means they were
sixteen years old and dropped out after their sophomore year, would go out and
go to work at the New Mode or the Bear Brand or the Easy-Way. These were jobs
that --  They weren’t like the foundry jobs, the quarrying jobs; they were
women’s jobs. But they were a step below women who went to --  We had a lot of
girls who went to business schools, and they would come out trained to type
ninety words a minute and handle the business machines of the time. They were
two steps higher than the mill hands.

REDMAN: Some historians have argued that the image of Rosie the Riveter, that
has since become a symbol of women’s labor during World War II, was somewhat
overblown because women have always been in the workforce, to a certain extent.
Gray: Well, not in the heavy workforce.

REDMAN: So you would say that the war did encourage more women to that. Gray: It
pulled people of my family into it. I had a very lovely lady, an honorary aunt,
who went to work in the shipyards, in the canvas shop. They cut canvas and sewed
tops for lifeboats or tarps, anything like that, heavy. This is a lady who had
never done anything any heavier than many mend a tear. But she went to work in
the shipyards. It was almost as if for the more genteel generation, they had
more genteel jobs. The younger gals that were just out of school, they’d teach
them welding or teach them burning or whatever. But the older ladies helping out
with the war effort, some of the knit socks for the troops and some of them went
to work in the shipyards and sewed lifeboat covers. Now, mind you, again,
there’s statistics and what I saw. I’m giving you empirical evidence, but I
can’t give you any absolute --

REDMAN: That’s fine. I want to talk about what your life was like at the end
of the war. Well, first, let’s talk about the end of the war in Germany, when
Germany surrenders. Did the perspective pretty quickly shift then to the
Pacific? I imagine there wasn’t much -- Gray: Yes, very quickly.

REDMAN:  -- of a sense of relief. Gray: I remember VJ Day. Marched up and down --

REDMAN: By that point, had you come to the Bay Area? Gray: Yes, I’d come to
Chevron [in Richmond, California]. I left Vancouver not long after VE Day. As I
told you, my brother’d been shot down. Well, he was recovered and got back,
and then I quit my job up north to go back to Denver to visit with him. I had
only been back to the Bay Area for about three days when VJ Day came.

REDMAN: Can you tell me what your reaction was when the announcement of the
dropping of the atomic weapons, in particular --  I understand that people
didn’t see images of what had happened. Gray: No, no. All we knew, that it was
a bigger bomb. All these pictures were taken many, many years later, and shown.
This was very secret.

REDMAN: So what was your reaction to that at the time? Gray: Well, my reaction
was, we knew there was something going on up there. Because there was the three
cities up in Central Washington, where they did a lot of the bomb work, the
atomic cities. Then there was the secret city at --

REDMAN: Oakridge, Tennessee and Los Alamos. Gray: Yes, Los Alamos, Oakridge.
People generally knew there was something going on, but you just didn’t ask
too much because it was none of your business. “Don’t you know there’s a
war on?” That was the catchphrase for five years.

REDMAN: Don’t you know there’s a war on? So that sort of phrase could
discourage people from asking too many questions. Gray: Yes. Well, “Loose lips
sink ships.”

REDMAN: So that’s another phrase. Gray: Yes, don’t say [things like],
“Hey, my buddy shipped out last night,” because there’s a German spy
sitting down on the corner and he’s probably got a radio. There was an awful
lot of propaganda. It was so juvenile that even those of us who went through it
thought it was ridiculous, but there was somebody in the federal government that
thought we’ve got to be treated as children.

REDMAN: So you thought some of the advertising and the slogans and the posters
came off as patronizing? Gray: I did.

REDMAN: Okay. Gray: But it worked for Germany. It worked for Mussolini.

REDMAN: Tell me then about your reaction to the end of the war. Obviously,
it’s very shortly after the dropping of the second bomb. What was life like
for you at that moment? Gray: Well, I had just gotten a job at Chevron Research,
which was a job that I wanted because I wanted to travel overseas, and I thought
if I get a job [with] any of the Standard Oil Companies, I can transfer to
Aramco or one of the overseas plants. So I had just started on my very first
day, on my job at Chevron Research, on the swing shift.

REDMAN: In Richmond? Gray: In Richmond. When I left the dormitory, the shipyard
dormitory, the war was not over. When I got to work, half an hour later, they
said, “Well, the war’s over. Everybody take three days off.” Well, this is
great, because I’d just had about ten days off; I was running out of money. I
figured, well, I’m not going to get paid for that. So the first thing I did
was get dressed and go over to San Francisco, and I marched up and down Market
Street with all the mobs. I didn’t know San Francisco at all, because I’d
just been here for three or four days.

REDMAN: So was that a pretty amazing moment, then, to be able to see? Gray:
Well, the fact that the streets were full and there were these kissing lines of
what they called the Treasure Island Commandos, if you’ve ever heard that term.

REDMAN: No. Treasure Island Commandos. Gray: Yes. Well, these were the brand new
Navy recruits. Treasure Island maybe housed 10,000 of them at a time, during the
war. They got a twenty-four hour leave. Go. So most of them were pretty young
and they formed the kissing lines in front of the St. Francis Hotel, and every
woman that came by got kissed. Then the second or third day, they got a little
nasty and had some windows smashed and cars broken. The thing is that they were
called Treasure Island Commandos, but they really weren’t; they were just
newly recruited kids who had never been to the big city before. That’s what,
to me, it was.

REDMAN: Right. Gray: But it also could be very nasty.

REDMAN: Some of these kids couldn’t handle having too much of a good time, no
supervision, in a big city. Gray: Yeah.

REDMAN: Place me Richmond in 1945. There’s been this massive influx we talked
about, of people from around the country, into Richmond. Richmond grows and
expands. In many ways, the city’s not ready for it, it’s not prepared. Gray:
There was no city.

REDMAN: There was no city [before the war]. Gray: No. There were vast amounts of
Santa Fe lands, all the way from Point Richmond clear out to San Pablo Avenue,
which is seven miles, was duplex housing apartments that were built.

REDMAN: At one point, there was a streetcar village of Native Americans from New
Mexico around there. Do you recall that village, by any chance? Gray: Yes. That
was long gone. That was not a streetcar village, that was a group of track hands
that worked on the Santa Fe Railroad. They were recruited from the Indian
villages in Northern New Mexico. They actually had something set up as a pueblo,
which is down --  The area doesn’t even exist anymore, but I remember seeing
it the first couple of times that I walked around that area. It was a New Mexico
pueblo; there’s no doubt about it. It was run by --  [pause to fix lights,
conversation about turning on lights and continuing interview redacted]

REDMAN: Let me ask then, can you describe for me how Richmond changes after the
war? What happens to Richmond after the war? Gray: Well, El Cerrito, for
example, was practically unbuilt. A lot of houses went up there. The public
housing that’s in Richmond today, Atchison Village and one other, are still
there. But they were built as permanent, and fifty years later, they’re still
there. But the rows and rows of those apartments that were built, basically
along Cutting Boulevard for six miles out from Point Richmond to San Pablo
Avenue, and for about two or three blocks on each side of Cutting, were on, I
think, railroad land. The government just went in and built these cookie-cutter
apartments. Then there were others. There was another, Corbanisas Village, over
in Berkeley [now University Village]. I think graduate students ended up living there.

REDMAN: So initially, it was wartime housing, that had to be converted? Gray:
Yeah. Yeah.

REDMAN: Okay. Can I ask a big question? And you can take a moment to think about
this. I’d like to ask first about the Great Depression, then I’m going to
ask the same question about World War II, if that’s all right. Gray: Sure.

REDMAN: The Great Depression, that experience, did that leave an impression on
you, a particular kind of impression on you? Can you talk about that? Gray:
Well, as I said earlier in the interview, that we were poor but we didn’t know
it. And we were only poor in relationship to the fact that we no longer had
colored servants, we no longer had Cadillacs. My grandfather, I’m sure, was a
very wealthy man, because besides being a retired doctor, he owned large amounts
of land. But I’m sure that he was hurting badly because if you did have a good
crop, the price of corn and wheat was so low that it didn’t afford you to
harvest. It’s like the corn crop this year. It may be so bad that it’ll cost
you more to harvest it than you can sell it for.

REDMAN: But your recollection is that the droughts the previous years before
1929 were really harsh and bad. Gray: Oh, the droughts, the Dust Bowl years
broke a lot of people. There were people who, if they’d had just normal years,
would’ve been okay. But when you have two or three years in a row, nothing
comes up. And you don’t put a crop in for free. That’s something a lot of
people think, well, the farmer just sits back and it grows. But you’ve got to --

REDMAN: You’ve got to invest in that -- Gray: Well, I still have one farm. It
costs, oh, close to $50,000 a year to put in a crop.

REDMAN: Wow. Gray: That’s just to put the crop in. Then you still hope it’s
going to rain and you’re going to get a good crop.

REDMAN: Right. Now let’s turn to World War II. What sort of an impact, then,
did World War II have on your life? [When you think of] those years, what do you
think [about]? Gray: I would say just sort of normal. Wars were going on all the
time. We grew up when the Fourth of July parade or the Memorial Day parade would
have a small carload of Civil War veterans. The Spanish-American War veterans
could still put a platoon out on the street to march in the parade. The American
Legion had an award-winning 400-piece drum and bugle corps. For a small town, we
could put on a pretty [good] parade. I knew all these veterans and we were
always told, don’t ask the veterans about anything, because they don’t want
to talk about it; but they all liked to go down to the American Legion and talk
about it. Also growing up, it was the period of the growth of Mussolini. Hitler
came a little later. But that was at the time when we sent General Smedley
Butler and the Marines into occupy Haiti and occupying Santa Domingo and
occupying Guatemala. We were constantly the great colossus of the north,
constantly meddling. I’m sure you’re more aware of this than I am because
you’re much closer to your books. But I was certainly aware of Mussolini
invading Ethiopia. We didn’t have TV at that time, but we always went to the
Saturday movie.

REDMAN: So you were aware of these developments as they were happening and it
was hard not to think of this as a [regular occurrence]. Gray: Yes. Yes, well,
the thing is, our war developed between the advent of the first movie cameras
and TV, so that if we went to the Saturday matinee movie, there’d be pictures
of --  These were Italian troops that were leaping out of the third-story
windows so they could be paratroopers, bombing the poor Ethiopians. There was a
barnstorming black pilot at that time, [a] self-appointed colonel, and he was
going to Ethiopia and lead his air force, his private air force, against
Mussolini. Well, of course, he was a big --  well, a thirty-day sensation. But
it turned out he couldn’t even fly a plane. But the thing is that this period
was not a peaceful period. There was the Balkan wars. The United States had
troops in Siberia, as late as 1929, I believe. Most people didn’t even know we
had troops in --  But we were supporting the whites, I guess, which --  Anyway,
we had troops there. And I think the British did not pull out of Murmansk until
about the same time.

REDMAN: How did you get the nickname Uncle Bob? Gray: Well, because I have been
Uncle Bob for most of my life. My niece, who is now seventy years old, arranged
for me to come in here when I was unable to arrange it for myself. And
undoubtedly, she calls me Uncle Bob. But I have been Uncle Bob to four or five
generations of my friends’ children. I never had any children myself, but
I’ve had four or five different close friends that all the kids call me Uncle
Bob, even the third generation. But I have been Uncle Bob ever since I was about
twenty years old. I don’t know, it just stuck.

REDMAN: It stuck. Gray: I like it because it differentiates me from the other
two Bobs who live here. So if you say Uncle Bob, they know it’s not the Bob
that lives over here and shows movies, and it’s not the Bob down here that growls.

REDMAN: With that, I’d like to ask, is there anything else that you’d like
to share about World War II? Gray: Well, there were 20-million people from the
United States that were in it; but there were still 100-million who weren’t.
That’s a big thing. We talk about the war and the war effort, but I think
basically, except for the rationing, things went on pretty much as they had all
along. Because there was rationing, but before that, we’d been too damn poor
to buy anything anyway. So my feeling was that things were just pretty ordinary.
Of course, part of that is because this is the time I was maturing. I was
between being a high school kid and being a full adult.

REDMAN: So you see some of that [continuity]. Gray: Oh, sure.

REDMAN: Yes. Well, with that, I’d like to say thank you very much for sitting
down. Gray: Well, thank you for listening to me.

REDMAN: It was great. Thank you.

 

 

 

 

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt></fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>