<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042308" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2012-06-05" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>David Lloyd | Interview 1 | June 5, 2012</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name>Rosie the Riveter WWII Home Front Oral History Project</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><subject>Rosie the Riveter WWII Home Front Oral History Project</subject><keyword>Labor</keyword><keyword> Education</keyword><keyword> Segregation</keyword><keyword> Religion</keyword><keyword> Economy</keyword><keyword> World War II recollections </keyword><interviewee>David Lloyd</interviewee><interviewer>Jess Rigelhaupt</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|14(8)|25(8)|34(12)|40(2)|50(14)|70(8)|83(3)|88(12)|95(8)|107(14)|115(13)|122(9)|130(13)|142(2)|147(6)|154(11)|161(1)|170(10)|178(11)|187(3)|198(10)|205(1)|214(11)|220(16)|232(4)|241(8)|249(16)|257(11)|275(8)|282(7)|290(9)|298(3)|305(14)|312(3)|318(11)|326(4)|338(13)|344(3)|354(9)|361(11)|369(3)|385(12)|392(12)|402(10)|407(11)|424(9)|432(6)|445(13)|452(11)|463(1)|465(3)|474(7)|483(1)|483(8)|491(5)|500(4)|507(6)|516(11)|526(13)|533(7)|540(2)|554(4)|560(16)|574(7)|584(2)|590(10)|599(1)|608(1)|616(10)|625(4)|634(9)|641(1)|649(7)|661(2)|670(1)|672(5)|677(6)|684(4)|691(14)|702(6)|709(12)|721(2)|725(10)|736(12)|746(4)|754(4)|764(9)|773(5)|781(1)|792(4)|803(3)|811(7)|817(8)|825(6)|834(4)|841(9)|850(1)|859(4)|865(7)|874(11)|882(9)|891(10)|901(15)|910(15)|923(5)|929(5)|937(6)|947(1)|960(13)|972(2)|978(13)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>fmJW-juaYy4</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index><point><time>0</time><title>Introduction and earliest memories</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>It is June 5, 2012. I am in Arlington, Virginia doing an oral history interview with David Lloyd. This is tape number one. And the way I like to start is if I could ask you to say your full name and where and when you were born.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Arlington, VA;Baptist;Chapel Hill, NC;DCFD;family history;heat;summer;Washington, DC</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Early memories;Fire Department;North Carolina;summer in Washington DC</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>534</time><title>Extended family, family vacations and war stories</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Did most of your extended family, grandparents, aunts, uncles, did they stay in North Carolina?</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Arlington Theater;Eleanor Roosevelt;gasoline;RAF;Rationing;roadtrip;Vacation;war bonds;war stamps;Washington Redskins</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Christmas party for poor children;Patrick Henry Elementary School;rationing;Roadtrips</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1211</time><title>Warplanes, getting news about World War II, enlisting in the air force and memories of Pearl Harbor</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>You sparked two questions. I’ll do one at a time. You mentioned all the airplanes. How did you learn about them?
</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Air Force;BB rifles;Focke-Wulf;Heinkel;Japanese Zero;Luftwaffe;Messerschmitt;pearl harbor;War movies</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Pearl Harbor;Rape of Nanking;Thirty Seconds Over Tokyo;Warplanes;Wings magazine</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>1687</time><title>US involvement in World War II, Uncles being killed in the war</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>did you have a sense before the war that the US was likely to become involved?</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>nationalism;neighborhood;Newspapers;patriotism;war efforts</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>attitudes about the war;News about World War II;playing baseball with friends;Uncles being killed in the war</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>2464</time><title>Talking as kids about World War II, America entering the war</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>I’m intrigued by what you said earlier, in the years leading up to the war. You were probably around ten. That you knew Germany and Japan were strong militarily.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>allies;Hitler;Pearl Harbor;War in Europe;war movies</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>reaction to Pearl Harbor;Thirty Seconds Over Tokyo;US entering the war</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>3138</time><title>Popular culture informing about the war, school activities</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>It sounds as though popular culture, movies in particular, were one of the ways you learned a lot about what was going on. Do you remember other forms of popular culture? Comic books, for example, or other things that informed you about the war?
</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>jujutsu;karate;marbles;Reader's Digest;soccer</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Learning about the war through popular culture;playing marbles;school activities</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>3460</time><title>Extended families, the impact of the Great Depression</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>And as I was changing tapes we talked briefly about the Depression and that it preceded World War II, and you were talking about what you remembered about people visiting your house and your mother.</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>CCC;homeless;Job Corps;New Deal;President Johnson;President Roosevelt;The Great Depression;Uncles;Washington DC</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Extended families;Family members living with their family;Helping the homeless;The Great Depression</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>4055</time><title>The impact of the New Deal, the transition from the Depression to World War II</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>But going back to the New Deal and some of the government programs that you’re talking about, certainly reading about Roosevelt and the New Deal retrospectively</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Arlington, VA;Democrat;FDR;Fort Myer;Forts;Four Mile Run;Job Corps;Pollard Street;President Roosevelt;the New Deal</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Finding Civil War Bullets;Growth of Arlington, VA;The New Deal</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>4748</time><title>Working at the Newsstand at the Pentagon</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>We saw it. We drove past. We could see the Pentagon being built, yeah. And I worked down at the Pentagon</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Four Mile Run;high school job;newspapers;newsstand;The Pentagon</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Cutting down the woods around Arlington;Expansion of Arlington, VA;Working at the Pentagon Newsstand</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>5182</time><title>People moving to Arlington, VA, and discrimination</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>No, this is great. Part of the expansion in Arlington and other parts of the country during World War II was new people moving in, right? People may have come for jobs. Many different reasons, perhaps .Did you have a sense that there were lots of new people moving in and perhaps attending school with you?
</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Arlington, VA;discrimination;Executive Order 8802;Migration;Racism;Sexism</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Disliking people being critical of Arlington;Executive Order 8802;Migration to Arlington</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>5674</time><title>importance of ethnicity in school, memories of V-E Day and the use of atomic weapons</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>Were there kids of different ethnicities at your—either through elementary or high school? Anywhere in your schooling? That ethnicity mattered more? If you were Italian or Irish or Jewish or Greek, as you mentioned.
</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>atomic weapons;Catholic;ethnicity;Hiroshima;mushroom cloud;Nagasaki;religion;V-E Day;Victory in Europe</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>Ethnicity and discrimination in school;Memories of V-E-Day;reaction to the use of atomic weapons;Victory in Europe</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point><point><time>6255</time><title>How would the reaction to WWII be different today? Conclusion of interview</title><title_alt></title_alt><partial_transcript>What was it like learning about that and thinking about that without television in the sense of—or even the Internet now. How do you think it would be different if something like that had been—the way we have television news, and they play it over and over and over again. Or—</partial_transcript><partial_transcript_alt></partial_transcript_alt><synopsis></synopsis><synopsis_alt></synopsis_alt><keywords>Internet;Television news</keywords><keywords_alt></keywords_alt><subjects>How things would be different today</subjects><subjects_alt></subjects_alt><gpspoints><gps></gps><gps_zoom>17</gps_zoom><gps_text></gps_text><gps_text_alt></gps_text_alt></gpspoints><hyperlinks><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text><hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlink_text_alt></hyperlinks></point></index><type></type><description>Living in Arlington, VA for most of his life, Lloyd gives his account of Virginia during World War II. Lloyd was well aware of the events taking place abroad duirng the war, and mentions the feelings and attitudes felt after Pearl Harbor, and news of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. He recalls mass efforts by schools, by newspapers, rationing, and war bonds to support of the war. Lloyd also remembers the segregation of his schooling, as well as, separations between Catholic and Protestant students. LLoyd experienced economic programs from both FDR's New Deal and LBJ's Great Society, and discusses the affect of those on Arlington's post-war growth. </description><rel /><transcript>RIGELHAUPT: It is June 5, 2012. I am in Arlington, Virginia doing an oral
history interview with David Lloyd. This is tape number one. And the way I like
to start is if I could ask you to say your full name and where and when you were born.

LLOYD: All right. David Andrews Lloyd, L-L-O-Y-D, and I was born in Washington, DC.

RIGELHAUPT: And what year were you born?

LLOYD: Nineteen thirty.

RIGELHAUPT: How would you describe some of your earliest memories of your
childhood in Washington?

LLOYD: I think I don&#039;t know of anything that was unpleasant. I enjoyed my
birthday, and we lived on Irving Street in DC at that time. My father was an
officer in the Washington, DC fire department, and we loved to go to the fire
station with him. Sometimes he&#039;d take us there when he was off, and we would
slide down the pole, which was a big exciting thing for our childhood. I had a
very great time then. Had no problems that I know of. Now, maybe I might change
that but I had a very pleasant boyhood.

RIGELHAUPT: What neighborhood in DC? You said Irving Street. What neighborhood
is that in?

LLOYD: That&#039;s in Northeast, I think. I don&#039;t even remember much about that place
at all because I was so young.

RIGELHAUPT: Well, before we get to your move to Arlington, I&#039;d like to ask a
couple of questions about your parents. Where and when were they born?

LLOYD: Let&#039;s see. My dad was born in 1901. My mother was born in 1905, I think
it was. And they were both born in Orange County, North Carolina, and that&#039;s
where Chapel Hill was located. My mother did some courses at Chapel Hill there,
at the University of North Carolina, and she taught school here in Fairfax
County during the war. So we enjoyed having her working, teaching, but it was
really tough during the war all around. It was like having two parents working.
We lived in a modest house, a new house but it was modest, in Arlington on
Fourteenth Street in South Arlington. And all my education up till college was
here. I say I taught because I did go into education as a career later on. I
went to school at Patrick Henry grade school in Arlington here, Thomas Jefferson
Junior High School and Washington-Lee as my high school. Two Confederate
soldiers--well, now, no; George Washington wasn&#039;t Confederate. [laughs] He was
very much not a Confederate. But Robert E. Lee was, and I went to Washington-Lee
High School here, which we considered the greatest high school in the world. It
really was. Wonderful, wonderful place to go to high school.

RIGELHAUPT: Did your parents meet in North Carolina?

LLOYD: Oh, yes. Because my dad was in the navy at the time, and my mother was
teaching. They both came from the same general area in North Carolina. So yes,
they were both from the same area, so that was good.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you know how they met?

LLOYD: I think they probably met at church.

RIGELHAUPT: Were both of them active in church growing up?

LLOYD: Yes, yes. All their life they were.

RIGELHAUPT: What denomination? What--

LLOYD: We were Baptists.

RIGELHAUPT: Okay. Now, did that continue when they moved to DC?

LLOYD: Oh, yes. Yes. They continued to go to Baptist church in DC and then again
when we came here we did the same thing.

RIGELHAUPT: So what brought them to Washington, DC?

LLOYD: Well, my dad first was in the Navy, and then he was stationed here in
Washington at the Naval Hospital. He liked Washington, and he applied for the
job and got a job with the fire department. He was an officer in the fire department.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you know what year they moved from North Carolina to Washington?

LLOYD: It must have been about 1926, I would think, something, yeah. Around 1926.

RIGELHAUPT: Okay. Did they ever talk about what neighborhood they chose in
Washington and why they chose to live there?

LLOYD: Well, as I have indicated, they lived in northeast and northwest
Washington. The last place we lived in Washington was in northwest, and I think
we lived earlier in northeast. Washington was a completely different town in
those days. It was not a rural town, of course. But it was so laidback, very
comfortable. I remember Joyce, my wife, also was born in Washington. And
Washington is noted, particularly in the summertime, as being very hot and
uncomfortable. Joyce&#039;s mother and some of her friends used to take a blanket and
go outside on the very, very hot days, hot nights, and they could sleep outside
in the park on the blanket. It was a very peaceful town. Joyce, my wife, was
born in Washington, I was born there, and we loved Washington. But Arlington was
a better place to raise a family.

RIGELHAUPT: Did most of your extended family, grandparents, aunts, uncles, did
they stay in North Carolina?

LLOYD: Most of them did. I had one uncle that came up here and two uncles killed
in the war. But most of them stayed in North Carolina.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you get to go back as a child?

LLOYD: Oh, yes. All the time. Every summer we went. That was what vacation was
in those days. You packed yourself in the car, your parents packed you, and you
went, and that was it.

I have a comment to make on during the war. You got a gasoline allotment, and I
remember one episode that we had. We had friends that were also from that area
of the country down in southern Virginia. In the summer we always went to
Carolina for a visit. These friends of ours had a place down there, too. And so
one time during the war, when we were on the gasoline allotment and so forth and
so on, we combined my father&#039;s license and got the gasoline, and this gentlemen
who we went with and his family got the gas, and we had nine people in that car.
We drove all the way down to southern Virginia with nine people in the car, and
then we went further down to my people&#039;s place. Then on the way back we did the
same thing. I remember it was so uncomfortable because there were four of them
and five of us. We had four children and so forth. So it was a very hard visit.
We enjoyed it. Laughed about it a lot because it was the way things went in that
time. I mean we had to have gasoline. We had to make all kinds of conditions to
get the gasoline. But that was one of the exciting things that I remember from
my childhood. I remember the gasoline rationing. And, of course, they had paper
drives, newspaper drives. They had aluminum and dishware, garden products,
everything that they collected during the war.

And Eleanor Roosevelt came out for a visit to the theater here, Arlington
Theater. There used to be an Arlington Theater in South Arlington. They built it
after we came, but I remember it so well because one winter Eleanor Roosevelt
came out, and we got free tickets to the movie. And we didn&#039;t know that it was a
movie. I don&#039;t know how this will reflect on us or anything. I don&#039;t mean we
were unhappy with this. But when we got up to the theater we were told that this
was for poor children, and she had a Christmas party with toys for what they
called poor children. And we didn&#039;t feel like we were poor children, so we
turned around and came home. It was just one of those things. We said, &quot;We&#039;re
not poor children. We don&#039;t have that problem.&quot; So I remember that so well. But
she was there, and we saw her, and they gave the toys out to all the kids who
came. That is one thing I remember so vividly from the time during the war.

Do you want any more war stories?

RIGELHAUPT: Yes, sure.

LLOYD: Okay. As I told you before, we went to Patrick Henry Elementary School,
and at that time they were having the air raids in England. So they sent two
children--I didn&#039;t know the girl, but I knew the boy--into Patrick Henry. I
remember he came to school, and he had on English knickers. You know those black
knickers, those very heavy knickers that kids had in those days? And we went to
school in dungarees, just regular cotton pants. And we had such a big laugh. We
didn&#039;t laugh at this kid because we knew he was so embarrassed. I remember his
name. Would you like to hear his name? His name was Edward Twentyman It was such
an English name. And at that time we were--I suppose I was in the fifth or sixth
at that time. And the boys lived on the fact that there was a war on. We weren&#039;t
glad it was on, but it was so exciting to have it on. We spent so much time
making toy balsa wood aircraft. I suppose you did that, too, at one time. But we
knew all the planes on every side. And we admired the RAF. So Edward Twentyman,
the boy I was telling you about earlier--. The interesting thing about that, and
I hope people will believe this, but in the sixth grade--whether this was an
effort to increase people&#039;s understanding what was going on during the war and
so forth, and to get Americans involved in thinking about this--they had us in
the sixth grade, the boys knitted these little patches-like--they were square
patches-- and then they sewed them all together and made up a quilt for the
English kids that were in the war bomb--I&#039;m looking for a word.

RIGELHAUPT: Shelters?

LLOYD: Yeah, the shelters, the air shelters. That&#039;s the word I was looking for.
I suppose they had those mostly in the underground railroads and stuff like
that. But we knitted these little squares, and they sewed them all together and
supposedly gave them to these British kids in the air shelters. And I honestly
thought these kids would think the war was over and they lost or something, they
getting [laughs] all these things were America; that this was something that was
supposed to help them. But we did it nonetheless.

Also they sold war stamps at school; you brought your money to school, you
bought a stamp, and they gave you a little book; you put in in there. And, of
course, this was--you could turn it in later on and get money for it. Of course,
we had an aunt that used to come out to our house every Christmas because she
was a lady who had lost her husband, and we had her out because she was an aunt
from Carolina. And she was a Redskin fan; everybody in Washington was a Redskin
fan and still is. There were four children in our family. She would bring a war
bond for each one of us; And we&#039;d have Christmas Eve and have the war bond. And
we thought we were the richest kids in the world. You got an $18.75 bond, and
you got $25 for it later on. We enjoyed that so much, getting the bond and
seeing my Aunt Mary who would come out.

And the Redskins were almost an institution; well they are an institution here,
and everybody follows them. And we used to follow them with all the good players
that they had. And that was a wonderful time.

What else might I contribute?

RIGELHAUPT: You sparked two questions. I&#039;ll do one at a time. You mentioned all
the airplanes. How did you learn about them?

LLOYD: They were in all the magazines. They were in all the movies. We knew the
Japanese Zero was such a great fighter plane. We knew the Germans had the
Luftwaffe, had the Heinkel and the Messerschmitt and the Focke-Wulf. We all had
BB rifles, the kids had BB rifles, and nobody thought anything of it. I remember
when France fell, when the French surrendered to the Germans, and they had Vichy
and all that they did, we organized a boys&#039; squad. We thought the Germans would
be soon over and all this kind of business. We all had BB rifles, and marched up
and down. It was just kid stuff, but it was significant at the time because we
really thought the Germans were going to win the war because it looked like they
were for a while. At this time they were about to engage the Russians, and the
French had fallen, and the Russians. So we were really into the war all the way.
Actually, what else was I going to say about the war?

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember what the magazines were that you were reading where
you learned about all the airplanes?

LLOYD: Yeah. They had it in most of the magazines, Wings and things like that.
And they had it in the movies, like Thirty Seconds over Tokyo. The British put
on all kinds of--planes and the RAF and the war in Italy. Not Italy, excuse me.
The war in Africa, I&#039;m thinking about now. They had all kinds of pictures about
the war in Africa and the British. The British were heroes of all of the kids,
as were the Chinese. Chiang Kai-shek. Madame Chiang Kai-shek The fact that they
were fighting the Japanese, though even at that time they had been so cruel. At
least we heard that they had been so cruel. We heard of the Rape of Nanking.
Remember that. You might have read it from somewhere. And Chiang Kai-shek and
Madame Chiang Kai-shek were heroes. So the war was just every part of our--we
thought about it every day. I had a dictionary that had in the back--it had some
drawn maps in the back of the dictionary. I had the maps where the Germans had
taken over and all that stuff. We enjoyed that. Not all the killing; we didn&#039;t
enjoy that. But we did enjoy keeping up with the war, as most of the kids in the
country did.

RIGELHAUPT: You mentioned the Rape of Nanking. So how did you learn about that?
Was it in newspapers, magazines, newsreels before films?

LLOYD: Yes, it was in the newspaper, in the paper. Magazines. And movies. All
the movies had that. And the Japanese and how cruel they were to the Chinese.
And how they were conquering the whole country and so forth and so on. The
Chinese were the victims of the Japanese. So that was part of my boyhood.

RIGELHAUPT: It sounds like you read the newspaper from a young age?

LLOYD: Oh, yes. Well, yeah. Well, see, I enlisted in the Air Force right after I
got out of high school. You had to be eighteen to get in the Air Force. Well, I
joined the Air Force when I was eighteen, and we were still--there was no war on
when I graduated in 1949, from high school. But they still had the draft, and I
went down to Clarendon here and registered for the draft. And I walked down from
Washington-Lee. A couple of others had to go, and so we all walked down from
Washington-Lee and registered, got our stickers and all for the Air Force. And
that&#039;s about it I guess for the war.

RIGELHAUPT: Now, you mentioned that you made a quilt for children in England
most likely sheltering in the underground tubes. Was this before the bombing at
Pearl Harbor and the US had actually entered World War II?

LLOYD: It was early in the war. It was early in the war. But I remember when we
entered the war with the Japanese because--this was on Sunday, as you all know.
We were playing football in the street in Arlington, on Pollard Street in
Arlington. Because we always played down there. And my dad came home from work
and came down and told us what had happened. The Japanese had bombed Pearl
Harbor. And we didn&#039;t even know where Pearl Harbor was. I don&#039;t think many
Americans did at that time because it was not significant at all. The Hawaiian
Islands were not as prominent and understanding--Americans didn&#039;t really
understand much about Pearl Harbor until that time. But yeah. What was the rest
of the question? Did you have another?

RIGELHAUPT: I was asking about if you knew the quilts that you made, if that was
taking place before Pearl Harbor and the US involvement. Not that--

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: Not that my question was aimed at you knowing exactly but part of it
was trying to get at what was--did you have a sense before the war that the US
was likely to become involved?

LLOYD: Oh, yes.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you know that this was something that--?

LLOYD: Absolutely. We couldn&#039;t see any way in the world that the United States
was not going to be involved in this because the Germans were so ruthless in the
way they handled everything and the way they invaded Poland. With Mussolini they
invaded parts of Africa and all of Italy and all of these things. Yeah. Every
day there was something in the newspapers about what was going on in Europe. Of
course, by this time I was in sixth or seventh grade. I could read, and I could
understand pretty well what was going on. Yes. We knew all of that. I think most
kids did because it was in the papers. Every day we saw that. And it was never
any question about who was right and who was wrong, who was invading someone
that had done nothing to them. Germans got a very bad name and so did the
Japanese. And you wonder sometimes if some of it might have been overdrawn but,
after all, people were getting killed. Efforts were being made to--whether we
were going to win this thing. Because people don&#039;t realize how strong the
Germans were and the Japanese. I read some stories about how the Japanese and
the Germans both had been prepared for the war and we had not been preparing for
the war. So that was my childhood, as all the people in this area.

I remember the first year I got to the Virginia school--this was Patrick Henry,
as I indicated. They grouped everybody together, and then they put--if you were
going into the fourth grade or the fifth grade they put you in that room, and
you would get to know some of the kids and so forth. And I remember they put me
in whatever grade I was at the time, and we had a lot of paperwork to do and so
forth and so on. And then they asked for volunteers to sing. I remember the two
girls; I later knew these two girls. One of them was going to sing something
from The Wizard of Oz and the other one was going to sing The White Cliffs of
Dover. And, of course, the Wizard of Oz was not a war song at all but The White
Cliffs of Dover, there was no question about that being a war song. &quot;The blue
birds over the white cliffs of Dover. Tomorrow when the world is free. There&#039;ll
be love and laughter and peace ever after tomorrow when the world is free.&quot; Here
I was in fourth grade. I was in the fourth grade. I was in sixth or seventh
grade; I don&#039;t know, but yeah, the war was a huge part of our lives at that time.

And then I remember two very bad personal experiences that I had. My mother had
two brothers that were killed in the war. One was killed in a training accident
they had. He was in the port--at the Army base in Indiana, I think it was.
Indiana. I came home from school, and my mother was lying on the bed and crying.
And I said, &quot;What in the world? What is this?&quot; I went in. I found out that she
had got a call from Carolina that he had been killed in war. That was a real
experience for me. And later on at Saint-Lô in France, at the time of the
invasion, her other brother, the other brother, was a chaplain&#039;s assistant in
the American Army, and they were at Saint-Lô, and the German artillery
blew--the truck that he was using; they killed him. And she was in the bed
again. It was a terrible time. There was nothing amusing about it at all or
anything. It was terrible. And, of course, at the invasion--well, we all know
what happened when they invaded--well, not invaded but sent troops into France
to stop, to halt the war if they could, which they did.

But I don&#039;t know what else to say about it. It was just a sad but memorable
experience in my life, and I still remember. I was in public education for my
career, and when I retired one of the things they gave me was my World War II
book because we had talked about it in class. Are there some other questions I could--

RIGELHAUPT: I was asking, obviously it had to have been incredibly hard to lose
family members. And you obviously weren&#039;t alone in the sense of hundreds of
thousands, if not millions of American families, lost--

LLOYD: Oh, yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: And I say that to ask did you talk about that with your friends? Did
friends have similar experiences?

LLOYD: Yes. We had a whole neighborhood group there that--we were all about the
same income. There was no competition or anything like that in that. There was
one lady that lived in our neighborhood that was of German extraction. In fact,
she had come over before the war, and her background was in Germany. We didn&#039;t
like her too much, and I think it was because of that fact. And we had some of
the older guys that took us under their wing when we were playing ball and stuff
like that because--see, one other thing about where I lived in South Arlington,
there was a meadow at the end of the Pollard Street in my neighborhood, sort of
in the heights of Arlington, which was subject to invasion by the--I guess you&#039;d
have to call it the Yankees when Arlington was a young and very southern city.
We played baseball there, and these guys would--these older guys would come by
and give us tips and stuff like that.

So we all had great admiration for the troops out there, and we had several that
were killed in the war that were neighbors that I knew very well. There was a
whole neighborhood there. A lady and husband up there from Greece and they&#039;d
come to the United States. And the Greeks had been invaded by the Germans. And
this lady that was a German--there was nothing in there like, for example, they
had out in California, I understand, during the first World War where the
Germans were sometimes persecuted. That wasn&#039;t the case; we didn&#039;t do that to
this lady because she was a nice lady, and she didn&#039;t try to claim the Germans
were correct and all this. But that kind of things we thought about all the time.

There was one incident that I remember so well. Up on Columbia Pike--you know
where Columbia Pike is? Well, you may not know that. But anyway, right after the
invasion of France and then Germany with Normandy and all of that, there was
this guy that I didn&#039;t know well. He wasn&#039;t one of the guys I knew very well. I
did recognize him, that he&#039;d been in the service. He had a fender-bender with an
older man, and they had almost gotten in a fight. They were yelling things at
one another, and I saw that he had been wounded, had a scar up in his eye, above
his eye. A scar that went there, and he&#039;s telling this guy, &quot;Come on, I can take
anything. I can take anything,&quot; he said. &quot;I can take anything. You want to
fight, we&#039;ll fight.&quot; And, of course, the other guy didn&#039;t want to fight. So that
never developed into anything, which I was glad of because there&#039;s no need
having an unnecessary thing like that. Most people that lived through the war
understand that. I don&#039;t know what else to tell you.

RIGELHAUPT: I&#039;m intrigued by what you said earlier, in the years leading up to
the war. You were probably around ten. That you knew Germany and Japan were
strong militarily.

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: And taking over territory around the world and invading other
countries. And that they might win.

LLOYD: Yeah, we knew that.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you talk about with your friends--again, you were ten years old.
It may not have been conversations you had of what would the world be like.

LLOYD: No, we didn&#039;t have any. I don&#039;t remember any really mature declarations
for anything that would happen. But, yeah, we did. Kids, eleven, twelve years
old, always going on, always hearing this stuff, they get to the point where
they think it&#039;s very interesting. But we were always hoping that the war would
be over and we would win it. That was what we were hoping. I remember
particularly when the movies, like Thirty Seconds over Tokyo, and we read about
that and saw that in the movies. And what was happening in North Africa with
Rommel and his soldiers, and the British soldiers and so forth. So yes, we were
very well informed. Whether it was completely accurate or not--but there was
never any sympathy for the Germans and what they were doing.

RIGELHAUPT: You just mentioned that you and your friends wanted to see the US
get into the war.

LLOYD: Well, it wasn&#039;t that we really wanted to see them get into the war. What
we wanted to see is that the Allies were going to win the war. That was the
thing that we wanted to see. And we had a great admiration for the British. Now,
I don&#039;t think we knew the Communists in Russia. I was in the glee club in high
school, and we used to sing Russian songs. The teacher never mentioned a war or
anything, but they had Russian combat songs and Russian &quot;tovarisch.&quot; I remember
the Russian word for--I think it was &quot;tovarisch.&quot; It was a Russian word for
comradeship and so forth. It was a good song; it sounded good. I remember that.
But it didn&#039;t take long before we decided the Russians weren&#039;t as admirable as
we thought they were.

RIGELHAUPT: And so before the US enters the war there&#039;s an uncertainty?

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: Right. It was very interesting to hear you articulate that. That you
and your friends could sense that the future was uncertain.

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: Trying to think back when your father first told you about Pearl
Harbor, did that seem to signal--what did that signal to you in terms of that
uncertain moment?

LLOYD: Well, I guess the thing that we realized at that time was, this was a
group that hated us because we saw they had--they didn&#039;t have any TV at that
time, but they had casters, broadcasters that would tell you about what happened
to the American Navy there, what happened to all the men that were killed and
all that. We just couldn&#039;t tolerate that. It was just such a cowardly blow. You
don&#039;t know what causes nations to do these kinds of things. You know world
history, you know that this has been going on in one area after another all
through man&#039;s history together. But it was such a cowardly act that
Americans--we were very naïve about that. Americans didn&#039;t do those kind of
things. We felt like Americans didn&#039;t do them. And, of course, we haven&#039;t done
like so many countries have done, but we&#039;ve had our day in court. So I hope I
haven&#039;t given you a too drastic picture there.

RIGELHAUPT: Part of what I&#039;ve read about and heard about after Pearl Harbor is
that people immediately, Monday morning, lined up at army recruiting stations.

LLOYD: They did.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember seeing anything like that? Obviously, you were too
young to go do that, but was there an immediate sense among you and your friends
and your family of &quot;we are going to contribute somehow, we are going to do something&quot;?

LLOYD: Yeah. There certainly was. And whether it was either out of British
propaganda or whether it was because of what officials in our country knew, that
we were going to have to fight these people, they let everything revolve around
that because the papers were always talking about what had happened at Pearl
Harbor. And the Jewish people being treated so badly and what the Germans were
doing and why they weren&#039;t cooperating, and things like that, without any kind
of gesture made to keep it peaceful. Remember Chamberlain and what he did? I was
always interested in this stuff. I just liked it. Might not like the outcome
sometimes, but it was interesting. I got to say it was interesting what was
going on.

And as I told you before, I had an old dictionary that had a map in it, and I
had where the Germans had advanced and what country they were going to now and
so forth and so on. And now Britain and France made that agreement that they
would fight if Germans invaded Poland. And they did. They just came right out
and invaded them. The Germans knew the war was going on. And it was just the way
it was in those days.

I hope we don&#039;t have to go through that again with anybody. Today, though, we
have serious ethnic and religious problems but not someone as ruthless and
powerful as Hitler was.]

And American music. I remember American music. You remember Hitler&#039;s song? That
they used to sing that? They would sing that in movies sometimes to get people
laughing. They&#039;d say--well, let me remember. Hitler says, &quot;We is the master
race,&quot; and they would accent it like that. &quot;Ve ist the master race.&quot; &quot;Ve ist.&quot;
We say &quot;Heil, heil, heil,&quot; and then they&#039;d make an obscene gesture, like
[spitting sound] right into the Fuhrer&#039;s face, and that&#039;s what they did. That
was a song that was very popular in those days. And then they had the movie
about Hitler and all. And then obviously you know it must have impressed me
because I remember so much of it. I&#039;m not glad it happened, but I&#039;m glad I do
remember it.

RIGELHAUPT: It sounds as though popular culture, movies in particular, were one
of the ways you learned a lot about what was going on. Do you remember other
forms of popular culture? Comic books, for example, or other things that
informed you about the war?

LLOYD: I read in Reader&#039;s Digest how this Japanese guy had picked an American to
box him, or to fight him. He was going to use his jujutsu, as he called it. He
said, &quot;He won&#039;t remember that.&quot; But it was a Japanese way of fighting someone.
And he was to box. And the Japanese guy beat him up one time, and then the next
time the American used his glove and beat him up, beat the Japanese guy up.

And what I was going to suggest, or talk to you about, was that fact that now
they have so many activities like karate and all the engagements for kids.
Soccer, all the soccer, all the different things they have. When I was growing
up the kids did more or less what they wanted to on their own. They didn&#039;t have
any organizations working with them. They didn&#039;t have any soccer practices,
anything like that. What we used to do in the summer was throw out the softball
and go play softball or baseball and then--summertime it was baseball. When fall
came it was football and basketball if you could get to a gym. But none of the
elementary schools had gyms so you didn&#039;t do that. And the sport that we used to
do that was so popular was marbles. I don&#039;t know whether you ever played marbles
or not. But we used to play marbles every--it would come in the springtime. When
it first got warm all the kids come to school with marbles, and we used to play
keepsies or comesies--or longsies. What was it? If you kept them you called them
keepsies. If you lost them, if the other kid&#039;s marble knocked yours out, you
lost your marble. I guess that&#039;s why &quot;you&#039;re losing your marbles.&quot; But we used
to do all of that kind of stuff. I remember in elementary school--and I was in
education, as I told you before--the teachers over at Patrick Henry would give
us what we&#039;d call recess, and then everybody would go outside and play ball of
some kind. The girls played hopscotch or something like that. The boys played
either football or basketball. Not basketball, but football or baseball or
marbles or something like that. And they didn&#039;t have any real extracurricular
sports activities, except just for recess, as we used to call it.

RIGELHAUPT: I&#039;m going to pause right there. I need to change tapes.

RIGELHAUPT: I am on tape number two with David Lloyd. Still June 5, 2012. And as
I was changing tapes we talked briefly about the Depression and that it preceded
World War II, and you were talking about what you remembered about people
visiting your house and your mother.

LLOYD: Yeah. Well, before I go into that I want to say that my father had a
steady job. All through the war he had the same job. My mother taught school on
an irregular basis because she had taught in North Carolina, and they needed
teachers all over the place. But I didn&#039;t say, I haven&#039;t talk about this, that
my mother and my father both had large rural families. My parents were both
country girls and boys. We had visitors from our family that came up and would
stay with us until they got a job somewhere in DC because the jobs were in DC.
If there was any way to have them, they were in DC because they could just get
more jobs there than they could down in Carolina or even in Richmond here or
Arlington. We used to have an uncle. He&#039;d come in most every summer and stay
with us until he got a job. They would get jobs either driving cabs or
other--working for funeral homes. Doing all kinds of stuff. They would stay and
work at our house. So we had a lot of that. Let&#039;s see, what else was I going to say?

Oh, I was going to tell about--lots of women did this. That they would give
sandwiches to hoboes and people that didn&#039;t have jobs that would come around to
the house. And I&#039;m just wondering now. I heard later on that the the people
without money, without a job or anything, had a way that they could leave a note
or some kind of something to make another one know that there was a lady there,
a kindly lady that would leave him with a sandwich or something. Because they
used to come by all the time, and my mother would usually give them a sandwich.
Wasn&#039;t anything fancy; it was just a sandwich. But we didn&#039;t think anything of
it. We thought the guy&#039;s just hungry, so we give that. We lived in Washington at
that time, and the jobs were up here. If they were any place, they were up here.
That&#039;s what I remember about that.

RIGELHAUPT: So you had family come up from North Carolina?

LLOYD: Family would come up and stay with us and work--get a job or something
like that.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you have a sense that the Depression hit your family in North
Carolina harder than your immediate family in--?

LLOYD: Well, no. The only thing we could realize from this thing is that my
background was always--on both sides they were rural people. And they always had
food. There was food to grow. You could grow food, and there weren&#039;t too many
jobs around down there, but there was food to be had. And a lot of boys from the
country, and the city, too, went out and went into this hoboing or what they
call--. And, of course, President Roosevelt--I can&#039;t remember the name of that
group now. Country boys and city boys that went out--and it was a very famous
program that skips my mind now, that these boys were able to get jobs working in
the woods or building roads or in the cities. CCC, the CCC boys. Because that
was very popular. But I don&#039;t know any of my relatives that were CCC boys. I do
know some CCC boys that--I used to have a friend that, when he was younger, went
out, was with the CCCs. And it was very popular.

RIGELHAUPT: Well, the CCC, the Civilian Conservation Corps, was a New Deal program.

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: What did your parents, or did they--actually, why don&#039;t I back up
and ask--did you, your family, your parents, your friends, did you talk about
the New Deal and what these programs meant for the country and the changes they implemented?

LLOYD: Well, I just remember that there was nothing--that my parents never
talked about these guys being people that were trying to get something for
nothing, like so many people did. And that they were thieves and all. They could
do this and that. And I wouldn&#039;t to have this or that to do with any of them. My
parents were always very understanding about these guys. They admired them in
many ways. I never had any relatives with them but I do know--I could say--I
never met a person who was a CCC guy that had anything to say about the group
except that it was the best around. They would really have a tough time if it
hadn&#039;t been for them. I think it was a very important, very good program.

And in Johnson&#039;s Administration, in the Job Corps that they used to have--as I
told you, I was a teacher, and then I was in administration. And we had many
boys, particularly boys, that were not anxious for school and had no interest in
school. And we dismissed them if they get in the Job Corps. And they would come
in--I used to come in and kids would come in my office and tell me how they&#039;d
gotten in the Job Corps and they were leaving school and so forth because so
many of the states had realistic--irrealistic, I should say--. Some people just
are not--they don&#039;t like algebra. They don&#039;t like physics or anything like that,
and they really like the Job Corps. They used to feel like it was a real triumph
to come in and get in the Job Corps. And I thought it was too, because they
wanted something useful to do, and this was it. Because Virginia, see, had
the--you have to. You can&#039;t just drop out of school. You can&#039;t say when you&#039;re
sixteen years old, say, &quot;I don&#039;t want school anymore,&quot; because we got a
compulsory attendance law. You&#039;ve got to stay in school. If you&#039;re not
interested in school, had nothing to do with school, you were just foreign to
everybody. So the Job Corps or something like that would put these kids to work,
and they loved it. They loved it. So I wish they still had it for kids that
can&#039;t--that don&#039;t like school and do something--I mean, they weren&#039;t dumb kids,
all of them; they just didn&#039;t like school. So I&#039;m letting out a lot of steam
here. I hope I didn&#039;t--

RIGELHAUPT: But going back to the New Deal and some of the government programs
that you&#039;re talking about, certainly reading about Roosevelt and the New Deal
retrospectively is--well, he&#039;s certainly held in high regard as a President. I&#039;m
curious if you had a sense--and, again, you were young but it sounds like very
aware of world events if you&#039;re mapping things in the back of the dictionary.
Did you have a sense that FDR was doing new and important things as they were happening?

LLOYD: We were--when I say we, I mean--I think that I was always a Democrat. I
mean, when I started voting--they didn&#039;t let kids vote, of course. But I thought
these programs were good. I thought when I was working in school administration
I thought the programs were good. When I used to have to teach--I taught history
and government a couple times--that these were great programs. There&#039;s no
question in my mind about it. I thought the Job Corps was good although you had
to be careful with that. You had some people that didn&#039;t do the best they can in
this, but that&#039;s always the case. There&#039;s always somebody that&#039;s not going to
appreciate, that&#039;s not going to work with you. But most of the guys were really,
that we talked to, wanted to work, and they wanted to do the right thing. That&#039;s
why I liked it.

RIGELHAUPT: So this moment of transition out of the Depression into World War
II. Arlington boomed. I&#039;m wondering if you could talk about what comes to mind
as you start thinking about the expansion of Arlington early in World War II.

LLOYD: The thing I remember most was the fact--now, we lived in the District. We
didn&#039;t live in the slums or something like that. But we lived in the District,
and it was crowded. Before the war started, people began to know that there was
going to be one, and there were going to be jobs somewhere, and the District was
the first place they came to. So the District was very crowded, and real estate
was expensive and so forth and so on. And the first time my dad drove us over to
see where we were going to live in Arlington, I was just fascinated with it.
Now, they didn&#039;t have what they have now, super highways coming in and out. They
had a second class airport on the Potomac here. It was really second class. No
Dulles or Reagan National or anything like that. Just a sort of second class
airport there. And the Pentagon wasn&#039;t there. When we moved to Arlington the
Pentagon wasn&#039;t there. And when I got out there I saw that it was--I don&#039;t know
whether this makes any difference or not, but I think--and I wouldn&#039;t want to
say whether I was positive of this or not--but I believe one of the first things
that I learned in school was the fact that Arlington had 20,000 people in it.
Now, I think now that Arlington has about 500,000. I think it says that. I
wouldn&#039;t want to be--the thing I&#039;m saying, it was enormous as far as the
population compared to what it is in those days. And the thing I liked best
about it is we came out, and they were building modest homes all over the place
and cutting down the trees. Now, I didn&#039;t like that because I loved the woods.
We used to spend all our time, most of our time, in the woods. We&#039;d build huts
down there. We had Four Mile Run, Four Mile Run down part of--it&#039;s part of
Arlington, between Arlington and Alexandria.

RIGELHAUPT: Well, could you describe what that was like when you were first
going there?

LLOYD: We never even thought about whether it could be contaminated or not. It
was a fresh water stream. If you were six feet tall you didn&#039;t--you thought it
was a little stream, no good to anybody. But when you&#039;re four feet tall or five
feet tall, it was a swimming hole. We swam in the Four Mile Run. And all the
time I swam in the Four Mile Run. We had the Four Mile Run. We had the lake at Barcroft.

RIGELHAUPT: One thing I was going to tell you about. If there&#039;s specific names
like this that just don&#039;t come to mind right now, you&#039;ll have a chance to look
at the transcript before it&#039;s finalized and fill in specific names like this.

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: So, it&#039;s no problem. If you can&#039;t remember now, you&#039;ll have a chance
to get it straight.

LLOYD: Fort Myer that&#039;s here, the Army base, Fort Myer. It was there, I think,
because it was over the height of what would be Arlington. But through the Civil
War they had had forts around Washington, some of them not full forts. And one
of these was at the end of Pollard Street in Arlington here. It was elevated. It
wasn&#039;t a fort but it was a high ground that they could--look down over the
valley that the Confederates would probably come up from the south. Obviously.
And that you would spot them coming up from the south on this sort of a plateau.
Fort Myer was operating then. And when I was a boy we used to have cavalrymen
ride their horses out to this height over Arlington and look down on Four Mile
Run and the creek and all of that, and that was very fascinating for a young
kid. We used to go out there, and we&#039;d find bullets that we used to think were
Civil War bullets. We never could figure out which ones were Civil War bullets
and which ones weren&#039;t. But we could find these bullets down there; we used to
look for them around on the height there. But the height looked down on Four
Mile Run Drive, and Four Mile Run was a creek; we used to call it a creek. And,
as I said, most of us I&#039;m talking about, were not--about four and a half, five
feet tall, and we could swim in there. We didn&#039;t have any problem about whether
it was clean or not because it was an outdoor stream, and we loved it up there.
We used Four Mile Run, and then there was Lubber&#039;s Run that&#039;s closer here, and
the Potomac River. I remember when we, in the springtime, we used to ride our
bicycles from Arlington here to Chain Bridge and go fishing in the river there
and all that. It was just wonderful for a kid because that&#039;s what boys like to
do. And we loved it. We loved the way Arlington was.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you ever go watch the Pentagon being built?

LLOYD: We saw it. We drove past. We could see the Pentagon being built, yeah.
And I worked down at the Pentagon. I don&#039;t mean I worked for the government or
anything, but during high school they needed a boy to work in the District
Newsstand, they called it, and that&#039;s where the Pentagon people could pick up
their newspapers, obviously, magazines and all. And they didn&#039;t choose me, but
they chose my brother to go down there and do this, to work for them. And, see,
we had a school bus. The school bus went right past my home, and I could get on
that school bus and go down to Columbia Pike and take the Pentagon down there
for a dime and work in the Pentagon. And I worked down there all through high
school. My brother and I and some of the other kids worked there. And it was a
wonderful kids job of some kind. It was so good. They gave me ten dollars a
week, and it cost a dime to ride down there on the bus. And you got down there,
and there&#039;s no security to my knowledge. I used to walk right on up there, go to
the newsstand and sell newspapers. I sold newspapers up at the shop up there,
and then they would take a group. They would take papers down to the south
parking. There was a south parking lot and so forth. I sold newspapers down
there. That was the greatest job I had in high school.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you have a sense at that point that the Pentagon wasn&#039;t--well,
that it had some symbolic meaning?

LLOYD: Yeah. We knew all along that it was a government building, that they
were--we didn&#039;t know exactly what they did, but we knew that it was a government
building. Because a good many of the people that came by and bought
newspapers--we sold newspapers and magazines, and we&#039;d didn&#039;t hawk them, or go
,&quot;Yeah, here&#039;s a newspaper.&quot; They came by, and they were mostly of the uniform;
there were a lot of uniformed guys that came by. They would come by and buy
their newspaper at this place. It was really a great job considering you&#039;re
looking for a job. I&#039;d ride the bus that came by my house that went right to the
Pentagon. I rode the bus from my house, and then when I came home I would ride
the bus out to Columbia Pike and catch the school bus. It was perfect. I
couldn&#039;t believe when he got that job.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember any other major expansions in terms of housing? I
think when we spoke briefly on the phone you mentioned that--was the airport
being built?

LLOYD: Yeah, the airport was being built all down there by the Potomac. But
there was an airport here before then. They had another airport that wasn&#039;t
as--I don&#039;t want to say grandiose, but it wasn&#039;t as, you know, up to date as the
one they have down there now. But there was one there, yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: Did you or your friends talk about the changes you were seeing in
Arlington? That it was becoming less rural, more urban, more built up during the
war? What did you guys think about it?

LLOYD: Well, actually, we didn&#039;t enjoy them cutting down all the woods. We
didn&#039;t enjoy that. And we didn&#039;t enjoy--on the other side of Four Mile Run,
there was a big mountain-like hill, and there was a farmer up there that was a
full-scale farmer. He still worked the land, and that was his main job. And he
used to invite everybody that wanted to, to come up and pick blackberries at his
place. It was such a nice thing to do. Go pick up blackberries and all. And his
name was the same as mine. He was no kin to us at all, but his name was Lloyd.
And the thing about it was, I told you that Four Mile Run is down at the run
below a mountainside on each side. There was a big hill on the other side.
There&#039;s a big hill still there now. If you look at Sixteenth Street, South
Arlington, and George Mason Drive, you&#039;ll see that they go down, way down. And
one of the things you felt like you&#039;d really accomplished was when you were able
to pump a bicycle up Lloyd&#039;s Hill. We used to call that Lloyd&#039;s Hill. And that
was no kin to me at all, but we used to enjoy going down Lloyd&#039;s Hill. Now, I&#039;ve
talked a lot. I hope I haven&#039;t bored you with some of this.

RIGELHAUPT: No, this is great. Part of the expansion in Arlington and other
parts of the country during World War II was new people moving in, right? People
may have come for jobs. Many different reasons, perhaps .Did you have a sense
that there were lots of new people moving in and perhaps attending school with you?

LLOYD: Yeah. Yeah, we did know that. But the only thing that bothered us, and it
would bother anyone, and it bothers anyone from any situation, was the fact that
a person would come in and be critical of Arlington County. And, of course, like
kids everywhere, you go up in the middle of New York, for example, and start
lambasting the schools up there, you would not like that. And I remember--this
is a funny thing. We had a guy that was an air raid warden. He works for the
government somewhere, but he was an air raid warden during the war. And he used
to be very critical of Arlington because he was from--I won&#039;t mention the town
he was from in Pennsylvania. But he thought he was--he liked to lambast
everything in Arlington. We used to think, and we never told him that, but he
ought to go to back to that town. If he didn&#039;t like Arlington, he could go back.
We didn&#039;t care. And there were lots of people. And I don&#039;t mean this to be
critical to people from Massachusetts, but I remember we lived a long time in
Fairfax, too, after I grew up and all. And we had a lady there that lived next
door to us, and she used to criticize everything that was in Fairfax. She didn&#039;t
like Fairfax. She wanted to go back to New England. She said we didn&#039;t know how
to drive during the snowstorms and things like that. It got irritating to hear that.

RIGELHAUPT: Now, you said your mom taught in school during World War II, and she
had been a teacher previously?

LLOYD: Yeah. She taught in North Carolina for a while, and then when she got
married she came back to--she came up here. And during the war there were a
whole lot of people had left their ranks and education, going in the army or to
come and work or something. So they were looking for teachers, and my mother
taught out at Bailey&#039;s Crossroads and taught out there during the war.

RIGELHAUPT: That&#039;s part of what I was going to ask, is that my understanding
from reading is that there was a time when a woman got married she could no
longer teach. And your mother was married during the war. Was that because, as
you said, there were shortages? They had to bend some of those rules to--

LLOYD: Well, I don&#039;t remember whether they had that rule. They might have
somewhere. But they were looking for teachers during the wartime, and she had
taught in North Carolina and had her certificate and so forth in North Carolina.
So they let her teach in the war. She didn&#039;t teach all through the war, but she
taught for a couple years there, and they always need teachers.

RIGELHAUPT: One other change nationally--and it may not have been as immediate
right in this area, but I&#039;m curious if you heard about it or have any
memories--was that Roosevelt issued Executive Order 8802, which banned
discrimination in terms of race in hiring in defense industries in 1941. And
part of what, right, that changed was that there were more African Americans
working in defense industries during World War II. Do you remember any sort of
similar changes occurring around Arlington? Of people who were in new places,
working in different jobs, different points of contact?

LLOYD: Well, I do in one respect. Of course--and everybody knows this, so I&#039;m
not telling you anything new--but Arlington was behind as far as African
Americans were concerned. I never went to school with an Afro-American until I
was in the service and I served in the service. I worked with these--but we
didn&#039;t persecute people like this or anything like that. But our school systems
were completely segregated. Elementary school to senior high school. We never
went to school with the colored guys. We wondered about it, but it was there. I
was talking a moment ago about the plateaus above the creek there, Four Mile
Run. Down at the bottom of Glebe Road, what is now Glebe Road, there was a large
Afro-American group of people living there. And we never had any trouble with
them at all. We never had any fights with anybody. We did occasionally run into
a group of black guys on the meadow up there. We would be up there playing ball,
and they would come by. We&#039;d look at them, talk to them. Sometimes we would
talk. We talked mostly about the base--not baseball but boxing because this was
Joe Louis time. Joe Louis. Max Schmeling was a German, and little did I know at
the time that Louis and Schmeling were great friends. There was no problem; they
knew each other. They weren&#039;t bosom buddies, but they knew each other and
respected each other. But we never had any difficulty with the black population
here. At least I don&#039;t remember any. We had no fighting with the black kids.

RIGELHAUPT: Were there kids of different ethnicities at your--either through
elementary or high school? Anywhere in your schooling? That ethnicity mattered
more? If you were Italian or Irish or Jewish or Greek, as you mentioned.

LLOYD: There was one problem that I know of, and it&#039;s not a problem to me, but
it was a problem with some of the kids that had to do this. Some of the Catholic
kids, apparently their parents didn&#039;t, or they didn&#039;t, I don&#039;t know who, but
there were times in school when the minister came in. Generally a Protestant
minister would come in, would come and talk to some of the classes. And the kids
that were not Protestants, they had a special place that they could go because
they didn&#039;t want to--and so as far as I know it was just the fact that they
didn&#039;t want to make kids that were not Protestant stay in there. So they just
went somewhere else, and they had a teacher in with them or someone that--no, I
don&#039;t remember any problems that we had at W and L [Washington-Lee], with the
religion of anybody that went to W and L, because when I was at W and L there
were like 2,600 kids. Twenty-five, twenty-four, something like that. It was a
large school, and we didn&#039;t pay attention to any of that. No one ever went there
that was black. But we had Italian kids, Greek kids, English kids, Irish kids.
Because there was no problem there.

RIGELHAUPT: How do you remember hearing about V-E Day?

LLOYD: V-E Day?

RIGELHAUPT: Yeah. Victory in Europe.

LLOYD: I was riding home from a track meet when I heard that. One of the kids
got on the bus and said, &quot;V-E Day. The war is over. V-E Day.&quot; Well, I told you
this before, I think. Didn&#039;t I tell you that we were playing football when the
Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor. I remember that clearly. I remember victory in
Europe and all the fun that went on there. Washington was like a--like it was a
fraternity house. Guys were kissing all the girls and making all the noise. It
was a great time. I didn&#039;t get downtown for that. But they had it on the movies
and all of that, and the fact of V-E Day and so forth. And it was a great, great
day. I&#039;ll never forget that because we saw that in the movies, and we heard it
on the television. There was no--I said we saw it on television. We didn&#039;t see
it on television. We saw it at the movies.

RIGELHAUPT: And how did you hear about the use of atomic weapons in Hiroshima
and Nagasaki?

LLOYD: Well, I was in school then. We didn&#039;t understand it. We didn&#039;t know about
the implications of it. I think everybody knew the Japanese were not going to
surrender easily. I think most people didn&#039;t like the fact that it took an
exercise of that sense in bringing the war to a close, but I think most people
thought that the war was--the Japanese were not going to surrender and that it
had to be done if the Japanese wouldn&#039;t surrender. Now, that&#039;s what I&#039;m saying.
A lot of people felt like that. I don&#039;t know. I don&#039;t know. It scares me because
I--when we&#039;re talking about a bomb that powerful. It really scared me, as it
scared most Americans. Most Americans were scared that we had a weapon of that
power. But at the same time they thought, well--that people were talking
about--I knew that people thought up to a hundred thousand men would be killed
if they had to invade Japan because the Japanese were not surrendering. They
were not surrendering anywhere. That wasn&#039;t a part of their culture, for people
to surrender. And they treated some Americans, particularly in the Philippines,
areas where a lot of American soldiers were, just treated so badly because a
soldier wasn&#039;t supposed to surrender and under their culture they didn&#039;t
surrender. To think about a hundred thousand men being killed because of a bomb.
Terrible. And they wanted the war to be over, I guess is what I&#039;m saying. What
can you say?

RIGELHAUPT: It sounds as though part of your initial reaction, and it sounds
like even perhaps you talked about it with other people, the part of the initial
reaction to the atomic bomb was fear, that this was something new and powerful
and unknown.

LLOYD: Yeah. That&#039;s true. That was it. We didn&#039;t understand it. Nobody knew
exactly what an atomic bomb was. They knew it was just terribly--as far as human
life, that it was--people were killed there in the hundreds of thousands. I
don&#039;t think anybody in the United States--even today, I don&#039;t think--nobody
wants to have to use that again. My God, they make all kinds of efforts not to
use it and to make sure no other country is going to use it. Right now, it
appears they have that same fear today.

RIGELHAUPT: Do you remember how you learned about the use of the atomic bomb in
Hiroshima and Nagasaki? Do you remember if you by chance saw a picture of a
mushroom cloud on a newspaper or a news--?

LLOYD: We did see what the thing involved, and we did have a lot of concern
about that. But we, I guess, figured that they&#039;d have to figure out a way to
live with it, or maybe we were going to die for it, you know. You think about
another war coming, all that. Something like that really shatters you, to think
that that could happen, to us. Could happen to anybody.

RIGELHAUPT: This may be an unanswerable question and in some ways not
necessarily a great comparison. But thinking about the atomic bomb as one symbol
of World War II that has had a lasting impact, that it changed the world--

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: What was it like learning about that and thinking about that without
television in the sense of--or even the Internet now. How do you think it would
be different if something like that had been--the way we have television news,
and they play it over and over and over again. Or--

LLOYD: I don&#039;t know. It would have just been such a--if it fell on an American
city it would have been such a terrible thing, such a tragedy to have it
so--like out here. An atomic bomb or something that hit Buckingham or something.
Just unbelievable. I can&#039;t even imagine what it would have been like. It was
such an awesome thing. Speaking of Buckingham, you know where Buckingham is?
That&#039;s down Glebe Road, to Buckingham. One of the movies we used to see in
Arlington was at Buckingham because we could get--we could ride up there on the
bus for a nickel. We used to do it, too. I&#039;d ride up there for a nickel. A
nickel back home. Ten cents you&#039;d ride the bus. It was about three miles from
Buckingham to where I lived, maybe less than that. Maybe two miles. But we used
to ride up that for a nickel. I can&#039;t imagine what it would be like to see this
area hit by an atomic bomb. Just beyond comprehension. I hope it never happens.
Hope it never happens anywhere. I think that&#039;s the only advantage of the fact
that it&#039;s such a tragic thing to happen to anybody. That people will go to great
lengths not to let it happen. I hope that&#039;s what we&#039;re doing now, going to great
lengths to not let it happen.

RIGELHAUPT: As I look at this I have pretty much asked about all the
questions--we have touched on most of the things I wanted to ask about. And I
tend to like to end with two questions. First, is there anything I should have
asked and I didn&#039;t? And, two, is there anything you&#039;d like to add?

LLOYD: Well, I&#039;d like to know, what is the purpose of all this?

RIGELHAUPT: The project?

LLOYD: Yeah.

RIGELHAUPT: The oral histories are going to be part of, and help to inform, the
Rosie the Riveter World War II Home Front National Historic Park in Richmond,
California. And so I&#039;m working for UC Berkeley, who&#039;s working with the National
Park Service to record and document what Americans remember about the home front
during World War II.

LLOYD: Well, I think everybody in a position like I&#039;m in, and talking about this
and thinking about it and working with someone with it, you don&#039;t want people to
think you&#039;re all wrong on all these things. And my name will be on it, this
conversation. Well, is it what you wanted? Is it something you think will be
interesting to people?

RIGELHAUPT: Yes. Hands down.

LLOYD: We&#039;re all vain enough to think if I&#039;m going to do it I want it to be on a
positive note and people will understand why I am seeing these things. Because
there&#039;ll be obviously hundreds of people that--maybe not the same mind, but I
mean, you see something like this, and there&#039;s always somebody that says, &quot;Oh,
that guy&#039;s all crazy.&quot; So you have enough concern to want to do well on the
thing. I could tell you something else but that wouldn&#039;t be too--you want to do
well in a situation like this. You want to think it means something to people
that--because I can&#039;t think of anything that made more of an impression on me
than World War II. I was at the right age, and I was at the right spot, and I
had tragedy in my life from the war. Right now I think of there&#039;s people that
are getting their kids killed in the war now, and I think if we can do something
better than what we&#039;re doing; I don&#039;t know how we&#039;re going to do it, but
something&#039;s got to be done. I&#039;m not un-American. I know we have to do some of
these things. But I think of those kids that are getting killed now--I mean,
they killed 40,000 people. That&#039;s unbelievable that it ever happened. I don&#039;t
know of anything else that I--anything this&#039;ll do to help it I&#039;d like to do.

RIGELHAUPT: All right. That&#039;s a nice note to end on. Thank you.

LLOYD: Well, I hope it helps.

RIGELHAUPT: It does. Thank you.

[End of Interview]

  

  

  

  

  

  PAGE  iv 

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>