<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00042031" dt="2017-10-20"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2002-12-16</date><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Harriette Stewart Interview #1: Rosie the Riveter World War II American Homefront Oral History Project</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Harriette Stewart</interviewee><interviewer>Kathryn Stine</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync></sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url></media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format></clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>﻿STINE: I’m here today with Harriet Stewart, and it’s the 16th of December
2002. We are going be talking a little bit about her time in Richmond, her time
working at the shipyard, and what she does now. Just to get started, I’d like
to talk about your background a little bit. Can we first get your full name and
where you were born?

STEWART: Yes! Harriette Dendinger Stewart was my maiden name. And I was born in
Harington, Nebraska, 7, 23,1919. The third of five children of Will and Martha
Dendinger. We grew up on the farm, 8 grades, then my folks sent my three sisters
and me to live at Mount Marty Academy in Yankton, South Dakota, a Benedictine
convent. We spent all our high school days there. We walked across the Missouri
River on Monday morning and up through town, past Lawrence Welk’s house and up
to the school and spent the week there. Then on Friday night, we walk back home
across the river and a hired man was there with the car to take us home for the
weekend. We had a wonderful life. Our folks didn’t give us a lot of money, but
they gave us rich things like trips. In 1926, two families of us drove to Long
Beach, California and spent the winter. There were five children in our family
and four in theirs. Every weekend in Long Beach, we went sight seeing.

STINE: How old were you then?

STEWART: I was in the first grade.

STINE: Oh, Wow!

STEWART: Scared to death, because our country school was altogether different
than 35 children in one room, in a city school. But it was quite an experience
and we talk about today even how wonderful that trip was. But our folks also
took us on trips to Yellowstone, the Black Hills, and Lake of [Calbogie], and
all over South Dakota and Nebraska. So we had a wonderful background for growing
up wholesome. We had wonderful parents. Oh, my goodness! Just such wonderful
parents and that meant a lot to us.

STINE: What did they do?

STEWART: We lived on the farm, but my Dad didn’t like to farm so we always had
a hired man. But he dealt in cattle -- buying and selling cattle, and he made
his living in cattle. My mother was a teacher before she was married and then
became a mother right away. So that took her time for five children. They
retired in 1946, I think it was, and came to San Francisco, and lived for 30
years, and enjoyed the wonders of the city. Of course, age caught up with them,
and they are both dead now. But we were a close family and that was good. We
always enjoyed going to see Mom and Dad, and the kids did too -- their
grandchild, so that was great.

STINE: That first trip that you had to California, do you remember your first
impressions of going to California? What kind of things your family would talk
about, remembering what was like?

STEWART: We camped. The two weeks or so that it took us to drive that far, and
there were hardly any maps, no paved roads, mostly gravel or dirt roads. Once in
a while, the two cars would stop and wonder if we were on the wrong road --
somebody said “You turned the wrong road” and “No, I didn’t.”
[laughter] They had to decide who was right, but we camped all the way. We took
everything with us, our tents, our sleeping things -- course you didn’t have
sleeping bags then. We put something tarp on the ground and our blankets were
the pillow and that was it. [laughter] So, you had a hard bed. When we landed in
Long Beach, both families landed in a motel right on the beach until they can
find a house to live in. That only took a week and we found a house, two houses
in the same block. So we lived there and the kids all went to the same school,
and that was great. But we went to all kinds of places, the Busch Gardens down
there, and out on the bay on the boat to see what boat life was -- they were
displaying, everything! There was a big fun village in Long Beach at that time,
something like Disneyland only not that great, but that was an eye opener too,
you know. We grew up as kids thinking we were grownup, you know [laughter],
seeing all that from the farm, it’s quite a change. One thing we were blessed
with, we were never sick, never sick. We never went to the doctor not unless
there was a broken bone. Home remedies took care of everything. That was it. The
two families of us when we came back, we always had parties and dinners
together. We would pop a dishpan of popcorn for nine kids and two batches of
fudge and play cards. [clearing throat] Of course, the folks went to the living
room, [laughter], and listened. That was great growing up with that other
family. It was a nice treat.

STINE: Did they ever make their way out to California also?

STEWART: Oh yes, they came up to see us. I just finished a Christmas letter to
the one that lives in Illinois and one more to write in Nebraska. So they are
two of them left and two of us left. We compare.

STINE: That’s great that you are still in touch.

STEWART: Yeah, oh yes! That’s marvelous. I think family friends of that
duration, say 70 years, it’s a good token to enjoy. So then I came out here. I
went to Creighton in Omaha, and took nurses training there and graduated in1941.

STINE: Before that, could you just talk a little bit about your decision to go
into nursing and how you mentioned that in your family none of children never
were sick and your parents weren’t sick.

STEWART: No, they never were. Well, my grandmother had cancer and was in bed at
home dying. They had a nurse come take care of her. It was Fern [Renner] who was
Mrs. Lawrence Welk eventually. She made such an impression on the family, what a
lady she was -- impressed us kids, we just looked at her and stared at her,
because she was such a wonderful person all around. I thought well, that would
be pretty good, because that would be different than being a teacher. My mother
was a teacher and I thought, “Well, let’s try this.” So I went into nurses
training and was scared to death. I was on limited income -- I didn’t have any
money, and another thing I had grown to be 5 foot 10 tall, so I was a freak. I
didn’t have a lot of clothes and I couldn’t borrow anything, so I didn’t
date anybody because I didn’t have the money to go out nor the clothes. When
you are that tall, you can’t borrow nor can I go across the street to have a
hamburger. But I was so used to growing up that way that it was okay.

STINE: So you’ve always been tall?

STEWART: Oh yeah! I was used to people, “What happened to you?” or
something. But that happened quite often and you just got so you shrug your
shoulders, you know. Fortunately, you grow up and you don’t let things like
that bother you too much. It’s pity if you do. I came out here with four other
nurses that we all graduated together. Two of us went to L.A, and two up here
because their husbands were in the navy, doctors and they were going to be
shipped out, so they came up to San Francisco. While they were waiting for the
husbands to call them to go overseas to live with them, they started to work at
the shipyard. They called us right a way and said, “If you want a good job,
come up here for pay.” So I worked at Good Samaritan in L.A for three months
and quit there and came up on the train. When I left Omaha, I had a hundred
dollars in my purse. My Dad asked me, “Do you have enough money,” and I said
“I have hundred dollars and my ticket. That was all right, I didn’t get
anymore, but that was all right. Of course you are on the train, you seat up for
two days, two nights, [laughter], and that’s way life was. But I came up here
and I went down to Pill Hill and applied with Millie Cutting.

STINE: In Pill Hill, Oakland?

STEWART: In Oakland, and that’s where the office was for the Kaiser people.
Millie Cutting read my application, and said, “Can you go to work this
afternoon at Yard One?” I said, “Well, yes.” I was pleased, I think, oh my
goodness! My friend had taken me, my nurse friend, so she took me to Yard One.
As we went down Cutting Blvd., it was two lanes wide and on 14th and Cutting,
they were just pouring the cement for the foundation of the first Kaiser
Hospital. So I went to work in yard one and let me tell you, that was an eye
opener, because I never seen so many people. Had to get my picture taken first
and given a badge so I have that, and was taken down to the first aid little
clinic area that we had. We had a doctor, three RNs and two first aid men and a
van for the medical care. We worked six days a week quite often. All of the
shipyard men worked six days a week. I lived in San Francisco for a month when I
first came up here. Then those girls got called to go with their husbands so
they left their apartment in Berkeley on Spruce and Hearst, so I slept over
there right away for shortening the commute thing and lived there for over four
years. So, that worked out great.

STINE: Had you considered moving to Richmond?

STEWART: No, no. It was so nice living in Berkeley, because it was very safe
then -- you can walk anywhere and not worry. Even though it was late at night,
people walked. I was lucky there were a man across the street that drove out to
the shipyard eventually, so I rode with him quite a bit to work. Of course, it
was ride to and from, so that worked out great. Then they saw the nurse that was
with me and got her call to go into the navy nurse corp. At that time, I have
met my husband-to-be and we were married January, 16th, 1944. He lived on
Woolsey and Berkeley and he moved over to my place, because we had a better
apartment. We lived there until I got pregnant with twins and then we had had a
place to live with two children. I had taken care of a lady whose husband was
head of the Richmond Housing authority. She said, “You go out and see him,
he’ll get you an apartment.” Because finding a place to live was impossible.

STINE: This is in 1940 -- ?

STEWART: ’46. It was really just -- . If anybody moved, there were somebody in
there the next day, they knew. We had a deposit on a place in Walnut Creek in
case nothing turned up, just in case we had a place to go. But we went out to
see this man and he gave us an apartment on South 13th . I thought that’s only
three blocks from the hospital, that’s good. So we lived there for four years
and saved every nickel and bought a lot on 14th and Virginia and built a duplex,
and I helped. Then, we bought a lot across the street and built another duplex,
and we kept buying lots on the south side and building houses on them and
renting them. We did that for twenty-seven years. My husband was ten years older
than I was and it was getting risky to go down at night to collect rent, if we
had to go back, so we sold them. We said that’s time enough. So we sold them.
We had bought this place, because another daughter was coming here so we had
three children needed a bigger house. I’ve been here since 1956, so this is
the last move I’ll make, I hope. My husband died thirteen years ago and I
lived fine. I took care of being four and half years giving daily care for his
health, and couldn’t go anywhere but that’s okay, I’d did what a wife
would do. We worked together all the time we were married -- forty-six years,
and we pulled together and that was good. Whatever we did, we did it together,
and that’s the way it worked. Didn’t know any different, really. We also
built a house up in Placerville for the summer home. We went up there every week
or two weeks and enjoyed that. That was a great deal.

STINE: I want to jump back now we kinda got a sense of where you’ve been
living and what you did from the war on. I’m gonna jump back and kind of
figure out what life was like for you being a young nurse in the shipyards and
kind of start there going in.

STEWART: You know, in the shipyard, we were the only women allowed in the
shipyard at first before Rosie the Riveter came. We wore uniforms and we’re so
well respected. The men treated us with courtesy beyond. We were very busy, we
didn’t sit at all, we were busy the eight hours at every shift.

STINE: So the pace was really --

STEWART: Yes, we had a clerk that would register the men and they sit out in the
front room until we could take them in the treatment room. There was really all
kinds of little injuries, bruises and broken bones and cuts and flash burns for
the welders and foreign bodies in their eyes. Believe or not, I learned to take
X-rays from the first aid man, and took all X-rays for the arms and legs of
people had been hurt.

STINE: And that wasn’t something that your nursing school you ever expected --

STEWART: [laughter] No, no. We developed our own film and everything.

STINE: Oh, wow! All right there?

STEWART: Yeah, all right there! Had an X-ray table and a little dark room that
was just a closet and we had plenty of films. It’s just learn it once, you
know what to do, you know -- how to expose the machine to get the right picture.
When I think of those foreign bodies in eyes, us nurses took care of all that --
dug those foreign bodies out. Didn’t even think about calling an optical man,
we just did it all by ourselves. We didn’t have a sterilizer for instruments,
but we washed our instrument very good and put them in trays of antiseptic and
that was it. We never had any infection. Never! If a nurse will wash her hands
and follow a lot of good old-fashioned rules, you’re all right. Gee, we had a
lot of burns -- people got burned from the machines that they had.

STINE: So not just from the welding but also --

STEWART: Any other things that was hot. A lot of sprained ankles and shoulders,
and sprained fingers and hands, and ankles. The people were treated and sent
back to work -- they didn’t go home for a week, no days off.

STINE: Wow, just immediately in most cases --

STEWART: Unless you are on a crutch then that was different. The first aid man
would put you in the van and take you to the gate. Of course, we call his family
and have them at the gate. The first aid man would take him to the gate and then
he has to see and go to Richmond Hospital for any further-up care until he can
come back.

STINE: How did people get to and from Kaiser Hospital from the van that you had
there or was there an ambulance?

STEWART: No. If the family wasn’t there, then the little van would takes them
to the hospital. But we’d always call and get the family to be there at the
gate -- be there and take them. Of course they were their husbands or their sons
or something, you know, so they wouldn’t fail to come. If they had a broken
leg and it was a hospital case, it would go to Richmond Hospital on 23rd Street.
Then Kaiser brought that old Fabiola in Oakland and expanded right out way. So
if anything had to go to or be hospitalized, then they would take them to Kaiser
Oakland. They take them to that back door -- used to be a back door on Broadway,
so that was the medic and surgery care that they had. Kaiser could be proud of
the care they gave them too without this so-called city ambulance coming that
they have today for people. Kaiser gave good care all along. The medical doctors
were very good. We had in Yard One several old retired doctors that had come
back, because of the war effort. So the one that we had Robert Jones in Yard One
for a long time was a pediatrician in Ventura. When the wartime came, the
doctors had to go in the service -- navy or army or Coast Guard. So the old
people came back, and that was the same picture with the nurses, the RNs. I was
the youngest one in Yard One, because all of the rest were older because their
husband or children or cousins or something had gone into the service and women
then wanted to help with the war effort and they did.

STINE: So all the other nurses had come out of retirement or -- ?

STEWART: Yes. They had kids in high school some of them, so that’s what
happened. The staff was older and reliable -- good old nurses. That was good.

STINE: Had they all had experience with kind of the first aid?

STEWART: No. No. They all been in hospital work, and that was about it. No, they
didn’t have any experience of outside work then. It wasn’t available, only
work that nurse could get would be in a hospital then, or doctor’s office, and
that be if you were really old and walking crippled or something, you know,
something where you couldn’t run on the floors like in the boards. I would say
we gave good respectable care. If a man got a bandage on his hand, he could come
back the next day and get a clean bandage until it was fixed, so it was a lot of
follow up care. But we expected that. The people who had a lot of flash burns
were people who didn’t know how to cover their eyes for welding and they get
exposed to that burn, that flash burn and then they’d be in trouble. Then the
welding people got a hold and clamped down on that happening a lot. But you
can’t avoid too much foreign bodies in the eyes from that flying stuff.

STINE: How much back and forth was there between people working in the first aid
and people managing workers out in the shipyard? How did they try to prevent
future hazards or future -- ?

STEWART: Well, that was the safety office where my husband was. The safety
office had men around the clock who were out in the yard and if there was an
accident, they were right there to see what happened, who was hurt, how they can
prevent it, and don’t let it happen again in any way. The safety office was
very productive and sought to it for the safety of the men. That was good,
because oh my land, a lot of those people didn’t have any experience about a
boat -- all they knew was climbing up fifty stairs and getting a job up there.
No, the people didn’t know anything about the job when they first came. They
had, I don’t know how many men they had hired, but from this picture here,
you’ll see how many thousands of men came. Some of them came because they had
sons in the service and they were seventy years old. It was all ages of men.

STINE: Did you have people that were 4F that had not been able to -- ?

STEWART: Yes! Yes! That was a lot of 4F.

STINE: I’m curious. Did you ever treat people that have pre-existing conditions?

STEWART: No. That we didn’t do. People were very good about that, and didn’t
take advantage of the care there.

STINE: I know that Kaiser didn’t have any limitations at that time. So did
people where they’ve been kind sent to Fabiola or to -- ?

STEWART: Referred to their own private doctor whoever they want to go to in the
downtown Richmond.

STINE: Okay. Were there many doctors still around at that point?

STEWART: Not too many. We had a fair amount of bottles of aspirin and I forget
what else but very little narcotics -- maybe one dose. And I think all we had in
that narcotic cupboard was morphine and some codeine tablets, nothing else. It
was in a cabinet on the wall back of the doctor’s desk and I don’t think the
key was in the door. That was the care we had then. Of course, you wouldn’t
last if you pull anything shady, because everybody would know it right
there,[laughter] you’re called on the carpet and out! Until some of the
doctors went into the service, they were young, and they were filling in maybe a
month or two of time before they had to leave. We had a fair amount of young
doctors. In fact, several of them stayed because they did become 4F and went to
Kaiser Oakland and worked. So, that was way life was, but it wasn’t fancy --
no trim, but basic good and no corners were cut for the care of the people. But
the whole staff was happy too. It was good. We were kind of like a family.
Doctor Jones lived in Albany and he had us to his home two or three times, you
know, a year. So, it was like a little social thing on the outside that we knew
everyone very well, and you got along that way. Even Doctor Jones’ wife worked
as a clerk there in a little, to register patients.

STINE: So everybody’s working there?

STEWART: Yes, everybody did. Everybody did.

STINE: I wonder if you could maybe kinda reconstruct a typical day for you in
those first couple of years at the shipyard? How you got to work? What the pace
of your day was like when you got to work? Where you ate lunch?

STEWART: Well, we did wear uniforms. I had a nurse’s cape from graduating from
school, but I didn’t wear it to and from work but I had to wear a coat or
sweater for warmth when you needed it. It was nothing to walk down University
Avenue to San Pablo in Berkeley and get on a bus so it take you to the shipyard.

STINE: So you walked from Hearst and Spruce all way down to San Pablo?

STEWART: Yes. Get on a bus and it would take you to right to the shipyard -- to
Yard One. There would be another bus along to take people to Yard Two or Yard
Three. When we came out the shipyard at three-thirty, right in front of the --
on Cutting Boulevard were the gates that you came out and there was a bus to
take you back to San Pablo and University. We had nurse that worked in with us
from Canada, Lily Vickerson was her name and she got her foot caught in the
railroad tracks right where the buses picked us up outside of 10th and Cutting.
She couldn’t get her foot out of the rut and the train came and ran over her.
We got the van to pick her up and take her Kaiser Oakland right away. Doctor
Cutting had been on duty all day, and when he found out it was one of the
nurses, he stayed until midnight taking care that nurse -- fixing her leg. We,
from the shipyard, her co-workers, we all went down in different shifts and
specialized her for two or three days so she would have a familiar face. When
she get better, Doctor Cutting released her in due time, and they provided her a
leg -- they had to amputate below the knee. She got a false leg, and Doctor
Cutting told her, “As long as you live, you can have a job at Kaiser.” So,
she managed the blood bank instead of doing floor work so it was less walking
for her. She did that for years, and she did it very well. Of course, she
retired and went back to Canada. When I was married, she gave me a cookbook, Joy
of Cooking, with her note in it and I treasure it. [laughter] They hired
wonderful people -- the nurses were very good. We weren’t society’s highest
level, but we were good people and we worked well and we did our work well. That
was what Kaiser wanted.

STINE: So do you think there is something about -- especially those early years
in the shipyards to coming down from Kaiser, the kinds of how they managed the
plant, how they trained people that were going out to the work force, how do
that have a role in creating this kind [inaudible]?

STEWART: We never saw the work that the people were trained to do, because that
was out in the field. Usually up on a boat where they were going to be working,
like the welding or the outfitting, the carpenter work, our little place -- our
little clinic was maybe just across the street from the ways where they did the
launching. We were right down on the ways.

STINE: Right in the middle.

STEWART: Oh, yes! If the men did get hurt, they didn’t have far to go to the
little clinic there. The clinic was open twenty-four hours. There was a doctor
around the clock. Henry Kaiser would come quite often and he’d be on the flat
bed of a truck sing his heart out and he’d bring in the Andrew Sisters or
anybody --

STINE: That he himself would be singing?

STEWART: Oh! He’d sing [singing] “I’m a looking over a four-leaf
clover.” He just belt out and wave his arms and he got the whole crowd join
in, you know. The war bonds were a hundred dollars apiece, he sold a quite bit
of that. That’s what he was trying to drum up too. Course, he was a guest and
they treated him and the Andrews Sisters or anybody like a guest. They
couldn’t roam the shipyard or roam all over the place, but they came in and
did what they were supposed to do. The same way with the launching, the people
who launch the boats were guests. They had them brought in cars and they walked
up on the pad for the launching to swing the champagne, and a little speech and
that was it. Then the boat would swish down in the water right under our noses.
Very interesting life.

STINE: There must been so much excitement going around, just amongst everybody
working there.

STEWART: Yes! And of course the war news wasn’t all roses all the time either.
Yard Three and little Yard Four and Yard Two and Yard One, we got along very
well. That was good. If you worked in Yard One, you didn’t have to go to Yard
Three and work, because they had their own staff there so you didn’t into a
new territory, or have to look for where the bandages were and all of those
things. That was well managed -- they had full staffs in each yard. The people
came in and got their treatment and did their work. At four o’clock or when
the shift was over, everybody headed for the gates to go home. But everybody had
to bring their own lunch and when the sun was out and it was hot, they’d sit
on the ground just below our windows in that little clinic and to be in the
shade. And at first, that was before Rosie the Riveter or anybody feminine were
allowed in the shipyards. So, at first, they were complaining about the
government taking their income tax out their check.

STINE: When did that start?

STEWART: I can’t remember for sure, must been ‘45 maybe or part of ‘44.
But they didn’t want anybody meddling with their check before they got it --
they were very upset about that. But it was a law made and that was it. But then
when they brought in the women, oh my land, the men laughed at them terribly at
first. “Look at her! Look at her walk! Look at her! She doesn’t even know
how to hold a hammer. I wonder what she’d do with that saw?” They were very
verbal about it. Their eyes got opened about how the women could do the work,
and did the work and learned the craft, carpenter or welder. So, then the talk
died down, you didn’t hear any more after they got, settle a bit.[laughter]
But it was interesting.

STINE: About how long do you think it took for -- , in your opinion?

STEWART: Six weeks, two months.

STINE: Time really prove themselves?

STEWART: Yes. I would have to say the nurses were treated royally. I mean people
backed out their way for us walking down the way to the clinic from the gates,
and that was quite a long walk, more than a block -- a long block down to we
were. There were men coming and going, you know.

STINE: This is consistent all the way through the war? People treated you with
the same -- ?

STEWART: Oh, yes they did! That was a godsend, because I guess you’d say we
weren’t holy but we were good people that acted right. So, that was the way to
if you want to get, you want to give. So, that was the way it was.

STINE: Oh, such a tremendous job! I can’t even imagine that there are just a
handful of you and so many workers.

STEWART: Oh, yes! That was it, but we were busy. We didn’t sit down, we took
our own lunches and we in this little clinic. There was a big eye room, an X-ray
room, and the big treatment room, and a room for them to register. That wasn’t
half of the building. The back half had a bathroom and room with a bed in it, in
case somebody had to lay down ‘til their wife could come or we could reach
someone. Then we had a room with a table with chairs around the corner. Course,
that was before microwave, so there was no heat, no fire cooking. You had cold
lunches, but that’s all right. You know, you didn’t know any different then.
So, that was the extended the little building --

STINE: How big would you say the building was?

STEWART: There was a place for the ambulance to back to our door. I would say it
was forty or fifty feet wide and seventy feet long, one story, and it was right
down on the way, in with the buildings of mechanics and the machine shop and
all. So, it was quite an experience, an eye opener too. See where you ready go
everyday. [laughter] Yard Two people were open before we were, so it was
automatic, that’s the way it was, you know. We chipped in and caught on out,
and the Yard Three got medical staff. They did fine too.

STINE: I know you didn’t work at the other yards, but did you have
communication with the other yards, the other teams, to kind of compare notes
and see how -- ?

STEWART: We didn’t communicate too much, no. The women that were older at the
end of the shift had to get home for some reason, you know. They did cook and
wash and clean the house besides coming to work. There were two or three of us
that were married, I think, and we all lived in Berkeley. We didn’t ride
together, but if we -- . Remember that Brennan’s Café down on, near Spenger?

STINE: Oh, that’s still there, yeah!

STEWART: Once a while, we meet in there and have hot something to eat and walk
home. Very little of that, but that was what we enjoyed. And of course, Doctor
Jones had us to his house. We all took potluck, so that was a nice way to see
each other too, off the job. That worked out well. The man that I rode with
across the street was a perfect gentlemen -- I forgot what craft he was doing,
to weld or something, I don’t know, but anyway, he have drove his car, pick me
up at the door when I started riding with him. Left me off at the gate on 10th
and Cutting, and I was there when he came out to come home, and that was it. So,
that worked out good. But it was quite an experience riding the bus from
Berkeley out to the shipyard, because it was all new territory for me. I hoped I
was going to land at the right place, you know, because I didn’t know where we
were going for sure. [laughter] But it was all very good.

STINE: Can you remember what the ride through Richmond was like -- the kind of
impressions that you had? When you were riding on the bus, did you go pass new
housing that has just gone up?

STEWART: Yes. There are some houses over here on Carlson that are there yet that
you recognize where you were, you know, you knew you were on the right road.
This man across the street also picked up another person and so he detoured a
little bit over into Albany to a corner where they were waiting. Sometimes,
there’d be two people there want a ride. That was what everybody did --
everybody shared rides then, because if you had a car, you couldn’t buy
another one, you couldn’t buy tires, gas was limited. If you were a shipyard
worker, you got a coupon for some gas that get you out to work all the time.
That was a little more than just a family car. I don’t know how much it was,
but they needed it. That was the way it was. Everybody was kinder in those days.
If you needed a ride or a hand, it was no problem, people would do that. Not
only that, I think of when if we would left Brennan’s to walk home, we thought
nothing of in the dark.

STINE: Again, that’s a really long way. And I think about it now to walk in
the dark.

STEWART: Of course, University wasn’t that busy then. It was an eye opener and
my folks wanted to be sure I was safe and everything from Nebraska. That was
about two years later that they retired and came out, so that was good.

STINE: I’m curious about what some of the big differences coming from Nebraska
-- coming out here? What some of the big changes were for you? Of course,
you’d come to California, when you were young, you had this idea of what it
was like.

STEWART: Well, living in Omaha, like I said, I had little allowance but I had
all my books and my white hose and anything out of that. And five of us could go
downtown in Omaha and ride in a cab for a nickel apiece -- twenty-five cents,
see? [laughter] I was used to spending money at all and I thought a hundred
dollars -- that was good, did private duty for a while there. I knew how it was
to save before I ever got here. It was a totally new world, because everything
was moving faster. I wasn’t used to streetcars and all of that or going to
work. When I got out of nurses training, I did private duty there and you rode
the bus to the house where you are gonna work and that was it. There was
somebody else in the class that came to California, because her husband-to-be
was going to be shipped out of San Francisco. And wrote back and told us the
rate of pay in Omaha was thirty-five or sixty-five a month, I forget, and one
hot meal and out here, it was probably seventy five, so that looked like more
money. So, you came out here --

STINE: Did that play into your decision to come out here?

STEWART: Yes. I knew I could do better than in Omaha, because if I stayed there,
I’ll be that position the rest of my life, and why not try something else. So
I did and it was the best thing I did, you know. But when I went to work for
Kaiser then, I got a hundred and thirty-five a month and one-fifty after three
months or so. That was a godsend. Since I knew how to save money, I did really
very well. I think our rent was, two of us in an apartment, was forty-five a
month, so that was the way life was then. Of course, there was food rationing
and I didn’t have a car, and it was public transportation, so that was all
right. I don’t remember the streetcars were in Berkeley then, but they
weren’t very much, so that was good.

STINE: Do you remember maybe with your first paycheck ever splurging on
something big for yourself now that you -- ?

STEWART: I remember looking at that paycheck and rubbing it, and rubbing it, and
folding it, and putting it away, and taking it out and looking at it again.
[laughter] And what was I gonna do with it? Didn’t want to lose it and to
think “oh my” that was so wonderful. I was blessed with good health, so I
never missed a day’s work. I got that check every two weeks from Kaiser and
that was so much better than what I ever had in Omaha. So, that was a godsend.
I’ve just written and mailed a letter to that George Helverson, the new CE for
Kaiser, and explain to him that when I see what this tenant group is doing, it
scares me. I hope that Kaiser is well aware of it, and us retired people are --
what they promise us is safe. It was a threatening letter, but it was a nice
letter said that I know what Kaiser is enjoying today was started by us in 1940,
50 and 60 and 70, and let’s keep it that way. So, we’ll see. Those days with
the respect that we were shown, all the time, women were more respected. Of
course, in the shipyard, it was wonderful how the people backed out of their way
for us. They were very courteous, that was great. I’ve always try to live up
to that too, you know, I would command respect. I met my husband --

STINE: You were talking about how you’ve met your husband.

STEWART: I met him at the shipyard, he was in the safety office. I think he
about was thirty-two or -four years old, and I was twenty-four or so -- ten
years younger. Anyway, he got a skin on his leg and spot and came in for
treatment -- get a patch on it and that was how I met him -- the first time I
met him. Since he was from the safety office, we intermingled -- the safety
office and the nursing office occasionally, because they came to see if someone
was hurt -- the extent of the injuries and things so they were in and out.

STINE: So they would do some follow up after the initial going to the
accident’s sight?

STEWART: So then, luckily he had a ‘39 Ford. [laughter] So, that worked out
good, because, oh having a car then was quite a treat. He worked swing shift
though, I didn’t ride to work with him, but anything after, you know, social
-- going anywhere, that car was such a godsend. I was a Catholic, he was not a
Catholic. He says, “I can become one.” So we went over to Saint
Augustine’s Church in Berkeley, that was his parish, and introduced ourselves
to the priest and my husband took instructions and became a Catholic. Before he
was baptized as a Catholic, the priest liked him and said, “Why don’t you
forget the girl and join the priesthood?” [laughter] But he didn’t.

STINE: Good for you.

STEWART: Yes. So we were married January, 16th, 1946 and he was a blessing for
me, and I hope I was a blessing for him, because we were very happy and very
well suited. My parents liked him, so that was good. The day we were married at
St. Augustine’s in Berkeley, everyone that worked at the shipyard came that
could. So that was good. It was nice. We went to Santa Cruz for one night or
two, I forget which, for our honeymoon and came back, because that’s all the
gas you could get, you know. That was it, but that was all right.

STINE: Did you saved up? Had you saved up knowing that need your coupons?

STEWART: [laughter] We did, yes. That was the way you did then -- you manage
whatever it was, whether it’s coupons for meat, gas or what. You know that was
part of life. We lived on Spruce Street until I got pregnant with the twins and
we had had a home for the children, so that was how we happened to land in
Richmond. I had only rode down Cutting Boulevard. to work before; I didn’t
know anything about Richmond or the town or anything. I knew some of the staff
at Kaiser Richmond, in case I needed something, you always had the children
checked, you know. I was only three blocks from the hospital and I had a baby
buggy, so I could go myself. You know, when you went the grocery store there,
you could park your buggy in the front by the windows and go get your grocery
and come back and put them in with the kids and go home. You never thought about
the danger of leaving a child alone in a -- and here I was with two in a buggy,
one here and one there. [laughter] But that’s the way everybody did then.
There were lot of women there when buggies or wagons in the front and they get
their groceries --

STINE: There just be a row of children waiting?

STEWART: Yeah, and that was common. The children were never sick, and that was
when we started to save and get a place to live in that duplex. So, we did that
and then Martha arrived in 1952, so we lived there until Martha was about ready
for school and then we moved up, bought this house. That’s why I’ve been in
Richmond, but yes, I’ve seen many changes. Cutting Boulevard, got widened to
four lanes that way, downtown Richmond was, oh my, it was something else -- it
was so flooded with people, you couldn’t walk two abreast down to Macdonald --
it was that crowded on the street.

STINE: Just in the middle of the day or -- ?

STEWART: In the middle of the day.

STINE: This is during the war also?

STEWART: Oh, yes! The government had gone to Oklahoma, and told people that can
come out here and get a job war effort, you know. A lot of them got
transportation from the government, they came and they came to Richmond because
that’s where the shipyards were. But they didn’t have a place to stay and a
lot of them slept in the theater or where they could. The war housing was
erected right away, it really went up, just oh, on any vacant lot, that south
side was just covered with housing. You know where that marina bay is now, that
was all housing. So, it was housing, housing, housing, people galore.

STINE: Was that one of the reasons why you chose or you had decide to move to
Berkeley from the city is that there just wasn’t housing?

STEWART: There wasn’t any housing in Berkeley and I was lucky to know that
manager of the housing authority that would let us move into an apartment -- a
housing apartment. It was impossible. Now we had that deposit in a place in
Walnut Creek, but I wasn’t near hospital at all in case of children got sick
or anything.

STINE: Kaiser didn’t have one there?

STEWART: No, Oakland was the nearest one. And when you are out there alone and
no car and a sick child, you could be in trouble. So, this is why Richmond
looked like a better place all around. Everybody in the building, they were
doctors and all kinds of medical people that were in the same boat, there were
navy people or navy doctors or whatever, the building was full of those people then.

STINE: This is your building in Berkeley?

STEWART: No, down here in Richmond. I think there were twelve apartments in most
of the buildings, some of them has sixteen, so you know that was a lot of people
and a lot of kids. It was good, safe place while we were there, but it was time
to move out. So, that’s why we saved and bought that lot on 14th and Virginia
and got a contractor to build the house and we took over a lot of it ourselves.
That’s where I learned pound a nail, use the paint brush and the saw and the
building is still there and occupied, both buildings, all the houses are still
occupied. So, that’s good.

STINE: I just want to jump back real quick to talk a little bit about all the
people they were in Richmond even in ‘46 when you moved in. And something
related to that that I forgot to ask you about earlier is I’d heard about
people coming in on trains from around the country with pneumonia and how that
was a big problem early on. There was a lot pneumonia coming in and people that
were malnourished and malnutrition.

STEWART: Malnourished was everything. If a husband had his wife and she was a
heart patient, but he could have a job, they came. So, there were a lot of
health problems with the people that came. No place to live right off the bat,
right at first, and of course Kaiser didn’t take care of their health problems
and it was an old personal thing that they had tend to. Some of them got medical
care, of course the county didn’t have medical care like they do now for those
people. But they ran up bills at the hospital on 23rd Richmond Hospital, it was
called, and they had surgery and everything there. It was full all the time. But
eventually the housing was developed and it took in thousands of people to give
them a home. Really, a lot of the hospital staff lived in the housing too after
they arrived here. A lot of the nurses lived in housing until they got their
feet on the ground a bit and maybe bought a house up in the hills or in Richmond
some place. There was just every type of person and we had one bedroom with the
two children and there was one washroom down stairs with the laundry tray and
clotheslines in the back. The day the twins were born, he went to Sears &amp;
Roebuck to the washing machine department and said, “If you think our
world’s in a chaos, I’m in a chaos, I had twins born this morning and I need
a washer machine.” [laughter] The next day, Sears sent out a washer machine,
so I was the only one with a wash machine in that building with all those
people. So, it was a godsend for me, because people respected that was your
property, they didn’t use it or unbeknown to me. I covered it and put it in
the corner when I, you know, couldn’t take it upstairs, it was in the washroom
-- a public room unlocked. My gosh, I took a day off when the twins were three
months old, next day, I had seventy-two diapers on the clothesline for two days
and two nights. You had to make your own formula. There was no refrigerator in
the unit -- it was an icebox and iceman came with twenty-five pounds of ice with
a pan underneath to catch the water [laughter] as the ice melted. But everybody
had the idea that they were so lucky to have a roof over their head, nobody
complained. There was no complaint about a tenant being too noisy or the kids
non-manageable or bothered anyone, everybody got along and that was marvelous.

STINE: Did it happen that the kids were just running around because both their
parents both had to be working?

STEWART: Both parents didn’t work, there was always a parent with the kid.
See, I didn’t work for twelve years. No, there wasn’t any women at
four-thirty when the kids got home at two, people didn’t do that then really
at first in the shipyard days. They stayed home, but they take in neighbors’
kids, no kids were left alone at any time. That was one remarkable thing about
the days then.

STINE: I know Kaiser had childcare centers that they were running.

STEWART: Yes. Little Kaiser Hospital was a godsend then for the people -- very
busy, had to have a full staff of medical doctors, and RNs, and first aid men,
X-ray men on duty, office help, and housekeeping help. Kaiser Hospital developed
appropriately to the crowd and they were given good care.

STINE: I’m gonna jump backward really quick if that’s okay?

STEWART: Sure.

STINE: I’m curious when you first met your husband in the shipyard and before
you got married, I know it must’ve been hard since you know food and money was
kind of tight and coupons and rationing, but what did you ever end up doing for
dating? Did you get to catch a movie?

STEWART: Well, no. A movie, uh huh. Out to dinner on his day off then and a
movie. Yeah, there was a movie right downtown in Berkeley, not the one been
there for the last few year, but it was on Shattuck way down a bit. Could go
there, and it was kind of nice for me to eat in a restaurant because I didn’t
do that very, you know. So was a treat for me. Or then we could go down to the
Pier in Richmond down where that University goes clear down to the water down to
Skates, the restaurant -- that wasn’t there then. Down there on the waterfront
towards Emeryville, you could get down on the beach, so that was great. We could
go to Tilden Park. Before the boys were born, we had to build a crib for them so
we took some of the lumber out there in Tilden Park -- many times we took with
us, and put that crib together. My husband chiseled his initials in the trunk of
s big tree out there; I’d like to find that tree. [laughter] But that’s the
way you did it a lot of things back then. Picnics or going to a park or something.

STINE: And you brought the building material out there just because it was just
a big open space?

STEWART: Oh yeah! Hardly anybody around in those days not crowded like it’s
now. People picnicked a lot then too, that was a source of entertainment that
didn’t cost anything -- just take your food and go. It was good. Then my folks
were in the city, so we went over to see them a lot before we were married. My
husband liked them and they liked him, so that worked out good. And of course,
there was a lot to see in San Francisco then. Oh yes! Shopping was so much fun
and delight then. Go down to Aquatic Park, my folks lived just a block or so
from there so that was like home to go out Aquatic Park for all of us. Then, it
was just a little short trip, a block from Fort Mason, and that was a nice place
to go.

STINE: What was happening there?

STEWART: We always went there for midnight mass. Anything at Fort Mason was all
classified, you didn’t mix in, but the scenery was nice there, and you could
sit anywhere and have lunch -- eat it on the grounds or anywhere then, and
nothing was open to the public then. No. You just couldn’t drive too far
because of the gas rationing. You were limited to developing what you did close
to home. I didn’t have to have a lot of entertainment to keep me happy, always
found a job to do -- housekeeping or something, you know. I felt that was part
of a woman’s work then and did it. When the kids were born out here, we would
drive up University, up to the campus there and take a lunch and sit down on
that big entrance that curves around, sit that mound and take their picture.
People were always amazed, “Two of them?” [laughter] So they always
attracted attention, but they were good -- they didn’t act like they were
special, they were just normal.

STINE: Are they identical?

STEWART: No. One was like the husband, one like me. And then out of the blue,
one that was him would turn more like me and other -- they switch at night. They
got along great, so that was good. When we moved here, it was a godsend, because
they could walk to school.

STINE: Did they go to public school?

STEWART: No. They went to Saint Cornelius Catholic School, and Martha did too,
all eight years. Then they went to Salesian. When Martha was ready for high
school, we wanted her to go to a nice high school, so we had her enrolled in San
Domenico over in San Anselmo -- it’s the high school that open for the
Dominican College. It was the first year they opened, and all the students had
to board so she came home once a month then for three years. Then they kinda got
loosened, they could come home on the weekend. But that was quite an experience
because she was exposed to the hoi polloi, the senators daughters, and all that.
She got along fine with the whole picture, you know, so she stayed there four
years and she got a wonderful education just like the Dominican College would
give to the college of the student -- high school students got it there too
great. To this day, she said she’s grateful for that high school education she
got because the basic was so good. But the boys finished Salesian. In a year or
so, they got out on their own trying a job, if it didn’t suit, they got
another job, that was it. They grew up kinda like they’d like to. They
weren’t here, they were in Los Angeles on jobs and so that was the way life
was, you know. When they left home, that was the way to do it, I guess and that
was good. Of course, we lost Patrick in that accident but Michael and Martha
have grown up to be honorable people in their position. They’re worth a lot of
money, but they’ve handled themselves and that’s the way they were taught
and we’re proud of them. Martha was here last week on her way back from Alaska
to where she lives in Washington D.C.

STINE: She went to Kaiser Nursing School, is that right?

STEWART: She did. She went to Kaiser Nursing and worked there a year in the ICU
then she went up to Alaska to see her classmates that wanted to get as far away
from home as possible. In that visit, it was to a town above the Arctic Circle
that had a hospital that took care of the needy people and it was job there. So,
she quit her job in Oakland and went up to Alaska and worked as a nurse for
fourteen years. She had the health care of fourteen villages and the end of her
career there. Then she wanted to do something else, so she started a newspaper
on her own and did it all according to all the state rules and everything.
Arctic Sounder, she called it, and that was every two weeks it was published,
it’s still published today. Two men bought it after she had it for two years
-- they bought it, they want to live up there. I don’t know they’re still
owners, but that newspaper is still going. She’s done very well, she works for
the senator for that area for a while -- six years I think. Then the governor
wanted her work for him and she did that for few years and the Department of
Education wanted her to go work for him, so that’s what she’s doing now. And
she likes this, because she could spend more time in Alaska, and that’s what
she likes. So she was here on the way home from Alaska and she’ll go back up
in February for another week on business. So, that makes her happy.

STINE: Is any of her work in Washington does she deal with health care at all?

STEWART: Not any health cares, no, she’s what you call kind of a lobbyist for
the state education department in Alaska. Whenever the state needs federal help
with anything, then it has to be presented to the Congress or the White House,
they give to Martha to go and present it and petition for what they want. So,
that’s why she’s in Washington. She has her condo there, she bought a duplex
up above the Arctic Circle, so she’s got that going for her too. [laughter]

STINE: Way up there.

STEWART: Imagine.

STINE: When you started your family, you and your husband -- had you wanted to
have a large family or small family or something that you talked about?

STEWART: Didn’t know what was going to happen. The twins were three years old
when I lost one, and three years later Martha came along, and I was much older
then and I decided -- so that was it. But I didn’t get pregnant again and I
was grateful for that, because when Martha was ready for school, I went to back
to work. When she was in school, I went back to Kaiser down in here, and went to
work one day a week for a while.

STINE: What year was that?

STEWART: Probably sixty something, very -- right in there. I worked one day a
week and then gradually school took more the kids’ time, I worked two days a
week or some three. When Martha was in high school, I went full time, and then I
worked the ward until they had vacancy in emergency and I went over there worked
in emergency for twenty years.

STINE: In Richmond or -- ?

STEWART: Kaiser Richmond.

STINE: Before emergency, what had you been doing?

STEWART: Well, just on the ward work. That was when emergency did not even have
a doctor in the department. So, whatever came in, I had to call and get a doctor
that was on call for that department that day -- medical or -- . We had an awful
a lot of children that ingested pills then, awful a lot, at least two a week.
Mothers bringing in kids that had gotten into bottle of pills or insecticides or
whatever -- we got an awful lot that. It was very interesting, because every
case was different -- you never got the same thing twice or two in a row. I got
along so well with the doctors, I’m still friends with them. So, it worked out
very well.

STINE: Working in emergency, do you feel like your experiences working in the
shipyard were good preparation?

STEWART: Good preparation, because I knew what it was to have foreign body in an
eye and you know what do for it, and sprained ankle what do for until the doctor
got there. Yeah, I was prepared very well.

STINE: Is that part of why you decided to work in emergency or just -- ?

STEWART: No. The nurse that was there retired and so I applied for it and was
accepted and I was grateful for it. So, that was the way it was, I was the only
nurse. I worked alone all those twenty years, I never had anyone work with me,
we got busier, busier and busier. I know I went to work at 7:15 or 8:15 and I
didn’t get to eat ‘til 2:00 or 2:30, because when you are all alone, you
can’t leave. So that was the way the crowd came in you -- took care the
patients first. But we had such a nice relationship with everybody, it was a
family. We all knew the doctors’ wives and we went to their houses
occasionally. They knew our husbands and our kids and we knew their kids. So, it
was always a family thing and if anybody was sick and couldn’t come, that was
understood -- they were sick they didn’t take advantage of anything. It was
good place to work. I’m very grateful; I was lucky to be there. Those were the
days when you retired, they had a big to do for you, big party -- retirement
party. For me, they had it down at where that Strings is over to the left
another restaurant over there, I think it’s still there, but I can’t
remember the name of it. Oh my gosh, there were hundred people there, all the
doctors came and had a big dinner. Lot of the doctor got up and talked in there,
and they gave the most wonderful string of pearls -- beautiful string of pearls.
Memories like that were held for everybody. So, that was a good, warm feeling
about everybody. That was the way it was. I don’t think they have the dinners
anymore; I think they just have a coffee klatch when somebody retires now down
at the hospital, but those were the days and that’s what they did.

STINE: When you decided to go back to work once your children were in school,
was there ever a question that you wouldn’t go back to work for Kaiser had you
had such good experience already?

STEWART: No. I wouldn’t go any place but there. There was a new hospital in
San Pablo, Doctor’s Hospital, and they were hiring nurses. No, Kaiser had the
appeal for me, because I knew so many of them, that was a place for me to go. It
was right.

STINE: In terms of being an employer, how do you feel that they took care of you
as a worker?

STEWART: Very good. We had a young man was came in as a nurse. I caught the fact
that we were short of narcotic and I went to nursing office right away with it
and told them what I had seen, would they come up check the chart? He had taken
that and he had charted it out of the book where you sign for and he gave it to
the patient he said and sign for on the chart, but he also told me we didn’t
have to do anything for him, didn’t give him anything, send him home. So and
then I asked the doctor, “Did he get a shot? No.” So that’s why I went
down to the nursing office and the nursing office stood behind me and believing
-- they didn’t doubt my word at all, and that was his last day. That was the
way Kaiser -- they stood behind you. Because that could’ve been a shady thing,
you know, him denying it or something, but he couldn’t deny, he couldn’t say
he gave a narcotic under a doctor’s order when it wasn’t order, you know.
But that happens occasionally a nurse will become shady with the narcotic, I
caught another one doing that too and they terminated him right away. But
that’s your vow about promising, about the way you do things -- you don’t
mess with narcotics. Amen! And so that was it. Kaiser was very good. The people
like Kaiser, because in those days, Kaiser had twenty bottles of cough syrup and
twenty bottles of this stomach settler, all kinds of things. When people came in
with those complaints, they were given a bottle besides, you know, their
treatment to take home free. That’s the way they did then.

STINE: Kind of above and beyond what you would expect.

STEWART: Yes. That made a good bond, you know, they did.

STINE: I’ve also just been reading about Kaiser and learning about Kaiser and
having been a Kaiser member know that they are very big on preventative care and
was that something that started early even back in the shipyards or -- ?

STEWART: We didn’t see that then. No, to be truthful, you didn’t see
preventative care then not until the fifties when it became apparent that was
good medicine. Before that, it was the care given for the case that came in that
needed it and give the good care and the follow up care. But no, doctors
didn’t do that at first.

STINE: But then later on the twenty years you were --

STEWART: Yeah, they did. They bloomed.

STINE: Another big thing about Kaiser is having integrated care, I wonder what
your experience with that was especially being in Richmond with so many
different people coming in?

STEWART: Racism and things. We never had any trouble. We laugh together, we work
together. We pulled joke on one another; we didn’t ever have any hard
feelings. There really was not apparent.

STINE: You mean among the integrated staff?

STEWART: Even if they were black or if they were Indian or what. No, there was
none of that. It wouldn’t have been allowed, but it wasn’t ever a case
brought up -- an incident that happened.

STINE: So you worked with doctors and nurses from a wide variety, is that right?

STEWART: Yes. Indian doctors from India, the black ones. You respected them for
their knowledge and their classification -- they were doctor, medical doctor and
that was it. The doctors never pulled anything shady on another race. If that
ever took place would be reported.

STINE: Yeah, I imagine that wouldn’t have been tolerated at all. And then in
the shipyard, were there nurses and doctors -- ?

STEWART: We didn’t have any other race other than white then, because the
foreign doctors hadn’t come to the states yet. Everybody was white, the first
aid people, the doctors and all the nurses. Now there were all kinds of people
out in the shipyard population -- men worked there. If it was a black man that
needed something, he got it.

STINE: Amongst your patients or amongst the workers, did you ever feel any kind
of tension?

STEWART: No. That was a blessing. We never had any back talking, backbiting or
any tension. No, we just didn’t do that; nobody did it. Nobody around where I
was, we never had that at that little hospital down here on Cutting; I never saw
it in Oakland. That was just the way you accepted things, you know. Some of it
was all in fun and some of it was -- the fun we had was really fun wasn’t
anything put down at all. This would entertain you. We had a nurse in emergency
that had an acid tongue and she was old so that she knew better than anybody,
but that’s all right -- you’d laugh with her. When she died and she was
ninety-two, she died two weeks ago. At her funeral, [laughter], in her casket,
she like to play golf so she had a shirt on that she wear playing golf and a
golf hat and a tennis racket and six balls in her casket, and across her cap she
had on her head, “Welcome to the zoo’. [laughter] So, we got another laugh
and said, “Well, Molly went out with a laugh.” That was just typical. All
the doctors laughed when we told them about what we saw at the funeral, you
know, we all had a such a good laugh about Molly’s leaving this earth with us
laughing about it. So that was the way --

STINE: That’s great.

STEWART: That’s what happened.

STINE: Was joking around pretty common in -- ?

STEWART: Quite common, yes. It wasn’t carried to the point where it was done
in front patients, you know, it was in the backroom when we were eating or
something, but we had priorities where that took place. There were no snide
remarks, nothing like that, no put-downs. “What you do that for? Let’s see
what you did?” that would be the way you’d be handle, but that was very
admirable and comfortable no matter who it was. We had a couple black porters
that were as dear to us as anything, you know. They eat our fried chicken and
we’d eat theirs, it was that way. So, it was very good.

STINE: Having been at Kaiser in the very, very beginning, and then taking a
little time off in going back, what were some things that you felt held over
from the beginning?

STEWART: The care that we gave, I sent that letter to him, was what we started
in the forties, and fifties, and sixties, good care. That was what we expected
to do, what we did and what we expect to see happening now and it is. I had a
total knee replacement last January, and had very good care. I have very good
care for my glasses, my eyes and I didn’t go to a doctor for twenty years so
my chart didn’t maybe like, now it has maybe that much. [laughter] But I
don’t go back, because if I needed something, I’d go down, but I’m
healthy, I’m doing my work and going to school, I couldn’t ask for anything
-- I don’t take any pain pills or sleeping pills. But if I did, I would expect
to be treated with the best care, and I think and hope I would get, but I think
I would, I don’t have any qualms. I just hope I don’t have to end up in a
nursing home, that would be the last straw, [laughter] but who knows.

STINE: What are some big differences that you sense working early on and then
going back after twelve years?

STEWART: See, I didn’t work for twelve years. You lose your talents, your
ability, but going through nurses training the way we did then, it was
[inaudible]. When we took the state board, there was no problem, we passed
beautifully. When I came out here, I just take a California state board pass
beautifully, didn’t have any trouble, because of the way we were trained. So,
that sticks with you and it makes an all around better person of you in many
ways what’s gonna be here because that’s right, then you developed those
right ways in other things that you do. You can’t drive through down the road,
and take the middle and get out of my way, you know. So, you become that kind of
a person where you want do right by everything, everybody. Really, the Kaiser
care I think I can’t complain at all about it. I haven’t used it much, but
if I needed, I would feel like I got excellent care.

STINE: But then from the working side of it, is there anything that you had
piece together or kind of deal with on the spot and the shipyard just never
would be done in the hospital or in emergency.

STEWART: No, I didn’t. I guessed you’d say well rounded. A nurse is a nurse,
and what they are taught from the very beginning, the school part of it last all
your life. So, that was the way it was. I didn’t have any trouble with
anything when I went back just one day a week, because I work on Sunday -- every
other Sunday at first, and I didn’t have a lot of exposure with the doctors
and it was what was ordered through the week. Then I worked on Saturday and
Sunday, I worked Friday, Saturday, and Sunday, so I guess I’d say I got back
into the swing slowly, but I didn’t have any trouble or did worry about not
knowing what was going on. So, that was good.

STINE: Just in terms of kind of routine procedures of how to deal with -- ?

STEWART: Routines that you learned years ago are still done today. When you
cauterize someone it was what you were taught years ago, and that’s what it be
today. So, that’s what a lot of it is, your basic nurses training.

STINE: It’s probably the only big differences is sterilization, which you
didn’t have, you didn’t even have access to, so --

STEWART: Yeah. We didn’t sterilize then. I think the only time the doctor wore
rubber gloves when he puts some stitches in someone and that was it. We had one
sink in that big treatment room, imagine, for patients and us. [laughter] One
hot plate. It was a sink about this long, so that two could be at the sink at
once. But you know you didn’t think anything about it. We didn’t have any
trouble with infections or nothing, so we must’ve been doing something right.
Now, oh my gosh, everything has to be in a sterilizer and the sterilizer
checked, and checked and checked working, sterilizing right degree and
everything. No. We had to blow our needles and our hypodermic syringes. We had
morphine that came in tablets, half grained and that was never ordered for
anybody, quarter-grain was for a great big man, you know. So you had to draw it,
boil your needle and syringe, draw up a cc and half of water and dissolve the
morphine in it, and then shoot out half of it, so you’d only have a quarter or
whatever was ordered, you know. But that was the way did, and everybody did that
then, it wasn’t only in the shipyard. What we learned in nurses training was
practice, and after we got out and things did finally developed into
sterilization and those kind of things, but that was life.

STINE: I just can’t imagine having some kind of injury and then patching it up
and going right back out to work.

STEWART: Yeah, that was it. Come in tomorrow if you want a clean bandage, come
back tomorrow, but that was it. No. People just didn’t go home or didn’t
come in for maybe a half days work that wasn’t allowed. If they did that, you
had to go out a gate and check out, the gate would question it and call the
boss, you know and he’d be sent back.

STINE: So, everyone would know.

STEWART: Yeah. So, people didn’t slip out. [laughter] At the gated Yard One,
there were about dozen stalls that you walk through, and there were somebody in
each stall so that could handle the crowd of men coming in. You had to show that
badge and they look at you, you know, and see your badge and then you were
allowed in. It took that many gates across the front there right on 10th and Cutting.

STINE: Like with a turnstile?

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt></fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link><translate>0</translate></record></ROOT>