<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00060414" dt="2021-03-30"><version>5.4</version><date value="2003-06-28" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Fay Hawkins | Interview 2 | June 28, 2003</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|11(8)|39(1)|56(6)|71(6)|82(5)|91(2)|101(7)|112(12)|121(9)|133(9)|141(2)|150(14)|160(9)|174(2)|188(2)|195(15)|204(2)|214(13)|224(4)|231(4)|241(5)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>t0wr9STWTqc</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description>Fay Hawkins worked for the Richmond Police Department from 1946 until the early 1970s. His father was with the police department from the 1920s until 1941. Topics discussed include police practices of the 1920s and 1940s, Fay's views as a long-term resident of the city, several interesting calls that he went on, and his experiences as he moved up through the ranks of the department to Lieutenant.</description><rel /><transcript>WHEELOCK: I wanted to ask you about when you were in the Navy, stationed in San
Francisco, and you said that you were working for Naval Intelligence. Is that
right? Just ask you what you did as part of that? What did that entail, I guess?

HAWKINS: Well, most of that work was office type work--filing and checking
through files and things of that nature. Just secretarial type work at that time.

WHEELOCK: And then you got reassigned to Honolulu, right near the end of the war?

HAWKINS: Yeah, towards the end of the war in 1945. I guess it was about, in
September or something like that, they were closing things down here, and
sending all of the personnel down to Honolulu, to what they called JICPOA, which
was Joint Army Navy Intelligence. And it was stationed just outside of Pearl
harbor in Honolulu, and in an area they called Aiea. I think it was Aiea, I
believe or something like that. And, so all of the intelligence stuff was going
through that office.

HAWKIN&#039;S WIFE: That&#039;s one of my, that little hummingbird crystal up there.
[referring to noise on the recording]

WHEELOCK: Go ahead.

HAWKINS: It&#039;s one of those in back of the--one of those. It won&#039;t do it now. [laughs]

HAWKIN&#039;S WIFE: It&#039;s just when the breeze--.

WHEELOCK: Just when the breeze comes in.

HAWKINS: I didn&#039;t that in the way. These things are so sensitive.

HAWKIN&#039;S WIFE: If I whispered, would you hear me?

HAWKINS: Probably.

WHEELOCK: Yeah, I&#039;m sure. Okay, I&#039;m sorry. So, you were saying everyone was reassigned.

HAWKINS: So we were being reassigned to Honolulu, in the Honolulu area. And
doing the same type of work over there. I was doing the same type of office work
and also security work around the perimeter itself.

WHEELOCK: So was that patrolling? Like actual security?

HAWKINS: No, just more or less building security, more than patrolling and so forth.

WHEELOCK: So was it similar to police work, some of it?

HAWKINS: In one respect, yes. Yes, it was similar to police work, slightly.
Not--it&#039;s kind of hard to define it really.

WHEELOCK: I was curious because in our earlier interview you talked about--I
asked you like, &quot;How did you decide to be a police officer?&quot; And you said,
&quot;Well, it didn&#039;t really pay that well.&quot; And so, I was wondering what your
motivation was considering that you could probably find--you already worked in a
bank. I&#039;m sure you could have find a lot of different things.

HAWKINS: I was pretty well satisfied that I was going to go on the police
department many years before that. I did my father&#039;s occupation as a police
officer here, and I knew that much about it, and I knew a lot of the personnel
who were on the police department at that time. So, I had pretty well decided
that&#039;s probably what I was going to do when I got home. In fact, I probably
would have gone on when I was twenty-one, except I was still in the service at
that time, so I had to lay there for two or three years.

HAWKIN&#039;S WIFE: He was over in the islands when our daughter turned one. So we
took pictures and sent those over.

WHEELOCK: Now you know nowadays, they have at the junior colleges and the
college level people can take classes in law enforcement? They didn&#039;t have
anything like that at that time?

HAWKINS: No, at that time they didn&#039;t have the present type of curriculum in the
colleges or in the schools for police work. Those were developed in the
late-fifties and sixties to where, in most case now, a lot of people going into
police work do go into the junior colleges that have a police academy and they
learn a lot about police work there. And a lot of departments now will use that
training and the graduates from there as personnel that they will choose from to
become a police officer for their community.

WHEELOCK: What did you think about that, when they started to implement these programs?

HAWKINS: I think it was good. Because when I went on in 1946 the schooling we
had was in-service training. They were by the department&#039;s own personnel, who
were good, and they would train us, give us courses in law and all kinds of
police work--apprehension, firearms training and everything on there. And that
went on for about four to six weeks of in-service training that way. Then we
were put out with a beat officer to ride along with him and observe and learn
beat work, and so forth, from the training officer. And that went on for two or
three weeks, and then you finally graduated to where you were on your own. And,
hopefully you learned enough to keep you out of trouble.

WHEELOCK: So you started, like you said, you started in 1946 with the police
department. And I was wondering if you felt like there was a difference between
the people that were from Richmond originally and the people that moved here
during the war, in terms of how they related to the police?

HAWKINS: Yes. Well they came here from all over the country, and during wartime.
And it was mainly because--well of the war, and the job opportunity that enabled
them to get a job and make good money while they were working here. And as the
war progressed, and finished. The shipyards cut back down, and a lot of the
people stayed here in the community. This became their home. And you could
understand why, because most of them were from other parts of the country where
job opportunities were not there. And so they were making good money out here
and they liked living here, so they continued to live here.

WHEELOCK: So, in terms of people that you ran into or people you had encounters
with--earlier in our interview, you had said that sometimes you would go into
bars and people would be fighting. And the idea was that if there were no
weapons involved, then it was just kind of let them brawl it out amongst
themselves, because that was how they had been--that was their, you know,
culture from?

HAWKINS: Yes, I understand. That&#039;s true to a certain extent. You tried--you
broke up the fight. You didn&#039;t let them continue fighting, regardless of whether
there were weapons or not. But in most cases, it was mutual combat between
people with no weapons involved. So you did break it up, you couldn&#039;t let them
go ahead and keep fighting, because others would probably get involved, which
you didn&#039;t want. But the main thing was to make sure there were no weapons
involved. And there were a lot of times people went out behind the barn, so to
speak, and they duked it out back there with no weapons involved. And you got a
long with the people better yourself, when you understood what the problem was
and you didn&#039;t go overboard with weapons yourself. They respected you more
because you didn&#039;t use any kind of weapons yourself in settling the situation
than otherwise.

WHEELOCK: The other thing I was curious about is that during the war they needed
more police officers, and obviously it was hard to find people to hire. So I was
wondering where did they find people to become police officers during World War II?

HAWKINS: They just wanted us to put an advertisement in the paper, and word of
mouth when you would talk to people on the street and say why don&#039;t you go down.
And at that time--during the wartime--all you had to do was apply and you
probably were taken in. They did a background check. It wasn&#039;t really a thorough
background check, but they would do a background check-- make sure you weren&#039;t
wanted in someplace for crimes yourself. And at those times you bought your own
equipment, and they handed you a badge and say, go on out. That&#039;s about what
happened in many cases with very little training. It was after I came on in 1946
that they really got into the training and the testing procedure to become a
police officer. The requirement was, always was, that you had to live in
Richmond and be a citizen of Richmond to be a member of the police department,
and you had to live in the city. Sometime in the 1950s or early-sixties they had
to abandon that requirement as unconstitutional, and as a result of that a lot
of people did not live in town. In fact, some of that did live in town moved out
of town. And I personally, I think that they should be able to keep that
requirement because I feel that the person that is working for the city as a
police officer or a firemen--it becomes more their property. And I think they
would take--they have more pride in taking care of that property, other than
just as jobs, like any other job around. That&#039;s my own personal feelings on the
thing. It&#039;s like your own property. You keep better care of your own property
than you do your neighbor&#039;s. If you come in here from out of town and it&#039;s just
a job, and soon as you&#039;re off of it you go out of town and so forth. So, you
don&#039;t care. And technically a police officer is a police officer twenty-four
hours a day in the community he&#039;s working at. With that they can live any place,
I personally think that they should change it. I&#039;m old fashioned enough on that.
There&#039;s a lot of things like that I think that they should not have changed. I
think they have broken down a lot of the strict requirements of eligibility to
become a police officer. I don&#039;t care who it is, as long as they have the
ability to do the job and that&#039;s the main thing.

WHEELOCK: I was wondering. The people that were--if you know about this--the
people that were hired during World War II, were they people that had lived in
Richmond before the war? Or had they moved to California along with a lot of
other people that came over here and they were hired?

HAWKINS: I don&#039;t really know, but I think that they just came to Richmond from
other areas, and either to work in the shipyards, or maybe they were working in
the shipyards and they weren&#039;t content enough. They would talk to other police
officers. And sometimes the police officers would say, &quot;Well why don&#039;t you go
down and apply to the police department, and so forth. And a lot of people were
recruited in that manner, just word of mouth. And they were able to meet the
requirements at that time and so forth.

WHEELOCK: Do you know if anybody was recruited out of state?

HAWKINS: Not that I know of. I believe that at one time or during some of the
times that they were recruiting for a chief of police that they did recruit from
out of state. But, let&#039;s see none of the chiefs that I worked under was
recruited from out of state. Most of them were members of the department, then
went through the ranks and became the chief.

WHEELOCK: Now, for something else I wanted to ask. How things changed after
Miranda, because you retired in &#039;72, was that right?

HAWKINS: Yeah.

WHEELOCK: And I was just wondering if you had a feeling of how things were
before and after that decision?

HAWKINS: Well, your interrogation, mainly with Miranda decision, when you talked
to a person if he was your private suspect, you had to be very careful of how
you talked to that person and got information from him--interrogated him.
Because under Miranda, there were so many ways that the fellow&#039;s attorney later
could have things thrown out of court because you didn&#039;t give him his rights and
so forth. Give him all of his rights that he was entitled to. It did affect your
ability to some respect. But you got around that. You learned to live with it.
And you would talk to people and so forth. You had to be very careful, and be
able to prove that you didn&#039;t violate the man&#039;s rights. A lot of things changed
as time went on, with civil rights and Miranda decision, and all of the others
like that, that made it actually more difficult for the officers to obtain the
information they needed to solve crime. There were so many loopholes that were
there, that would trip the officer up and his presenting of the evidence, that
they were thrown out of court. And so it made it, as I said, it made it a little
more difficult in how you obtained your evidence.

WHEELOCK: There was something that you wanted to say about, something we brought
up in the other interview with the--.

HAWKINS: As far as I mentioned before, about the taking of vagrants to the San
Rafael Ferry or to the city limits and saying, &quot;Well, goodbye. Don&#039;t come back.&quot;
Those things have happened from time to time when a lot of departments--. But
they mostly were in years ago, thirty, forty--well, I have remember I&#039;ve been
retired thirty some odd years. Sixty, seventy years ago back in the twenties and
the thirties, something like that, before they even thought of civil rights. Not
that people&#039;s civil rights were violated all the time, but it just the way that
the country grew up. And you could do a lot of things back in the 1920s and
thirties that you couldn&#039;t do today because of the legal requirements that are
in place now. Not that what you did was really violates a lot of rights, it was
just that is was one of those things man to man that you understood each other.

WHEELOCK: So, my final question. Looking back on your career, if you were
talking to somebody who was wanting to get into law enforcement, is there
anything that you would give them as advice or reflection on your career?

HAWKINS: Go ahead; take all the training that you can get and law enforcement is
still a good occupation and there are benefits to it, both financially and
otherwise that you would get from it. And just have a good judgment. And take in
all of the training that you can in the various aspects of it. And things are
different now than they were when I went on. A lot of the things they changed
are for the better. Some I don&#039;t think are. They should do some of the old
things, I think. They talk about community policing. That&#039;s pretty much what I
was brought up on in the department, because we had the city was cut up into
what we call beats at that time--certain areas of the town. And an officer was
assigned to that beat, and his sergeant kept pretty well track of him and told
him you keep, you be clean. In other words, in those days you took care of
everything that happened on your beat. No matter whether it was murder or
robbery or thefts or parking or traffic or whatever. You took care of the
problem. You didn&#039;t say, &quot;Well we&#039;ll get somebody else out here, we have a
parking enforcement, we have a traffic enforcement, and so forth. That&#039;s what
they have. They have more of less specialists. In those days, every officer on
his beat was a specialist in everything. And he took the initial reports, and he
may turn everything over to the detective later. But the initial thing was done
by the officer himself. And nowadays, I don&#039;t know whether that&#039;s done now or not.

WHEELOCK: Is there anything else you want to add?

HAWKINS: Well, like I said there, the community policing, I was more or less
brought up on that, and to me community policing is the officer knowing the
people that live in the area that he&#039;s patrolling, and getting the people to
know him. And when this happens, I think the officer has a much easier time with
solving crimes and so forth on his beat.

WHEELOCK: Well thank you for all of this.

HAWKINS: Yeah.

[end of interview]

</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>