<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd"><record id="00042066" dt="2018-11-30"><version>5.2</version><date value="2003-04-10" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/><date_nonpreferred_format></date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Maggie Gee | Interview 1 | April 10, 2003</title><accession></accession><duration></duration><collection_id></collection_id><collection_name></collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Oral History Center, UC Berkeley</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Maggie Gee</interviewee><interviewer>Leah McGarrigle</interviewer><interviewer>Robin Li</interviewer><interviewer>Kathryn Stine</interviewer><file_name></file_name><sync>1:|20(3)|26(3)|40(4)|58(13)|76(1)|88(6)|98(13)|107(11)|117(14)|132(4)|149(16)|162(12)|178(3)|192(9)|204(12)|220(16)|230(1)|249(5)|261(14)|280(8)|295(15)|309(7)|321(3)|326(15)|338(11)|354(8)|370(8)|383(10)|396(12)|405(1)|416(2)|426(2)|443(8)|453(2)|466(8)|473(14)|492(4)|504(6)|516(11)|531(10)|545(12)|553(12)|562(8)|574(11)|589(15)|600(3)|618(11)|631(2)|644(13)|658(11)|680(7)|692(8)|706(13)|731(13)|763(10)|780(2)|790(1)|798(13)|811(2)|823(15)|842(14)|850(12)|858(4)|875(8)|883(2)|894(1)|902(7)|912(7)|920(5)|931(1)|940(1)|948(7)|955(3)|968(14)|980(1)|993(16)|1006(2)|1018(5)|1030(9)|1044(2)</sync><sync_alt></sync_alt><transcript_alt_lang></transcript_alt_lang><translate>0</translate><media_id></media_id><media_url>RfsVWPFaZjc</media_url><mediafile><host>YouTube</host><avalon_target_domain></avalon_target_domain><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>video</clip_format></mediafile><kembed></kembed><language></language><user_notes></user_notes><index></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>LI: It&#039;s April 9th, and this is Robin Li and Kathryn Stine and Leah McGarrigle,
interviewing Maggie Gee. Do you know what the Chinese character means?

GEE: Yes--oh, I forgot what it means.

LI: But it&#039;s in Cantonese?

GEE: It&#039;s in Cantonese. Gee Mei Gue, that&#039;s my Chinese name.

LI: What does it mean?

GEE: Mei Gue. Mei is &quot;pretty&quot; something. I forget what is pretty. Everyone is
Mei. Aren&#039;t you Mei-something?

LI: No, I&#039;m Yue Bin. Yue, like &quot;happiness.&quot; Doesn&#039;t sound as good in English.

Once again, we were talking about maybe just sort of starting in the beginning,
talking about your grandparents, where they were from and how they ended up in California.

GEE: My grandparents were from Guangzhou area, which is Canton I guess, in those
days. They came here because of the Taiping Revolution, I believe. They came
because of economic reasons. They didn&#039;t come to work on the railroads. They
were fishermen. It was very unusual at that particular time; it was probably the
1870s. They came as a couple. I don&#039;t know whether anyone has looked at it, but
when we talked to Sandy Lydon, he said that there were some Chinese that came
over in junks. [laughs] Well, there were quite a few, and not very many got
here. We could never prove it, though. There were some that came over as
families, because at that particular time it was just men that came. Then there
was the Exclusion Act--women couldn&#039;t come. My grandmother was quite a bit
younger than my grandfather when she came to this country. She had thirteen
children. They landed in Monterey; well, they probably landed in San Francisco,
then they went to Monterey. There was a fishing community down there, of Chinese.

MCGARRIGLE: Do you think they would have known before they came that that was
their destination, Monterey?

GEE: I have no idea. I never got a chance to speak to them; my mother didn&#039;t
talk about it. My mother was born in Monterey.

LI: Were the thirteen children all born here?

GEE: I believe all thirteen were born in this country, yes. Maybe there were
more than thirteen, but the thirteen survived.

LI: Where was your mother in the birth order?

GEE: My mother was--I would think about the fifth one down. She was just one of
the mouths to feed at that particular time.

LI: Do you know when she was born?

GEE: She was born 1895, I believe.

LI: Would she talk about growing up in Monterey?

GEE: No, she didn&#039;t talk. I picked it up. We used to go down to Monterey all the
time to visit friends, but she never--well, by the time I became interested, she
didn&#039;t talk very much about it and I didn&#039;t ask her, which was unfortunate. You
know, as children you grow up and your parents are speaking, they&#039;re telling you
things and you really don&#039;t listen very well. At least, I found myself not doing
it. I regret it. I picked up most of the information just by being around my
uncles and my aunts.

LI: The family kept in touch.

GEE: Oh yeah, the family kept in touch like most Chinese families, because at
that particular time there was the isolation. There was a lot of discrimination,
so the families were very close. All the brothers and sisters of my mother&#039;s
generation were very close, as long as my grandmother was living, in particular
when my grandmother was living.

MCGARRIGLE: Do you know what kind of house they moved to in Monterey? Where did
they set up house?

GEE: Well, we had a reunion almost twenty years ago. They were down in Seventeen
Mile Drive, where the Tennis and Beach Club is. We had it there, which was
really great fun. They were squatters; the Chinese couldn&#039;t own property at that
particular time. I&#039;ll just generalize and say Asians could not own property. I&#039;m
not quite sure whethersome people bought it in their children&#039;s name that were
born in this country, but I&#039;m not quite sure. Some people might have.

MCGARRIGLE: So squatters in the sense that they would into an existing home?

GEE: No, no. Squatters in a sense you build something on land that you don&#039;t
own, I believe. I don&#039;t think there are any houses there. It&#039;s beautiful
property that Del Monte finally developed, though, and became Seventeen Mile Drive.

LI: Did they work as fishermen in Monterey?

GEE: Yes, as fisherman for the Chinese in San Francisco. They dried fish, went
out and got abalone and dried abalone; it was just part of the Chinese
community. There was a big Chinese community there in Monterey, Watsonville, and
Salinas. They were all either fishermen or they had grocery shops. Some farming,
but not much farming, I don&#039;t think.

LI: Did your mother work with her parents?

GEE: I&#039;m sure all of the children worked, whatever they did. In fact, they
collected abalone shells, because they kept them and they polished them, and
they sold them in stands. I don&#039;t have one of them. My sister had one and
they&#039;re just beautiful. When I was a child when we went down to Monterey, we
used to go and pick these abalones off of the beach--they were very small.
Nowadays you have to wait until they&#039;re seven inches and you have to dive for
them. We would just boil them on the beach. We would get a fire going and we&#039;d
eat these little abalones. They were absolutely delicious, I remember that. You
could just pick them up on the rocks, like you would be able to get mussels, but
no longer. At that time, most of the otters had gone and now we have otters that
have come back, because they&#039;re an endangered species. And so I don&#039;t have to
eat abalone anymore; the otters can have it. [laughs] They don&#039;t commercialize
them here, because they&#039;re so few and the otters go after them.

LI: How did your mother come to leave Monterey?

GEE: The family moved up. My grandfather died, I believe. He was quite a bit
older than my grandmother. So they moved up to San Francisco Chinatown. I just
don&#039;t know exactly how this happened, but my father came as a merchant from Hong
Kong. At that time, there was the Exclusion Act and so the only people that
could come to this country were professionals or merchants or businessmen. So he
came. He was an importer. He had a company in Hong Kong and so he set up a
company here. He wanted to get married, so who did he go to? A marriage
arranger, a marriage counselor, whatever you call &#039;em. So it was an arranged marriage.

LI: Had your mother registered, sort of, with the--

GEE: I don&#039;t know how that works, I really don&#039;t. Usually it&#039;s families that
know each other. This was something that wasn&#039;t, though. He was someone who had
a little means. He was a young man and looking for a wife. Whether he looked
through many of them and chose my mother--it was an okay marriage.

MCGARRIGLE: How old was she when they married?

GEE: My mother, when she got married--if she was a &#039;95, I would say she was
twenty, at least. About 1915. Is that right?

MCGARRIGLE: That would be right.

GEE: Did you get hold of the book by Xiao Jiu.

LI: I was reading her book, because there&#039;s one chapter which is based almost
entirely on that article. I was reading in there about your mother losing her
citizenship when she got married. Would she talk about that?

GEE: Oh, yes, but she didn&#039;t lose it until a few years later, in something
called the Cable Act.

LI: Right, so it&#039;s 1922.

GEE: They were married for some time and then the Cable Act came and it was
directed to really Asians. I&#039;d have to look at the Cable Act. Is it specifically Asians?

LI: It&#039;s any American woman who marries someone ineligible for citizenship,
which is pretty much just Asians. So even if a white woman married an Asian--

GEE: She&#039;d lose her citizenship, yes. So my mother lost her citizenship. It
really bothered her, as I remember, but she got it back. It was a big thing for
that particular time. Where are you a citizen of, then, if you lose your
citizenship? Are you a citizen of China? She had been to China I think, but
that&#039;s about all.

LI: Had she gone back to visit?

GEE: She went back to visit. It had to be about 1920, because my sister wasn&#039;t
born, just my brother. My sister was born in 1921.

MCGARRIGLE: So that was a long trip. Who went back, when they went back?

GEE: My mother and my father and my brother. I think she had a baby there, which
she lost, in China at that particular time. There was one child which she lost.

MCGARRIGLE: That might have been a business trip, then.

GEE: Some trip. Business, I guess, because he was able to come back.

LI: Do you know if they ever considered moving back to China, after she lost her citizenship?

GEE: I don&#039;t think so. She really was an American, though, even though we lived
in a Chinese community up till then. It must be after they came back that my
father decided to move to Berkeley. They lived in San Francisco.

LI: Do you know why he decided to move to Berkeley?

GEE: Well, he wanted his children to grow up outside of Chinatown. He didn&#039;t
speak English at all, but he commuted from Berkeley because we had such
wonderful transportation here. I think I told you there was a train on Tenth
Street, a train on Sixth Street, a train on Sacramento, a train on California,
two on Shattuck Avenue. One went along Claremont to the Claremont Hotel. These
are all trains to San Francisco. Pretty nice.

LI: Did they run across the Bay Bridge?

GEE: There was no Bay Bridge. There was a ferry. Where the toll gate is, that&#039;s
where the ferry slip was. It was really wonderful. It took you about the same
amount of time; faster, no traffic. It&#039;s a short distance. Have you ever taken
the ferry to San Francisco? Well, do it. It&#039;s really a nice ride. You pick the
ferry up at Jack London and it&#039;s only a half hour. What you do is you go along
the channel, then you go under the Bay

Bridge. But in the channel is where all the container ships are and you see them
loading them. It&#039;s really interesting. Then you come to the Bay Bridge; I think
you get very close to Yerba Buena, I&#039;m not sure. You go under the Bay Bridge,
then you&#039;re at the Ferry Building. You park your car down at Twelfth Street, at
the garage or on the street, then you take BART home if you don&#039;t want to stay.
You can get off at Twelfth Street and you just walk to your car if you don&#039;t
want to wait for the ferry, which runs probably every hour. You go over and have
lunch, and then take BART back. It&#039;s more flexible.

LI: When you were a child, did Chinatown feel close, even if you weren&#039;t living there?

GEE: Yes, I think so. When I was a child, Chinatown was close, because all my
relatives lived in San Francisco Chinatown. My uncle had moved to this side of
the bay, lived in Oakland Chinatown. Everyone lived in Chinatown. There were so
many restrictions of where you could live.

MCGARRIGLE: So Berkeley was kind of outside of that.

GEE: Well, what happened was in 1906 there was a big earthquake. People came
over to this side of the bay and a lot of people in Chinatown came over. The
Chinese had these little truck farms down below San Pablo, I guess.

LI: How did they get that land, do you know? Was it just sort of empty?

GEE: I have no idea because there was no ownership. Didn&#039;t I show you my little
pamphlet Looking Back at Berkeley? [Looking Back at Berkeley: a Pictorial
History of a Diverse City. Berkeley, 1984] I want to

show you what Chinese--I just picked these up from the basement recently,
because someone had asked me so I brought a whole bunch of them up. This was
Berkeley Chinese. It&#039;s actually there. I&#039;ll give you this. Let me see if I can
see those. This talks about the Chinese in Berkeley. I love this picture. In
Berkeley? There it is, this one. It&#039;s down here on Hearst Street and Shattuck, I
think. It&#039;s just like the Farmer&#039;s Market.

MCGARRIGLE: Comes full circle.

GEE: [laughs] They&#039;d bring up the vegetables in these, just like in China. You
can have that.

LI: Are you sure?

GEE: I have so many copies of it. I still have a bunch of copies, that&#039;s why I
had them in the basement and I said I gotta give &#039;em away.

LI: It&#039;s amazing. It looks just like Berkeley; the houses look the same, and the street.

GEE: Oh yeah, Berkeley hasn&#039;t changed. In this neighborhood everything burned in
&#039;23, but on your side, on the other side of campus, some of the same houses are
still around.

MCGARRIGLE: What was your father&#039;s business at that point? Did it evolve?

GEE: My father imported foodstuff from China, rice, and I guess the usual
foodstuff, and then he exported soap products back to China. From China, the
foodstuff, just like you do today, more so. At that particular time, America
wasn&#039;t a rice-eating community. There was still Texas; I guess maybe in the
South people ate rice, but rice was not a big item.

LI: Did that make him an important member of the community?

GEE: Oh, he was a businessman in San Francisco, yes. We used to go over there, I
remember, to his warehouse--it was on Clay Street and he had one of these
elevators, one of those things that open up in the street, on the sidewalk. You
put the stuff down there and the elevator goes down. I guess you store it inside
the shop. Are they still around?

MCGARRIGLE: I see that, yes. In other cities, also. More Eastern cities, where
they load. Big steel doors open up and this lift comes up and they download
everything. You see that more in the East.

GEE: But you don&#039;t see that here anymore.

LI: In Chinatown, they have them. In the restaurants, behind the restaurants
you&#039;ll see all this bok choy--

GEE: Is that right? [laughs] Going down there. It was practical. They had it on
the sidewalk. I remember his on Clay Street. I think it was Clay Street, yeah,
Commercial and about Kearny.

LI: Was your mother staying at home at this time?

GEE: She stayed at home. She had six children, so she stayed at home.

LI: You said her first child was born in 1920? That&#039;s when your older brother
was born?

GEE: My brother was born in 1917 or &#039;18. Eighteen, I think. No, it has to be
1917. I was born in &#039;23 and he&#039;s six years older than me, so whatever that is.
[laughs] That&#039;s 1917.

LI: The youngest was born--

GEE: The youngest in the family was born--probably &#039;28.

MCGARRIGLE: She had six children in ten or eleven years.

GEE: Every two years, that&#039;s what you do. You have sex, you just get pregnant. [laughs]

MCGARRIGLE: Did she maintain contact with her mother and all the extended family?

GEE: Oh yes, yes. On her side, but my father died when I was quite young so that
I really didn&#039;t know [his side of the family]. I just had a cousin that lived
here and the rest were in Hong Kong, so I as a person, or none

of us in fact, had an opportunity to really know that side of the family. Part
of it is communication. Today you would know. To go from China from here was a
long ways.

LI: What year did your father pass away? When was that?

GEE: What was the Depression? &#039;30, &#039;31? Whenever the stock market crashed. He
had a heart attack. That&#039;s because he had so much in the stock market. It&#039;s
interesting. I think five percent was all you had to put down. People bought.
Like a lot of Chinese, they gambled a lot. I think the stock market is gambling,
somewhat. In those days, more so. Today we hope we&#039;re intelligent about it,
sometimes we&#039;re not very intelligent. [laughs] But in those days, that&#039;s right.
When the market crashed he had either a heart attack or stroke in the streets of
San Francisco, came home and died shortly after that.

MCGARRIGLE: Was your mother then following up on his business?

GEE: Oh no, she didn&#039;t know anything about it, but my uncles had worked for him.
They were very smart. We owned a house, then, and they were smart enough
to--when the market crashes and the margin, you owe people a lot of money. But
they quickly arranged it so the house was in my mother&#039;s name. It was hard to
tell how you do this, so she wouldn&#039;t lose her house. Someone loses when the
market crashes, besides you, but someone else loses, too. Usually you have to
pay off your margin and everything you have goes to pay off your margin account.

LI: How did you parents come to buy a house in Berkeley, because of the restrictions?

GEE: It was down in the flats, down by Sacramento Street. There weren&#039;t any
houses down there to begin with. Here&#039;s this little house with empty lots all
around. It wasn&#039;t a big, established place. The only owner of the house was
whether they built there or had it built, or whatever. I don&#039;t know.

MCGARRIGLE: What was that church on Acton Street that your mother had been
active in? Isn&#039;t there a Chinese church--

GEE: Oh yes, my mother was very active in that Chinese church. In fact, she
moved from one part of Acton Street to the other part, and the church was in
between. Have you ever visited that church?

MCGARRIGLE: We gave a talk about oral history to them once. I remember you
telling me that your mother had been active there.

GEE: Very active in that church, yeah. Do you remember the architect Roger Lee
He was a fairly well-known local architect and he built that church. It&#039;s a nice
church, yeah. This is not an interview about me, you know. This is background.

MCGARRIGLE: What was the denomination of that church?

GEE: The church was very interesting. Now, my little book here--It was founded
by the Mason-MacDuffie Ladies of the First Congregational Church, so it was a
Congregational Church. It was on Addison. Do you know where Gertie&#039;s is? It used
to be Gertie&#039;s Restaurant. The church was there. They owned the property there.
It was a house that was used as a church, but also it was a big house. It had a
large room;

that was the downstairs. Maybe they took out some of the walls. The upstairs was
housing for students: Chinese students had a hard time finding housing here when
they were going to school, particularly the Chinese from China. There were some
students from China, so they lived there. So it was more. I went to Chinese
school there. It was more than a church, it was a Chinese community center. Most
of the people in Berkeley, at least the Cantonese, went to that church. So you
knew everyone in Berkeley at that particular time.

LI: You said you went to Chinese school there?

GEE: Went to Chinese school there. It was Chinese school after school there.

LI: When did you start going to Chinese school?

GEE: Oh, I don&#039;t remember. When I was young, we used to have a teacher come to
our house. It was really for my brother--so I was quite young--it was for my
brother to know Chinese. The girls got a little bit of Chinese. It was important
because it was an insult, if your children didn&#039;t know Chinese; you were ashamed
of it. There used to be a name--I forget what the word is, a very derogatory
name for people who did not speak Chinese in the Chinese community. As I grew
up, my mother was ashamed, a little bit. [laughs] Not really, though, but you
know, people would always mention &quot;Your children don&#039;t speak Chinese.&quot;

LI: Did she try? She tried to send you to Chinese school.

GEE: I went to Chinese school for a long time and hated it. [laughs] Because it
was school after school. My regret was that I was not a better student. I went
for a long time, I can&#039;t tell you how many years.

MCGARRIGLE: They spoke Chinese at home, because you said your father didn&#039;t
speak English.

GEE: Well yes, but see, my father died when I was relatively young, and my
mother spoke English. She might speak to us in Chinese, and you answer in
English. It&#039;s typical with that generation, though. But with my generation, you
didn&#039;t want to speak Chinese, because you wanted to integrate. Didn&#039;t want to
eat with chopsticks, none of that. &quot;Why are we having rice all the time?&quot;

LI: Did you feel that separation from your home life and outside?

GEE: A little bit, because we were not living in Chinatown. See, if you were
living in Chinatown then it&#039;s all the same, pretty much. My friends in school
were not Chinese, here. But if I stop and think about it, most of them, their
parents were immigrants. This was in the twenties and I remember there was this
one family who are plumbers, Italian family in Berkeley. Nice kids. Plumbing was
considered kind of a lowly profession, and of course it turns out that it&#039;s the
Jacuzzi family. [laughs] You start out as a plumber-- everyone has to start
someplace. They were smart plumbers.

MCGARRIGLE: The schools were integrated then and the neighborhoods--

GEE: Oh yeah, the schools were really integrated. There were black kids; Walter
Gordon lived down the street from me. Walter Gordon is a black man who was
early, he was a lawyer, he played football. This was before civil rights, so he
could only live in a certain place and he couldn&#039;t go places, stay in hotels and
things like that. He was appointed by Earl Warren to the head of the probation
board. I&#039;m not quite sure exactly what it was. Then later on he was appointed by
Eisenhower to be the Governor of the Virgin Islands. But he was black, and at
that time they still could not do a lot of things. It took civil rights, and you
still couldn&#039;t do a lot of things. But the community was pretty well integrated.
We had quite a few blacks in Berkeley, and the reason why we had them was
because it was the end of the railroad line and so the blacks worked as Pullmans
on the trains. That&#039;s where Dellums comes from. I&#039;m not sure that Dellums&#039; uncle
or his father was a Pullman porter. So they all had jobs and they all had
houses, they had children like anyone else. They were middle-class. It was
before the onset of the war that brought in lots of people from elsewheres.
Berkeley was integrated, in that sense.

LI: Even at that time, in the 1920s.

GEE: In the 1920s, yes. There were blacks, whites living in the neighborhood,
quite a few Japanese, and some Chinese. More Japanese in my neighborhood than Chinese.

LI: Was your mother friends with all?

GEE: My mother was pretty much friends with everyone. Yeah, because your
children, I think that&#039;s part of it, in the neighborhood. She spoke English
pretty well, spoke Chinese very well, so that was good.

MCGARRIGLE: Did she always cook Chinese at home, or did she adopt some other foods?

GEE: It was either, sometimes Chinese and sometimes not. Okay, my mother--

LI: How did her life change after her husband died?

GEE: She had some money for a while. You own a house, that really made a
difference. Today it does, too. She owned a house, it was in the depths of the
Depression. She was in her thirties, if you kind of stop and think about it. She
should have sent us all out to the orphanage or some place like that. [laughs]
But she didn&#039;t. She didn&#039;t work for a long time; then she took in sewing. I
remember she had this big sewing machine, so she&#039;d sew during the middle of the
night. A lot of Chinese did that. They&#039;d go to the sewing factory in Chinatown
and they did it by piece. She did that; then she went out and she did housework
for a while. She was a terrible housekeeper; I don&#039;t know how she ever did any
housework. Then the war came on, and that made a lot of difference. She had a
real job. But we never lacked for money. There was not a lot of money around or
anything like that, for anything we wanted, but we always had a automobile. I
mean, I just don&#039;t know how it all worked. She learned to drive, by the way,
when my father died in the early &#039;30s. We had a &#039;28 Studebaker, then my mother
started buying Buicks, I remember, so there was a little money coming in.

LI: Do you think you were getting support still from your uncles?

GEE: She might have. That I don&#039;t know. She might have, because we had one uncle
who wasn&#039;t married and he always came around. He was sort of the father figure
around, one of her brothers. I don&#039;t know

whether he was older or younger. He was about the same age that she was. One
thing I&#039;ll always remember, he was a hunter and he&#039;d go hunting for deer. It
really kind of amazes me now. Every year it seems like he shot a deer, before
the days of Bambi. [laughs] And we&#039;d have this deer hanging in the garage. Well,
you have to hang meat for a while, and I can always remember that. I&#039;m not big
on deer meat, never was. I&#039;ve never been big on deer or meat or anything, but I
do remember that. That&#039;s very unusual for a Chinese man to go hunting. Now, who
he went with, I have no idea. I just remember there was this deer hanging in the
garage. One didn&#039;t have a freezer then, so we had a lot of meat.

LI: Would your mother maybe cure it?

GEE: Well, any meat is hung for weeks. You&#039;d think it&#039;d rot, wouldn&#039;t you?
[laughs] But that&#039;s aging.

MCGARRIGLE: You had an icebox?

GEE: We had an icebox then, though. So what do you do with all this meat? I
guess a lot of people got a piece of it. He slaughtered it all alone. I think my
uncle skinned it. Yuck. [laughs] Now that I stop and think about it--

MCGARRIGLE: Sounds like she was very independent, in that she learned to drive--

GEE: Which was pretty unusual; that&#039;s right. She has these six kids? [laughs]
Oh, my goodness. She learned to drive, she had a car; she never taught us to
drive, none of us, and she was very smart. We knew exactly

why it was, because she didn&#039;t want us to be asking for the car, so she kept the
car to herself. Smart. So we all had to learn how to drive on our own.

MCGARRIGLE: Were there messages that she imparted to you and the other sisters
and your brother, from her experience about independence or about becoming self-sufficient?

GEE: I think so. She really knew how to do things. As I grew older, I became
aware that she knew how to change the lights--I mean, these are small things
that we can do, but the light socket, she could fix, do a little plumbing; she
could do simple things that a lot of women can&#039;t do, particularly of that
generation. You had to. If you own a house, as you know, you don&#039;t have anyone
to take care of all the little things. You learned how to do them yourself. My
sister said she was really smart. See, I didn&#039;t have that sense. When you&#039;re a
child, you&#039;re so wrapped in yourself. You have to kind of look behind. My sister
not so long ago, when I was asking her, says, &quot;You know, your mother really was
very smart.&quot; Too bad she didn&#039;t have the opportunity for education.

LI: Did you get a sense that she had other aspirations? Would she talk about
things that she would have liked to have done?

GEE: No, she really didn&#039;t talk a lot, no. Not to me. She always had a meal on
the table. We always sat down and ate. What the conversation was about, you
know, with all these kids around [laughs]--it&#039;s not very good at different ages.
Although, you know, when you have your two kids, you know how it is when you sit
down to eat, how chaotic it is. If you have six of &#039;em, well--[laughs] at all
different ages. The older ones are telling you to knock it off a little bit.

MCGARRIGLE: Was there a kind of method she had for discipline that you remember,
that she would do?

GEE: No, I think we were all kind of disciplined. You had to, in a sense, in
order to have a calm household. No prima donnas. They were too difficult.

MCGARRIGLE: Because she&#039;s at that time the mother and the father figure.

GEE: I know, and she did the laundry and just everything. There were no dryers.
[laughs] Now that I stop and think about it, there must have been big
clotheslines outside. Everyone must have pitched in, had to pitch in a little bit.

LI: When she started working, doing housework outside the home, would those
other siblings take care of the younger ones?

GEE: I think the older ones took care of the younger ones. Simpler times, you
know. You probably could leave the house and not be too concerned about someone
getting hurt or someone coming by. We lived in a stable neighborhood. No one&#039;s
going anyplace, and there&#039;s no television or radio. You go out in the streets
and play, or you play in the local lots and everyone sort of look after each
other. In fact, we lived very close to San Pablo Park.

MCGARRIGLE: Did she distinguish, like your father had, between the sons and the
daughters? Your father got the Chinese tutor for your brother to learn Chinese,
and then you learned--

GEE: I think that it was important. I don&#039;t think my mother, so much though, but
I think when my father was alive the boys had to be--well, I have one brother at
the top and one at the bottom, so the one at the top, a lot of attention was put
on him. That was important. The girls are all right too, but it was important
that he do well.

LI: How did your mother transition from housework to defense work?

GEE: You know, it&#039;s really surprising, though. I wish I knew. She realized, I
guess, that there was need, and she started very early, I think when the war
first started, to apply for a job out in the shipyards. It was a real job. I
think that was the important thing. It was a real job and you did something for
the war effort. Some one else must have told her, but she might have found out
all by herself, because I don&#039;t think any of her friends went out to work in the
shipyards. Maybe there was a group of younger generations, but I don&#039;t remember,
though. Someone might have said, you know, there&#039;s good jobs out in the
shipyards and you could do something for the war effort and make good money. She
really enjoyed that. My sister was telling us. I guess I wasn&#039;t at home at that
particular time, but she really enjoyed getting up in the morning, going to
work, and feeling as if she were doing something and being out there with other people.

STINE: Do you think that was a large part of why she, aside from wanting to have a real
job, was that a big part, the doing your part? Do you think that patriotism had
anything to do with helping in the war effort?

GEE: I think it was a combination of all. I think that during World War II,
almost everyone wanted to do something for the war effort. There was a
tremendous amount of patriotism. Since it was an Asian

country that we were fighting, I think it made a lot of difference. It could
have been the Chinese. It couldn&#039;t have been, but people felt that since the
Japanese and Chinese look alike, it could have been the Chinese that attacked
Pearl Harbor. I mean, there was no chance, of course, but you felt as if you
wanted to do something.

LI: Do you think being Chinese made you want to demonstrate your patriotism even more?

GEE: I think so, yeah. Even though the Chinese and Japanese did not get along at
that particular time, because the Japanese had invaded China.

LI: Do you think your mother felt conflicted, because she had lost her
citizenship earlier?

GEE: She might have felt that this is one way of proving it, too. She did. You
could work in the shipyards and not be a citizen. You could join the Army and
not be a citizen and get your citizenship, too.

MCGARRIGLE: You said last time when we were visiting, that some of her Chinese
friends looked down on her decision to go to work.

GEE: I think so. Some of her women friends, because those were things you didn&#039;t
do, but I don&#039;t think too many. It&#039;s just more gossip. [laughs] They did. It
wasn&#039;t a closed society, but the families all knew each other quite well. In
Berkeley, there were quite a few Chinese families there. I don&#039;t think anyone of
her generation--my mother was one of the older people working in the shipyards,
I believe. Women, that is,

working in the shipyards. She was in her forties. That&#039;s not very old today, is
it? She was forty-five, at least.

MCGARRIGLE: She had already had adult children.

GEE: Yeah, she already had adult children. She was an old lady, then. Your life
expectancy then probably was sixty or something like that, sixty-five.

LI: Do you remember her making friends at work?

GEE: I think she did, but I didn&#039;t know any of them. She liked it, though. She
really liked it.

LI: What was she doing?

GEE: She was a burner. And so, what is a burner? I didn&#039;t know the difference
between a burner and a welder. A burner has a torch, too. It&#039;s like light
welding or cleaning up the welds and things like that. The welders did stuff in
ships, and the burner--I suspect the burner works with the welder. I don&#039;t know,
but I suspect that.

LI: Was she trained on the job?

GEE: Oh yes, they trained you on the job, so that you could come with nothing
and learn. She was a fast learner in things of that sort. She was good with her
hands. I never saw her change a tire, but she probably changed a tire. [laughs]
I don&#039;t know who&#039;s going to change it for you.

MCGARRIGLE: Do you remember when Kaiser first came in and they got that contract
to build all those shipyards, and how that transformed the area?

GEE: Oh, yes. Well, with my mother, it was the first time. They had this
wonderful health plan, the beginning of whatever you call an HMO nowadays. I do
remember them, somewhat, Kaiser coming in. They had been around for a while.
Benevolent, somewhat, I guess you&#039;d call that. They&#039;d take care of their
workers. The workers did get hurt on the job, so they started an infirmary or
something like that that just grew into something bigger. My mother had such a
low number. She was so proud of it, that she had this low number as a member of
Kaiser, as being one of the first. Just like the co-op. Do you remember the co-op?

MCGARRIGLE: Yeah.

GEE: I had a number of 17,500 and something. My mother had 1044. And the co-op,
that was a store that we had here. It&#039;s now Andronico&#039;s. It&#039;s all the new Andronico&#039;s.

LI: Is that where she shopped?

GEE: That&#039;s where we shopped. Berkeley. The Finns started here in Berkeley, the
co-op. It really worked very well and everyone belonged. Your mother must have belonged.

MCGARRIGLE: My father did.

GEE: Your father did. A good liberal community, you pay into it a little bit.
They over-expanded, and then they sort of bellied-up, because they didn&#039;t stick
to food. They should have stuck to food. They started a little banking, which is
fine. Credit unions are fine. But then they wanted to do a lot of social things,
so it became a bookstore, lost lots of money on that. Lost money here, lost
money there, so they folded up.

MCGARRIGLE: It was a real institution in Berkeley.

GEE: Maybe it lived its life. Sometimes things live their lives. It was a
wonderful institution.

LI: When did it start?

GEE: When did it start, when did it end? I can&#039;t remember.

LI: But your mother shopped there when you were a kid.

GEE: Oh, yeah. But the co-ops, I&#039;ll tell you where they are, Andronico&#039;s bought
all the co-ops. Someone else did first, but the co-op was where the University
Andronico&#039;s is, and this one here, Shattuck, and then

there was one on the other side. Oh, I know, it&#039;s one on Telegraph and Ashby.
It&#039;s a Whole Foods. They&#039;re all big stores, and those were the three big co-ops
here. Big stores.

MCGARRIGLE: Would you conjecture what her politics were, your mother, at that time?

GEE: Oh, I think my mother&#039;s politics were inclined to be on the liberal side.
Pretty much so.

MCGARRIGLE: Do you think she would have been actively following national
politics or voting in elections?

GEE: I don&#039;t know. That&#039;s hard to say at that particular time. There was a group
of Caucasian women and Chinese women that worked together for these Chinese
orphanages. There was two of them; one for girls and one for boys. She worked
with the Baptist Church to raise money for them, and the church actually did.
They had these little church socials where ladies would make things and sell
them. One of the homes for the girls is one of the dormitories for Mills College
now. If you go out to Mills College and look at one of the dormitories, it has a
little Chinese effect in it. It has these little curlicue things, the building.
I think it has a tile roof. Out here in El Cerrito there is a private school
called Windrush. Do you know it at all?

LI: Is this the boys&#039; orphanage?

GEE: Yes.

LI: I remember hearing about this. My grandfather taught there.

GEE: Oh, he did? It&#039;s very close to the El Cerrito BART station. It has
architecture, little curlicues on it. You can see it looks a little Chinese.
Your grandfather taught there? Is that right?

LI: Yes, when he first came here he taught Chinese at the orphanage.

GEE: He taught Chinese there. It was a boys&#039; orphanage, yeah. We used to go out
there, Chung Mei Home, to look at all those good-looking boys. [laughs]

MCGARRIGLE: Go out there with your mother, you mean?

GEE: Oh, yes. Because we were raising money for them and bringing them things.
It was up &#039;till high school. There were a lot of children that were not all
Chinese. Not a lot. A few, because the families didn&#039;t want them.

MCGARRIGLE: So she had the six kids, even if some of you were out of the house,
she still had kids at home, and she had full-time work and she did community work.

GEE: Oh, she did a lot of community work. I don&#039;t know how she found the time.
It&#039;s because she had a car. You know, it really makes a difference, because she
could run around. She never was home.

LI: So when was this that she was working with the orphanage and the church, in
this philanthropy?

GEE: To me, it seemed like all her life. Probably more so during the war and
then after the war. I don&#039;t think in the &#039;30s; I don&#039;t know.

MCGARRIGLE: Those Kaiser medical benefits, were those lifetime? Did they give
those to their employees for lifetime?

GEE: No, you always had to belong and pay.

MCGARRIGLE: So when she stopped working in the shipyards?

GEE: Oh, she just kept it.

MCGARRIGLE: She kept it, but she paid her premium?

GEE: Oh yeah, she paid her own premium.

MCGARRIGLE: Did she have Kaiser the rest of her life, then?

GEE: Kaiser the rest of life, yeah. It&#039;s really amazing, though. In a sense,
Kaiser was good. When you&#039;re young, you don&#039;t need it.

MCGARRIGLE: It was meaningful, though.

GEE: I think it gives you that security, a little security blanket that you have.

MCGARRIGLE: Did any of the people that worked in the shipyards have retirement?

STINE: Not that I know of. Not in the beginning.

GEE: What did they have?

MCGARRIGLE: No retirement for the shipyards.

GEE: Oh, I don&#039;t think so, no. Just Social Security, and that was never
considered retirement money. That was just to help you with your retirement.

STINE: This is tape two with Maggie Gee. I had a question.

GEE: A question? I&#039;ll see if I can answer it.

STINE: To go back with the Kaiser healthcare, I was wondering about the physical
properties of the job that your mom was doing, burning. Did she ever get injured
on the job?

GEE: No, she never got injured on the job. Nothing major, no. She probably might
have gotten burned or something like that, but nothing major.

STINE: Did she ever have to use her healthcare while she was there?

GEE: That I don&#039;t know. I don&#039;t know whether she did or not. I&#039;m assuming that
they probably checked on you, gave you a physical occasionally, but I don&#039;t know.

STINE: And then beyond that, it sounds like it was a very tiring job, that it involved
so much physical labor and such physical effort. Did she talk about that?

GEE: She came home quite tired, but I always have to say that I wasn&#039;t home very
much. But my sister said that there was always dinner, whether she fixed it
ahead of time. She did the shopping, and there was always dinner. There were no
fast-food places at that particular time. I find it pretty remarkable; if one
has to do things, one does them. She had a very busy schedule. They worked long
hours. At the shipyard, she started at the graveyard shift. That&#039;s when they
first train you, and then you get a better shift, which is the evening shift,
the early evening shift. It&#039;s the one where you leave at midnight, where you&#039;re
on from about four o&#039;clock. Actually, it works out well in a sense, if you have
a family, because you can do many things during the day and then you can go to
work. Then you can sleep from one o&#039;clock to whatever time, ten o&#039;clock. So that
worked out. It worked out quite well. They had good public transportation out to
the shipyards. As you know, or maybe you don&#039;t know, that there was this train.
The trains came from the East; I think they were New York elevated trains. They
ran along the existing tracks that we had from Oakland to Richmond. A lot of
people didn&#039;t have automobiles then.

LI: Were they brought in just for the defense workers? They brought them when
the factory was there?

GEE: When did they build these trains? They brought them in, actually. I don&#039;t
think there were any existing trains going on those tracks when the war began.
If there were, there were a few trains that went on it. They were brought in so
that they could be used as commuter trains, to go to work. At that particular
time, I was just trying to think--yes, we were getting rid of all our trains and
streetcars here, because California, everyone wants to have their own
automobile. So I think there were no longer trains that went to San Francisco.
Of course, there weren&#039;t very many trains because the ferries had already left
by then. There was the bridge that was built about 1937, &#039;38. There were trains
that went over the bridge from East Bay to San Francisco, but from Berkeley
there was just the F Train. I believe that was the only train, the one that ran
on Shattuck Avenue that went over the bridge. There weren&#039;t all these from all
over town.

MCGARRIGLE: Did she go to that, what&#039;s now a restaurant, the depot at the base
of University? About Fifth Street, is that where she caught the train?

GEE: No, the train was on Sixth Street, I believe, Sixth or Seventh Street. I&#039;m
not sure, but for some reason I thought it was a little further. I didn&#039;t think
it was way down there.

MCGARRIGLE: There&#039;s that building--

GEE: I know, that&#039;s the old S.P. train station.

MCGARRIGLE: Do you remember when that was?

GEE: Santa Fe train station--no, the Santa Fe is where the Montessori school is
now. It was the S.P. train station. Yeah, it was a Chinese restaurant, then it
was a fancier Chinese restaurant called Xandau or something like that. It went
out of business.

MCGARRIGLE: Did Richmond seem a very far ways away at that time?

GEE: Yes. Richmond seemed like quite a ways off. It was a different type of
community. It was a small community, I believe. They had twenty-odd thousand
people, then it went up to a hundred thousand. It was a blue-collar community.
Standard Oil was one of the big employers there. The Ford Plant was there. Then
there was the Pullman Company where the Pullman cars were built, I believe. Not
quite sure, but they were refurbished there. I remember the Pullman cars,
though. I don&#039;t remember the Ford, but I remember Standard Oil. I mean, we all
know of Standard Oil. They&#039;re still there. It was a blue-collar town. It had one
section where Point Richmond is--there is a very nice section when you go
through the tunnel to Point Richmond, where all the houses are along the water.
Have you ever seen them? They&#039;re very nice houses along there. A lot of Italians
built there, as I remember, because it reminded them of the Riviera. If you&#039;ve
been to any of the houses, some of the houses go down to the water. They&#039;re very
nice. All of a sudden you come through the tunnel and all these lovely houses,
down on the right-hand side. In a way, it was not considered a desirable place
to live because of the odor--that&#039;s the one thing I remember. There was a lot of
odor, sort of gaseous odors of some sort. Wasn&#039;t really unpleasant, but you were
aware of it. It was a thriving little community. Mostly Caucasians lived there,
until the shipyards came. I was going to say it was a redneck community, but I
won&#039;t say it. [laughs]

MCGARRIGLE: Do you think she would have ever gone there before she took the job?
Would there have been a reason for her to visit?

GEE: There were reasons to go there, oh yes. There was a big swimming pool.
Well, we couldn&#039;t swim in the swimming pool, though. There was a whaling station
there at Richmond. There was a ferry that left from there to go to where the
bridge is. There was a nice ferry that went over to Marin County. So there were
all sorts of positive things. My mother got in her car and we went over to the
other side of the bay.

MCGARRIGLE: The prohibition was against any non-whites swimming in the pool, or
was it specifically targeted at one group or another?

GEE: Well, you know there was a prohibition for a long time for non-whites
swimming in pools. But I can&#039;t remember when that was sort of lifted, though.
It&#039;s a big pool there, a big Plunge there. It&#039;s been there a long time. I
suspect non-whites couldn&#039;t swim there. That meant really Asians, at that
particular time, because I knew that was at Neptune Beach over in Alameda County.

MCGARRIGLE: Did she talk at all to you or her other children about discrimination?

GEE: No, she did not. I can&#039;t remember her talking about it. It&#039;s not vivid in
my mind. Actually, I think in Berkeley her white friends, these would be the
church ladies. They&#039;re there to help you, in a sense, because they feel that
they want to do something for the Asian community. There was a great group
called the Wah Mei Club, in which there were the Caucasian women and the Chinese
ladies. They just took on projects and got to know each other pretty well. The
Caucasian ladies were, I would say, upper-

middle class ladies. Their husbands were professional people. Like any church
group, you&#039;re looking for a project and so they sort of adopted the Chinese
church. The women remained friends for a long time.

When I was working at the laboratory I came across a young man and he said to
me, &quot;You know, my grandmother knew your mother.&quot; It was someone I knew. I said,
how? He said, &quot;There&#039;s an old real estate company called Forbes in Berkeley.&quot;
His grandmother was Mrs. Forbes, and they owned this real estate company. They
remained friends for a long time. After he told me, I called Mrs. Forbes up and
we talked at great length. She remembered my mother quite well. My mother had
died by then, so that was kind of nice. Any more questions, ladies?

STINE: Thinking about Richmond, you had the perception that it was a little more
redneck-y and out of the way, maybe?

GEE: When I say that, it&#039;s that there is more discrimination. I always use San
Leandro as a better community, in a sense. They were a blue-collar city and they
really, up until recent times, it was very difficult for anyone besides the
Caucasian people to even move into San Leandro. They just wanted to keep it a
white community. They were threatened by the blacks moving in from Oakland and
also the Asians, too.

Actually, when you see it, groups do take over. You look at Fremont; I remember
seeing Fremont. It&#039;s really a melting pot of all of the various ethnic groups,
because one moves in, everyone else moves there. Fremont is a melting pot. I
mean, it has lots of Chinese, Taiwanese, lots of Afghans, lots of Hindus, lots
of everything. So if you wanted to keep yourself a white community--and
small--in those days, then you just not allow anyone to move in, except the
whites. If you feel threatened, your job threatened--if you&#039;re a blue-collar
worker, any new immigrant is willing to take your job for much less and they
work harder, too. So there&#039;s always that kind of threat. The shipyards just made
a change, because everyone came in at one time and there was such a shortage of
help that people just moved in. I bet if I looked at Standard Oil, who was on
their working roll in the &#039;30s, I bet they were probably mostly white. Very few
Hispanics, or

Mexicans, they would be; I guess that&#039;s what you called them at that particular
time. Or Asians. But then on the other hand, there were fewer of our so-called
minority groups, ethnic groups, at that particular time, too. It&#039;s not one thing
that causes the other; there&#039;s many factors.

STINE: Do you remember actually seeing the Bay Area change? This large population
explosion that was centered in Richmond because of the shipyards, so do you have
any kind of personal recollection of feeling all these people moving in?

GEE: Oh, I think so. Things just seemed a little more crowded, that&#039;s all. You
became aware of it in the stores. I didn&#039;t live in Richmond. I&#039;m sure Richmond
was really impacted. I saw a little bit of it when I was out at Treasure Island.
I saw a little bit in Vallejo. That was a quiet, sleepy town once upon a time.
When the war started, it took on a lot of workers. Not like Richmond did,
because they were launching a Liberty ship a day. But it did have more people
there. They say it was sort of a dying town, and then it became very vibrant
because of the new people coming in. So I would compare it with Richmond
somewhat, and I would say Richmond was just that much more. I&#039;m just trying to
think--did I go out Richmond very much? Well, I remember all those houses going
up. That&#039;s the one thing I do remember. We didn&#039;t have much gasoline, but we had
a little bit. We did, or maybe I did with my friends--at that time, I was much
older then--we went over to Marin County. There were just a lot of things
buzzing in Richmond with all these new houses. They must have been put up in a
very short time. I do remember that there were jokes made about the shortage of
housing. If you had a room and you had a bed, you could rent it out to three
different people. One shift could sleep, and then another person could sleep the
next shift, and another person. You did not have to change the sheets, I
remember. The housing really was short. I&#039;m sure that you&#039;ve read about it. It&#039;s
well documented. But houses went up very fast then. The war only lasted less
than five years, and people came in, had to house &#039;em, feed &#039;em, then some of
them moved out.

LI: Were you a teenager at this point?

GEE: No, I had really left home. I went into the war myself. I went out to work.
Like any young person, you&#039;re really involved in yourself, more so, trying to
figure out what you&#039;re doing.

MCGARRIGLE: After the war, did your mother find different employment, or was
that the end of her working?

GEE: No, my mother went to work in the post office after the war. I think she
must have retired from the post office. I don&#039;t know how long she worked in the
post office, but then she ended up helping {Homer Lee} who had this florist.
They had a very nice article about Homer in the Sunday supplement: &quot;From Rags to
Riches.&quot; But he still lived the same. I called him after I saw it in the paper
and I spoke to his son. I said, is Homer coming down to cook lunch for you? And
he said, &quot;Yes, he&#039;s not here yet.&quot; [laughs]

LI: I was thinking about the influx of workers in Richmond. Was it exciting, as
a young person, to have all these new people here?

GEE: I think so. I think it was. People have to find things to do,
entertainment, so there was just a lot of people around. Which there wasn&#039;t,
though. What do you do at nighttime, after working all day? If you&#039;re young, you
go to the movies or you look for something to do. There was a certain amount of
excitement. How much overflowed into Berkeley, that I just can&#039;t remember. But
Richmond had a lot of things going at that time.

LI: Would you go to restaurants or bars in Richmond? Would you go out, there?

GEE: I used to go to bars, sort of. [laughs]

MCGARRIGLE: The whole music scene there; did you go to any places where there
was live music? There was a whole developing scene in Richmond.

GEE: I think so. I used to like music. I wouldn&#039;t go out now to listen to music,
unless it&#039;s the symphony or the opera, something like that. But just to hang out
in bars, I don&#039;t. I used to; I think I was dating someone at that time and we&#039;d
go down and see what the action was, follow it. There was nothing going on here,
go find some other place.

LI: The people who were coming to Richmond, they were from--

GEE: From the South. There were a lot of blacks, but they were from every part.

LI: Did it feel really--

GEE: I don&#039;t have a vision of it. I know a varied lot of blacks came in, and
there had to be people from elsewheres. I think if I lived there, then I would
have become much more aware of it, who had come to town. But they were just more
people around.

STINE: You didn&#039;t live in Richmond, but in a way that gives you a perspective from not
being part of that community and knowing what the general perception of Richmond
was, once all these big changes had occurred there. I was wondering how your
friends or your colleagues would talk about it in a different way than maybe
before the war. If it became some place that you wanted to go to, more? Or if it
became some place that you--

GEE: Wanted to stay away from? Richmond was not on the horizon when I was
growing up, except for the Chinese home there and some of the people. The
Chinese Boys home, Chung Mei Home, was there and we used to go out there quite a
bit. That&#039;s really El Cerrito, right on the edge of Richmond. The boys did go to
Richmond High School. No, I don&#039;t think that Richmond was a place I would go to,
to seek out entertainment at that particular time. It was close, though. San
Francisco was a place you go to seek out entertainment, but sometimes it&#039;s
difficult to get to San Francisco.

MCGARRIGLE: I was just thinking about what you said about Standard Oil and I
remembered there&#039;s a neighborhood in El Cerrito, close to Richmond, that had
beautiful homes like you see around the Claremont Hotel. They were all owned by
the Standard Oil executives. Large-scale, what would now be very, very expensive
homes in the hills there.

GEE: Richmond, in the hill area, there&#039;s some very large homes up on the top. I
think there are several Maybecks up there. I haven&#039;t seen them, but they say
where the Maybecks and the Julia Morgans are. I think there are one or two
there. There are just very large homes, because of the Standard Oil.

MCGARRIGLE: So the children of those executives were in public schools with the
children of the shipyard workers who came in. It must have been interesting.

GEE: You&#039;ve hit it on the head, in the sense that on the West coast, we don&#039;t
have private schools. There&#039;s so very few private schools, so the children
probably did go to public school. Otherwise, you have to be shipping them all
the way to Berkeley. The private schools in Berkeley were really small. What&#039;s
the one that was on Benvenue?

MCGARRIGLE: The Academy?

GEE: California Preparatory School on College {CPS} was small there was another
one called Brentley, just a house on Benvenue Street. That&#039;s the nice part about
the West Coast: it&#039;s very liberal in that, because we don&#039;t have private
schools. We do in San Francisco. There&#039;s some in San Francisco.

[end of interview]</transcript><transcript_alt></transcript_alt><rights></rights><fmt>video</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>